<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA 1.1 Composite//EN"
  "http://docs.oasis-open.org/dita/v1.1/OS/dtd/ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic_a">
  <title></title>
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
<title id="oj998314">psqlODBC</title>
<body>
<p>psqlODBC is the official PostgreSQL ODBC Driver. The driver is currently maintained by a number
        of contributors to the PostgreSQL project at <xref
          href="http://pgfoundry.org/projects/psqlodbc" scope="external" format="html"
          >http://pgfoundry.org/projects/psqlodbc</xref>. It is developed and supported through the
        pgsql-odbc@postgresql.org mailing list. psqlODBC is released under the Library General
        Public Licence, or LGPL. </p>
</body>
</topic>

<topic id="topic2" xml:lang="en">
<title id="oj998322">PostgreSQL JDBC Interface</title>
<body>
<p id="oj998324">The PostgreSQL JDB interface is the official PostgreSQL JDBC driver. The driver is
        currently maintained by a number of contributors to the PostgreSQL project at <xref
          href="https://jdbc.postgresql.org" scope="external" format="html"
          >https://jdbc.postgresql.org</xref>. JDBC is a core API of Java 1.1 and later. It provides
        a standard set of interfaces to SQL-compliant databases. PostgreSQL provides a type 4 JDBC
        driver. Type 4 indicates that the driver is written in Pure Java, and communicates in the
        database system's own network protocol. Because of this, the driver is platform independent;
        once compiled, the driver can be used on any system. The PostgreSQL JDBC Interface has not
        been modified from the original PostgreSQL distribution.</p>
</body>
</topic>

<topic id="topic3" xml:lang="en">
<title id="oj998328">libpq</title>
<body>
<p><codeph>libpq</codeph> is the C application programmer's interface
(API) to PostgreSQL (and Greenplum Database). <codeph>libpq</codeph>
is a set of library functions that allow client programs to pass queries
to the PostgreSQL backend server and to receive the results of these
queries. </p>
<p>For more information on using <codeph>libpq</codeph>, see <xref
          href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/8.3/static/libpq.html" scope="external" format="html"
          >libpq - C Library</xref> in the PostgreSQL documentation.</p>

</body>
</topic></topic>

