<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="ip141161">Configuring Client Authentication</title>
  <shortdesc>This topic explains how to configure client connections and authentication for
    Greenplum Database.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>When a Greenplum Database system is first initialized, the system contains one predefined
        <i>superuser</i> role. This role will have the same name as the operating system user who
      initialized the Greenplum Database system. This role is referred to as
        <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>. By default, the system is configured to only allow local
      connections to the database from the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> role. If you want to allow any
      other roles to connect, or if you want to allow connections from remote hosts, you have to
      configure Greenplum Database to allow such connections. This section explains how to configure
      client connections and authentication to Greenplum Database.</p>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic2" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ip142171">Allowing Connections to Greenplum Database</title>
    <body>
      <p>Client access and authentication is controlled by the standard PostgreSQL host-based
        authentication file, <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath>. For detailed information about this
        file, see <xref href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/auth-pg-hba-conf.html"
          scope="external" format="html">The pg_hba.conf File</xref> in the PostgreSQL
        documentation. </p>
      <p>In Greenplum Database, the <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file of the master instance
        controls client access and authentication to your Greenplum Database system. The Greenplum
        Database segments also have <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> files, but these are already
        correctly configured to allow only client connections from the master host. The segments
        never accept outside client connections, so there is no need to alter the
          <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file on segments.</p>
      <p>The general format of the <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file is a set of records, one
        per line. Greenplum Database ignores blank lines and any text after the <codeph>#</codeph>
        comment character. A record consists of a number of fields that are separated by spaces or
        tabs. Fields can contain white space if the field value is quoted. Records cannot be
        continued across lines. Each remote client access record has the following format:</p>
      <codeblock><i>host</i>   <i>database</i>   <i>role</i>   <i>address</i>   <i>authentication-method</i></codeblock>
      <p>Each UNIX-domain socket access record is in this format:</p>
      <codeblock><i>local</i>   <i>database</i>   <i>role</i>   <i>authentication-method</i></codeblock>
      <p>The following table describes meaning of each field. </p>
      <table id="ip141709">
        <title>pg_hba.conf Fields</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="3*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Field</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">local</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Matches connection attempts using UNIX-domain sockets. Without a
                record of this type, UNIX-domain socket connections are disallowed.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">host</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Matches connection attempts made using TCP/IP. Remote TCP/IP
                connections will not be possible unless the server is started with an appropriate
                value for the <codeph>listen_addresses</codeph> server configuration
                parameter.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">hostssl</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Matches connection attempts made using TCP/IP, but only when the
                connection is made with SSL encryption. SSL must be enabled at server start time by
                setting the <codeph>ssl</codeph> server configuration parameter. </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">hostnossl</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Matches connection attempts made over TCP/IP that do not use
                SSL.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">database</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Specifies which database names this record matches. The value
                  <codeph>all</codeph> specifies that it matches all databases. Multiple database
                names can be supplied by separating them with commas. A separate file containing
                database names can be specified by preceding the file name with a
                <codeph>@</codeph>.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">role</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Specifies which database role names this record matches. The
                value <codeph>all</codeph> specifies that it matches all roles. If the specified
                role is a group and you want all members of that group to be included, precede the
                role name with a <codeph>+</codeph>. Multiple role names can be supplied by
                separating them with commas. A separate file containing role names can be specified
                by preceding the file name with a <codeph>@</codeph>.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">address</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Specifies the client machine addresses that this record matches.
                This field can contain an IP address, an IP address range, or a host name. <p>An IP
                  address range is specified using standard numeric notation for the range's
                  starting address, then a slash (<codeph>/</codeph>) and a CIDR mask length. The
                  mask length indicates the number of high-order bits of the client IP address that
                  must match. Bits to the right of this should be zero in the given IP address.
                  There must not be any white space between the IP address, the <codeph>/</codeph>,
                  and the CIDR mask length.</p><p>Typical examples of an IPv4 address range
                  specified this way are <codeph>172.20.143.89/32</codeph> for a single host, or
                    <codeph>172.20.143.0/24</codeph> for a small network, or
                    <codeph>10.6.0.0/16</codeph> for a larger one. An IPv6 address range might look
                  like <codeph>::1/128</codeph> for a single host (in this case the IPv6 loopback
                  address) or <codeph>fe80::7a31:c1ff:0000:0000/96</codeph> for a small network.
                    <codeph>0.0.0.0/0</codeph> represents all IPv4 addresses, and
                    <codeph>::0/0</codeph> represents all IPv6 addresses. To specify a single host,
                  use a mask length of 32 for IPv4 or 128 for IPv6. In a network address, do not
                  omit trailing zeroes.</p><p>An entry given in IPv4 format will match only IPv4
                  connections, and an entry given in IPv6 format will match only IPv6 connections,
                  even if the represented address is in the IPv4-in-IPv6 range.
                  <note>Entries in IPv6 format will be rejected if the host system C library does
                    not have support for IPv6 addresses.</note></p><p>If a host name is specified
                  (an address that is not an IP address or IP range is treated as a host name), that
                  name is compared with the result of a reverse name resolution of the client IP
                  address (for example, reverse DNS lookup, if DNS is used). Host name comparisons
                  are case insensitive. If there is a match, then a forward name resolution (for
                  example, forward DNS lookup) is performed on the host name to check whether any of
                  the addresses it resolves to are equal to the client IP address. If both
                  directions match, then the entry is considered to match. </p><p>Some host name
                  databases allow associating an IP address with multiple host names, but the
                  operating system only returns one host name when asked to resolve an IP address.
                  The host name that is used in <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> must be the one that
                  the address-to-name resolution of the client IP address returns, otherwise the
                  line will not be considered a match. </p><p>When host names are specified in
                    <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph>, you should ensure that name resolution is
                  reasonably fast. It can be of advantage to set up a local name resolution cache
                  such as <codeph>nscd</codeph>. Also, you can enable the server configuration
                  parameter <codeph>log_hostname</codeph> to see the client host name instead of the
                  IP address in the log. </p></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">IP-address<p>IP-mask</p></entry>
              <entry colname="col2">These fields can be used as an alternative to the CIDR address
                notation. Instead of specifying the mask length, the actual mask is specified in a
                separate column. For example, <codeph>255.0.0.0</codeph> represents an IPv4 CIDR
                mask length of 8, and <codeph>255.255.255.255</codeph> represents a CIDR mask length
                of 32.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">authentication-method</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Specifies the authentication method to use when connecting.
                Greenplum supports the <xref
                  href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/auth-methods.html" scope="external"
                  format="html">authentication methods</xref> supported by PostgreSQL 9.4.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <note type="caution">For a more secure system, consider removing records for remote
        connections that use trust authentication from the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file. Trust
        authentication grants any user who can connect to the server access to the database using
        any role they specify. You can safely replace trust authentication with ident authentication
        for local UNIX-socket connections. You can also use ident authentication for local and
        remote TCP clients, but the client host must be running an ident service and you must trust
        the integrity of that machine.</note>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic3" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ip141322">Editing the pg_hba.conf File</title>
      <body>
        <p>Initially, the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file is set up with generous permissions for
          the gpadmin user and no database access for other Greenplum Database roles. You will need
          to edit the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file to enable users' access to databases and to
          secure the gpadmin user. Consider removing entries that have trust authentication, since
          they allow anyone with access to the server to connect with any role they choose. For
          local (UNIX socket) connections, use ident authentication, which requires the operating
          system user to match the role specified. For local and remote TCP connections, ident
          authentication requires the client's host to run an indent service. You can install an
          ident service on the master host and then use ident authentication for local TCP
          connections, for example <codeph>127.0.0.1/28</codeph>. Using ident authentication for
          remote TCP connections is less secure because it requires you to trust the integrity of
          the ident service on the client's host.</p>
        <p>This example shows how to edit the <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file of the master to
          allow remote client access to all databases from all roles using encrypted password
          authentication.</p>
        <section id="ip144328">
          <title>Editing pg_hba.conf</title>
          <ol id="ol_xz4_x15_jp">
            <li id="ip142837">Open the file <filepath>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY/pg_hba.conf</filepath>
              in a text editor.</li>
            <li id="ip141930">Add a line to the file for each type of connection you want to allow.
              Records are read sequentially, so the order of the records is significant. Typically,
              earlier records will have tight connection match parameters and weaker authentication
              methods, while later records will have looser match parameters and stronger
              authentication methods. For
              example:<codeblock># allow the gpadmin user local access to all databases
# using ident authentication
local   all   gpadmin   ident         sameuser
host    all   gpadmin   127.0.0.1/32  ident
host    all   gpadmin   ::1/128       ident
# allow the 'dba' role access to any database from any
# host with IP address 192.168.x.x and use md5 encrypted
# passwords to authenticate the user
# Note that to use SHA-256 encryption, replace <i>md5</i> with
# password in the line below
host    all   dba   192.168.0.0/32  md5
# allow all roles access to any database from any
# host and use ldap to authenticate the user. Greenplum role
# names must match the LDAP common name.
host    all   all   192.168.0.0/32  ldap ldapserver=usldap1 ldapport=1389 ldapprefix="cn=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=company,dc=com"</codeblock></li>
            <li id="ip141945">Save and close the file.</li>
            <li id="ip142080">Reload the <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> configuration file for
              your changes to take effect:<p>
                <codeblock>$ gpstop -u</codeblock>
              </p></li>
          </ol>
          <note type="note">Note that you can also control database access by setting object
            privileges as described in <xref href="roles_privs.xml#topic6" type="topic"
              format="dita"/>. The <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file just controls who can
            initiate a database session and how those connections are authenticated.</note>
        </section>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic4" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ip145021">Limiting Concurrent Connections</title>
    <shortdesc>Greenplum Database allocates some resources on a per-connection basis, so setting the
      maximum number of connections allowed is recommended.</shortdesc>
    <body>
      <p>To limit the number of active concurrent sessions to your Greenplum Database system, you
        can configure the <codeph>max_connections</codeph> server configuration parameter. This is a
          <i>local</i> parameter, meaning that you must set it in the
          <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file of the master, the standby master, and each segment
        instance (primary and mirror). The recommended value of <codeph>max_connections</codeph> on
        segments is 5-10 times the value on the master.</p>
      <p>When you set <codeph>max_connections</codeph>, you must also set the dependent parameter
          <codeph>max_prepared_transactions</codeph>. This value must be at least as large as the
        value of <codeph>max_connections</codeph> on the master, and segment instances should be set
        to the same value as the master.</p>
      <p>For example:</p>
      <ul id="ul_jlg_3b5_jp">
        <li>
          <p>In <codeph>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY/postgresql.conf</codeph> (including standby
            master):</p>
          <p>
            <codeblock>max_connections=100
max_prepared_transactions=100
</codeblock>
          </p>
        </li>
        <li>
          <p>In <codeph><i>SEGMENT_DATA_DIRECTORY</i>/postgresql.conf</codeph> for all segment
            instances:</p>
          <p>
            <codeblock>max_connections=500
max_prepared_transactions=100
</codeblock>
          </p>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>The following steps set the parameter values with the Greenplum Database utility
          <codeph>gpconfig</codeph>. </p>
      <p>For information about <codeph>gpconfig</codeph>, see the <i>Greenplum Database Utility
          Guide</i>.</p>
      <section id="ip142411">
        <title>To change the number of allowed connections</title>
        <ol id="ol_sty_r15_jp">
          <li id="ip146498">Log into the Greenplum Database master host as the Greenplum Database
            administrator and source the file <codeph>$GPHOME/greenplum_path.sh</codeph>. </li>
          <li id="ip146499">Set the value of the <codeph>max_connections</codeph> parameter. This
              <codeph>gpconfig</codeph> command sets the value on the segments to 1000 and the value
            on the master to 200.<p>
              <codeblock>$ gpconfig -c max_connections -v 1000 -m 200
</codeblock>
            </p><p>The value on the segments must be greater than the value on the master. The
              recommended value of <codeph>max_connections</codeph> on segments is 5-10 times the
              value on the master. </p></li>
          <li id="ip146502">Set the value of the <codeph>max_prepared_transactions</codeph>
            parameter. This <codeph>gpconfig</codeph> command sets the value to 200 on the master
            and all segments.<p>
              <codeblock>$ gpconfig -c max_prepared_transactions -v 200
</codeblock>
            </p><p>The value of <codeph>max_prepared_transactions</codeph> must be greater than or
              equal to <codeph>max_connections</codeph> on the master.</p></li>
          <li id="ip146508">Stop and restart your Greenplum Database system.<p>
              <codeblock>$ gpstop -r
</codeblock>
            </p></li>
          <li id="ip146510">You can check the value of parameters on the master and segments with
            the <codeph>gpconfig</codeph>
            <codeph>-s</codeph> option. This <codeph>gpconfig</codeph> command displays the values
            of the <codeph>max_connections</codeph> parameter. <p>
              <codeblock>$ gpconfig -s max_connections
</codeblock>
            </p></li>
        </ol>
        <note type="note">Raising the values of these parameters may cause Greenplum Database to
          request more shared memory. To mitigate this effect, consider decreasing other
          memory-related parameters such as <codeph>gp_cached_segworkers_threshold</codeph>. </note>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic5" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ip142639">Encrypting Client/Server Connections</title>
    <shortdesc>Enable SSL for client connections to Greenplum Database to encrypt the data passed
      over the network between the client and the database.</shortdesc>
    <body>
      <p>Greenplum Database has native support for SSL connections between the client and the master
        server. SSL connections prevent third parties from snooping on the packets, and also prevent
        man-in-the-middle attacks. SSL should be used whenever the client connection goes through an
        insecure link, and must be used whenever client certificate authentication is used.</p>
      <p>Enabling Greenplum Database in SSL mode requires the following items.<ul
          id="ul_ocx_df1_dlb">
          <li>OpenSSL installed on both the client and the master server hosts (master and standby
            master).</li>
          <li>The SSL files <filepath>server.key</filepath> (server private key) and
              <filepath>server.crt</filepath> (server certificate) should be correctly generated for
            the master host and standby master host. <ul id="ul_pwr_dg1_dlb">
              <li>The private key should not be protected with a passphrase. The server does not
                prompt for a passphrase for the private key, and Greenplum Database start up fails
                with an error if one is required.</li>
              <li>On a production system, there should be a key and certificate pair for the master
                host and a pair for the standby master host with a subject CN (Common Name) for the
                master host and standby master host.</li>
            </ul><p>A self-signed certificate can be used for testing, but a certificate signed by a
              certificate authority (CA) should be used in production, so the client can verify the
              identity of the server. Either a global or local CA can be used. If all the clients
              are local to the organization, a local CA is recommended.</p></li>
          <li>Ensure that Greenplum Database can access <filepath>server.key</filepath> and
              <filepath>server.crt</filepath>, and any additional authentication files such as
              <codeph>root.crt</codeph> (for trusted certificate authorities). When starting in SSL
            mode, the Greenplum Database master looks for <filepath>server.key</filepath> and
              <filepath>server.crt</filepath>. As the default, Greenplum Database does not start if
            the files are not in the master data directory
            (<codeph>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY</codeph>). Also, if you use other SSL authentication
            files such as <codeph>root.crt</codeph> (trusted certificate authorities), the files
            must be on the master host.<p>If Greenplum Database master mirroring is enabled with SSL
              client authentication, SSL authentication files must be on both the master host and
              standby master host and <i>should not be placed</i> in the default directory
                <codeph>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY</codeph>. When master mirroring is enabled, an
                <codeph>initstandby</codeph> operation copies the contents of the
                <codeph>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY</codeph> from the master to the standby master and
              the incorrect SSL key, and cert files (the master files, and not the standby master
              files) will prevent standby master start up. </p><p>You can specify a different
              directory for the location of the SSL server files with the
                <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> parameters <codeph>sslcert</codeph>,
                <codeph>sslkey</codeph>, <codeph>sslrootcert</codeph>, and <codeph>sslcrl</codeph>.
              For more information about the parameters, see <xref
                href="../security-guide/topics/Authenticate.xml#topic_fzv_wb2_jr"/> in the
                <cite>Security Configuration Guide</cite>. </p></li>
        </ul> Greenplum Database can be started with SSL enabled by setting the server configuration
        parameter <codeph>ssl=on</codeph> in the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file on the master
        and standby master hosts. This <codeph>gpconfig</codeph> command sets the
        parameter:<codeblock>gpconfig -c ssl -m on -v off</codeblock></p>
      <p>Setting the parameter requires a server restart. This command restarts the system:
          <codeph>gpstop -ra</codeph>.</p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic6" xml:lang="en">
      <title>Creating a Self-signed Certificate without a Passphrase for Testing Only</title>
      <body>
        <p>To create a quick self-signed certificate for the server for testing, use the following
          OpenSSL command:</p>
        <p>
          <codeblock># openssl req -new -text -out server.req
</codeblock>
        </p>
        <p>Enter the information requested by the prompts. Be sure to enter the local host name as
            <i>Common Name</i>. The challenge password can be left blank.</p>
        <p>The program will generate a key that is passphrase protected, and does not accept a
          passphrase that is less than four characters long. </p>
        <p>To use this certificate with Greenplum Database, remove the passphrase with the following
          commands:</p>
        <p>
          <codeblock># openssl rsa -in privkey.pem -out server.key
# rm privkey.pem</codeblock>
        </p>
        <p>Enter the old passphrase when prompted to unlock the existing key. </p>
        <p>Then, enter the following command to turn the certificate into a self-signed certificate
          and to copy the key and certificate to a location where the server will look for them.</p>
        <codeblock># openssl req -x509 -in server.req -text -key server.key -out server.crt</codeblock>
        <p>Finally, change the permissions on the key with the following command. The server will
          reject the file if the permissions are less restrictive than these.</p>
        <p>
          <codeblock># chmod og-rwx server.key</codeblock>
        </p>
        <p>For more details on how to create your server private key and certificate, refer to the
            <xref href="https://www.openssl.org/docs/" format="html" scope="external">OpenSSL
            documentation</xref>.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</topic>
