<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="ix146103">Inserting, Updating, and Deleting Data</title>
  <shortdesc>This section provides information about manipulating data and concurrent access in
    Greenplum Database.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>This topic includes the following subtopics:<ul id="ul_ahw_hty_sp">
        <li><xref href="#topic2" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic3" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic4" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic5" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic7" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic9" format="dita"/></li>
      </ul></p>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic2" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ix140249">About Concurrency Control in Greenplum Database</title>
    <body>
      <p>Greenplum Database and PostgreSQL do not use locks for concurrency control. They maintain
        data consistency using a multiversion model, Multiversion Concurrency Control (MVCC). MVCC
        achieves transaction isolation for each database session, and each query transaction sees a
        snapshot of data. This ensures the transaction sees consistent data that is not affected by
        other concurrent transactions. </p>
      <p>Because MVCC does not use explicit locks for concurrency control, lock contention is
        minimized and Greenplum Database maintains reasonable performance in multiuser environments.
        Locks acquired for querying (reading) data do not conflict with locks acquired for writing
        data.</p>
      <p>Greenplum Database provides multiple lock modes to control concurrent access to data in
        tables. Most Greenplum Database SQL commands automatically acquire the appropriate locks to
        ensure that referenced tables are not dropped or modified in incompatible ways while a
        command executes. For applications that cannot adapt easily to MVCC behavior, you can use
        the <codeph>LOCK</codeph> command to acquire explicit locks. However, proper use of MVCC
        generally provides better performance.</p>
      <table id="ix140861">
        <title>Lock Modes in Greenplum Database</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="2*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="3*"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="3*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Lock Mode</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Associated SQL Commands</entry>
              <entry colname="col3">Conflicts With</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">ACCESS SHARE</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">
                <codeph>SELECT</codeph>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="col3">ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">ROW SHARE</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">
                <codeph>SELECT FOR SHARE, SELECT FOR UPDATE</codeph>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="col3">EXCLUSIVE, ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">ROW EXCLUSIVE</entry>
              <entry colname="col2"><codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>COPY</codeph></entry>
              <entry colname="col3">SHARE, SHARE ROW EXCLUSIVE, EXCLUSIVE, ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">SHARE UPDATE EXCLUSIVE</entry>
              <entry colname="col2"><codeph>VACUUM</codeph> (without <codeph>FULL</codeph>),
                  <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph></entry>
              <entry colname="col3">SHARE UPDATE EXCLUSIVE, SHARE, SHARE ROW EXCLUSIVE, EXCLUSIVE,
                ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">SHARE</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">
                <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="col3">ROW EXCLUSIVE, SHARE UPDATE EXCLUSIVE, SHARE ROW EXCLUSIVE,
                EXCLUSIVE, ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">SHARE ROW EXCLUSIVE</entry>
              <entry colname="col2"/>
              <entry colname="col3">ROW EXCLUSIVE, SHARE UPDATE EXCLUSIVE, SHARE, SHARE ROW
                EXCLUSIVE, EXCLUSIVE, ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">EXCLUSIVE</entry>
              <entry colname="col2"><codeph>DELETE</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, <codeph>SELECT
                  FOR UPDATE</codeph>, See <xref href="#topic2/lock_note" format="dita"
                >Note</xref></entry>
              <entry colname="col3">ROW SHARE, ROW EXCLUSIVE, SHARE UPDATE EXCLUSIVE, SHARE, SHARE
                ROW EXCLUSIVE, EXCLUSIVE, ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</entry>
              <entry colname="col2"><codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph>, <codeph>DROP TABLE</codeph>,
                  <codeph>TRUNCATE</codeph>, <codeph>REINDEX</codeph>, <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>,
                  <codeph>VACUUM FULL</codeph>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="col3">ACCESS SHARE, ROW SHARE, ROW EXCLUSIVE, SHARE UPDATE EXCLUSIVE,
                SHARE, SHARE ROW EXCLUSIVE, EXCLUSIVE, ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <note id="lock_note">Greenplum Database acquires the more restrictive EXCLUSIVE lock (rather
        than ROW EXCLUSIVE in PostgreSQL) for <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, <codeph>DELETE</codeph>, and
        <codeph>SELECT FOR UPDATE</codeph>.</note>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic3" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ix140259">Inserting Rows</title>
    <body>
      <p>Use the <codeph>INSERT</codeph> command to create rows in a table. This command requires
        the table name and a value for each column in the table; you may optionally specify the
        column names in any order. If you do not specify column names, list the data values in the
        order of the columns in the table, separated by commas. </p>
      <p>For example, to specify the column names and the values to insert:</p>
      <codeblock>INSERT INTO products (name, price, product_no) VALUES ('Cheese', 9.99, 1);</codeblock>
      <p>To specify only the values to insert:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>INSERT INTO products VALUES (1, 'Cheese', 9.99);
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>Usually, the data values are literals (constants), but you can also use scalar expressions.
        For example:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>INSERT INTO films SELECT * FROM tmp_films WHERE date_prod &lt; 
'2016-05-07';
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>You can insert multiple rows in a single command. For example:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>INSERT INTO products (product_no, name, price) VALUES
    (1, 'Cheese', 9.99),
    (2, 'Bread', 1.99),
    (3, 'Milk', 2.99);
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>To insert data into a partitioned table, you specify the root partitioned table, the table
        created with the <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> command. You also can specify a leaf child
        table of the partitioned table in an <codeph>INSERT</codeph> command. An error is returned
        if the data is not valid for the specified leaf child table. Specifying a child table that
        is not a leaf child table in the <codeph>INSERT</codeph> command is not supported. </p>
      <p>To insert large amounts of data, use external tables or the <codeph>COPY</codeph> command.
        These load mechanisms are more efficient than <codeph>INSERT</codeph> for inserting large
        quantities of rows. See <xref href="load/topics/g-loading-and-unloading-data.xml#topic1"/>
        for more information about bulk data loading.</p>
      <p>The storage model of append-optimized tables is optimized for bulk data loading. Greenplum
        does not recommend single row <codeph>INSERT</codeph> statements for append-optimized
        tables. For append-optimized tables, Greenplum Database supports a maximum of 127 concurrent
          <codeph>INSERT</codeph> transactions into a single append-optimized table.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic4" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ix156852">Updating Existing Rows</title>
    <body>
      <p>The <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> command updates rows in a table. You can update all rows, a
        subset of all rows, or individual rows in a table. You can update each column separately
        without affecting other columns.</p>
      <p>To perform an update, you need: </p>
      <ul>
        <li id="ix142075">The name of the table and columns to update</li>
        <li id="ix142076">The new values of the columns</li>
        <li id="ix142077">One or more conditions specifying the row or rows to be updated.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>For example, the following command updates all products that have a price of <i>5</i> to
        have a price of <i>10</i>:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>UPDATE products SET price = 10 WHERE price = 5;
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>Using <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> in Greenplum Database has the following restrictions:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="ix155050">The Greenplum distribution key columns may not be updated.</li>
        <li id="ix142137">If mirrors are enabled, you cannot use <codeph>STABLE</codeph> or
            <codeph>VOLATILE</codeph> functions in an <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> statement.</li>
        <li id="ix154711">Greenplum Database does not support the <codeph>RETURNING</codeph>
          clause.</li>
        <li id="ix155339">Greenplum Database partitioning columns cannot be updated.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic5" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ix140451">Deleting Rows</title>
    <body>
      <p>The <codeph>DELETE</codeph> command deletes rows from a table. Specify a
          <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause to delete rows that match certain criteria. If you do not
        specify a <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause, all rows in the table are deleted. The result is a
        valid, but empty, table. For example, to remove all rows from the products table that have a
        price of <i>10</i>:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>DELETE FROM products WHERE price = 10;
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>To delete all rows from a table:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>DELETE FROM products; 
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>Using <codeph>DELETE</codeph> in Greenplum Database has similar restrictions to using
          <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="ix155065">If mirrors are enabled, you cannot use <codeph>STABLE</codeph> or
            <codeph>VOLATILE</codeph> functions in an <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> statement.</li>
        <li id="ix154839">The <codeph>RETURNING</codeph> clause is not supported in Greenplum
          Database.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic6" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ix142374">Truncating a Table</title>
      <body>
        <p>Use the <codeph>TRUNCATE</codeph> command to quickly remove all rows in a table. For
          example:</p>
        <p>
          <codeblock>TRUNCATE mytable;
</codeblock>
        </p>
        <p>This command empties a table of all rows in one operation. Note that
            <codeph>TRUNCATE</codeph> does not scan the table, therefore it does not process
          inherited child tables or <codeph>ON DELETE</codeph> rewrite rules. The command truncates
          only rows in the named table.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic7" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ix140458">Working With Transactions</title>
    <body>
      <p>Transactions allow you to bundle multiple SQL statements in one all-or-nothing
        operation.</p>
      <p>The following are the Greenplum Database SQL transaction commands:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="ix140816"><codeph>BEGIN</codeph> or <codeph>START TRANSACTION </codeph>starts a
          transaction block. </li>
        <li id="ix140821"><codeph>END</codeph> or <codeph>COMMIT</codeph> commits the results of a
          transaction.</li>
        <li id="ix140822"><codeph>ROLLBACK</codeph> abandons a transaction without making any
          changes. </li>
        <li id="ix155584"><codeph>SAVEPOINT</codeph> marks a place in a transaction and enables
          partial rollback. You can roll back commands executed after a savepoint while maintaining
          commands executed before the savepoint.</li>
        <li id="ix155585"><codeph>ROLLBACK TO SAVEPOINT </codeph>rolls back a transaction to a
          savepoint. </li>
        <li id="ix155589"><codeph>RELEASE SAVEPOINT </codeph>destroys a savepoint within a
          transaction.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic8" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ix153949">Transaction Isolation Levels</title>
      <body>
        <p>Greenplum Database accepts the standard SQL transaction levels as follows:</p>
        <ul>
          <li id="ix153961"><i>read uncommitted</i> and <i>read committed </i> behave like the
            standard <i>read committed</i></li>
          <li><i>repeatable read</i> is disallowed. If the behavior of <i>repeatable read</i> is
            required, use <i>serializable</i>.</li>
          <li id="ix153971"><i>serializable</i> behaves in a manner similar to SQL standard
              <i>serializable</i></li>
        </ul>
        <p>The following information describes the behavior of the Greenplum transaction levels:</p>
        <ul>
          <li id="ix153954"><b>read committed/read uncommitted</b> — Provides fast, simple, partial
            transaction isolation. With read committed and read uncommitted transaction isolation,
              <codeph>SELECT</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, and <codeph>DELETE</codeph>
            transactions operate on a snapshot of the database taken when the query started.</li>
        </ul>
        <p> A <codeph>SELECT</codeph> query:</p>
        <ul>
          <li id="ix154052">Sees data committed before the query starts.</li>
          <li id="ix154063">Sees updates executed within the transaction.</li>
          <li id="ix154073">Does not see uncommitted data outside the transaction.</li>
          <li id="ix154080">Can possibly see changes that concurrent transactions made if the
            concurrent transaction is committed after the initial read in its own transaction.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Successive <codeph>SELECT</codeph> queries in the same transaction can see different data
          if other concurrent transactions commit changes before the queries start.
            <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> and <codeph>DELETE</codeph> commands find only rows committed
          before the commands started. </p>
        <p>Read committed or read uncommitted transaction isolation allows concurrent transactions
          to modify or lock a row before <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> or <codeph>DELETE</codeph> finds
          the row. Read committed or read uncommitted transaction isolation may be inadequate for
          applications that perform complex queries and updates and require a consistent view of the
          database.</p>
        <ul>
          <li id="ix141722"><b>serializable</b> — Provides strict transaction isolation in which
            transactions execute as if they run one after another rather than concurrently.
            Applications on the serializable level must be designed to retry transactions in case of
            serialization failures. In Greenplum Database, <codeph>SERIALIZABLE</codeph> prevents
            dirty reads, non-repeatable reads, and phantom reads without expensive locking, but
            there are other interactions that can occur between some <codeph>SERIALIZABLE</codeph>
            transactions in Greenplum Database that prevent them from being truly serializable.
            Transactions that run concurrently should be examined to identify interactions that are
            not prevented by disallowing concurrent updates of the same data. Problems identified
            can be prevented by using explicit table locks or by requiring the conflicting
            transactions to update a dummy row introduced to represent the conflict. </li>
        </ul>
        <p>A <codeph>SELECT</codeph> query:</p>
        <ul>
          <li id="ix154139">Sees a snapshot of the data as of the start of the transaction (not as
            of the start of the current query within the transaction).</li>
          <li id="ix155116">Sees only data committed before the query starts.</li>
          <li id="ix154149">Sees updates executed within the transaction.</li>
          <li id="ix154156">Does not see uncommitted data outside the transaction.</li>
          <li id="ix154163">Does not see changes that concurrent transactions made.<p>Successive
                <codeph>SELECT</codeph> commands within a single transaction always see the same
              data.</p><p><codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, <codeph>DELETE, SELECT FOR UPDATE,</codeph> and
                <codeph>SELECT FOR SHARE</codeph> commands find only rows committed before the
              command started. If a concurrent transaction has already updated, deleted, or locked a
              target row when the row is found, the serializable or repeatable read transaction
              waits for the concurrent transaction to update the row, delete the row, or roll
              back.</p><p>If the concurrent transaction updates or deletes the row, the serializable
              or repeatable read transaction rolls back. If the concurrent transaction rolls back,
              then the serializable or repeatable read transaction updates or deletes the
            row.</p></li>
        </ul>
        <p id="ix141505">The default transaction isolation level in Greenplum Database is <i>read
            committed</i>. To change the isolation level for a transaction, declare the isolation
          level when you <codeph>BEGIN</codeph> the transaction or use the <codeph>SET
            TRANSACTION</codeph> command after the transaction starts.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic9" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ix141487">Vacuuming the Database</title>
    <body>
      <p>Deleted or updated data rows occupy physical space on disk even though new transactions
        cannot see them. Periodically running the <codeph>VACUUM</codeph> command removes these
        expired rows. For example:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>VACUUM mytable;
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>The <codeph>VACUUM</codeph> command collects table-level statistics such as the number of
        rows and pages. Vacuum all tables after loading data, including append-optimized tables. For
        information about recommended routine vacuum operations, see <xref
          href="managing/maintain.xml#topic2" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</p>
      <note type="important">The <codeph>VACUUM</codeph>, <codeph>VACUUM FULL</codeph>, and
          <codeph>VACUUM ANALYZE</codeph> commands should be used to maintain the data in a
        Greenplum database especially if updates and deletes are frequently performed on your
        database data. See the <codeph>VACUUM</codeph> command in the <cite>Greenplum Database
          Reference Guide</cite> for information about using the command.</note>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic10" xml:lang="en">
      <title>Configuring the Free Space Map</title>
      <body>
        <p>Expired rows are held in the <i>free space map</i>. The free space map must be sized
          large enough to hold all expired rows in your database. If not, a regular
            <codeph>VACUUM</codeph> command cannot reclaim space occupied by expired rows that
          overflow the free space map.</p>
        <p><codeph>VACUUM FULL</codeph> reclaims all expired row space, but it is an expensive
          operation and can take an unacceptably long time to finish on large, distributed Greenplum
          Database tables. If the free space map overflows, you can recreate the table with a
            <codeph>CREATE TABLE AS </codeph>statement and drop the old table. Using <codeph>VACUUM FULL</codeph> is discouraged.</p>
        <p>Size the free space map with the following server configuration parameters:<ul
            id="ul_cj2_xc5_h4">
            <li><codeph>max_fsm_pages</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>max_fsm_relations</codeph></li>
          </ul></p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</topic>
