<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="nr110126">Using Kerberos Authentication</title>
  <shortdesc>You can control access to Greenplum Database with a Kerberos authentication server. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum Database supports the Generic Security Service Application Program Interface
      (GSSAPI) with Kerberos authentication. GSSAPI provides automatic authentication (single
      sign-on) for systems that support it. You specify the Greenplum Database users (roles) that
      require Kerberos authentication in the Greenplum Database configuration file
        <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath>. The login fails if Kerberos authentication is not
      available when a role attempts to log in to Greenplum Database.</p>
    <p>Kerberos provides a secure, encrypted authentication service. It does not encrypt data
      exchanged between the client and database and provides no authorization services. To encrypt
      data exchanged over the network, you must use an SSL connection. To manage authorization for
      access to Greenplum databases and objects such as schemas and tables, you use settings in the
        <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file and privileges given to Greenplum Database users and
      roles within the database. For information about managing authorization privileges, see <xref
        href="roles_privs.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</p>
    <p>For more information about Kerberos, see <xref href="http://web.mit.edu/kerberos/"
        format="html">http://web.mit.edu/kerberos/</xref>.</p>
    <section id="kerberos_prereq">
      <title id="nr159116">Requirements for Using Kerberos with Greenplum Database</title>
      <p>The following items are required for using Kerberos with Greenplum Database:</p>
      <ul id="ul_ojr_rvj_2p">
        <li id="nr157373">Kerberos Key Distribution Center (KDC) server using the
            <codeph>krb5-server</codeph> library</li>
        <li id="nr163731">Kerberos version 5 <codeph>krb5-libs</codeph> and
            <codeph>krb5-workstation</codeph> packages installed on the Greenplum Database master
          host </li>
        <li id="nr159901">Greenplum Database version with support for Kerberos</li>
        <li>System time on the Kerberos server and Greenplum Database master host must be
          synchronized. (Install Linux <codeph>ntp</codeph> package on both servers.) </li>
        <li id="nr163891">Network connectivity between the Kerberos server and the Greenplum
          Database master</li>
        <li id="nr166917">Java 1.7.0_17 or later is required to use Kerberos-authenticated JDBC on
          Red Hat Enterprise Linux 6.x</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="nr166539">
      <title>Enabling Kerberos Authentication for Greenplum Database</title>
      <p>Complete the following tasks to set up Kerberos authentication with Greenplum Database:</p>
      <ol>
        <li>Verify your system satisfies the prequisites for using Kerberos with Greenplum Database.
          See <xref href="#topic1/kerberos_prereq" format="dita" type="section"/>.</li>
        <li id="nr165098">Set up, or identify, a Kerberos Key Distribution Center (KDC) server to
          use for authentication. See <xref href="#task_setup_kdc" format="dita"/>.</li>
        <li>In a Kerberos database on the KDC server, set up a Kerberos realm and principals on the
          server. For Greenplum Database, a principal is a Greenplum Database role that uses
          Kerberos authentication. In the Kerberos database, a realm groups together Kerberos
          principals that are Greenplum Database roles.</li>
        <li id="nr165106">Create Kerberos <filepath>keytab</filepath> files for Greenplum Database.
          To access Greenplum Database, you create a service key known only by Kerberos and
          Greenplum Database. On the Kerberos server, the service key is stored in the Kerberos
            database.<p>On the Greenplum Database master, the service key is stored in key tables,
            which are files known as keytabs. The service keys are usually stored in the keytab file
              <codeph>/etc/krb5.keytab</codeph>. This service key is the equivalent of the service's
            password, and must be kept secure. Data that is meant to be read-only by the service is
            encrypted using this key.</p></li>
        <li id="nr165107">Install the Kerberos client packages and the keytab file on Greenplum
          Database master.</li>
        <li id="nr165111">Create a Kerberos ticket for <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> on the Greenplum
          Database master node using the keytab file. The ticket contains the Kerberos
          authentication credentials that grant access to the Greenplum Database.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>With Kerberos authentication configured on the Greenplum Database, you can use Kerberos for
        PSQL and JDBC.<ul id="ul_iks_hss_bz">
          <li><xref href="#topic7" type="task" format="dita"/></li>
          <li><xref href="#topic9" type="task" format="dita"/></li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>You can also configure external authentication for clients running on a Microsoft Windows
          system.<ul id="ul_rvk_vrs_bz">
          <li>Configure Kerberos authentication for the Greenplum Database client utilities
              <codeph>gpload</codeph> and <codeph>psql</codeph> on a Microsoft Windows system. See
              <xref href="kerberos-win-client.xml#topic_vjg_d5m_sv" format="dita"/>.</li>
          <li>Configure a Microsoft Windows user with a Microsoft Active Directory (AD) account for
            single sign-on to a Greenplum Database system. See <xref
              href="kerberos-win-client.xml#topic_uzb_t5m_sv" format="dita"/>.</li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>
  </body>
  <task id="task_setup_kdc">
    <title>Install and Configure a Kerberos KDC Server</title>
    <shortdesc>Steps to set up a Kerberos Key Distribution Center (KDC) server on a Red Hat
      Enterprise Linux host for use with Greenplum Database.</shortdesc>
    <taskbody>
      <context>Follow these steps to install and configure a Kerberos Key Distribution Center (KDC)
        server on a Red Hat Enterprise Linux host. </context>
      <steps id="steps_r5w_rtc_2p">
        <step>
          <cmd>Install the Kerberos server packages:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>sudo yum install krb5-libs krb5-server krb5-workstation</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>Edit the <filepath>/etc/krb5.conf</filepath> configuration file. The following
            example shows a Kerberos server with a default <codeph>KRB.GREENPLUM.COM</codeph> realm. </cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>[logging]
 default = FILE:/var/log/krb5libs.log
 kdc = FILE:/var/log/krb5kdc.log
 admin_server = FILE:/var/log/kadmind.log

[libdefaults]
 default_realm = KRB.GREENPLUM.COM
 dns_lookup_realm = false
 dns_lookup_kdc = false
 ticket_lifetime = 24h
 renew_lifetime = 7d
 forwardable = true
 default_tgs_enctypes = aes128-cts des3-hmac-sha1 des-cbc-crc des-cbc-md5
 default_tkt_enctypes = aes128-cts des3-hmac-sha1 des-cbc-crc des-cbc-md5
 permitted_enctypes = aes128-cts des3-hmac-sha1 des-cbc-crc des-cbc-md5

[realms]
 KRB.GREENPLUM.COM = {
  kdc = kerberos-gpdb:88
  admin_server = kerberos-gpdb:749
  default_domain = kerberos-gpdb
 }

[domain_realm]
 .kerberos-gpdb = KRB.GREENPLUM.COM
 kerberos-gpdb = KRB.GREENPLUM.COM

[appdefaults]
 pam = {
    debug = false
    ticket_lifetime = 36000
    renew_lifetime = 36000
    forwardable = true
    krb4_convert = false
 }
</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
          <info>
            <p>The <codeph>kdc</codeph> and <codeph>admin_server</codeph> keys in the
                <codeph>[realms]</codeph> section specify the host (<codeph>kerberos-gpdb</codeph>)
              and port where the Kerberos server is running. IP numbers can be used in place of host
              names. </p>
            <p>If your Kerberos server manages authentication for other realms, you would instead
              add the <codeph>KRB.GREENPLUM.COM</codeph> realm in the <codeph>[realms]</codeph> and
                <codeph>[domain_realm]</codeph> section of the <codeph>kdc.conf</codeph> file. See
              the <xref href="http://web.mit.edu/kerberos/krb5-latest/doc/" format="html"
                scope="external">Kerberos documentation</xref> for information about the
                <codeph>kdc.conf</codeph> file.</p>
          </info>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>To create a Kerberos KDC database, run the <codeph>kdb5_util</codeph>. </cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>kdb5_util create -s</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
          <info>The <codeph>kdb5_util</codeph>
            <option>create</option> option creates the database to store keys for the Kerberos
            realms that are managed by this KDC server. The <option>-s</option> option creates a
            stash file. Without the stash file, every time the KDC server starts it requests a
            password.</info>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>Add an administrative user to the KDC database with the <codeph>kadmin.local</codeph>
            utility. Because it does not itself depend on Kerberos authentication, the
              <codeph>kadmin.local</codeph> utility allows you to add an initial administrative user
            to the local Kerberos server. To add the user <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> as an
            administrative user to the KDC database, run the following command:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>kadmin.local -q "addprinc gpadmin/admin"</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
          <info>Most users do not need administrative access to the Kerberos server. They can use
              <codeph>kadmin</codeph> to manage their own principals (for example, to change their
            own password). For information about <codeph>kadmin</codeph>, see the <xref
              href="http://web.mit.edu/kerberos/krb5-latest/doc/" format="html" scope="external"
              >Kerberos documentation</xref>. </info>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>If needed, edit the <filepath>/var/kerberos/krb5kdc/kadm5.acl</filepath> file to
            grant the appropriate permissions to <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>.</cmd>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>Start the Kerberos daemons:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>/sbin/service krb5kdc start
/sbin/service kadmin start</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>To start Kerberos automatically upon restart:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>/sbin/chkconfig krb5kdc on
/sbin/chkconfig kadmin on</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
      </steps>
    </taskbody>
  </task>
  <task id="task_m43_vwl_2p">
    <title>Create Greenplum Database Roles in the KDC Database</title>
    <shortdesc>Add principals to the Kerberos realm for Greenplum Database.</shortdesc>
    <taskbody>
      <context>Start <codeph>kadmin.local</codeph> in interactive mode, then add two principals to
        the Greenplum Database Realm.</context>
      <steps id="steps_gq5_hzl_2p">
        <step>
          <cmd>Start <codeph>kadmin.local</codeph> in interactive mode:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>kadmin.local</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>Add principals:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <pre>kadmin.local: <userinput>addprinc gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb@KRB.EXAMPLE.COM
</userinput>kadmin.local: <userinput>addprinc postgres/master.test.com@KRB.EXAMPLE.COM</userinput></pre>
          </stepxmp>
          <info>The <codeph>adprinc</codeph> commands prompt for passwords for each principal. The
            first <codeph>addprinc</codeph> creates a Greenplum Database user as a principal,
              <codeph>gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb</codeph>. The second <codeph>addprinc</codeph> command
            creates the <codeph>postgres</codeph> process on the Greenplum Database master host as a
            principal in the Kerberos KDC. This principal is required when using Kerberos
            authentication with Greenplum Database. </info>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>Create a Kerberos keytab file with <codeph>kadmin.local</codeph>. The following
            example creates a keytab file <codeph>gpdb-kerberos.keytab</codeph> in the current
            directory with authentication information for the two principals.</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>kadmin.local: <userinput>xst -k gpdb-kerberos.keytab
    gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb@KRB.EXAMPLE.COM
    postgres/master.test.com@KRB.EXAMPLE.COM</userinput></codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
          <info>You will copy this file to the Greenplum Database master host.</info>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>Exit <codeph>kadmin.local</codeph> interactive mode with the <codeph>quit</codeph>
            command:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeph>kadmin.local: <userinput>quit</userinput></codeph>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
      </steps>
    </taskbody>
  </task>
  <task id="topic6">
    <title id="nr162022">Install and Configure the Kerberos Client</title>
    <shortdesc>Steps to install the Kerberos client on the Greenplum Database master
      host.</shortdesc>
    <taskbody>
      <context>Install the Kerberos client libraries on the Greenplum Database master and configure
        the Kerberos client.</context>
      <steps>
        <step id="nr162024">
          <cmd>Install the Kerberos packages on the Greenplum Database master.</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>sudo yum install krb5-libs krb5-workstation</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
        <step id="nr162025">
          <cmd>Ensure that the <codeph>/etc/krb5.conf</codeph> file is the same as the one that is
            on the Kerberos server.</cmd>
        </step>
        <step id="nr157526">
          <cmd>Copy the <codeph>gpdb-kerberos.keytab</codeph> file that was generated on the
            Kerberos server to the Greenplum Database master host.</cmd>
        </step>
        <step id="nr157528">
          <cmd>Remove any existing tickets with the Kerberos utility <codeph>kdestroy</codeph>. Run
            the utility as root.</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>sudo kdestroy</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
        <step id="nr157529">
          <cmd>Use the Kerberos utility <codeph>kinit</codeph> to request a ticket using the keytab
            file on the Greenplum Database master for
              <codeph>gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb@KRB.EXAMPLE.COM</codeph>. The <option>-t</option> option
            specifies the keytab file on the Greenplum Database master.</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock># kinit -k -t gpdb-kerberos.keytab gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb@KRB.EXAMPLE.COM</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>Use the Kerberos utility <codeph>klist</codeph> to display the contents of the
            Kerberos ticket cache on the Greenplum Database master. The following is an
            example:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <screen># klist
Ticket cache: FILE:/tmp/krb5cc_108061
Default principal: gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb@KRB.EXAMPLE.COM
Valid starting     Expires            Service principal
03/28/13 14:50:26  03/29/13 14:50:26  krbtgt/KRB.GREENPLUM.COM     @KRB.EXAMPLE.COM
    renew until 03/28/13 14:50:26</screen>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
      </steps>
    </taskbody>
    <task id="topic7" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="nr157582">Set up Greenplum Database with Kerberos for PSQL</title>
      <shortdesc>Configure a Greenplum Database to use Kerberos.</shortdesc>
      <taskbody>
        <context>After you have set up Kerberos on the Greenplum Database master, you can configure
          Greenplum Database to use Kerberos. For information on setting up the Greenplum Database
          master, see <xref href="#topic6" type="task" format="dita"/>.</context>
        <steps>
          <step>
            <cmd>Create a Greenplum Database administrator role in the database
                <codeph>postgres</codeph> for the Kerberos principal that is used as the database
              administrator. The following example uses <codeph>gpamin/kerberos-gpdb</codeph>.</cmd>
            <stepxmp>
              <codeblock>psql postgres -c 'create role "gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb" login superuser;'
</codeblock>
            </stepxmp>
            <info> The role you create in the database <codeph>postgres</codeph> will be available
              in any new Greenplum Database that you create. </info>
          </step>
          <step id="nr157586">
            <cmd>Modify <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> to specify the location of the keytab file.
              For example, adding this line to the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> specifies the
              folder <filepath>/home/gpadmin</filepath> as the location of the keytab file<filepath>
                gpdb-kerberos.keytab</filepath>.</cmd>
            <stepxmp>
              <codeblock>krb_server_keyfile = '/home/gpadmin/gpdb-kerberos.keytab'
</codeblock>
            </stepxmp>
          </step>
          <step id="nr157589">
            <cmd>Modify the Greenplum Database file <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> to enable Kerberos
              support. Then restart Greenplum Database (<codeph>gpstop -ar</codeph>). For example,
              adding the following line to <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> adds GSSAPI and Kerberos
              support. The value for <codeph>krb_realm</codeph> is the Kerberos realm that is used
              for authentication to Greenplum Database.</cmd>
            <stepxmp>
              <codeblock>host all all 0.0.0.0/0 gss include_realm=0 krb_realm=KRB.GREENPLUM.COM</codeblock>
            </stepxmp>
            <info>For information about the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file, see <xref
                href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/8.4/static/auth-pg-hba-conf.html"
                scope="external" format="html">The pg_hba.conf file</xref> in the Postgres
              documentation.</info>
          </step>
          <step id="nr166157">
            <cmd>Create a ticket using <codeph>kinit</codeph> and show the tickets in the Kerberos
              ticket cache with <codeph>klist</codeph>.</cmd>
          </step>
          <step id="nr166158">
            <cmd>As a test, log in to the database as the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> role with the
              Kerberos credentials <codeph>gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb</codeph>:</cmd>
            <stepxmp>
              <codeblock>psql -U "gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb" -h master.test postgres
</codeblock>
            </stepxmp>
            <info>
              <p>A username map can be defined in the <codeph>pg_ident.conf</codeph> file and
                specified in the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file to simplify logging into
                Greenplum Database. For example, this <codeph>psql</codeph> command logs into the
                default Greenplum Database on <codeph>mdw.proddb</codeph> as the Kerberos principal
                  <codeph>adminuser/mdw.proddb</codeph>:
                <codeblock>$ psql -U "adminuser/mdw.proddb" -h mdw.proddb</codeblock>
              </p>
              <p>If the default user is <codeph>adminuser</codeph>, the
                  <filepath>pg_ident.conf</filepath> file and the <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath>
                file can be configured so that the <codeph>adminuser</codeph> can log in to the
                database as the Kerberos principal <codeph>adminuser/mdw.proddb</codeph> without
                specifying the <codeph>-U</codeph> option:
                <codeblock>$ psql -h mdw.proddb</codeblock>
              </p>
              <p>The following username map is defined in the Greenplum Database file
                  <codeph>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY/pg_ident.conf</codeph>: </p>
              <p>
                <codeblock># MAPNAME   SYSTEM-USERNAME        GP-USERNAME
mymap       /^(.*)mdw\.proddb$     adminuser</codeblock>
              </p>
              <p>The map can be specified in the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file as part of the
                line that enables Kerberos support:</p>
              <p>
                <codeblock>host all all 0.0.0.0/0 krb5 include_realm=0 krb_realm=proddb map=mymap</codeblock>
              </p>
              <p>For more information about specifying username maps see <xref
                  href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/8.4/static/auth-username-maps.html"
                  scope="external" format="html">Username maps</xref> in the Postgres
                documentation.</p>
            </info>
          </step>
          <step id="nr169659">
            <cmd>If a Kerberos principal is not a Greenplum Database user, a message similar to the
              following is displayed from the <codeph>psql</codeph> command line when the user
              attempts to log in to the database:</cmd>
            <stepxmp>
              <codeblock>psql: krb5_sendauth: Bad response</codeblock>
            </stepxmp>
            <info>The principal must be added as a Greenplum Database user. </info>
          </step>
        </steps>
      </taskbody>
    </task>
    <task id="topic9" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="nr168681">Set up Greenplum Database with Kerberos for JDBC</title>
      <shortdesc>Enable Kerberos-authenticated JDBC access to Greenplum Database.</shortdesc>
      <taskbody>
        <context>You can configure Greenplum Database to use Kerberos to run user-defined Java
          functions. </context>
        <steps>
          <step>
            <cmd id="nr161502">Ensure that Kerberos is installed and configured on the Greenplum
              Database master. See <xref href="#topic6" type="task" format="dita"/>.</cmd>
          </step>
          <step>
            <cmd id="nr161503">Create the file <filepath>.java.login.config</filepath> in the folder
              /home/gpadmin and add the following text to the file:</cmd>
            <stepxmp>
              <codeblock>pgjdbc {
  com.sun.security.auth.module.Krb5LoginModule required
  doNotPrompt=true
  useTicketCache=true
  debug=true
  client=true;
};</codeblock>
            </stepxmp>
          </step>
          <step id="nr157728">
            <cmd>Create a Java application that connects to Greenplum Database using Kerberos
              authentication. The following example database connection URL uses a PostgreSQL JDBC
              driver and specifies parameters for Kerberos authentication:</cmd>
            <stepxmp>
              <codeblock>jdbc:postgresql://mdw:5432/mytest?kerberosServerName=postgres
&amp;jaasApplicationName=pgjdbc&amp;user=gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb</codeblock>
            </stepxmp>
            <info>The parameter names and values specified depend on how the Java application
              performs Kerberos authentication.</info>
          </step>
          <step id="nr157717">
            <cmd>Test the Kerberos login by running a sample Java application from Greenplum
              Database.</cmd>
          </step>
        </steps>
      </taskbody>
    </task>
  </task>
</topic>
