<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_j1d_4qz_rz">
  <title>Configuring Kerberos for Linux Clients</title>
  <shortdesc>You can configure Linux client applications to connect to a Greenplum Database system
    that is configured to authenticate with Kerberos.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>If your JDBC application on Red Hat Enterprise Linux uses Kerberos authentication when it
      connects to your Greenplum Database, your client system must be configured to use Kerberos
      authentication. If you are not using Kerberos authentication to connect to a Greenplum
      Database, Kerberos is not needed on your client system.</p>
    <ul id="ul_nmz_1rz_rz">
      <li id="kd158375">
        <xref href="#topic13" type="topic" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li id="kd158379">
        <xref href="#topic17" type="topic" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li id="kd158383">
        <xref href="#topic18" type="topic" format="dita"/>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>For information about enabling Kerberos authentication with Greenplum Database, see the
      chapter "Setting Up Kerberos Authentication" in the <i>Greenplum Database Administrator
        Guide</i>. </p>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic13" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="kd158392">Requirements</title>
    <body>
      <p>The following are requirements to connect to a Greenplum Database that is enabled with
        Kerberos authentication from a client system with a JDBC application.</p>
      <ul id="ul_hrb_crz_rz">
        <li id="kd158400">
          <xref href="#topic14" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="kd158404">
          <xref href="#topic15" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic14" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="kd158410">Prerequisites</title>
      <body>
        <ul id="ul_irb_crz_rz">
          <li id="kd158414">Kerberos must be installed and configured on the Greenplum Database
            master host. <note type="important">Greenplum Database must be configured so that a
              remote user can connect to Greenplum Database with Kerberos authentication.
              Authorization to access Greenplum Database is controlled by the
                <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file. For details, see "Editing the pg_hba.conf File"
              in the <i>Greenplum Database Administration Guide</i>, and also see the <i>Greenplum
                Database Security Configuration Guide</i>.</note></li>
          <li id="kd158429">The client system requires the Kerberos configuration file
              <codeph>krb5.conf</codeph> from the Greenplum Database master. </li>
          <li id="kd158433">The client system requires a Kerberos keytab file that contains the
            authentication credentials for the Greenplum Database user that is used to log into the
            database. </li>
          <li id="kd158440">The client machine must be able to connect to Greenplum Database master
            host. <p>If necessary, add the Greenplum Database master host name and IP address to the
              system <codeph>hosts</codeph> file. On Linux systems, the <codeph>hosts</codeph> file
              is in <codeph>/etc</codeph>.</p></li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic15" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="kd158447">Required Software on the Client Machine</title>
      <body>
        <ul id="ul_jrb_crz_rz">
          <li id="kd158448">The Kerberos <codeph>kinit</codeph> utility is required on the client
            machine. The <codeph>kinit</codeph> utility is available when you install the Kerberos
            packages: <p>
              <ul id="ul_qkg_zhr_l4">
                <li>krb5-libs</li>
                <li>krb5-workstation</li>
              </ul>
              <note>When you install the Kerberos packages, you can use other Kerberos utilities
                such as <codeph>klist</codeph> to display Kerberos ticket information. </note>
            </p></li>
        </ul>
        <p>Java applications require this additional software:<ul id="ul_w5p_pxj_h1b">
            <li id="kd158450">Java JDK <p>Java JDK 1.7.0_17 is supported on Red Hat Enterprise Linux
                6.x. </p></li>
            <li id="kd158455">Ensure that JAVA_HOME is set to the installation directory of the
              supported Java JDK. </li>
          </ul></p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic17" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="kd158460">Setting Up Client System with Kerberos Authentication</title>
    <body>
      <p>To connect to Greenplum Database with Kerberos authentication requires a Kerberos ticket.
        On client systems, tickets are generated from Kerberos keytab files with the
          <codeph>kinit</codeph> utility and are stored in a cache file.</p>
      <ol id="ol_lrb_crz_rz">
        <li id="kd158467">Install a copy of the Kerberos configuration file
            <codeph>krb5.conf</codeph> from the Greenplum Database master. The file is used by the
          Greenplum Database client software and the Kerberos utilities. <p>Install
              <codeph>krb5.conf</codeph> in the directory <codeph>/etc</codeph>. </p><p>If needed,
            add the parameter <codeph>default_ccache_name</codeph> to the
              <codeph>[libdefaults]</codeph> section of the <codeph>krb5.ini</codeph> file and
            specify location of the Kerberos ticket cache file on the client system. </p></li>
        <li id="kd158474">Obtain a Kerberos keytab file that contains the authentication credentials
          for the Greenplum Database user. </li>
        <li id="kd158478">Run <codeph>kinit</codeph> specifying the keytab file to create a ticket
          on the client machine. For this example, the keytab file
            <codeph>gpdb-kerberos.keytab</codeph> is in the the current directory. The ticket cache
          file is in the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user home directory.
          <codeblock>&gt; kinit -k -t gpdb-kerberos.keytab -c /home/gpadmin/cache.txt 
   gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb@KRB.EXAMPLE.COM</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic12" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="mh151086">Running psql </title>
    <body>
      <p>From a remote system, you can access a Greenplum Database that has Kerberos authentication
        enabled. </p>
      <section id="mh151095">
        <title>To connect to Greenplum Database with psql</title>
        <ol id="ol_xzc_lxj_h1b">
          <li id="mh151096">As the gpadmin user, open a command window. </li>
          <li id="mh151099">Start <codeph>psql</codeph> from the command window and specify a
            connection to the Greenplum Database specifying the user that is configured with
            Kerberos authentication.<p>The following example logs into the Greenplum Database on the
              machine <codeph>kerberos-gpdb</codeph> as the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user with the
              Kerberos credentials
            <codeph>gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb</codeph>:</p><codeblock>$ psql -U "gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb" -h kerberos-gpdb postgres</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic18" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="kd158481">Running a Java Application </title>
    <body>
      <p>Accessing Greenplum Database from a Java application with Kerberos authentication uses the
        Java Authentication and Authorization Service (JAAS) </p>
      <ol id="ol_mrb_crz_rz">
        <li id="kd158486">Create the file <codeph>.java.login.config</codeph> in the user home
          folder. <p>For example, on a Linux system, the home folder is similar to
              <codeph>/home/gpadmin</codeph>. </p><p>Add the following text to the
          file:</p><codeblock>pgjdbc {
  com.sun.security.auth.module.Krb5LoginModule required
  doNotPrompt=true
  useTicketCache=true
  ticketCache = "/home/gpadmin/cache.txt"
  debug=true
  client=true;
};</codeblock></li>
        <li id="kd158493">Create a Java application that connects to Greenplum Database using
          Kerberos authentication and run the application as the user. </li>
      </ol>
      <p>This example database connection URL uses a PostgreSQL JDBC driver and specifies parameters
        for Kerberos authentication.</p>
      <codeblock>jdbc:postgresql://kerberos-gpdb:5432/mytest? 
  kerberosServerName=postgres&amp;jaasApplicationName=pgjdbc&amp; 
  user=gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb</codeblock>
      <p>The parameter names and values specified depend on how the Java application performs
        Kerberos authentication.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
