<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_z4g_32q_54">
  <title>Using LDAP Authentication with TLS/SSL </title>
  <shortdesc>You can control access to Greenplum Database with an LDAP server and, optionally,
    secure the connection with encryption by adding parameters to <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath>
    file entries.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum Database supports LDAP authentication with the TLS/SSL protocol to encrypt
      communication with an LDAP server: <ul id="ul_eyn_1gq_54">
        <li>LDAP authentication with STARTTLS and TLS protocol &#8211; STARTTLS starts with a clear
          text connection (no encryption) and upgrades it to a secure connection (with
          encryption).</li>
        <li>LDAP authentication with a secure connection and TLS/SSL (LDAPS) &#8211; Greenplum
          Database uses the TLS or SSL protocol based on the protocol that is used by the LDAP
          server. </li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>If no protocol is specified, Greenplum Database communicates with the LDAP server with a
      clear text connection.</p>
    <p>To use LDAP authentication, the Greenplum Database master host must be configured as an LDAP
      client. See your LDAP documentation for information about configuring LDAP clients.</p>
    <section>
      <title>Enabing LDAP Authentication with STARTTLS and TLS</title>
      <p>To enable STARTTLS with the TLS protocol, in the pg_hba.conf file, add an
          <codeph>ldap</codeph> line and specify the <codeph>ldaptls</codeph> parameter with the
        value 1. The default port is 389. In this example, the authentication method parameters
        include the <codeph>ldaptls</codeph> parameter.
        <codeblock>ldap ldapserver=myldap.com ldaptls=1 ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=example,dc=com"</codeblock></p>
      <p>Specify a non-default port with the <codeph>ldapport</codeph> parameter. In this example,
        the authentication method includes the <codeph>ldaptls</codeph> parameter and the
          <codeph>ldapport</codeph> parameter to specify the port
        550.<codeblock>ldap ldapserver=myldap.com ldaptls=1 ldapport=500 ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=example,dc=com"</codeblock></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Enabing LDAP Authentication with a Secure Connection and TLS/SSL </title>
      <p>To enable a secure connection with TLS/SSL, add <codeph>ldaps://</codeph> as the prefix to
        the LDAP server name specified in the <codeph>ldapserver</codeph> parameter. The default
        port is 636.</p>
      <p>This example <codeph>ldapserver</codeph> parameter specifies a secure connection and the
        TLS/SSL protocol for the LDAP server <codeph>myldap.com</codeph>.</p>
      <codeblock>ldapserver=ldaps://myldap.com</codeblock>
      <p>To specify a non-default port, add a colon (:) and the port number after the LDAP server
        name. This example <codeph>ldapserver</codeph> parameter includes the
          <codeph>ldaps://</codeph> prefix and the non-default port 550.</p>
      <codeblock>ldapserver=ldaps://myldap.com:550</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Configuring Authentication with a System-wide OpenLDAP System</title>
      <p>If you have a system-wide OpenLDAP system and logins are configured to use LDAP with TLS or
        SSL in the pg_hba.conf file, logins may fail with the following
        message:<codeblock>could not start LDAP TLS session: error code '-11'</codeblock></p>
      <p>To use an existing OpenLDAP system for authentication, Greenplum Database must be set up to
        use the LDAP server's CA certificate to validate user certificates. Follow these steps on
        both the master and standby hosts to configure Greenplum Database:<ol id="ol_k5c_s3h_4v">
          <li>Copy the base64-encoded root CA chain file from the Active Directory or LDAP server to
            the Greenplum Database master and standby master hosts. This example uses the directory
              <codeph>/etc/pki/tls/certs</codeph>.</li>
          <li>Change to the directory where you copied the CA certificate file and, as the root
            user, generate the hash for
            OpenLDAP:<codeblock># cd /etc/pki/tls/certs  
# openssl x509 -noout -hash -in &lt;ca-certificate-file>  
# ln -s &lt;ca-certificate-file> &lt;ca-certificate-file>.0</codeblock></li>
          <li>Configure an OpenLDAP configuration file for Greenplum Database with the CA
            certificate directory and certificate file specified.<p>As the root user, edit the
              OpenLDAP configuration file
              <codeph>/etc/openldap/ldap.conf</codeph>:</p><codeblock>SASL_NOCANON on
 URI ldaps://ldapA.example.priv ldaps://ldapB.example.priv ldaps://ldapC.example.priv
 BASE dc=example,dc=priv
 TLS_CACERTDIR /etc/pki/tls/certs
 TLS_CACERT /etc/pki/tls/certs/&lt;ca-certificate-file></codeblock><note>For
              certificate validation to succeed, the hostname in the certificate must match a
              hostname in the URI property. Otherwise, you must also add <codeph>TLS_REQCERT
                allow</codeph> to the file.</note></li>
          <li>As the gpadmin user, edit <codeph>/usr/local/greenplum-db/greenplum_path.sh</codeph>
            and add the following
            line.<codeblock>export LDAPCONF=/etc/openldap/ldap.conf</codeblock></li>
        </ol></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p>Greenplum Database logs an error if the following are specified in an
          <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file entry: <ul id="ul_cws_m3q_54">
          <li>If both the <codeph>ldaps://</codeph> prefix and the <codeph>ldaptls=1</codeph>
            parameter are specified.</li>
          <li>If both the <codeph>ldaps://</codeph> prefix and the <codeph>ldapport</codeph>
            parameter are specified.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>Enabling encrypted communication for LDAP authentication only encrypts the communication
        between Greenplum Database and the LDAP server. </p>
      <p>See <xref href="client_auth.xml#topic5" format="dita"/> for information
        about encrypting client connections. </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>These are example entries from an <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> file.</p>
      <p>This example specifies LDAP authentication with no encryption between Greenplum Database
        and the LDAP server. </p>
      <codeblock>host all plainuser 0.0.0.0/0 ldap ldapserver=myldap.com ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=example,dc=com"</codeblock>
      <p>This example specifies LDAP authentication with the STARTTLS and TLS protocol between
        Greenplum Database and the LDAP server. </p>
      <codeblock>host all tlsuser 0.0.0.0/0 ldap ldapserver=myldap.com ldaptls=1 ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=example,dc=com" </codeblock>
      <p>This example specifies LDAP authentication with a secure connection and TLS/SSL protocol
        between Greenplum Database and the LDAP server. </p>
      <codeblock>host all ldapsuser 0.0.0.0/0 ldap ldapserver=ldaps://myldap.com ldapprefix="uid=" ldapsuffix=",ou=People,dc=example,dc=com"</codeblock>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
