<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="ja155679">Defining Database Performance</title>
  <shortdesc>Managing system performance includes measuring performance, identifying the causes of
    performance problems, and applying the tools and techniques available to you to remedy the
    problems. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum measures database performance based on the rate at
      which the database management system (DBMS) supplies information to requesters.</p>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic2" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ja155234">Understanding the Performance Factors</title>
    <body>
      <p>Several key performance factors influence database performance. Understanding these factors
        helps identify performance opportunities and avoid problems:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="ja155414">
          <xref href="#topic3" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="ja155435">
          <xref href="#topic4" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="ja155440">
          <xref href="#topic5" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="ja155445">
          <xref href="#topic6" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="ja155450">
          <xref href="#topic7" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic3" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ja150771">System Resources</title>
      <body>
        <p>Database performance relies heavily on disk I/O and memory usage. To accurately set
          performance expectations, you need to know the baseline performance of the hardware on
          which your DBMS is deployed. Performance of hardware components such as CPUs, hard disks,
          disk controllers, RAM, and network interfaces will significantly affect how fast your
          database performs.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic4" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ja151122">Workload</title>
      <body>
        <p>The workload equals the total demand from the DBMS, and it varies over time. The total
          workload is a combination of user queries, applications, batch jobs, transactions, and
          system commands directed through the DBMS at any given time. For example, it can increase
          when month-end reports are run or decrease on weekends when most users are out of the
          office. Workload strongly influences database performance. Knowing your workload and peak
          demand times helps you plan for the most efficient use of your system resources and
          enables processing the largest possible workload.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic5" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ja150729">Throughput</title>
      <body>
        <p>A system's throughput defines its overall capability to process data. DBMS throughput is
          measured in queries per second, transactions per second, or average response times. DBMS
          throughput is closely related to the processing capacity of the underlying systems (disk
          I/O, CPU speed, memory bandwidth, and so on), so it is important to know the throughput
          capacity of your hardware when setting DBMS throughput goals.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic6" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ja150733">Contention</title>
      <body>
        <p>Contention is the condition in which two or more components of the workload attempt to
          use the system in a conflicting way — for example, multiple queries that try to update the
          same piece of data at the same time or multiple large workloads that compete for system
          resources. As contention increases, throughput decreases.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic7" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ja155364">Optimization</title>
      <body>
        <p>DBMS optimizations can affect the overall system performance. SQL formulation, database
          configuration parameters, table design, data distribution, and so on enable the database
          query optimizer to create the most efficient access plans.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic8" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ja150561">Determining Acceptable Performance</title>
    <body>
      <p>When approaching a performance tuning initiative, you should know your system's expected
        level of performance and define measurable performance requirements so you can accurately
        evaluate your system's performance. Consider the following when setting performance
        goals:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="ja150844">
          <xref href="#topic9" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="ja151014">
          <xref href="#topic10" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic9" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ja150845">Baseline Hardware Performance</title>
      <body>
        <p>Most database performance problems are caused not by the database, but by the underlying
          systems on which the database runs. I/O bottlenecks, memory problems, and network issues
          can notably degrade database performance. Knowing the baseline capabilities of your
          hardware and operating system (OS) will help you identify and troubleshoot
          hardware-related problems before you explore database-level or query-level tuning
          initiatives. </p>
        <p>See the <i>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</i> for information about
          running the <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> utility to validate hardware and network
          performance.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic10" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ja155920">Performance Benchmarks</title>
      <body>
        <p>To maintain good performance or fix performance issues, you should know the capabilities
          of your DBMS on a defined workload. A benchmark is a predefined workload that produces a
          known result set. Periodically run the same benchmark tests to help identify
          system-related performance degradation over time. Use benchmarks to compare workloads and
          identify queries or applications that need optimization.</p>
        <p>Many third-party organizations, such as the Transaction Processing Performance Council
          (TPC), provide benchmark tools for the database industry. TPC provides TPC-H, a decision
          support system that examines large volumes of data, executes queries with a high degree of
          complexity, and gives answers to critical business questions. For more information about
          TPC-H, go to:</p>
        <p>
          <xref href="http://www.tpc.org/tpch" scope="external" format="html">
            <ph>http://www.tpc.org/tpch</ph>
          </xref>
        </p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</topic>
