<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="iz173472">Managing Resources</title>
  <shortdesc>Greenplum Database provides features to help you prioritize and allocate resources to
    queries according to business requirements and to prevent queries from starting when resources
    are unavailable.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>You can use resource management features to limit the number of concurrent queries, the
      amount of memory used to execute a query, and the relative amount of CPU devoted to processing
      a query. Greenplum Database provides two schemes to manage resources - Resource Queues and
      Resource Groups.</p>
    <note type="important">Significant Greenplum Database performance degradation has been observed
      when enabling resource group-based workload management on RedHat 6.x, CentOS 6.x, and SuSE 11
      systems. This issue is caused by a Linux cgroup kernel bug. This kernel bug has been fixed in
      CentOS 7.x and Red Hat 7.x systems. <p>If you use RedHat 6 and the performance with resource
        groups is acceptable for your use case, upgrade your kernel to version 2.6.32-696 or higher
        to benefit from other fixes to the cgroups implementation. </p><p>SuSE 11 does not have a
        kernel version that resolves this issue; resource groups are still considered to be an
        experimental feature on this platform. <ph otherprops="pivotal">Resource groups are not
          supported on SuSE 11 for production use.</ph></p></note>
    <p>Either the resource queue or the resource group management scheme can be active in Greenplum
      Database; both schemes cannot be active at the same time.</p>
    <p>Resource queues are enabled by default when you install your Greenplum Database cluster.
      While you can create and assign resource groups when resource queues are active, you must
      explicitly enable resource groups to start using that management scheme.</p>
    <p>The following table summarizes some of the differences between Resource Queues and Resource
      Groups.</p>
    <table id="queue_group_compare">
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry colname="col1">Metric</entry>
            <entry colname="col2">Resource Queues</entry>
            <entry colname="col3">Resource Groups</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry colname="col1">Concurrency</entry>
            <entry colname="col2">Managed at the query level</entry>
            <entry colname="col3">Managed at the transaction level</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="col1">CPU</entry>
            <entry colname="col2">Specify query priority</entry>
            <entry colname="col3">Specify percentage of CPU resources; uses Linux Control
              Groups</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="col1">Memory</entry>
            <entry colname="col2">Managed at the queue and operator level; users can
              over-subscribe</entry>
            <entry colname="col3">Managed at the transaction level, with enhanced allocation and
              tracking; users cannot over-subscribe</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="col1">Memory Isolation</entry>
            <entry colname="col2">None</entry>
            <entry colname="col3">Memory is isolated between resource groups and between
              transactions within the same resource group</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="col1">Users</entry>
            <entry colname="col2">Limits are applied only to non-admin users</entry>
            <entry colname="col3">Limits are applied to <codeph>SUPERUSER</codeph> and non-admin
              users alike</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="col1">Queueing</entry>
            <entry colname="col2">Queue only when no slot available</entry>
            <entry colname="col3">Queue when no slot is available or not enough available
              memory</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="col1">Query Failure</entry>
            <entry colname="col2">Query may fail immediately if not enough memory</entry>
            <entry colname="col3">Query may fail after reaching transaction memory limit</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry colname="col1">Limit Bypass</entry>
            <entry colname="col2">Limits are not enforced for <codeph>SUPERUSER</codeph> roles and
              certain operators and functions</entry>
            <entry colname="col3">Limits are not enforced on <codeph>SET</codeph>, <codeph>RESET</codeph>, and <codeph>SHOW</codeph> commands</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </body>
</topic>
