<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="iz173472">Greenplum Database Memory Overview</title>
    <shortdesc>Memory is a key resource for a Greenplum Database system and, when used efficiently,
      can ensure high performance and throughput. This topic describes how segment host memory is
      allocated between segments and the options available to administrators to configure
      memory.</shortdesc>
    <body id="body_bk2_fvw_wq">
      <p>A Greenplum Database segment host runs multiple PostgreSQL instances, all sharing the
        host's memory. The segments have an identical configuration and they consume similar amounts
        of memory, CPU, and disk IO simultaneously, while working on queries in parallel. </p>
      <p>For best query throughput, the memory configuration should be managed carefully. There are
        memory configuration options at every level in Greenplum Database, from operating system
        parameters, to managing resources with resource queues and resource groups, to setting the amount of memory
        allocated to an individual query.</p>
      <section>
        <title>Segment Host Memory</title>
        <p>On a Greenplum Database segment host, the available host memory is shared among all the
          processes executing on the computer, including the operating system, Greenplum Database
          segment instances, and other application processes. Administrators must determine what
          Greenplum Database and non-Greenplum Database processes share the hosts' memory and
          configure the system to use the memory efficiently. It is equally important to monitor
          memory usage regularly to detect any changes in the way host memory is consumed by
          Greenplum Database or other processes.</p>
        <p>The following figure illustrates how memory is consumed on a Greenplum Database segment
            host when resource queue-based resource management is active.<fig id="fig_py5_1sl_zp">
            <title>Greenplum Database Segment Host Memory</title>
            <image href="graphics/memory.png" id="image_iqn_dsl_zp"/>
          </fig></p>
        <p>Beginning at the bottom of the illustration, the line labeled <i>A</i> represents the
          total host memory. The line directly above line <i>A</i> shows that the total host memory
          comprises both physical RAM and swap space. </p>
        <p>The line labelled <i>B</i> shows that the total memory available must be shared by
          Greenplum Database and all other processes on the host. Non-Greenplum Database processes
          include the operating system and any other applications, for example system monitoring
          agents. Some applications may use a significant portion of memory and, as a result, you
          may have to adjust the number of segments per Greenplum Database host or the amount of
          memory per segment.</p>
        <p>The segments (<i>C</i>) each get an equal share of the Greenplum Database Memory
            (<i>B</i>). </p>
        <p>Within a segment, the currently active resource management scheme, <i>Resource Queues</i>
        or <i>Resource Groups</i>, governs how memory is allocated to execute a SQL statement. These
        constructs allow you to translate business requirements into execution policies in your
        Greenplum Database system and to guard against queries that could degrade performance. For
        an overview of resource groups and resource queues, refer to <xref href="wlmgmt.xml#topic1"
          type="topic" format="dita"/>.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Options for Configuring Segment Host Memory</title>
        <p>Host memory is the total memory shared by all applications on the segment host. You
          can configure the amount of host memory using any of the following methods:<ul
            id="ul_y5m_xzs_zp">
            <li>Add more RAM to the nodes to increase the physical memory.</li>
            <li>Allocate swap space to increase the size of virtual memory.</li>
            <li>Set the kernel parameters <varname>vm.overcommit_memory</varname> and
                <varname>vm.overcommit_ratio</varname> to configure how the operating system handles
              large memory allocation requests.</li>
          </ul></p>
        <p>The physical RAM and OS configuration are usually managed by the platform team and system
        administrators. See the <xref href="../install_guide/prep_os.html#topic3" format="dita"
          scope="peer">Greenplum Database Installation Guide</xref> for the recommended kernel
        parameters and for how to set the <codeph>/etc/sysctl.conf</codeph> file parameters.</p>
        <p>The amount of memory to reserve for the operating system and other processes is workload
          dependent. The minimum recommendation for operating system memory is 32GB, but if there is
          much concurrency in Greenplum Database, increasing to 64GB of reserved memory may be
          required. The largest user of operating system memory is SLAB, which increases as
          Greenplum Database concurrency and the number of sockets used increases.</p>
        <p>The <codeph>vm.overcommit_memory</codeph> kernel parameter should always be set to 2, the
          only safe value for Greenplum Database.</p>
        <p>The <codeph>vm.overcommit_ratio</codeph> kernel parameter sets the percentage of RAM that
          is used for application processes, the remainder reserved for the operating system. The
          default for Red Hat is 50 (50%). Setting this parameter too high may result in
          insufficient memory reserved for the operating system, which can cause segment host
          failure or database failure. Leaving the setting at the default of 50 is generally safe,
          but conservative. Setting the value too low reduces the amount of concurrency and the
          complexity of queries you can run at the same time by reducing the amount of memory available to
          Greenplum Database. When increasing <codeph>vm.overcommit_ratio</codeph>, it is important
          to remember to always reserve some memory for operating system activities.</p>

      <sectiondiv>
        <p><b>Configuring vm.overcommit_ratio when Resource Group-Based Resource Management is Active</b></p>
        <p>When resource group-based resource management is active, tune the operating system <codeph>vm.overcommit_ratio</codeph> as necessary. If your memory utilization is too low, increase the value; if your memory or swap usage is too high, decrease the setting.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p><b>Configuring vm.overcommit_ratio when Resource Queue-Based Resource Management is Active</b></p>
        <p>To calculate a safe value for <codeph>vm.overcommit_ratio</codeph> when resource queue-based resource management is active, first determine the
          total memory available to Greenplum Database processes, <codeph>gp_vmem_rq</codeph>,
          with this
          formula:<codeblock>gp_vmem_rq = ((SWAP + RAM) – (7.5GB + 0.05 * RAM)) / 1.7</codeblock></p>
        <p>where <codeph>SWAP</codeph> is the swap space on the host in GB, and <codeph>RAM</codeph>
          is the number of GB of RAM installed on the host. When resource queue-based resource management is active, use <codeph>gp_vmem_rq</codeph> to calculate the <codeph>vm.overcommit_ratio</codeph> value with this
          formula:<codeblock>vm.overcommit_ratio = (RAM - 0.026 * gp_vmem_rq) / RAM</codeblock></p>
      </sectiondiv>
      </section>
      <section id="section_nfn_q5r_bs">
        <title>Configuring Greenplum Database Memory</title>
        <p>Greenplum Database Memory is the amount of memory available to all Greenplum Database
          segment instances. </p>
        <p>When you set up the Greenplum Database cluster, you determine the number of primary
          segments to run per host and the amount of memory to allocate for each segment. Depending
          on the CPU cores, amount of physical RAM, and workload characteristics, the number of
          segments is usually a value between 4 and 8. With segment mirroring enabled, it is
          important to allocate memory for the maximum number of primary segments executing on a
          host during a failure. For example, if you use the default grouping mirror configuration,
          a segment host failure doubles the number of acting primaries on the host that has the
          failed host's mirrors. Mirror configurations that spread each host's mirrors over multiple
          other hosts can lower the maximum, allowing more memory to be allocated for each segment.
          For example, if you use a block mirroring configuration with 4 hosts per block and 8
          primary segments per host, a single host failure would cause other hosts in the block to
          have a maximum of 11 active primaries, compared to 16 for the default grouping mirror
          configuration.</p>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p><b>Configuring Segment Memory when Resource Group-Based Resource Management is Active</b></p>
        <p>When resource group-based resource management is active, the amount of memory allocated
          to each segment on a segment host is the memory available to Greenplum Database multiplied by the
          <varname>gp_resource_group_memory_limit</varname> server configuration parameter and
          divided by the number of active primary segments on the host. Use the following
          formula to calculate segment memory when using resource groups for
          resource management.</p>
        <p><codeblock>
rg_perseg_mem = ((RAM * (vm.overcommit_ratio / 100) + SWAP) * gp_resource_group_memory_limit) / num_active_primary_segments</codeblock></p>
        <p>Resource groups expose additional configuration parameters that
           enable you to further control and refine the amount of memory allocated for queries.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p><b>Configuring Segment Memory when Resource Queue-Based Resource Management is Active</b></p>
        <p>When resource queue-based resource management is active, the <varname>gp_vmem_protect_limit</varname> server configuration parameter value 
          identifies the amount of memory to allocate to
          each segment. This value is estimated by calculating the memory available for all Greenplum
          Database processes and dividing by the maximum number of primary segments during a
          failure. If <varname>gp_vmem_protect_limit</varname> is set too high, queries can
          fail. Use the following formula to calculate a safe value for
          <varname>gp_vmem_protect_limit</varname>; provide the <codeph>gp_vmem_rq</codeph>
          value that you calculated earlier.</p><p><codeblock>
gp_vmem_protect_limit = gp_vmem_rq / max_acting_primary_segments</codeblock></p>
          <p>where <codeph>max_acting_primary_segments</codeph> is the maximum number of
          primary segments that could be running on a host when mirror segments are activated
          due to a host or segment failure.</p>
        <p><varname>gp_vmem_protect_limit</varname> does not affect segment memory when using 
          resource groups for Greenplum Database resource management.</p>
        <p>Resource queues expose additional configuration parameters that
           enable you to further control and refine the amount of memory allocated for queries.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      </section>
      <section id="section_example">
        <title>Example Memory Configuration Calculations</title>
        <p>This section provides example memory calculations for resource queues and
          resource groups for a Greenplum Database system with the following specifications:</p>
        <ul id="ul_q4x_g1g_zt">
          <li>Total RAM = 256GB </li>
          <li>Swap = 64GB </li>
          <li>8 primary segments and 8 mirror segments per host, in blocks of 4 hosts</li>
          <li>Maximum number of primaries per host during failure is 11</li>
        </ul>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p><b>Resource Group Example</b></p>
          <p>When resource group-based resource management is active in Greenplum
            Database, the usable memory available on a host is a function of 
            the amount of RAM and swap space configured for the system, as well as the
            <codeph>vm.overcommit_ratio</codeph> system parameter setting:</p>
            <codeblock>
total_node_usable_memory = RAM * (vm.overcommit_ratio / 100) + Swap
                         = 256GB * (50/100) + 64GB
                         = 192GB</codeblock>
          <p>Assuming the default <codeph>gp_resource_group_memory_limit</codeph> value (.7),
            the memory allocated to a Greenplum Database host with the example configuration is:</p>
        <codeblock>
total_gp_memory = total_node_usable_memory * gp_resource_group_memory_limit
                = 192GB * .7
                = 134.4GB</codeblock>
          <p>The memory available to a Greenplum Database segment on a segment host is a function
            of the memory reserved for Greenplum on the host and the number of active primary
            segments on the host. On cluster startup:</p>
        <codeblock>
gp_seg_memory = total_gp_memory / number_of_active_primary_segments
              = 134.4GB / 8
              = 16.8GB</codeblock>
          <p>Note that when 3 mirror segments switch to primary segments, the per-segment
            memory is still 16.8GB. Total memory usage on the segment host may approach:
            <codeblock>total_gp_memory_with_primaries = 16.8GB * 11 = 184.8GB</codeblock></p>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv>
        <p><b>Resource Queue Example</b></p>
        <p>The <codeph>vm.overcommit_ratio</codeph>
          calculation for the example system when resource queue-based resource management
          is active in Greenplum Database follows:</p>
        <codeblock>
gp_vmem_rq = ((SWAP + RAM) – (7.5GB + 0.05 * RAM)) / 1.7
        = ((64 + 256) - (7.5 + 0.05 * 256)) / 1.7
        = 176

vm.overcommit_ratio = (RAM - (0.026 * gp_vmem_rq)) / RAM
                    = (256 - (0.026 * 176)) / 256
                    = .982</codeblock>
        <p>You would set <codeph>vm.overcommit_ratio</codeph> of the example system to 98. </p>
        <p>The <codeph>gp_vmem_protect_limit</codeph> calculation when resource queue-based
        resource management is active in Greenplum Database:</p>
        <codeblock>
gp_vmem_protect_limit = gp_vmem_rq / maximum_acting_primary_segments
                      = 176 / 11
                      = 16GB
                      = 16384MB
</codeblock>
        <p>You would set the <codeph>gp_vmem_protect_limit</codeph> server configuration
          parameter on the example system to 16384.</p>
      </sectiondiv>
      </section>

    </body>
</topic>
