<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="greenplum_database_ports_and_protocols">
  <title>Greenplum Database Ports and Protocols</title>
  <shortdesc>Lists network ports and protocols used within the Greenplum cluster.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum Database clients connect with TCP to the Greenplum master instance at the client
      connection port, 5432 by default. The listen port can be reconfigured in the
        <filepath>postgresql.conf</filepath> configuration file. Client connections use the
      PostgreSQL libpq API. The <codeph>psql</codeph> command-line interface, several Greenplum
      utilities, and language-specific programming APIs all either use the libpq library directly or
      implement the libpq protocol internally. </p>
    <p>Each segment instance also has a client connection port, used solely by the master instance
      to coordinate database operations with the segments. The <codeph>gpstate -p</codeph> command,
      executed on the Greenplum master, lists the port assignments for the Greenplum master and the
      primary segments and mirrors. For example:
      <codeblock>[gpadmin@mdw ~]$ gpstate -p
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-Starting gpstate with args: -p
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-local Greenplum Version: 'postgres (Greenplum Database) 4.3.6.0 build 62994'
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-master Greenplum Version: 'PostgreSQL 8.2.15 (Greenplum Database 4.3.6.0 build 62994) on x86_64-unknown-linux-gnu, compiled by GCC gcc (GCC) 4.4.2 compiled on Jul 24 2015 11:35:08'
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-Obtaining Segment details from master...
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:--Master segment instance  /data/master/gpseg-1  port = 5432
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:--Segment instance port assignments
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-----------------------------------
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-   Host   Datadir                Port
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-   sdw1   /data/primary/gpseg0   40000
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-   sdw2   /data/mirror/gpseg0    50000
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-   sdw2   /data/primary/gpseg1   40000
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-   sdw1   /data/mirror/gpseg1    50001
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-   sdw3   /data/primary/gpseg2   40000
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-   sdw4   /data/mirror/gpseg2    50000
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-   sdw4   /data/primary/gpseg3   40000
20160126:15:40:22:028389 gpstate:mdw:gpadmin-[INFO]:-   sdw3   /data/mirror/gpseg3    50001
</codeblock></p>
    <p>Additional Greenplum Database network connections are created for features such as standby
      replication, segment mirroring, statistics collection, and data exchange between segments.
      Some persistent connections are established when the database starts up and other transient
      connections are created during operations such as query execution. Transient connections for
      query execution processes, data movement, and statistics collection use available ports in the
      range 1025 to 65535 with both TCP and UDP protocols. </p>
    <p>Some add-on products and services that work with Greenplum Database have additional
      networking requirements. The following table lists ports and protocols used within the
      Greenplum cluster, and includes services and applications that integrate with Greenplum
      Database.</p>
    <table frame="all" rowsep="1" colsep="1" id="table_zf3_lzz_s5">
      <title>Greenplum Database Ports and Protocols</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec colname="newCol1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
        <colspec colname="c1" colnum="2" colwidth="1.0*"/>
        <colspec colname="c3" colnum="3" colwidth="2.0*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Service</entry>
            <entry>Protocol/Port</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Master SQL client connection</entry>
            <entry>TCP 5432, libpq</entry>
            <entry>SQL client connection port on the Greenplum master host. Supports clients using
              the PostgreSQL libpq API. Configurable.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Segment SQL client connection</entry>
            <entry>varies, libpq</entry>
            <entry>The SQL client connection port for a segment instance. Each primary and mirror
              segment on a host must have a unique port. Ports are assigned when the Greenplum
              system is initialized or expanded. The <codeph>gp_segment_configuration</codeph>
              system catalog records port numbers for each segment in the <codeph>port</codeph>
              column. Run <codeph>gpstate -p</codeph> to view the ports in use.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Segment mirroring port</entry>
            <entry>varies, libpq</entry>
            <entry>The port where a segment receives mirrored blocks from its primary. The port is
              assigned when the mirror is set up. The port number is stored in the
                <codeph>gp_segment_configuration</codeph> system catalog in the
                <codeph>mirror_port</codeph> column.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Greenplum Database Interconnect</entry>
            <entry>UDP 1025-65535, dynamically allocated</entry>
            <entry>The Interconnect transports database tuples between Greenplum segments during
              query execution. </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Standby master client listener</entry>
            <entry>TCP 5432, libpq</entry>
            <entry>SQL client connection port on the standby master host. Usually the same as the
              master client connection port. Configure with the <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph>
              utility <codeph>-P</codeph> option.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Standby master replicator</entry>
            <entry>TCP 1025-65535, gpsyncmaster</entry>
            <entry>The <codeph>gpsyncmaster</codeph> process on the master host establishes a
              connection to the secondary master host to replicate the master's log to the standby
              master. </entry>
          </row>
          <row otherprops="pivotal">
            <entry>Greenplum Control Center (GPCC)</entry>
            <entry>TCP 28080, HTTP/HTTPS</entry>
            <entry>Default listen port for the GPCC console web server, which is usually installed
              on the master host. Configured in the <filepath>lighttpd.conf</filepath> file in the
              GPCC instance.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Greenplum database file load and transfer utilities: gpfdist, gpload,
              gptransfer</entry>
            <entry>TCP 8080, HTTP<p>TCP 9000, HTTPS</p></entry>
            <entry>The gpfdist file serving utility can run on Greenplum hosts or external hosts.
              Specify the connection port with the <codeph>-p</codeph> option when starting the
              server. <p>The gpload and gptransfer utilities run one or more instances of gpfdist
                with ports or port ranges specified in a configuration file.</p></entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>GPCC agents</entry>
            <entry>TCP 8888</entry>
            <entry>Connection port for GPCC agents executing on each Greenplum host. Configure by
              setting the <codeph>gpperfmon_port</codeph> configuration variable in
                <filepath>postgresql.conf</filepath> on master and segment hosts.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Backup completion notification</entry>
            <entry>TCP 25, TCP 587, SMTP</entry>
            <entry>The gpcrondump backup utility can optionally send email to a list of email
              addresses at completion of a backup. The SMTP service must be enabled on the Greenplum
              master host. </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Greenplum Database secure shell (SSH): gpssh, gpscp, gpssh-exkeys, gppkg,
              gpseginstall</entry>
            <entry>TCP 22, SSH</entry>
            <entry>Many Greenplum utilities use scp and ssh to transfer files between hosts and
              manage the Greenplum system within the cluster. </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>gphdfs</entry>
            <entry>TCP 8020</entry>
            <entry>The gphdfs protocol allows access to data in a Hadoop file system via Greenplum
              external tables. The URL in the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause of the <codeph>CREATE
                EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> command specifies the host address and port number for the
              Hadoop namenode service. </entry>
          </row>
          <row otherprops="pivotal">
            <entry morerows="2">Greenplum Workload Manager (GP-WLM)</entry>
            <entry>TCP 4369, epmd</entry>
            <entry>Erlang port mapper (epmd) allows nodes in the cluster to resolve node names.
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row otherprops="pivotal">
            <entry>TCP 25672</entry>
            <entry>rabbitmq clustering</entry>
          </row>
          <row otherprops="pivotal">
            <entry>TCP 7777</entry>
            <entry>rabbitmq main port</entry>
          </row>
          <row otherprops="pivotal">
            <entry morerows="3">EMC Data Domain and DD Boost</entry>
            <entry>TCP/UDP 111, NFS portmapper </entry>
            <entry>Used to assign a random port for the mountd service used by NFS and DD Boost. The
              mountd service port can be statically assigned on the Data Domain server.</entry>
          </row>
          <row otherprops="pivotal">
            <entry>TCP 2052</entry>
            <entry>Main port used by NFS mountd. This port can be set on the Data Domain system
              using the <codeph>nfs set mountd-port</codeph> command .</entry>
          </row>
          <row otherprops="pivotal">
            <entry>TCP 2049, NFS</entry>
            <entry>Main port used by NFS. This port can be configured using the <codeph>nfs set
                server-port</codeph> command on the Data Domain server. </entry>
          </row>
          <row otherprops="pivotal">
            <entry>TCP 2051, replication</entry>
            <entry>Used when replication is configured on the Data Domain system. This port can be
              configured using the <codeph>replication modify</codeph> command on the Data Domain
              server.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry morerows="1">Symantec NetBackup</entry>
            <entry>TCP/UDB 1556, veritas-pbx</entry>
            <entry>The Symantec NetBackup client network port. </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>TCP 13724, vnetd</entry>
            <entry>Symantec NetBackup vnetd communication port.</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Pgbouncer connection pooler</entry>
            <entry>TCP, libpq</entry>
            <entry>The pgbouncer connection pooler runs between libpq clients and Greenplum (or
              PostgreSQL) databases. It can be run on the Greenplum master host, but running it on a
              host outside of the Greenplum cluster is recommended. When it runs on a separate host,
              pgbouncer can act as a warm standby mechanism for the Greenplum master host, switching
              to the Greenplum standby host without requiring clients to reconfigure. Set the client
              connection port and the Greenplum master host address and port in the
                <filepath>pgbouncer.ini</filepath> configuration file. </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>stunnel SSL proxy</entry>
            <entry>TCP, ssh, libpq</entry>
            <entry>A stunnel SSL proxy can be used to add SSL support for database clients accessing
              the database through a pgbouncer connection pool. A secure tunnel can be set up by
              setting up stunnel on the client and the pgbouncer host. Newer versions of stunnel
              that support encrypted libpq connections only require stunnel on the pgbouncer host.
              The stunnel proxy's connection ports and the pgbouncer host and port are specified in
              the <filepath>stunnel.conf</filepath> configuration file.</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </body>
</topic>
