<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="pz212122">Greenplum PL/Container Extension</title>
  <body>
    <p>This section includes the following information:</p>
    <ul>
      <li id="pz219023"><xref href="#topic2" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic_tcm_htd_gw" format="dita"/></li>
      <li id="pz213664" otherprops="pivotal"><xref href="#topic3" type="topic" format="dita"/></li>
      <li id="pz213668"><xref href="#topic6" type="topic" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li id="pz215253"><xref href="#topic_rh3_p3q_dw" format="dita"/></li>
      <li><xref href="#topic_ehl_r3q_dw" format="dita"/></li>
      <li><xref href="#topic_lqz_t3q_dw" format="dita"/></li>
      <li><xref href="#topic_sk1_gdq_dw" format="dita"/></li>
      <li><xref href="#topic_ydt_rtc_rbb" format="dita"/></li>
      <li><xref href="#topic_kds_plk_rbb" format="dita"/></li>
    </ul>
    <note type="warning">PL/Container is an experimental feature and is not intended for use in a
      production environment. Experimental features are subject to change without notice in future
      releases.</note>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic2" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="pz217886">About the PL/Container Extension</title>
    <body>
      <p>The Greenplum Database PL/Container extension is an interface that allows Greenplum
        Database to interact with a Docker container to execute a user-defined function (UDF) in the
        container. Docker containers ensure the user code cannot access the file system of the
        source host. Also, containers are started with limited network access and cannot connect
        back to Greenplum Database or open any other external connections. For information about
        available UDF languages, see <xref href="#topic_tcm_htd_gw" format="dita"/></p>
      <p>Generally speaking, a Docker <i>container</i> is a Linux process that runs in a managed way
        by using Linux kernel features such as cgroups, namespaces and union file systems. A Docker
          <i>image</i> is the basis of a container. A Docker container is a running instance of a
        Docker image. When you start a Docker container you specify a Docker image. A Docker image
        is the collection of root filesystem changes and execution parameters that are used when you
        run a Docker container on the host system. An image does not have state and never changes.
        For information about Docker, see the Docker web site <xref href="https://www.docker.com/"
          format="html" scope="external">https://www.docker.com/</xref>. </p>
      <p>Greenplum Database starts a container only on the first call to a function in that
        container. For example, consider a query that selects table data using all available
        segments, and applies a transformation to the data using a PL/Container function. In this
        case, Greenplum Database would start the Docker container only once on each segment, and
        then contact the running container to obtain the results.</p>
      <p>After starting a full cycle of a query execution. The executor sends a call to the
        container. The container might respond with an SPI - SQL query executed by the container to
        get some data back from the database, returning the result to the query executor. For
        set-returning functions these steps might be executed many times.</p>
      <p>The container shuts down when the connection to it is closed. This occurs when you close
        the Greenplum Database session that started the container. A container running in standby
        mode has almost no consumption of CPU resources as it is waiting on the socket. PL/Container
        memory consumption depends on the amount of data you cache in global dictionaries.</p>
      <p>The PL/Container extension is available as an open source module. For information about the
        module, see the README file in the GitHub repository at <xref
          href="https://github.com/greenplum-db/plcontainer" format="html" scope="external"
          >https://github.com/greenplum-db/plcontainer</xref>.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_tcm_htd_gw">
    <title>PL/Container Language Docker Images</title>
    <body>
      <p>Pivotal provides 2 Docker images for customers, a Python image and an R image. The Docker
        images are available under <codeph>pivotaldata</codeph> organization in Docker Hub (<xref
          href="https://hub.docker.com/r/pivotaldata/" format="html" scope="external"
          >https://hub.docker.com/r/pivotaldata/</xref>):</p>
      <ul id="ul_epg_t2v_qbb">
        <li><codeph>plc_python_shared</codeph> - Docker image with Python 2.7.12 installed.<p>The
            Python Data Science Module is also installed. The module contains a set python libraries
            related to data science. <ph otherprops="pivotal">For information about the module, see
                <xref href="../../install_guide/install_python_dsmod.xml" format="dita" scope="peer"
                >Python Data Science Module Package</xref>.</ph></p></li>
      </ul>
      <ul id="ul_fpg_t2v_qbb">
        <li><codeph>plc_r_shared</codeph> - A Docker image with container with R-3.3.3 installed.
            <p>The R Data Science package is also installed. The package contains a set of R
            libraries related to data science. <ph otherprops="pivotal">For information about the
              module, see <xref href="../../install_guide/install_r_dslib.xml" format="dita"
                scope="peer">R Data Science Library Package</xref>.</ph></p></li>
      </ul>
      <p>The Docker container tag represents the PL/Container extension release version (for
        example, 1.0.0). For example, the full container name for <codeph>plc_python_shared</codeph>
        is similar to <codeph>pivotaldata/plc_python_shared:1.0.0, version 1.0.0</codeph>. This is
        the name that is referred to in the default PL/Container configuration. Also, You can also
        create custom Docker images and add the image to the PL/Container configuration. </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_i31_3tr_dw">
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <body>
      <p>Ensure your Greenplum Database system meets the following prerequisites:</p>
      <ul id="ul_ztj_kzp_dw">
        <li>PL/Container is supported on <ph otherprops="pivotal">Pivotal </ph>Greenplum Database
          5.2.x on Red Hat Enterprise Linux (RHEL) 7.x or 6.6+ (or later) and CentOS 7.x or 6.6+ (or
          later).</li>
        <li>These are Docker host operating system prerequisites.<p>RHEL or CentOS 7.x - Minimum
            supported Linux OS kernel version is 3.10. RHEL 7.x and CentOS 7.x use this kernel
            version.</p><p>RHEL or CentOS 6.6+ - Minimum supported Linux OS kernel version
            2.6.32-431</p><p>You can check your kernel version with the command <codeph>uname
              -r</codeph></p><note>The Red Hat provided, maintained, and supported version of Docker
            is only available on RHEL 7. Red Hat does not recommend running any version of Docker on
            any RHEL 6 releases. Docker feature developments are tied to RHEL7.x infrastructure
            components for kernel, devicemapper (thin provisioning, direct lvm), sVirt and
            systemd.</note></li>
      </ul>
      <ul id="ul_b5j_kzp_dw">
        <li>Docker is installed on Greenplum Database hosts (master, primary and all standby
            hosts)<ul id="ul_z2t_bxd_rbb">
            <li>For RHEL or CentOS 7.x - Docker 17.05</li>
            <li>RHEL or CentOS 6.6+ - Docker 1.7</li>
          </ul><p>See <xref href="#topic_ydt_rtc_rbb" format="dita"/>.</p></li>
        <li>On each Greenplum Database host the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user should be part of the
            <codeph>docker</codeph> group for the user to be able to manage Docker images and
          containers.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic3" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="pz214493">Installing the PL/Container Extension</title>
    <body>
      <p>To use PL/Container languages, install PL/Container, install Docker images, and configure
        PL/Container to use the images.<ol id="ol_uw5_xdn_sbb">
          <li>Ensure the Greenplum Database hosts meet the prerequisites, see <xref
              href="#topic_i31_3tr_dw" format="dita"/>.</li>
          <li otherprops="pivotal">Install the PL/Container extension, see <xref
              href="#topic_ifk_2tr_dw" format="dita"/>.</li>
          <li otherprops="oss-only">Build and Install the PL/Container extension from source, see
              <xref href="#topic_i2t_v2n_sbb" format="dita"/>.</li>
          <li>Install Docker images and configure PL/Container, see <xref href="#topic_qcr_bfk_rbb"
              format="dita"/>.</li>
        </ol></p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic_ifk_2tr_dw" otherprops="pivotal">
      <title>Installing the PL/Container Extension Package</title>
      <body>
        <p>Install the PL/Container extension with the Greenplum Database <codeph>gppkg</codeph>
          utility.</p>
        <ol id="ul_w5b_nzp_dw">
          <li>Copy the PL/Container extension package to the Greenplum Database master host as the
              <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user.</li>
          <li>Make sure Greenplum Database is up and running. If not, bring it up with this
            command.<codeblock>gpstart -a</codeblock></li>
          <li>Run the package installation
            command.<codeblock>gppkg -i plcontainer-1.0.0-rhel7-x86_64.gppkg</codeblock></li>
          <li>Source the file
            <codeph>$GPHOME/greenplum_path.sh</codeph>.<codeblock>source $GPHOME/greenplum_path.sh</codeblock></li>
          <li>Restart Greenplum Database.<codeblock>gpstop -ra</codeblock></li>
          <li>Enable PL/Container for specific databases by
              running<codeblock>psql -d <codeph>your_database</codeph> -f $GPHOME/share/postgresql/plcontainer/plcontainer_install.sql</codeblock><p>The
              SQL script registers the language <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> in the database creates
              PL/Container specific UDFs.</p></li>
          <li>Initialize PL/Container configuration on the Greenplum Database hosts by running the
              <codeph>plcontainer configure</codeph>
              command.<codeblock>plcontainer configure --reset</codeblock><p>The
                <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> utility is included with the PL/Container
              extension.</p></li>
        </ol>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_i2t_v2n_sbb" otherprops="oss-only">
      <title>Building and Installing the PL/Container Extension</title>
      <body>
        <p>The PL/Container extension is available as an open source module. For information about
          the building and installing the module as part of Greenplum Database, see the README file
          in the GitHub repository at <xref href="https://github.com/greenplum-db/plcontainer"
            format="html" scope="external">https://github.com/greenplum-db/plcontainer</xref>.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_qcr_bfk_rbb">
    <title>Installing PL/Container Language Docker Images</title>
    <body>
      <p>The PL/Container extension includes the <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> utility that installs
        Docker images in the host Docker repository and adds the installed image to the PL/Container
        configuration. The utility adds the Docker image to all Greenplum Database hosts and updates
        configuration information on all the hosts. For information about
          <codeph>plcontainer</codeph>, see <xref href="#topic_rw3_52s_dw" format="dita"/>.</p>
      <!--Pivotal conent-->
      <p otherprops="pivotal">Download the <codeph>tar.gz</codeph> file that contains the Docker
        images from <xref href="https://network.pivotal.io/products/pivotal-gpdb" scope="external"
          format="html" class="- topic/xref ">Pivotal Network</xref>. <ul id="ul_vsj_pxb_tbb">
          <li><codeph>plcontainer-python-images-1.0.0-beta1.tar.gz</codeph></li>
          <li><codeph>plcontainer-r-images-1.0.0-beta1.tar.gz</codeph></li>
        </ul></p>
      <!--oss only conent-->
      <p otherprops="oss-only">The PL/Container open source module contains dockerfiles to build
        Docker images that can be used with PL/Container. You can build a Docker image to run
        PL/Python UDFs and a Docker image to run PL/R UDFs. See the dockerfiles in the GitHub
        repository at <xref href="https://github.com/greenplum-db/plcontainer" format="html"
          scope="external">https://github.com/greenplum-db/plcontainer</xref>.</p>
      <p>Install the Docker images on the Greenplum Database hosts. These examples use the
          <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> utility to install Docker images for Python and R and add the
        images to the PL/Container configuration. The utility installs the images and configures all
        the Greenplum Database hosts. The examples assume the Docker images are in
          <codeph>/home/gpadmin</codeph>.</p>
      <p>This example runs <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> to install the Docker image for PL/Python
        and add the image to the PL/Container configuration.
        <codeblock>plcontainer install -n plc_python_shared -i /home/gpadmin/plcontainer-python-images-0.9.3.tar.gz \
  -c  pivotaldata/plc_python_shared:1.0.0 \
  -l python -v /tmp:/clientdir:rw</codeblock></p>
      <p>This example runs <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> to install the Docker image for PL/R and add
        the image to the PL/Container configuration.</p>
      <codeblock>plcontainer install -n plc_r -i /home/gpadmin/plcontainer-r-images-0.9.3.tar.gz \
  -c pivotaldata/plc_r_shared:1.0.0 \
  -l r -v /tmp:/clientdir:rw</codeblock>
      <p>You can view the host system Docker repository with the <codeph>docker images</codeph>
        command. The image name specified with the <codeph>-c</codeph> option appears in the list of
        Docker images.</p>
      <p>You can view the updated the PL/Container configuration file with the <codeph>plcontainer
          configure -s</codeph> command. A container element in the configuration XML file with the
        name specified with the <codeph>-n</codeph> option appears in the file. </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic6" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="pz213704">Uninstalling PL/Container</title>
    <body>
      <p>When you remove support for the PL/Container extension, the <codeph>plcontainer</codeph>
        user-defined functions that you created in the database will no longer work. </p>
    </body>
    <topic xml:lang="en" id="topic_qnb_3cj_kw">
      <title>Remove PL/Container Support for a Database</title>
      <body>
        <p>For a database that no long requires PL/Container languages, remove support for
          PL/Container. Run the <codeph>plcontainer_uninstall.sql</codeph> script as the
            <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user. For example, this command removes the
            <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> language in the <codeph>mytest</codeph> database. </p>
        <codeblock>psql -d mytest -f $GPHOME/share/postgresql/plcontainer/plcontainer_uninstall.sql</codeblock>
        <p>The script drops the <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> language with <codeph>CASCADE</codeph>
          to drop functions that depend on the language.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic xml:lang="en" id="topic_dty_fcj_kw" otherprops="pivotal">
      <title>Uninstalling PL/Container Extension</title>
      <body>
        <p>If no databases have <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> as a registered language, uninstall the
          Greenplum Database PL/Container extension with the <codeph>gppkg</codeph> utility. </p>
        <ol id="ol_ety_fcj_kw">
          <li>Use the Greenplum Database <codeph>gppkg</codeph> utility with the <codeph>-r</codeph>
            option to uninstall the PL/Container extension. This example uninstalls the PL/Container
            extension on a Linux
              system:<codeblock>$ gppkg -r plcontainer-1.0.0-rhel7</codeblock><p>You can run the
                <codeph>gppkg</codeph> utility with the options <codeph>-q --all</codeph> to list
              the installed extensions and their versions.</p></li>
          <li>Reload
            <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph>.<codeblock>$ source $GPHOME/greenplum_path.sh</codeblock></li>
          <li>Restart the database.<codeblock>$ gpstop -ra</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_rnb_4s5_lw">
      <title>Uninstall Docker Containers and Images</title>
      <body>
        <p>On the Greenplum Database hosts, uninstall the Docker containers and images that are no
          longer required.<ul id="ul_emd_ts5_lw">
            <li>The command <codeph>docker ps -a</codeph> lists the containers on a host. The
              command <codeph>docker stop</codeph> stops a container.</li>
            <li>The command <codeph>docker images</codeph> lists the images on a host.</li>
            <li>The command <codeph>docker rmi</codeph> removes images.</li>
            <li>The command <codeph>docker rm</codeph> removes containers. </li>
          </ul></p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_rh3_p3q_dw">
    <title>Using PL/Container Languages</title>
    <body>
      <p>When you have enabled the <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> language, you can create and run
        user-defined functions in the procedural languages supported by the PL/Container Docker
        images. To create a UDF that uses PL/Container, the UDF must have the these items.</p>
      <ul id="ul_z2m_1kj_kw">
        <li>The first line of the UDF must be <codeph># container:
          <varname>name</varname></codeph></li>
        <li>The <codeph>LANGUAGE</codeph> attribute must be <codeph>plcontainer</codeph></li>
      </ul>
      <p>The <varname>name</varname> is the name that PL/Container uses to identify the Docker
        container that runs the UDF. in the XML configuration file
          <codeph>plcontainer_configuration.xml</codeph>, there should be a
          <codeph>container</codeph> XML element with a corresponding <codeph>name</codeph> XML
        element that specifies the detail Docker container information. See <xref
          href="#topic_sk1_gdq_dw" format="dita"/> for information about how PL/Container maps the
          <varname>name</varname> to a Docker container.</p>
      <p>The PL/Container configuration file is read only on the first invocation of a PL/Container
        function in each Greenplum Database session that runs PL/Container functions. You can force
        the configuration file to be re-read by calling the function
          <codeph>plcontainer_refresh_config()</codeph> during the session. For example, this
          <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command forces a the configuration file to be read.</p>
      <codeblock>select * from plcontainer_refresh_config();</codeblock>
      <p>Also, you can show all the configurations in the session by calling the function
          <codeph>plcontainer_show_config();</codeph>. For example, this <codeph>SELECT</codeph>
        command returns the PL/Container configurations. </p>
      <codeblock>select * from plcontainer_show_config();</codeblock>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic9" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="pz215232">Examples</title>
      <body>
        <p>This is an example of PL/Python function that runs using the
            <codeph>plc_python_shared</codeph>
          container:<codeblock>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION pylog100() RETURNS double precision AS $$
# container: plc_python_shared
import math
return math.log10(100)
$$ LANGUAGE plcontainer;</codeblock></p>
        <p>This is an example of a similar function using the <codeph>plc_r_shared</codeph>
          container:<codeblock>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION rlog100() RETURNS text AS $$
# container: plc_r_shared
return(log10(100))
$$ LANGUAGE plcontainer;</codeblock></p>
        <p>The PL/Container Docker container that you specify, <codeph>plc_python_shared</codeph>
          and <codeph>plc_r_shared</codeph> in the examples, are the <codeph>name</codeph> elements
          defined in <codeph>plcontainer_config.xml</codeph> file, and they are mapped to the
            <codeph>image</codeph> XML element that specifies the Docker image to be started.
          Removing a specific <codeph>container</codeph> XML element from the configuration file
          makes it impossible for end users to start the container. </p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_ehl_r3q_dw">
    <title>About PL/Container Running PL/Python </title>
    <body>
      <p>In the Python language container, the module <codeph>plpy</codeph> is implemented. The
        module contains these methods:</p>
      <ul id="ul_qfd_mdq_dw">
        <li><codeph>plpy.execute(stmt)</codeph> - Executes the query string <codeph>stmt</codeph>
          and returns query result in a list of dictionary objects. To be able to access the result
          fields ensure your query returns named fields.</li>
        <li><codeph>plpy.prepare(stmt,[, argtypes])</codeph> - Prepares the execution plan for a
          query. It is called with a query string and a list of parameter types, if you have
          parameter references in the query.</li>
        <li><codeph>plpy.execute(plan, ,[, argtypes])</codeph> - Executes a prepared plan.</li>
        <li><codeph>plpy.debug(msg)</codeph> - Send a DEBUG2 message to the Greenplum Database
          log.</li>
        <li><codeph>plpy.log(msg)</codeph> - Send a LOG message to the Greenplum Database log.</li>
        <li><codeph>plpy.info(msg)</codeph> - Send an INFO message to the Greenplum Database
          log.</li>
        <li><codeph>plpy.notice(msg)</codeph> - Send a NOTICE message to the Greenplum Database
          log.</li>
        <li><codeph>plpy.warning(msg)</codeph> - Send a WARNING message to the Greenplum Database
          log.</li>
        <li><codeph>plpy.error(msg)</codeph> - Send an ERROR message to the Greenplum Database log.
          An ERROR message raised in Greenplum Database causes the query execution process to stop
          and the transaction to rollback.</li>
        <li><codeph>plpy.fatal(msg)</codeph> - Send a FATAL message to the Greenplum Database log. A
          FATAL message causes Greenplum Database session to be closed and transaction to be rolled
          back.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Also, the Python module has two global dictionary objects that retain the data between
        function calls. They are named GD and SD. GD is used to share the data between all the
        function running within the same container, while SD is used for sharing the data between
        multiple calls of each separate function. Be aware that accessing the data is possible only
        within the same session, when the container process lives on a segment or master. Be aware
        that for idle sessions Greenplum Database terminates segment processes, which means the
        related containers would be shut down and the data from GD and SD lost.</p>
      <p>For information about PL/Python, see <xref href="pl_python.xml#topic1"/>. </p>
      <p>For information about the <codeph>plpy</codeph> methods, see <xref
          href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/8.4/static/plpython-database.html" format="html"
          scope="external">https://www.postgresql.org/docs/8.4/static/plpython-database.htm</xref>.
      </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_lqz_t3q_dw">
    <title>About PL/Container Running PL/R</title>
    <body>
      <p>In the R language container, the module <codeph>pg.spi</codeph> is implemented. The module
        contains these methods:</p>
      <ul id="ul_mqz_t3q_dw">
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.exec(stmt)</codeph> - Executes the query string <codeph>stmt</codeph> and
          returns query result in R data.frame. To be able to access the result fields make sure
          your query returns named fields.</li>
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.prepare(stmt,[, argtypes])</codeph> - Prepares the execution plan for a
          query. It is called with a query string and a list of parameter types if you have
          parameter references in the query.</li>
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.execp(plan, ,[, argtypes])</codeph> - Execute a prepared plan.</li>
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.debug(msg)</codeph> - Send a DEBUG2 message to the Greenplum Database
          log.</li>
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.log(msg)</codeph> - Send a LOG message to the Greenplum Database
          log.</li>
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.info(msg)</codeph> - Send an INFO message to the Greenplum Database
          log.</li>
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.notice(msg)</codeph> - Send a NOTICE message to the Greenplum Database
          log.</li>
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.warning(msg)</codeph> - Send a WARNING message to the Greenplum Database
          log.</li>
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.error(msg)</codeph> - Send an ERROR message to the Greenplum Database
          log. An ERROR message raised in Greenplum Database causes the query execution process to
          stop and the transaction to rollback.</li>
        <li><codeph>pg.spi.fatal(msg)</codeph> - sSend a FATAL message to the Greenplum Database
          log. A FATAL message causes Greenplum Database session to be closed and transaction to be
          rolled back.</li>
      </ul>
      <p>For information about PL/R, see <xref href="pl_r.xml#topic1"/>.</p>
      <p>For information about the <codeph>pg.spi</codeph> methods, see <xref
          href="http://www.joeconway.com/plr/doc/plr-spi-rsupport-funcs-normal.html" format="html"
          scope="external"
          >http://www.joeconway.com/plr/doc/plr-spi-rsupport-funcs-normal.html</xref></p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_sk1_gdq_dw">
    <title>Configuring PL/Container</title>
    <body>
      <p>The Greenplum Database utility <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> manages the PL/Container
        configuration files in a Greenplum Database system. The utility ensures that the
        configuration files are consistent across the Greenplum Database master and segment
        hosts.</p>
      <note type="warning"> Modifying the configuration files manually might create different,
        incompatible configurations on different Greenplum Database segments that could cause
        unexpected behavior. </note>
      <p>Configuration changes that are made with the utility are applied to the XML files on all
        Greenplum Database segments. However, PL/Container configurations of currently running
        sessions use the configuration that existed during session start up. To update the
        PL/Container configuration in a running session, execute this command in the session.</p>
      <codeblock>select * from plcontainer_refresh_config();</codeblock>
      <p>When you change the <codeph>plcontainer_configuration.xml</codeph> configuration file with
        the <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> utility, the utility creates a back up of the original
        configuration file in the same directory. The backup file name is
            <codeph>plcontainer_configuration.xml.bak<varname>YYYYMMDD</varname>_<varname>hhmmss</varname></codeph>.
        The timestamp of the change is appended to the file name. Using the <codeph>plcontainer
          configure</codeph> command with the <codeph>--restore</codeph> option, you can roll back
        the configuration changes to the previous version.</p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic_rw3_52s_dw">
      <title>plcontainer Utility</title>
      <body>
        <p>The <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> utility installs Docker images and manages the
          PL/Container configuration. The utility consists of two commands.</p>
        <ul id="ul_kxp_byw_qbb">
          <li><codeph>plcontainer configure</codeph> - Manages the PL/Container configuration file
            on the hosts. You can add Docker image information to the PL/Container configuration
            file including the image name, location, and shared folder information. You can also
            edit the configuration file.</li>
          <li><codeph>plcontainer install</codeph> - Install a Docker image in Docker repository and
            add the image information to the PL/Container configuration file on each host.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>The <codeph>plcontainer</codeph> utility
          syntax:<codeblock><b>plcontainer configure</b> {{<b>-n</b> | <b>--name</b>} <varname>container-name</varname>
               {<b>-i</b> | <b>--image</b>} <varname>image-location</varname>
               {<b>-l</b> | <b>--language</b>} <varname>language</varname>
               {<b>-v</b> | <b>--volume</b>} <varname>shared-volumes</varname> } |
             {[<b>-e</b> <b>--editor</b> [<varname>editor</varname>] } |
             { <b>--reset</b> | <b>--restore</b> } |
             { | {<b>-s</b> | <b>--show</b>} | 
             {<b>-f</b> <b>--file</b>} <varname>config-file</varname>} 
             [{<b>-y</b> | <b>--yes</b>)]
             [<b>--verbose</b>] 

<b>plcontainer install</b> {<b>-n</b> | <b>--name</b>} <varname>container-name</varname> 
             {<b>-i</b> | <b>--image</b>} <varname>image-location</varname>
             {<b>-c</b> | <b>--imagename</b>} <varname>docker-image</varname>
             {<b>-l</b> | <b>--language</b>} <varname>language</varname>
             {<b>-v</b> | <b>--volume</b>} <varname>shared-volumes</varname>

<b>plcontainer</b> {<b>configure</b> | <b>install</b>} {<b>-h</b> | <b>--help</b>}</codeblock></p>
        <section>
          <title>Options</title>
          <parml>
            <plentry>
              <pt>{-c | --imagename} <varname>local-image</varname></pt>
              <pd>The utility installs the Docker image on the Greenplum Database hosts with the
                specified Docker name and uses the name in the PL/Container configuration file
                element <codeph>image</codeph> when creating a container element in the
                configuration file.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>{-e | --editor } [<varname>editor</varname>]</pt>
              <pd>Open the file <codeph>plcontainer_configuration.xml</codeph> with the specified
                editor. The default is the <codeph>vi</codeph> editor.</pd>
              <pd>Saving the file updates the configuration file on all Greenplum Database hosts and
                saves the previous version of the file.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>{-f | --file} <varname>config-file</varname></pt>
              <pd>
                <p>The utility replaces the existing PL/Container configuration file with the
                  specified file. Specify the absolute path to a configuration file. The
                  configuration file is replaced on all Greenplum Database hosts.</p>
              </pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>{-i | --image} <varname>docker-image</varname></pt>
              <pd>Specify a full Docker image. For example
                  <codeph>pivotaldata/plcontainer_python:1.0.0</codeph>.<ul id="ul_l5l_jmd_rbb">
                  <li><codeph>configure</codeph> - When creating a <codeph>container</codeph> entry
                    in PL/Container configuration this is the value of configuration file element
                      <codeph>image</codeph>. The Docker image must be installed. </li>
                  <li><codeph>install</codeph> - Installs the Docker image from the specified
                    location. You can specify a URL to a Docker registry or the absolute path to a
                      <codeph>tar.gz</codeph> file that contains a docker image. When installing a
                    docker image, the utility uses <codeph>--imagename
                        <varname>local-image</varname></codeph> for the value of configuration file
                    element <codeph>image</codeph>.</li>
                </ul></pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>{-l | --language} <varname>language</varname></pt>
              <pd>
                <p> Configure PL/Container language type, supported values are
                    <codeph>python</codeph> (PL/Python) and <codeph>r</codeph> (PL/R).</p>
              </pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>{-n | --name} <varname>container-name</varname></pt>
              <pd>When adding a container element in the PL/Container configuration file, this is
                the value of the <codeph>name</codeph> element. You specify the name in the
                Greenplum Database UDF on the <codeph># container</codeph> line. For example, this
                line in a PL/Container UDF <codeph>plc_r_shared</codeph> specifies using the
                information in the <codeph>plc_r_shared</codeph> container element to create a
                Docker container.<codeblock># container: plc_r_shared</codeblock></pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>--reset</pt>
              <pd>Reset the configuration file to the default.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>--restore</pt>
              <pd>Restore the previous version of the PL/Container configuration file.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>-s | --show</pt>
              <pd>Display the contents of the PL/Container configuration file.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>{-v | --volume} <varname>shared-volume</varname></pt>
              <pd>Specify a Docker volume to bind mount. You can specify multiple volumes as a comma
                separated lists of volumes.</pd>
              <pd>The format for a shared volume:
                    <codeph><varname>host-dir</varname>:<varname>container-dir</varname>:[rw|ro]</codeph>.<ul
                  id="ul_k2l_f4d_rbb">
                  <li><varname>host-dir</varname> - absolute path to a directory on the host system.
                    The Greenplum Database administrator user (gpadmin) must have appropiate access
                    to the directory.</li>
                  <li><varname>container-dir</varname> - absolute path to a directory in the Docker
                    container.</li>
                  <li><codeph>[rw|ro]</codeph> - read-write or read-only access to the host
                    directory from the container. Information is stored in the configuration file
                    element shared_directory.</li>
                </ul></pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>--verbose</pt>
              <pd>Enable verbose logging.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>-y | --yes</pt>
              <pd>Continue without confirmation prompts.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
              <pt>h | --help</pt>
              <pd>Display help text.</pd>
            </plentry>
          </parml>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Examples</title>
          <p>The most common commands you would run are the following:</p>
          <ul id="ul_fn5_1bw_qbb">
            <li>
              <p>Initialize the Greenplum Database installation with default configuration file
                after installing a PL/Container
                package:<codeblock>plcontainer configure --reset</codeblock></p>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <ul id="ul_gn5_1bw_qbb">
            <li>
              <p>Edit the configuration in interactive editor of your
                choice:<codeblock>plcontainer configure -e vim</codeblock></p>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <ul id="ul_hn5_1bw_qbb">
            <li>
              <p>Show the current
                configuration:<codeblock>plcontainer configure --show</codeblock></p>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <ul id="ul_in5_1bw_qbb">
            <li>
              <p>Restore previous configuration from the
                backup:<codeblock>plcontainer configure --restore</codeblock></p>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <ul id="ul_jn5_1bw_qbb">
            <li>
              <p>Overwrite plcontainer configurations with xml file directly
                :<codeblock>plcontainer configure -f new_plcontainer_configuration.xml </codeblock></p>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <ul id="ul_kn5_1bw_qbb">
            <li>
              <p>Configure new container entry to plcontainer
                configurations<codeblock>plcontainer configure -n plc_python_newpy -l python
  -i pivotaldata/plc_python_newimage:latest -v /tmp:/clientdir:rw</codeblock></p>
            </li>
          </ul>
          <ul id="ul_ln5_1bw_qbb">
            <li>
              <p>Install new docker image and configure it to plcontainer
                configurations.<codeblock>plcontainer install -n plc_r_newr -i plc_newr.tar.gz -c pivotaldata/plc_r_newr:latest 
  -l r -v /tmp:/clientdir:rw</codeblock></p>
            </li>
          </ul>
        </section>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_ojn_r2s_dw">
      <title>PL/Container Configuration File</title>
      <body>
        <p>The default PL/Container configuration file is in
            <codeph>$GPHOME/share/postgresql/plcontainer/plcontainer_configuration.xml</codeph> of
          each host. The PL/Container configuration file is an XML file. In the XML file, the root
          element <codeph>configuration</codeph> contains a one or more <codeph>container</codeph>
          elements, one element for each PL/Container language in the Greenplum Database
          installation.
          <codeblock>&lt;configuration>
   &lt;container>
      &lt;name>plc_python_shared&lt;/name>
      &lt;image>pivotaldata/plcontainer_python:1.0.0&lt;/image>
      &lt;command>./client&lt;/command>
      &lt;memory_mb>128&lt;/memory_mb>
      &lt;use_network>no&lt;/use_network>
      &lt;shared_directory access="ro" container="/clientdir" host="/path/to/pyclient"/>
   &lt;/container>
   &lt;container>
      &lt;name>plc_r&lt;/name>
      &lt;image>pivotaldata/plcontainer_r:1.0.0&lt;/image>
      &lt;command>/rclient.sh&lt;/command>
      &lt;memory_mb>256&lt;/memory_mb>
      &lt;use_network>yes&lt;/use_network>
      &lt;shared_directory access="rw" container="/plc_log" host="/tmp/plc_log"/>
   &lt;/container>
&lt;/configuration></codeblock></p>
        <p>These are the XML elements and attributes in a PL/Container configuration file.</p>
        <parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt>configuration</pt>
            <pd>Root element for the XML file.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>container</pt>
            <pd>One element for each specific container available in the system. Child element of
              the <codeph>configuration</codeph> element.</pd>
            <pd>
              <parml>
                <plentry>
                  <pt>name</pt>
                  <pd>Required. The value is used to reference a Docker container from a function.
                    Only containers defined in the PL/Container configuration file can be specified
                    in PL/Container functions. A Docker container cannot be referenced by its full
                    Docker name (container ID) for security reasons. This name must be unique in the
                    configuration file.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                  <pt>container_id</pt>
                  <pd>
                    <p>Required. The value is the full Docker image name, including image tag. The
                      same way you specify them for starting this container in Docker. Configuration
                      allows to have many container objects referencing the same image name, this
                      way in Docker they would be represented by identical containers. </p>
                    <p>For example, you might have two containers named
                        <codeph>plc_python_128</codeph> and <codeph>plc_python_256</codeph>, both
                      referencing the Docker image
                        <codeph>pivotaldata/plcontainer_python:1.0.0</codeph>, but first one with
                      128MB RAM limit and the second one with 256MB limit that is specified by the
                        <codeph>memory_mb</codeph> element.</p>
                  </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                  <pt>command</pt>
                  <pd>Required. The value is the command to be run inside of container to start the
                    client process inside in the container. </pd>
                  <pd>You should modify it only if you build your custom container and want to
                    implement some additional initialization logic before the container
                      starts.<note>this cannot be set via plcontainer utility, will need to be set
                      by advanced users via -e option</note></pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                  <pt>memory_mb</pt>
                  <pd>The value specifies the amount of memory container is allowed to use, in MB.
                    Each container is started with this amount of RAM and twice the amount of swap
                    space. The container memory consumption is limited by the host system
                      <codeph>cgroups</codeph>configuration, which means in case of memory
                    overcommit, the container is killed by the System.<note>You can add this element
                      by editing the configuration file with the <codeph>plcontainer configure
                        -e</codeph> command.</note></pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                  <pt>shared_directory</pt>
                  <pd>Required. This element specifies one or more shared directories for a
                    container, with different sharing options. There must be at least one shared
                    directory between client location and the directory in the container,
                      <codeph>/clientdir</codeph> usually in the Pivotal provided image. </pd>
                  <pd>XML attributes allowed:<ul id="ul_x4d_lcs_dw">
                      <li><codeph>host</codeph> - specifies a shared directory location on the host
                        system.</li>
                      <li><codeph>container</codeph> - specifies a directory location inside of
                        container.</li>
                      <li><codeph>access</codeph> - specifies access level to this shared directory,
                        which can be either <codeph>ro</codeph> (read-only) or <codeph>rw</codeph>
                        (read-write). </li>
                    </ul></pd>
                  <pd>You should be careful specifying writable shared directories on the host.
                    Write access to the host system might be used to exchange the data between
                    containers and possibly compromise the host system.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                  <pt>use_network</pt>
                  <pd>
                    <p>Optional. The value can be either <codeph>yes</codeph> or <codeph>no</codeph>
                      to specify whether use <codeph>TCP</codeph> or <codeph>IPC</codeph> for
                      communication between the Greenplum Database process and the Docker container
                      process. The default is <codeph>no</codeph> use <codeph>IPC</codeph>.</p>
                  </pd>
                </plentry>
              </parml>
            </pd>
          </plentry>
        </parml>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_v3s_qv3_kw">
      <title>Updating the PL/Container Configuration</title>
      <body>
        <p>You can add a <codeph>container</codeph> element to the PL/Container configuration file
          with the <codeph>plcontainer configure</codeph> command specifying options with options
          that specify values such as the name, Docker image, command, and shared directory. You can
          use the <codeph>plcontainer configure</codeph> command with the -e option to edit the
          configuration file. The utility updates the configuration file on all hosts.</p>
        <p>The PL/Container configuration file can contain multiple <codeph>container</codeph>
          elements that reference the same Docker image specified by the XML element
            <codeph>image</codeph>. In the example configuration file, the <codeph>image</codeph>
          specifies contains <codeph>container</codeph> elements named
            <codeph>plc_python_128</codeph> and <codeph>plc_python_256</codeph>, both referencing
          the Docker container <codeph>pivotaldata/plcontainer_python:1.0.0</codeph>. The first
          element is defined with a 128MB RAM limit and the second one with a 256MB RAM limit.</p>
        <codeblock>&lt;configuration>
  &lt;container>
    &lt;name>plc_python_128&lt;/name>
    &lt;image>pivotaldata/plcontainer_python:1.0.0&lt;/image>
    &lt;command>./client&lt;/command>
    &lt;memory_mb>128&lt;/memory_mb>
  &lt;/container>
  &lt;container>
    &lt;name>plc_python_256&lt;/name>
    &lt;cimage>pivotaldata/plcontainer_python:1.0.0&lt;/image>
    &lt;command>./client&lt;/command>
    &lt;memory_mb>256&lt;/memory_mb>
  &lt;/container>
&lt;configuration></codeblock>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_oyl_zv3_kw">
      <title>Notes</title>
      <body>
        <p>PL/Container configuration file <codeph>plcontainer_configuration.xml</codeph> is stored
          in all the Greenplum Database data directories for all the Greenplum Database segment
          instances: master, standby master, primary and mirror. This query lists the Greenplum
          Database system data
          directories:<codeblock>select g.hostname, fe.fselocation as directory 
   from pg_filespace as f, pg_filespace_entry as fe, 
       gp_segment_configuration as g
   where f.oid = fe.fsefsoid and g.dbid = fe.fsedbid 
       and f.fsname = 'pg_system';</codeblock></p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_ydt_rtc_rbb">
    <title>Installing Docker</title>
    <body>
      <p>To use PL/Container, Docker must be installed on all Greenplum Database host systems. The
        these instructions show how to set up the Docker service on CentOS 6 and CentOS 7.
        Installing on RHEL 6 or RHEL 7 is a similar process.</p>
      <p>Before performing the Docker installation ensure these requirements are met.<ul
          id="ul_ygx_ms2_rbb">
          <li>The CentOS <codeph>extras</codeph> repository is accessible.</li>
          <li>The user has sudo privileges or is root.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>See also the Docker site installation instructions for CentOS<xref
          href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/installation/linux/centos/" format="html"
          scope="external">https://docs.docker.com/engine/installation/linux/centos/</xref>. For a
        list of Docker commands, see the Docker engine Run Reference <xref
          href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/run/" format="html" scope="external"
          >https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/run/</xref>.</p>
      <section>
        <title>Installing Docker on CentOS 7</title>
        <p>These steps install the docker package and start the docker service as a user with sudo
          privileges.</p>
        <ol id="ol_e4g_sb2_rbb">
          <li>Install dependencies required for
            Docker<codeblock>sudo yum install -y yum-utils device-mapper-persistent-data lvm2</codeblock></li>
          <li>Add the Docker
            repo<codeblock>sudo yum-config-manager --add-repo https://download.docker.com/linux/centos/docker-ce.repo</codeblock></li>
          <li>Update yum cache<codeblock>sudo yum makecache fast</codeblock></li>
          <li>Install Docker<codeblock>sudo yum -y install docker-ce</codeblock></li>
          <li>Start Docker daemon.<codeblock>sudo systemctl start docker</codeblock></li>
          <li>To give access to the Docker daemon and docker commands, assign the Greenplum Database
            administrator (gpadmin) to the group
            <codeph>docker</codeph>.<codeblock>sudo usermod -aG docker gpadmin</codeblock></li>
          <li>Exit the session and login again to update the privileges.</li>
          <li>Run a Docker command Run to the Docker installation.
            <codeblock>docker ps</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
        <p>To configure Docker to start when the server
          starts.<codeblock>sudo systemctl start  docker.service</codeblock></p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Installing Docker on CentOS 6</title>
        <p>These steps install the Docker package and start the docker service as a user with sudo
          privileges.</p>
        <ol id="ol_lrx_zb2_rbb">
          <li>Install EPEL package<codeblock>sudo yum -y install epel-release</codeblock></li>
          <li>Install Docker<codeblock>sudo yum -y install docker-io</codeblock></li>
          <li>Start Docker<codeblock>sudo service docker start</codeblock></li>
          <li>To give access to the Docker daemon and docker commands, assign the Greenplum Database
            administrator (gpadmin) to the group
            <codeph>docker</codeph>.<codeblock>sudo usermod -aG docker gpadmin</codeblock></li>
          <li>Exit the session and login again to active </li>
          <li>Run a docker command. This command lists the currently running Docker containers.
            <codeblock>docker ps</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
        <p>To configure Docker to start when the server
          starts.<codeblock>sudo chkconfig docker on</codeblock></p>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic xml:lang="en" id="topic_kds_plk_rbb">
    <title>References</title>
    <body>
      <p>Docker home page <xref href="https://www.docker.com/" format="html" scope="external"
          >https://www.docker.com/</xref></p>
      <p>Docker command line interface <xref
          href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/commandline/cli/" format="html"
          scope="external">https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/commandline/cli/</xref></p>
      <p>Dockerfile reference <xref href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/builder/"
          format="html" scope="external"
        >https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/builder/</xref></p>
      <p>Installing Docker on Linux systems <xref
          href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/installation/linux/centos/" format="html"
          scope="external">https://docs.docker.com/engine/installation/linux/centos/</xref></p>
      <p>Control and configure Docker with systemd <xref
          href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/admin/systemd/" format="html" scope="external"
          >https://docs.docker.com/engine/admin/systemd/</xref></p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
