<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="ih135496">Server Configuration Parameters</title>
  <body>
    <p>There are many Greenplum server configuration parameters that affect the behavior of the
      Greenplum Database system. Many of these configuration parameters have the same names,
      settings, and behaviors as in a regular PostgreSQL database system. </p>
    <ul id="ul_nss_zzh_3p">
      <li><xref href="#topic_vsn_22l_z4" format="dita"/> describes the parameter data types and
        values.</li>
      <li><xref href="#topic_cyz_p2l_z4" format="dita"/> describes limitations on who can change
        them and where or when they can be set.</li>
      <li><xref href="guc_category-list.xml#guc-cat-list">Parameter Categories</xref> organizes
        parameters by functionality.</li>
      <li><xref href="guc-list.xml#topic3">Configuration Parameters</xref> lists the parameter
        descriptions in alphabetic order.</li>
    </ul>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_vsn_22l_z4">
    <title>Parameter Types and Values</title>
    <body>
      <p>All parameter names are case-insensitive. Every parameter takes a value of one of the
        following types: <codeph>Boolean</codeph>, <codeph>integer</codeph>, <codeph>floating point</codeph>,
        <codeph>enum</codeph>, or <codeph>string</codeph>.</p>
      <p>Boolean values may be specified as <codeph>ON</codeph>,
          <codeph>OFF</codeph>, <codeph>TRUE</codeph>, <codeph>FALSE</codeph>, <codeph>YES</codeph>,
          <codeph>NO</codeph>, <codeph>1</codeph>, <codeph>0</codeph> (all case-insensitive).</p>
      <p>Enum-type parameters are specified in the same manner as string parameters, but are
        restricted to a limited set of values. Enum parameter values are case-insensitive.</p> 
      <p>Some settings specify a memory size or time value. Each of these has an implicit unit,
        which is either kilobytes, blocks (typically eight kilobytes), milliseconds, seconds, or
        minutes. Valid memory size units are <codeph>kB</codeph> (kilobytes), <codeph>MB</codeph>
        (megabytes), and <codeph>GB</codeph> (gigabytes). Valid time units are <codeph>ms</codeph>
        (milliseconds), <codeph>s</codeph> (seconds), <codeph>min</codeph> (minutes),
          <codeph>h</codeph> (hours), and <codeph>d</codeph> (days). Note that the multiplier for
        memory units is 1024, not 1000. A valid time expression contains a number and a unit. When
        specifying a memory or time unit using the <codeph>SET</codeph> command, enclose the value
        in quotes. For example:</p>
      <codeblock>SET statement_mem TO '200MB';</codeblock>
      <note type="note">There is no space between the value and the unit names.</note>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_cyz_p2l_z4">
    <title>Setting Parameters</title>
    <body>
      <p>Many of the configuration parameters have limitations on who can change them and where or
        when they can be set. For example, to change certain parameters, you must be a Greenplum
        Database superuser. Other parameters require a restart of the system for the changes to take
        effect. A parameter that is classified as <i>session</i> can be set at the system level (in
        the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file), at the database-level (using <codeph>ALTER
          DATABASE</codeph>), at the role-level (using <codeph>ALTER ROLE</codeph>), or at the
        session-level (using <codeph>SET</codeph>). System parameters can only be set in the
          <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file.</p>
      <p>In Greenplum Database, the master and each segment instance has its own
          <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file (located in their respective data directories). Some
        parameters are considered <i>local</i> parameters, meaning that each segment instance looks
        to its own <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file to get the value of that parameter. You
        must set local parameters on every instance in the system (master and segments). Others
        parameters are considered <i>master</i> parameters. Master parameters need only be set at
        the master instance.</p>
      <p>This table describes the values in the Settable Classifications column of the table in the
        description of a server configuration parameter.</p>
      <table id="ih389119">
        <title>Settable Classifications</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="110pt"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="367pt"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Set Classification</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">master or local</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">A <i>master</i> parameter only needs to be set in the
                  <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file of the Greenplum master instance. The value
                for this parameter is then either passed to (or ignored by) the segments at run
                  time.<p>A local parameter must be set in the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file
                  of the master AND each segment instance. Each segment instance looks to its own
                  configuration to get the value for the parameter. Local parameters always requires
                  a system restart for changes to take effect.</p></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">session or system</entry>
              <entry colname="col2"><i>Session</i> parameters can be changed on the fly within a
                database session, and can have a hierarchy of settings: at the system level
                  (<codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph>), at the database level (<codeph>ALTER
                  DATABASE...SET</codeph>), at the role level (<codeph>ALTER ROLE...SET</codeph>),
                or at the session level (<codeph>SET</codeph>). If the parameter is set at multiple
                levels, then the most granular setting takes precedence (for example, session
                overrides role, role overrides database, and database overrides system).<p>A
                    <i>system</i> parameter can only be changed via the <codeph>postgresql.conf
                  </codeph>file(s).</p></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">restart or reload</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">When changing parameter values in the postgresql.conf file(s),
                some require a <i>restart</i> of Greenplum Database for the change to take effect.
                Other parameter values can be refreshed by just reloading the server configuration
                file (using <codeph>gpstop -u</codeph>), and do not require stopping the
                system.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">superuser</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">These session parameters can only be set by a database
                superuser. Regular database users cannot set this parameter.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">read only</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">These parameters are not settable by database users or
                superusers. The current value of the parameter can be shown but not altered.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
