<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="ap20941">ALTER INDEX</title><body><p id="sql_command_desc">Changes the definition of an index.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">ALTER INDEX <varname>name</varname> RENAME TO <varname>new_name</varname>

ALTER INDEX <varname>name</varname> SET TABLESPACE <varname>tablespace_name</varname>

ALTER INDEX <varname>name</varname> SET ( FILLFACTOR = <varname>value</varname> )

ALTER INDEX <varname>name</varname> RESET ( FILLFACTOR )</codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>ALTER INDEX</codeph> changes the definition of an existing index.
There are several subforms: </p><ul><li id="ap136518"><b>RENAME</b> — Changes the name of the index. There is no effect
on the stored data.</li><li id="ap136521"><b>SET TABLESPACE</b> — Changes the index's tablespace to the specified
tablespace and moves the data file(s) associated with the index to the
new tablespace. See also <codeph>CREATE TABLESPACE</codeph>. </li><li id="ap136524"><b>SET FILLFACTOR</b> — Changes the index-method-specific storage
parameters for the index. The built-in index methods all accept a single
parameter: <codeph>FILLFACTOR</codeph>. The fillfactor for an index is
a percentage that determines how full the index method will try to pack
index pages. Index contents will not be modified immediately by this
command. Use <codeph>REINDEX</codeph> to rebuild the index to get the
desired effects. </li><li id="ap136527"><b>RESET FILLFACTOR</b> — Resets <codeph>FILLFACTOR</codeph> to the
default. As with <codeph>SET</codeph>, a <codeph>REINDEX</codeph> may
be needed to update the index entirely.</li></ul></section><section id="section4"><title>Parameters</title><parml><plentry><pt><varname>name</varname></pt><pd>The name (optionally schema-qualified) of an existing index to alter.
</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>new_name</varname></pt><pd>New name for the index. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>tablespace_name</varname></pt><pd>The tablespace to which the index will be moved. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>FILLFACTOR</pt><pd>The fillfactor for an index is a percentage that determines how full
the index method will try to pack index pages. For B-trees, leaf pages
are filled to this percentage during initial index build, and also when
extending the index at the right (largest key values). If pages subsequently
become completely full, they will be split, leading to gradual degradation
in the index's efficiency. </pd><pd>B-trees use a default fillfactor of 90, but any value from 10 to
100 can be selected. If the table is static then fillfactor 100 is best
to minimize the index's physical size, but for heavily updated tables
a smaller fillfactor is better to minimize the need for page splits.
The other index methods use fillfactor in different but roughly analogous
ways; the default fillfactor varies between methods.</pd></plentry></parml></section><section id="section5"><title>Notes</title><p>These operations are also possible using <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph>.</p><p>Changing any part of a system catalog index is not permitted.</p></section><section id="section6"><title>Examples</title><p>To rename an existing index:</p><codeblock>ALTER INDEX distributors RENAME TO suppliers;</codeblock><p>To move an index to a different tablespace:</p><codeblock>ALTER INDEX distributors SET TABLESPACE fasttablespace;</codeblock><p>To change an index's fill factor (assuming that the index method supports
it):</p><codeblock>ALTER INDEX distributors SET (fillfactor = 75);
REINDEX INDEX distributors;</codeblock></section><section id="section7"><title>Compatibility</title><p><codeph>ALTER INDEX</codeph> is a Greenplum Database extension.</p></section><section id="section8"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref href="./CREATE_INDEX.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./REINDEX.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./ALTER_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p></section></body></topic>
