<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="ak20941">ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</title><body><p id="sql_command_desc">Changes the definition of an external table.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE <varname>name</varname> RENAME [COLUMN] <varname>column</varname> TO <varname>new_column</varname>

ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE <varname>name</varname> RENAME TO <varname>new_name</varname>

ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE <varname>name</varname> SET SCHEMA <varname>new_schema</varname>

ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE <varname>name</varname> <varname>action</varname> [, ... ]</codeblock><p>where <varname>action</varname> is one of:</p><codeblock>  ADD [COLUMN] <varname>column_name type</varname>
  DROP [COLUMN] <varname>column</varname>
  ALTER [COLUMN] <varname>column</varname>
  TYPE <varname>type</varname> [USING <varname>expression</varname>]
  OWNER TO <varname>new_owner</varname></codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> changes the definition of an existing
external table. There are several subforms: </p><ul><li id="ak136720"><b>ADD COLUMN</b> — Adds a new column to the external table definition.
</li><li id="ak136723"><b>DROP COLUMN</b> — Drops a column from the external table definition.
Note that if you drop readable external table columns, it only changes
the table definition in Greenplum Database. External data files are not
changed. </li><li id="ak142648"><b>ALTER COLUMN TYPE</b> — Changes the data type of a column of a
table. The optional <codeph>USING</codeph> clause specifies how to compute
the new column value from the old. If omitted, the default conversion
is the same as an assignment cast from old data type to new. A <codeph>USING</codeph>
clause must be provided if there is no implicit or assignment cast from
the old to new type.</li><li id="ak137262"><b>OWNER</b> — Changes the owner of the external table to the specified
user. </li><li id="ak137292"><b>RENAME</b> — Changes the name of an external table or the name
of an individual column in the table. There is no effect on the external
data.</li><li id="ak137307"><b>SET SCHEMA</b> — Moves the external table into another schema.</li></ul><p>You must own the external table to use <codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph>.
To change the schema of an external table, you must also have <codeph>CREATE</codeph>
privilege on the new schema. To alter the owner, you must also be a direct
or indirect member of the new owning role, and that role must have <codeph>CREATE</codeph>
privilege on the external table's schema. A superuser has these privileges
automatically.</p><p>In this release, <codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> cannot modify
the external table type, the data format, or the location of the external
data. To modify this information, you must drop and recreate the external
table definition. </p></section><section id="section4"><title>Parameters</title><parml><plentry><pt><varname>name</varname></pt><pd>The name (possibly schema-qualified) of an existing external table
definition to alter.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>column</varname></pt><pd>Name of a new or existing column.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>new_column</varname></pt><pd>New name for an existing column. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>new_name</varname></pt><pd>New name for the external table. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>type</varname></pt><pd>Data type of the new column, or new data type for an existing column.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>new_owner</varname></pt><pd>The role name of the new owner of the external table. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>new_schema</varname></pt><pd>The name of the schema to which the external table will be moved.
</pd></plentry></parml></section><section id="section5"><title>Examples</title><p>Add a new column to an external table definition:</p><codeblock>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE ext_expenses ADD COLUMN manager text;</codeblock><p>Change the name of an external table:</p><codeblock>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE ext_data RENAME TO ext_sales_data;</codeblock><p>Change the owner of an external table:</p><codeblock>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE ext_data OWNER TO jojo;</codeblock><p>Change the schema of an external table:</p><codeblock>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE ext_leads SET SCHEMA marketing;</codeblock></section><section id="section6"><title>Compatibility</title><p><codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> is a Greenplum Database extension.
There is no <codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> statement in the SQL
standard or regular PostgreSQL. </p></section><section id="section7"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref href="./CREATE_EXTERNAL_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./DROP_EXTERNAL_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
          /></codeph></p></section></body></topic>
