<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title id="ak20941">ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</title>
  <body>
    <p id="sql_command_desc">Changes the definition of an external table.</p>
    <section id="section2"
      ><title>Synopsis</title>
      <sectiondiv id="sql_cmd_synopsis" >
        <codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE <varname>name</varname> <varname>action</varname> [, ... ]</codeblock>
        <p>where <varname>action</varname> is one of:</p>
        <codeblock>  ADD [COLUMN] <varname>new_column</varname> <varname>type</varname>
  DROP [COLUMN] <varname>column</varname> [RESTRICT|CASCADE]
  ALTER [COLUMN] <varname>column</varname> TYPE <varname>type</varname> [USING <varname>expression</varname>]
  OWNER TO <varname>new_owner</varname></codeblock>
      </sectiondiv></section>
    <section id="section3">
      <title>Description</title>
      <p><codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> changes the definition of an existing external table.
        These are the supported <codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> actions: </p>
      <ul>
        <li id="ak136720"><b>ADD COLUMN</b> — Adds a new column to the external table definition. </li>
        <li id="ak136723"><b>DROP COLUMN</b> — Drops a column from the external table definition. If
          you drop readable external table columns, it only changes the table definition in
          Greenplum Database. The <codeph>CASCADE</codeph> keyword is required if anything outside
          the table depends on the column, such as a view that references the column. </li>
        <li id="ak142648"><b>ALTER COLUMN TYPE</b> — Changes the data type of a table column. </li>
        <li id="ak137262"><b>OWNER</b> — Changes the owner of the external table to the specified
          user. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Use the <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph> command to perform these actions on an external
          table.<ul id="ul_gtv_mcm_kbb">
          <li>Set (change) the table schema.</li>
          <li>Rename the table.</li>
          <li>Rename a table column.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>You must own the external table to use <codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph>. To change the
        schema of an external table, you must also have <codeph>CREATE</codeph> privilege on the new
        schema. To alter the owner, you must also be a direct or indirect member of the new owning
        role, and that role must have <codeph>CREATE</codeph> privilege on the external table's
        schema. A superuser has these privileges automatically.</p>
      <p>Changes to the external table definition with either <codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph>
        or <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph> do not affect the external data. </p>
      <p>The <codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> and <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph> commands cannot
        modify the type external table (read, write, web), the table <codeph>FORMAT</codeph>
        information, or the location of the external data. To modify this information, you must drop
        and recreate the external table definition. </p>
    </section>
    <section id="section4"><title>Parameters</title><parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><varname>name</varname></pt>
          <pd>The name (possibly schema-qualified) of an existing external table definition to
            alter.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><varname>column</varname></pt>
          <pd>Name of an existing column.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><varname>new_column</varname></pt>
          <pd>Name of a new column.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>USING <varname>expression</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional if an implicit or assignment cast exists from the old column data type to new
            data type. The clause is required if there is no implicit or assignment cast. </pd>
          <pd>The <codeph>USING</codeph> clause does not affect the external data.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><varname>type</varname></pt>
          <pd>Data type of the new column, or new data type for an existing column.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><varname>new_owner</varname></pt>
          <pd>The role name of the new owner of the external table. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>CASCADE</pt>
          <pd>Automatically drop objects that depend on the dropped column, such as a view that
            references the column. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>RESTRICT</pt>
          <pd>Refuse to drop the column or constraint if there are any dependent objects. This is
            the default behavior. </pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml></section>
    <section id="section5"><title>Examples</title><p>Add a new column to an external table
        definition:</p><codeblock>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE ext_expenses ADD COLUMN manager text;</codeblock><p>Change
        the owner of an external
        table:</p><codeblock>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE ext_data OWNER TO jojo;</codeblock><p>Change the
        data type of an external table:</p><codeblock>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE ext_leads ALTER COLUMN acct_code TYPE integer USING acct_code::integer</codeblock>
      <p>When altering the column data type from <codeph>text</codeph> to <codeph>integer</codeph>,
        the <codeph>USING</codeph> clause is required but does not affect the external data.
      </p></section>
    <section id="section6"><title>Compatibility</title><p><codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> is a
        Greenplum Database extension. There is no <codeph>ALTER EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> statement in
        the SQL standard or regular PostgreSQL. </p></section>
    <section id="section7"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref
            href="./CREATE_EXTERNAL_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./DROP_EXTERNAL_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
          /></codeph>, <codeph><xref href="./ALTER_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
          /></codeph></p></section>
  </body>
</topic>
