<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="ax20941">ALTER SEQUENCE</title><body><p id="sql_command_desc">Changes the definition of a sequence generator.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">ALTER SEQUENCE <varname>name</varname> [INCREMENT [ BY ] <varname>increment</varname>] 
     [MINVALUE <varname>minvalue</varname> | NO MINVALUE] 
     [MAXVALUE <varname>maxvalue</varname> | NO MAXVALUE] 
     [RESTART [ WITH ] <varname>start</varname>] 
     [CACHE <varname>cache</varname>] [[ NO ] CYCLE] 
     [OWNED BY {<varname>table.column</varname> | NONE}]

ALTER SEQUENCE <varname>name</varname> RENAME TO <varname>new_name
</varname>
ALTER SEQUENCE <varname>name</varname> SET SCHEMA <varname>new_schema</varname></codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>ALTER SEQUENCE</codeph> changes the parameters of an existing
sequence generator. Any parameters not specifically set in the <codeph>ALTER
SEQUENCE</codeph> command retain their prior settings.</p><p>You must own the sequence to use <codeph>ALTER SEQUENCE</codeph>.
To change a sequence's schema, you must also have <codeph>CREATE</codeph>
privilege on the new schema. Note that superusers have all these privileges
automatically.</p></section><section id="section4"><title>Parameters</title><parml><plentry><pt><varname>name</varname></pt><pd>The name (optionally schema-qualified) of a sequence to be altered.
</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>increment</varname></pt><pd>The clause <codeph>INCREMENT BY <varname>increment</varname></codeph> is optional. A positive value will
            make an ascending sequence, a negative one a descending sequence. If unspecified, the
            old increment value will be maintained. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>minvalue</varname></pt><pt>NO MINVALUE</pt><pd>The optional clause <codeph>MINVALUE <varname>minvalue</varname></codeph> determines the minimum value a
            sequence can generate. If <codeph>NO MINVALUE</codeph> is specified, the defaults of 1
            and -263-1 for ascending and descending sequences, respectively, will be used. If
            neither option is specified, the current minimum value will be maintained. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>maxvalue</varname></pt><pt>NO MAXVALUE</pt><pd>The optional clause <codeph>MAXVALUE <varname>maxvalue</varname></codeph> determines the maximum value for
            the sequence. If <codeph>NO MAXVALUE</codeph> is specified, the defaults are 263-1 and
            -1 for ascending and descending sequences, respectively, will be used. If neither option
            is specified, the current maximum value will be maintained.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>start</varname></pt><pd>The optional clause <codeph>RESTART WITH</codeph> <varname>start</varname> changes the
current value of the sequence. Altering the sequence in this manner is equivalent to calling the <codeph>setval(sequence, start_val, is_called)</codeph> function with <codeph>is_called = false</codeph>. The first <codeph>nextval()</codeph> call after you alter the sequence start value does not increment the sequence and returns <varname>start</varname>.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>cache</varname></pt><pd>The clause <codeph>CACHE <varname>cache</varname></codeph> enables sequence numbers to be preallocated and
            stored in memory for faster access. The minimum value is 1 (only one value can be
            generated at a time, i.e., no cache). If unspecified, the old cache value will be
            maintained.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>CYCLE</pt><pd>The optional <codeph>CYCLE</codeph> key word may be used to enable
the sequence to wrap around when the <varname>maxvalue</varname> or <varname>minvalue</varname>
has been reached by an ascending or descending sequence. If the limit
is reached, the next number generated will be the respective <varname>minvalue</varname>
or <varname>maxvalue</varname>. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>NO CYCLE</pt><pd>If the optional <codeph>NO CYCLE</codeph> key word is specified,
any calls to <codeph>nextval()</codeph> after the sequence has reached
its maximum value will return an error. If neither <codeph>CYCLE</codeph>
or <codeph>NO CYCLE</codeph> are specified, the old cycle behavior will
be maintained.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>OWNED BY <varname>table.column</varname></pt><pt>OWNED BY NONE</pt><pd>The <codeph>OWNED BY</codeph> option causes the sequence to be associated
with a specific table column, such that if that column (or its whole
table) is dropped, the sequence will be automatically dropped as well.
If specified, this association replaces any previously specified association
for the sequence. The specified table must have the same owner and be
in the same schema as the sequence. Specifying <codeph>OWNED BY NONE</codeph>
removes any existing table column association.</pd></plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><varname>new_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>The new name for the sequence.</pd>
        </plentry><plentry><pt><varname>new_schema</varname></pt><pd>The new schema for the sequence.</pd></plentry></parml></section><section id="section5"><title>Notes</title><p>To avoid blocking of concurrent transactions that obtain numbers from the same sequence,
          <codeph>ALTER SEQUENCE</codeph>'s effects on the sequence generation parameters are never
        rolled back; those changes take effect immediately and are not reversible. However, the
          <codeph>OWNED BY</codeph>, <codeph>RENAME TO</codeph>, and <codeph>SET SCHEMA</codeph>
        clauses are ordinary catalog updates and can be rolled back.</p><p><codeph>ALTER SEQUENCE</codeph> will not immediately affect <codeph>nextval()</codeph>
results in sessions, other than the current one, that have preallocated
(cached) sequence values. They will use up all cached values prior to
noticing the changed sequence generation parameters. The current session
will be affected immediately.</p><p>Some variants of <codeph><xref href="./ALTER_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
          /></codeph> can be used with sequences as well. For example, to rename a sequence use
          <codeph>ALTER TABLE RENAME</codeph>.</p></section><section id="section6"><title>Examples</title><p>Restart a sequence called <codeph>serial</codeph> at <codeph>105</codeph>:</p><codeblock>ALTER SEQUENCE serial RESTART WITH 105;</codeblock></section><section id="section7"><title>Compatibility</title><p><codeph>ALTER SEQUENCE</codeph> conforms to the SQL standard, except for the <codeph>OWNED
          BY</codeph>, <codeph>RENAME TO</codeph>, and <codeph>SET SCHEMA</codeph> clauses, which
        are Greenplum Database extensions.</p></section><section id="section8"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref href="./CREATE_SEQUENCE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./DROP_SEQUENCE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./ALTER_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p></section></body></topic>
