<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="bh20941">CLUSTER</title><body><p id="sql_command_desc">Physically reorders a heap storage table on disk according to an index.
Not a recommended operation in Greenplum Database.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">CLUSTER <varname>indexname</varname> ON <varname>tablename</varname>

CLUSTER [VERBOSE] <varname>tablename</varname>

CLUSTER [VERBOSE]</codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> orders a heap storage table based on an index.
<codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> on non-B-tree indexes is not supported on append-optmized storage
tables. Clustering an index means that the records are physically ordered
on disk according to the index information. If the records you need are
distributed randomly on disk, then the database has to seek across the
disk to get the records requested. If those records are stored more closely
together, then the fetching from disk is more sequential. A good example
for a clustered index is on a date column where the data is ordered sequentially
by date. A query against a specific date range will result in an ordered
fetch from the disk, which leverages faster sequential access.</p><p>Clustering is a one-time operation: when the table is subsequently updated, the changes are not
clustered. That is, no attempt is made to store new or updated rows
according to their index order. If you wish, you can periodically
recluster by issuing the command again. Setting the table's <codeph>FILLFACTOR</codeph> storage parameter to less than
        100% can aid in preserving cluster ordering during updates, because updated
        rows are kept on the same page if enough space is available there.
</p><p>When a table is clustered using this command, Greenplum Database remembers on which index it was
                                clustered. The form <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>
                                <varname>tablename</varname> reclusters the table on the same index
                                that it was clustered before. You can use the
                                        <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> or <codeph>SET WITHOUT
                                        CLUSTER</codeph> forms of <codeph><xref
                                                href="ALTER_TABLE.xml#topic1">ALTER
                                        TABLE</xref></codeph> to set the index to use for future
                                cluster operations, or to clear any previous setting.
                                        <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> without any parameter reclusters
                                all previously clustered tables in the current database that the
                                calling user owns, or all tables if called by a superuser. This form
                                of <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> cannot be executed inside a transaction
                                block.</p><p>When a table is being clustered, an <codeph>ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</codeph>
lock is acquired on it. This prevents any other database operations (both
reads and writes) from operating on the table until the <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>
is finished.</p></section><section id="section4"><title>Parameters</title><parml><plentry><pt><varname>indexname</varname></pt><pd>The name of an index. </pd></plentry>
                                <plentry>
                                        <pt><codeph>VERBOSE</codeph></pt>
                                        <pd>Prints a progress report as each table is clustered.</pd>
                                </plentry><plentry><pt><varname>tablename</varname></pt><pd>The name (optionally schema-qualified) of a table. </pd></plentry></parml></section><section id="section5"><title>Notes</title><p>In cases where you are accessing single rows randomly within a table,
the actual order of the data in the table is unimportant. However, if
you tend to access some data more than others, and there is an index
that groups them together, you will benefit from using <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>.
If you are requesting a range of indexed values from a table, or a single
indexed value that has multiple rows that match, <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>
will help because once the index identifies the table page for the first
row that matches, all other rows that match are probably already on the
same table page, and so you save disk accesses and speed up the query.
                                </p>
                        <p><codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> can re-sort the table using either an index scan
                                on the specified index, or (if the index is a b-tree) a sequential
                                scan followed by sorting. It will attempt to choose the method that
                                will be faster, based on planner cost parameters and available
                                statistical information. </p>
                        <p> When an index scan is used, a temporary copy of the table is created
                                that contains the table data in the index order. Temporary copies of
                                each index on the table are created as well. Therefore, you need
                                free space on disk at least equal to the sum of the table size and
                                the index sizes. </p>
                        <p> When a sequential scan and sort is used, a temporary sort file is also
                                created, so that the peak temporary space requirement is as much as
                                double the table size, plus the index sizes. This method is often
                                faster than the index scan method, but if the disk space requirement
                                is intolerable, you can disable this choice by temporarily setting
                                the <xref href="../config_params/guc-list.xml#enable_sort"
                                        >enable_sort</xref> configuration parameter to
                                        <codeph>off</codeph>. </p>
                        <p> It is advisable to set <xref
                                        href="../config_params/guc-list.xml#maintenance_work_mem"/>
                                configuration parameter to a reasonably large value (but not more
                                than the amount of RAM you can dedicate to the
                                        <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> operation) before clustering. </p>
                                        <p>Because the query optimizer records statistics about the ordering of tables, it is advisable to
        run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> on the newly clustered table. Otherwise, the planner may make
                                                poor choices of query plans. </p>
                        <p>Because <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> remembers which indexes are clustered,
                                you can cluster the tables you want clustered manually the first
                                time, then set up a periodic maintenance script that executes
                                        <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> without any parameters, so that the
                                desired tables are periodically reclustered.</p><note><codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> on non-B-tree indexes is not supported with append-optimized tables.</note></section><section id="section6"><title>Examples</title><p>Cluster the table <codeph>employees</codeph> on the basis of its index
        <codeph>emp_ind</codeph>:</p><codeblock>CLUSTER emp_ind ON emp;</codeblock><p>Cluster a large table by recreating it and loading it in the correct index
order:</p><codeblock>CREATE TABLE newtable AS SELECT * FROM table ORDER BY column;
DROP table;
ALTER TABLE newtable RENAME TO table;
CREATE INDEX column_ix ON table (column);
VACUUM ANALYZE table;</codeblock></section><section id="section7"><title>Compatibility</title><p>There is no <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> statement in the SQL standard.</p></section><section id="section8"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref href="./CREATE_TABLE_AS.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./CREATE_INDEX.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p></section></body></topic>
