<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="bh20941">CLUSTER</title><body><p id="sql_command_desc">Physically reorders a heap storage table on disk according to an index.
Not a recommended operation in Greenplum Database.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">CLUSTER <varname>indexname</varname> ON <varname>tablename</varname>

CLUSTER [VERBOSE] <varname>tablename</varname>

CLUSTER [VERBOSE]</codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> orders a heap storage table based on an index.
<codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> is not supported on append-optmized storage
tables. Clustering an index means that the records are physically ordered
on disk according to the index information. If the records you need are
distributed randomly on disk, then the database has to seek across the
disk to get the records requested. If those records are stored more closely
together, then the fetching from disk is more sequential. A good example
for a clustered index is on a date column where the data is ordered sequentially
by date. A query against a specific date range will result in an ordered
fetch from the disk, which leverages faster sequential access.</p><p>Clustering is a one-time operation: when the table is subsequently
updated, the changes are not clustered. That is, no attempt is made to
store new or updated rows according to their index order. If one wishes,
one can periodically recluster by issuing the command again. </p><p>When a table is clustered using this command, Greenplum Database remembers
on which index it was clustered. The form <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> <varname>tablename</varname>
reclusters the table on the same index that it was clustered before.
<codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> without any parameter reclusters all previously
clustered tables in the current database that the calling user owns,
or all tables if called by a superuser. This form of <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>
cannot be executed inside a transaction block.</p><p>When a table is being clustered, an <codeph>ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</codeph>
lock is acquired on it. This prevents any other database operations (both
reads and writes) from operating on the table until the <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>
is finished.</p></section><section id="section4"><title>Parameters</title><parml><plentry><pt><varname>indexname</varname></pt><pd>The name of an index. </pd></plentry>
                                <plentry>
                                        <pt><codeph>VERBOSE</codeph></pt>
                                        <pd>Prints a progress report as each table is clustered.</pd>
                                </plentry><plentry><pt><varname>tablename</varname></pt><pd>The name (optionally schema-qualified) of a table. </pd></plentry></parml></section><section id="section5"><title>Notes</title><p>In cases where you are accessing single rows randomly within a table,
the actual order of the data in the table is unimportant. However, if
you tend to access some data more than others, and there is an index
that groups them together, you will benefit from using <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>.
If you are requesting a range of indexed values from a table, or a single
indexed value that has multiple rows that match, <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>
will help because once the index identifies the table page for the first
row that matches, all other rows that match are probably already on the
same table page, and so you save disk accesses and speed up the query.
</p><p>During the cluster operation, a temporary copy of the table is created
that contains the table data in the index order. Temporary copies of
each index on the table are created as well. Therefore, you need free
space on disk at least equal to the sum of the table size and the index
sizes. </p><p>Because the query optimizer records statistics about the ordering of tables, it is advisable to
        run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> on the newly clustered table. Otherwise, the planner may make
        poor choices of query plans. </p><p>There is another way to cluster data. The <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph>
command reorders the original table by scanning it using the index you
specify. This can be slow on large tables because the rows are fetched
from the table in index order, and if the table is disordered, the entries
are on random pages, so there is one disk page retrieved for every row
moved. (Greenplum Database has a cache, but the majority of a big table
will not fit in the cache.) The other way to cluster a table is to use
a statement such as:</p><codeblock>CREATE TABLE newtable AS SELECT * FROM table ORDER BY column;</codeblock><p>This uses the Greenplum Database sorting code to produce the desired
order, which is usually much faster than an index scan for disordered
data. Then you drop the old table, use <codeph>ALTER TABLE ... RENAME</codeph>
to rename <varname>newtable</varname> to the old name, and recreate the table's
indexes. The big disadvantage of this approach is that it does not preserve
OIDs, constraints, granted privileges, and other ancillary properties
of the table — all such items must be manually recreated. Another disadvantage
is that this way requires a sort temporary file about the same size as
the table itself, so peak disk usage is about three times the table size
instead of twice the table size.</p><note><codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> is not supported with append-optimized tables.</note></section><section id="section6"><title>Examples</title><p>Cluster the table <codeph>employees</codeph> on the basis of its index
        <codeph>emp_ind</codeph>:</p><codeblock>CLUSTER emp_ind ON emp;</codeblock><p>Cluster a large table by recreating it and loading it in the correct index
order:</p><codeblock>CREATE TABLE newtable AS SELECT * FROM table ORDER BY column;
DROP table;
ALTER TABLE newtable RENAME TO table;
CREATE INDEX column_ix ON table (column);
VACUUM ANALYZE table;</codeblock></section><section id="section7"><title>Compatibility</title><p>There is no <codeph>CLUSTER</codeph> statement in the SQL standard.</p></section><section id="section8"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref href="./CREATE_TABLE_AS.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./CREATE_INDEX.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p></section></body></topic>
