<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title id="ce20941">CREATE TABLE AS</title>
  <body>
    <p id="sql_command_desc">Defines a new table from the results of a query.</p>
    <section id="section2">
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">CREATE [ [GLOBAL | LOCAL] {TEMPORARY | TEMP} ] TABLE <varname>table_name</varname>
   [(<varname>column_name</varname> [, ...] )]
   [ WITH ( <varname>storage_parameter</varname>=<varname>value</varname> [, ... ] ) ]
   [ON COMMIT {PRESERVE ROWS | DELETE ROWS | DROP}]
   [TABLESPACE <varname>tablespace</varname>]
   AS <varname>query</varname>
   [DISTRIBUTED BY (<varname>column</varname>, [ ... ] ) | DISTRIBUTED RANDOMLY]</codeblock>
      <p>where <varname>storage_parameter</varname> is:</p>
      <codeblock>   APPENDONLY={TRUE|FALSE}
   BLOCKSIZE={8192-2097152}
   ORIENTATION={COLUMN|ROW}
   COMPRESSTYPE={ZLIB|ZSTD|QUICKLZ}
   COMPRESSLEVEL={1-9 | 1}
   FILLFACTOR={10-100}
   OIDS[=TRUE|FALSE]</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section3">
      <title>Description</title>
      <p><codeph>CREATE TABLE AS</codeph> creates a table and fills it with data computed by a
            <codeph><xref href="./SELECT.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph> command.
        The table columns have the names and data types associated with the output columns of the
          <codeph>SELECT</codeph>, however you can override the column names by giving an explicit
        list of new column names. </p>
      <p><codeph>CREATE TABLE AS</codeph> creates a new table and evaluates the query just once to
        fill the new table initially. The new table will not track subsequent changes to the source
        tables of the query.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section4">
      <title>Parameters</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt>GLOBAL | LOCAL</pt>
          <pd>These keywords are present for SQL standard compatibility, but have no effect in
            Greenplum Database. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>TEMPORARY | TEMP</pt>
          <pd>If specified, the new table is created as a temporary table. Temporary tables are
            automatically dropped at the end of a session, or optionally at the end of the current
            transaction (see <codeph>ON COMMIT</codeph>). Existing permanent tables with the same
            name are not visible to the current session while the temporary table exists, unless
            they are referenced with schema-qualified names. Any indexes created on a temporary
            table are automatically temporary as well.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>table_name</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>The name (optionally schema-qualified) of the new table to be created. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>column_name</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>The name of a column in the new table. If column names are not provided, they are
            taken from the output column names of the query. If the table is created from an
              <codeph>EXECUTE</codeph> command, a column name list cannot be specified.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>WITH ( <varname>storage_parameter=value</varname> )</pt>
          <pd>The <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause can be used to set storage options for the table or
            its indexes. Note that you can also set different storage parameters on a particular
            partition or subpartition by declaring the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause in the partition
            specification. The following storage options are available:</pd>
          <pd>APPENDONLY — Set to <codeph>TRUE</codeph> to create the table as an append-optimized
            table. If <codeph>FALSE</codeph> or not declared, the table will be created as a regular
            heap-storage table.</pd>
          <pd>BLOCKSIZE — Set to the size, in bytes for each block in a table. The <codeph>BLOCKSIZE
            </codeph>must be between 8192 and 2097152 bytes, and be a multiple of 8192. The default
            is 32768.</pd>
          <pd>ORIENTATION — Set to <codeph>column</codeph> for column-oriented storage, or
              <codeph>row</codeph> (the default) for row-oriented storage. This option is only valid
            if <codeph>APPENDONLY=TRUE</codeph>. Heap-storage tables can only be row-oriented.</pd>
          <pd>COMPRESSTYPE — Set to <codeph>ZLIB</codeph> (the default), <codeph>ZSTD</codeph>,
              or <codeph>QUICKLZ</codeph><sup>1</sup> to specify the type
              of compression used. The value <codeph>NONE</codeph>disables compression. Zstd provides
	      for both speed or a good compression ratio, tunable with the compression level option.
	      QuickLZ and zlib are provided for backwards-compatibility, they are less flexible and
	      zstd outperforms them on usual workloads. This option
            is only valid if <codeph>APPENDONLY=TRUE</codeph>.<p>
              <note type="note"><sup>1</sup>QuickLZ compression is available only in the commercial
                release of Pivotal Greenplum Database.</note>
          <pd><b>COMPRESSLEVEL</b> — For Zstd compression of append-optimized tables, set to an
            integer values between 1 (fastest compression) to 19 (highest compression ratio).
	    For zlib compression, the valid range is between 1 and 9. QuickLZ
            compression level can only be set to 1. If not declared, the default is 1.
            This option is valid only if <codeph>APPENDONLY=TRUE</codeph>.</pd>
          <pd>FILLFACTOR — See <codeph><xref href="CREATE_INDEX.xml#topic1" type="topic"
                format="dita"/></codeph> for more information about this index storage parameter. </pd>
          <pd>OIDS — Set to <codeph>OIDS=FALSE</codeph> (the default) so that rows do not have
            object identifiers assigned to them. Greenplum strongly recommends that you do not
            enable OIDS when creating a table. On large tables, such as those in a typical Greenplum
            Database system, using OIDs for table rows can cause wrap-around of the 32-bit OID
            counter. Once the counter wraps around, OIDs can no longer be assumed to be unique,
            which not only makes them useless to user applications, but can also cause problems in
            the Greenplum Database system catalog tables. In addition, excluding OIDs from a table
            reduces the space required to store the table on disk by 4 bytes per row, slightly
            improving performance. OIDS are not allowed on column-oriented tables.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>ON COMMIT</pt>
          <pd>The behavior of temporary tables at the end of a transaction block can be controlled
            using <codeph>ON COMMIT</codeph>. The three options are: </pd>
          <pd>PRESERVE ROWS — No special action is taken at the ends of transactions for temporary
            tables. This is the default behavior. </pd>
          <pd>DELETE ROWS — All rows in the temporary table will be deleted at the end of each
            transaction block. Essentially, an automatic <codeph>TRUNCATE</codeph> is done at each
            commit. </pd>
          <pd>DROP — The temporary table will be dropped at the end of the current transaction
            block. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>TABLESPACE <varname>tablespace</varname></pt>
          <pd>The tablespace is the name of the tablespace in which the new table is to be created.
            If not specified, the database's default tablespace is used.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>AS <varname>query</varname></pt>
          <pd>A <codeph><xref href="./SELECT.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph> or
                <codeph><xref href="./VALUES.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>
            command, or an <codeph><xref href="./EXECUTE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
              /></codeph> command that runs a prepared <codeph>SELECT</codeph> or <codeph>VALUES
            </codeph>query.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>DISTRIBUTED BY (<varname>column</varname>, [ ... ] )</pt>
          <pt>DISTRIBUTED RANDOMLY</pt>
          <pd>Used to declare the Greenplum Database distribution policy for the table.
              <codeph>DISTIBUTED BY</codeph> uses hash distribution with one or more columns
            declared as the distribution key. For the most even data distribution, the distribution
            key should be the primary key of the table or a unique column (or set of columns). If
            that is not possible, then you may choose <codeph>DISTRIBUTED RANDOMLY</codeph>, which
            will send the data round-robin to the segment instances. </pd>
          <pd>The Greenplum Database server configuration parameter
              <codeph>gp_create_table_random_default_distribution</codeph> controls the default
            table distribution policy if the <cmdname>DISTRIBUTED BY</cmdname> clause is not
            specified when you create a table. Greenplum Database follows these rules to create a
            table if a distribution policy is not specified.<ul id="ul_ejv_m1b_kr">
              <li>If the legacy query optimizer creates the table, and the value of the parameter is
                  <codeph>off</codeph>, the table distribution policy is determined based on the
                command.</li>
              <li>If the legacy query optimizer creates the table, and the value of the parameter is
                  <codeph>on</codeph>, the table distribution policy is random.</li>
              <li>If GPORCA creates the table, the table distribution policy is
                random. The parameter value has no affect. </li>
            </ul></pd>
          <pd>For information about the parameter, see "Server Configuration Parameters." For
            information about the legacy query optimizer and GPORCA, see
            "Querying Data" in the <cite>Greenplum Database Administrator Guide</cite>. </pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section id="section5">
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p>This command is functionally similar to <codeph><xref href="./SELECT_INTO.xml#topic1"
            type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>, but it is preferred since it is less likely to be
        confused with other uses of the <codeph>SELECT INTO</codeph> syntax. Furthermore,
          <codeph>CREATE TABLE AS</codeph> offers a superset of the functionality offered by
          <codeph>SELECT INTO</codeph>. </p>
      <p><codeph>CREATE TABLE AS</codeph> can be used for fast data loading from external table data
        sources. See <codeph><xref href="CREATE_EXTERNAL_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic"
            format="dita"/></codeph>.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section6">
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>Create a new table <codeph>films_recent</codeph> consisting of only recent entries from the
        table <codeph>films</codeph>:</p>
      <codeblock>CREATE TABLE films_recent AS SELECT * FROM films WHERE 
date_prod &gt;= '2007-01-01';</codeblock>
      <p>Create a new temporary table <codeph>films_recent</codeph>, consisting of only recent
        entries from the table films, using a prepared statement. The new table has OIDs and will be
        dropped at commit: </p>
      <codeblock>PREPARE recentfilms(date) AS SELECT * FROM films WHERE 
date_prod &gt; $1;
CREATE TEMP TABLE films_recent WITH (OIDS) ON COMMIT DROP AS 
EXECUTE recentfilms('2007-01-01');</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section7">
      <title>Compatibility</title>
      <p><codeph>CREATE TABLE AS</codeph> conforms to the SQL standard, with the following
        exceptions: </p>
      <ul>
        <li id="ce151719">The standard requires parentheses around the subquery clause; in Greenplum
          Database, these parentheses are optional. </li>
        <li id="ce151721">The standard defines a <codeph>WITH [NO] DATA</codeph> clause; this is not
          currently implemented by Greenplum Database. The behavior provided by Greenplum Database
          is equivalent to the standard's <codeph>WITH DATA</codeph> case. <codeph>WITH NO
            DATA</codeph> can be simulated by appending <codeph>LIMIT 0</codeph> to the query. </li>
        <li id="ce151723">Greenplum Database handles temporary tables differently from the standard;
          see <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> for details.</li>
        <li id="ce151725">The <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause is a Greenplum Database extension;
          neither storage parameters nor <codeph>OIDs</codeph> are in the standard. </li>
        <li id="ce151727">The Greenplum Database concept of tablespaces is not part of the standard.
          The <codeph>TABLESPACE</codeph> clause is an extension.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="section8">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p><codeph><xref href="CREATE_EXTERNAL_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
        /></codeph>, <codeph><xref href="CREATE_EXTERNAL_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic"
            format="dita"/></codeph>, <codeph><xref href="./EXECUTE.xml#topic1" type="topic"
            format="dita"/></codeph>, <codeph><xref href="./SELECT.xml#topic1" type="topic"
            format="dita"/></codeph>, <codeph><xref href="./SELECT_INTO.xml#topic1" type="topic"
            format="dita"/></codeph>, <codeph><xref href="./VALUES.xml#topic1" type="topic"
            format="dita"/></codeph></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
