<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="bp20941">CREATE DATABASE</title><body><p id="sql_command_desc">Creates a new database.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">CREATE DATABASE name [ [WITH] [OWNER [=] <varname>user_name</varname>]
                     [TEMPLATE [=] <varname>template</varname>]
                     [ENCODING [=] <varname>encoding</varname>]
                     [LC_COLLATE [=] <varname>lc_collate</varname>]
                     [LC_CTYPE [=] <varname>lc_ctype</varname>]
                     [TABLESPACE [=] <varname>tablespace</varname>]
                     [CONNECTION LIMIT [=] connlimit ] ]</codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>CREATE DATABASE</codeph> creates a new database. To create a
database, you must be a superuser or have the special <codeph>CREATEDB</codeph>
privilege.</p><p>The creator becomes the owner of the new database by default. Superusers
can create databases owned by other users by using the <codeph>OWNER</codeph>
clause. They can even create databases owned by users with no special
privileges. Non-superusers with <codeph>CREATEDB</codeph> privilege can
only create databases owned by themselves.</p><p>By default, the new database will be created by cloning the standard system database
          <codeph>template1</codeph>. A different template can be specified by writing
          <codeph>TEMPLATE <varname>name</varname></codeph>. In particular, by writing <codeph>TEMPLATE
          template0</codeph>, you can create a clean database containing only the standard objects
        predefined by Greenplum Database. This is useful if you wish to avoid copying any
        installation-local objects that may have been added to <codeph>template1</codeph>. </p></section><section id="section4"><title>Parameters</title><parml><plentry><pt><varname>name</varname></pt><pd>The name of a database to create.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>user_name</varname></pt><pd>The name of the database user who will own the new database, or <codeph>DEFAULT</codeph>
to use the default owner (the user executing the command). </pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>template</varname></pt><pd>The name of the template from which to create the new database, or
<codeph>DEFAULT</codeph> to use the default template (<varname>template1</varname>).
</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>encoding</varname></pt><pd>Character set encoding to use in the new database. Specify a string constant (such as
              <codeph>'SQL_ASCII'</codeph>), an integer encoding number, or <codeph>DEFAULT</codeph>
            to use the default encoding. For more information, see <xref
              href="../character_sets.xml" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</pd></plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><varname>lc_collate</varname></pt>
          <pd>The collation order (<codeph>LC_COLLATE</codeph>) to use in the new database. This
            affects the sort order applied to strings, e.g. in queries with <codeph>ORDER
              BY</codeph>, as well as the order used in indexes on text columns. The default is to
            use the collation order of the template database. See the Notes  section for additional
            restrictions.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><varname>lc_ctype</varname></pt>
          <pd>The character classification (<codeph>LC_CTYPE</codeph>) to use in the new 
            database. This affects the categorization of characters, e.g. lower,
            upper and digit. The default is to use the character classification of
            the template database. See below for additional restrictions.</pd>
        </plentry><plentry><pt><varname>tablespace</varname></pt><pd>The name of the tablespace that will be associated with the new database,
or <codeph>DEFAULT</codeph> to use the template database's tablespace.
This tablespace will be the default tablespace used for objects created
in this database.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>connlimit</varname></pt><pd>The maximum number of concurrent connections possible. The default
of -1 means there is no limitation.</pd></plentry></parml></section><section id="section5">
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p><codeph>CREATE DATABASE</codeph> cannot be executed inside a transaction block.</p>
      <p>When you copy a database by specifying its name as the template, no other sessions can be
        connected to the template database while it is being copied. New connections to the template
        database are locked out until <codeph>CREATE DATABASE</codeph> completes.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>CONNECTION LIMIT</codeph> is not enforced against superusers.</p>
      <p>The character set encoding specified for the new database must be compatible with the
        chosen locale settings (<codeph>LC_COLLATE</codeph> and <codeph>LC_CTYPE</codeph>). If the
        locale is <codeph>C</codeph> (or equivalently <codeph>POSIX</codeph>), then all encodings
        are allowed, but for other locale settings there is only one encoding that will work
        properly. <codeph>CREATE
          DATABASE</codeph> will allow superusers to specify <codeph>SQL_ASCII</codeph> encoding
        regardless of the locale settings, but this choice is deprecated and may result in
        misbehavior of character-string functions if data that is not encoding-compatible with the
        locale is stored in the database. </p>
      <p>The encoding and locale settings must match those of the template database, except when
          <codeph>template0</codeph> is used as template. This is
        because <codeph>COLLATE</codeph> and <codeph>CTYPE</codeph> affect the ordering in indexes,
        so that any indexes copied from the template database would be invalid in the new database
        with different settings. <codeph>template0</codeph>, however, is known to not contain any 
        data or indexes that would be affected.</p>
    </section><section id="section6"><title>Examples</title><p>To create a new database: </p><codeblock>CREATE DATABASE gpdb;</codeblock><p>To create a database <codeph>sales</codeph> owned by user <codeph>salesapp</codeph> with a
        default tablespace of <codeph>salesspace</codeph>: </p><codeblock>CREATE DATABASE sales OWNER salesapp TABLESPACE salesspace;</codeblock><p>To create a database <codeph>music</codeph> which supports the ISO-8859-1 character set: </p><codeblock>CREATE DATABASE music ENCODING 'LATIN1' TEMPLATE template0;</codeblock>
      <p>In this example, the <codeph>TEMPLATE template0</codeph> clause would only be required if
          <codeph>template1</codeph>'s encoding is not ISO-8859-1. Note that changing encoding might
        require selecting new <codeph>LC_COLLATE</codeph> and <codeph>LC_CTYPE</codeph> settings as
        well.</p></section><section id="section7"><title>Compatibility</title><p>There is no <codeph>CREATE DATABASE</codeph> statement in the SQL standard.
Databases are equivalent to catalogs, whose creation is implementation-defined.</p></section><section id="section8"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref href="ALTER_DATABASE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./DROP_DATABASE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
        /></codeph></p></section></body></topic>
