<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="cf20941">CREATE TABLESPACE</title><body><p id="sql_command_desc">Defines a new tablespace.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">CREATE TABLESPACE <varname>tablespace_name</varname> [OWNER <varname>username</varname>] 
       FILESPACE <varname>filespace_name</varname></codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>CREATE TABLESPACE</codeph> registers a new tablespace for your
Greenplum Database system. The tablespace name must be distinct from
the name of any existing tablespace in the system. </p><p>A tablespace allows superusers to define an alternative location on
the file system where the data files containing database objects (such
as tables and indexes) may reside.</p><p>A user with appropriate privileges can pass a tablespace name to <codeph><xref
            href="CREATE_DATABASE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>, <codeph><xref
            href="CREATE_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>, or <codeph><xref
            href="CREATE_INDEX.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph> to have the data
        files for these objects stored within the specified tablespace.</p><p>In Greenplum Database, there must be a file system location defined for the master, each primary
        segment, and each mirror segment in order for the tablespace to have a location to store its
        objects across an entire Greenplum system. This collection of file system locations is
        defined in a filespace object. A filespace must be defined before you can create a
        tablespace. See <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph> in the <i>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</i>
        for more information.</p></section><section id="section4"><title>Parameters</title><parml><plentry><pt><varname>tablespacename</varname></pt><pd>The name of a tablespace to be created. The name cannot begin with <codeph>pg_</codeph> or
              <codeph>gp_</codeph>, as such names are reserved for system tablespaces. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>OWNER <varname>username</varname></pt><pd>The name of the user who will own the tablespace. If omitted, defaults
to the user executing the command. Only superusers may create tablespaces,
but they can assign ownership of tablespaces to non-superusers. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>FILESPACE</pt><pd>The name of a Greenplum Database filespace that was defined using
the <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph> management utility.</pd></plentry></parml></section><section id="section5"><title>Notes</title><p>You must first create a filespace to be used by the tablespace. See <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph>
        in the <i>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</i> for more information.</p><p>Tablespaces are only supported on systems that support symbolic links.
</p><p><codeph>CREATE TABLESPACE</codeph> cannot be executed inside a transaction
block.</p></section><section id="section6"><title>Examples</title><p>Create a new tablespace by specifying the corresponding filespace to
use: </p><codeblock>CREATE TABLESPACE mytblspace FILESPACE myfilespace;</codeblock></section><section id="section7"><title>Compatibility</title><p><codeph>CREATE TABLESPACE</codeph> is a Greenplum Database extension.
</p></section><section id="section8"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref href="CREATE_DATABASE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="CREATE_TABLE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="CREATE_INDEX.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./DROP_TABLESPACE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="ALTER_TABLESPACE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
          <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph> in the <i>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</i>
      </p></section></body></topic>
