<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
    <title id="bs20941">CREATE FUNCTION</title>
    <body>
        <p id="sql_command_desc">Defines a new function.</p>
        <section id="section2"
            ><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">CREATE [OR REPLACE] FUNCTION <varname>name</varname>    
    ( [ [<varname>argmode</varname>] [<varname>argname</varname>] <varname>argtype</varname> [ { DEFAULT | = } <varname>defexpr</varname> ] [, ...] ] )
      [ RETURNS { [ SETOF ] rettype 
        | TABLE ([{ argname argtype | LIKE other table }
          [, ...]])
        } ]
    { LANGUAGE <varname>langname</varname>
    | IMMUTABLE | STABLE | VOLATILE
    | CALLED ON NULL INPUT | RETURNS NULL ON NULL INPUT | STRICT
    | [EXTERNAL] SECURITY INVOKER | [EXTERNAL] SECURITY DEFINE
    | EXECUTE ON { ANY | MASTER | ALL SEGMENTS }
    | COST <varname>execution_cost</varname>
    | SET <varname>configuration_parameter</varname> { TO <varname>value</varname> | = <varname>value</varname> | FROM CURRENT }
    | AS '<varname>definition</varname>'
    | AS '<varname>obj_file</varname>', '<varname>link_symbol</varname>' } ...
    [ WITH ({ DESCRIBE = describe_function
           } [, ...] ) ]</codeblock></section>
        <section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>CREATE FUNCTION</codeph> defines
                a new function. <codeph>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION</codeph> will either create a new
                function, or replace an existing definition. </p><p>The name of the new function
                must not match any existing function with the same argument types in the same
                schema. However, functions of different argument types may share a name
                (overloading). </p><p>To update the definition of an existing function, use
                    <codeph>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION</codeph>. It is not possible to change the
                name or argument types of a function this way (this would actually create a new,
                distinct function). Also, <codeph>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION</codeph> will not let
                you change the return type of an existing function. To do that, you must drop and
                recreate the function. If you drop and then recreate a function, you will have to
                drop existing objects (rules, views, triggers, and so on) that refer to the old
                function. Use <codeph>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION</codeph> to change a function
                definition without breaking objects that refer to the function.</p><p>For more
                information about creating functions, see the <xref
                    href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/8.3/static/xfunc.html" scope="external"
                    format="html">User Defined Functions</xref> section of the PostgreSQL
                documentation.</p><sectiondiv id="section4"><b>Limited Use of VOLATILE and STABLE
                    Functions</b><p>To prevent data from becoming out-of-sync across the segments in
                    Greenplum Database, any function classified as <codeph>STABLE</codeph> or
                        <codeph>VOLATILE</codeph> cannot be executed at the segment level if it
                    contains SQL or modifies the database in any way. For example, functions such as
                        <codeph>random()</codeph> or <codeph>timeofday()</codeph> are not allowed to
                    execute on distributed data in Greenplum Database because they could potentially
                    cause inconsistent data between the segment instances.</p><p>To ensure data
                    consistency, <codeph>VOLATILE</codeph> and <codeph>STABLE</codeph> functions can
                    safely be used in statements that are evaluated on and execute from the master.
                    For example, the following statements are always executed on the master
                    (statements without a <codeph>FROM</codeph>
                    clause):</p><codeblock>SELECT setval('myseq', 201);
SELECT foo();</codeblock><p>In
                    cases where a statement has a <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause containing a
                    distributed table and the function used in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause
                    simply returns a set of rows, execution may be allowed on the
                    segments:</p><codeblock>SELECT * FROM foo();</codeblock><p>One exception to this
                    rule are functions that return a table reference (<codeph>rangeFuncs</codeph>)
                    or functions that use the <codeph>refCursor</codeph> data type. Note that you
                    cannot return a <codeph>refcursor</codeph> from any kind of function in
                    Greenplum Database.</p></sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv><b>Function Volitionality and EXECUTE ON Attributes</b><p>Volatility
                    attributes (<codeph>IMMUTABLE</codeph>, <codeph>STABLE</codeph>,
                        <codeph>VOLATILE</codeph>) and <codeph>EXECUTE ON</codeph> attributes
                    specify two different aspects of function execution. In general, volatility
                    indicates when the function is executed, and <codeph>EXECUTE ON</codeph>
                    indicates where it is executed. </p><p>For example, a function defined with the
                        <codeph>IMMUTABLE</codeph> attribute can be executed at query planning time,
                    while a function with the <codeph>VOLATILE</codeph> attribute must be executed
                    for every row in the query. A function with the <codeph>EXECUTE ON
                        MASTER</codeph> attribute is executed only on the master segment and a
                    function with the <codeph>EXECUTE ON ALL SEGMENTS</codeph> attribute is executed
                    on all primary segment instances (not the master).</p><p>See <xref
                        href="../../admin_guide/query/topics/functions-operators.xml#topic26/in151167"
                        >Using Functions and Operators</xref> in the <cite>Greenplum Database
                        Administrator Guide</cite>.</p></sectiondiv></section>
        <section id="section5"><title>Parameters</title><parml>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>name</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The name (optionally schema-qualified) of the function to create.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>argmode</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The mode of an argument: either <codeph>IN</codeph>, <codeph>OUT</codeph>,
                            <codeph>INOUT</codeph>, or <codeph>VARIADIC</codeph>. Only
                            <codeph>OUT</codeph> arguments can follow an argument declared as
                            <codeph>VARIADIC</codeph>. If omitted, the default is
                            <codeph>IN</codeph>. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>argname</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The name of an argument. Some languages (currently only PL/pgSQL) let you
                        use the name in the function body. For other languages the name of an input
                        argument is just extra documentation. But the name of an output argument is
                        significant, since it defines the column name in the result row type. (If
                        you omit the name for an output argument, the system will choose a default
                        column name.) </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>argtype</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The data type(s) of the function's arguments (optionally schema-qualified),
                        if any. The argument types may be base, composite, or domain types, or may
                        reference the type of a table column. </pd>
                    <pd>Depending on the implementation language it may also be allowed to specify
                        pseudotypes such as <codeph>cstring</codeph>. Pseudotypes indicate that the
                        actual argument type is either incompletely specified, or outside the set of
                        ordinary SQL data types. </pd>
                    <pd>The type of a column is referenced by writing
                                <codeph><varname>tablename</varname>.<varname>columnname</varname>%TYPE</codeph>.
                        Using this feature can sometimes help make a function independent of changes
                        to the definition of a table. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>defexpr</varname></pt>
                    <pd>An expression to be used as the default value if the parameter is not
                        specified. The expression must be coercible to the argument type of the
                        parameter. Only <codeph>IN</codeph> and <codeph>INOUT</codeph> parameters
                        can have a default value. Each input parameter in the argument list that
                        follows a parameter with a default value must have a default value as
                        well.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>rettype</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The return data type (optionally schema-qualified). The return type can be a
                        base, composite, or domain type, or may reference the type of a table
                        column. Depending on the implementation language it may also be allowed to
                        specify pseudotypes such as <codeph>cstring</codeph>. If the function is not
                        supposed to return a value, specify <codeph>void</codeph> as the return
                        type. </pd>
                    <pd>When there are <codeph>OUT</codeph> or <codeph>INOUT</codeph> parameters,
                        the <codeph>RETURNS</codeph> clause may be omitted. If present, it must
                        agree with the result type implied by the output parameters:
                            <codeph>RECORD</codeph> if there are multiple output parameters, or the
                        same type as the single output parameter. </pd>
                    <pd>The <codeph>SETOF</codeph> modifier indicates that the function will return
                        a set of items, rather than a single item. </pd>
                    <pd>The type of a column is referenced by writing
                                <codeph><varname>tablename</varname>.<varname>columnname</varname>%TYPE</codeph>.
                    </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>langname</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The name of the language that the function is implemented in. May be
                            <codeph>SQL</codeph>, <codeph>C</codeph>, <codeph>internal</codeph>, or
                        the name of a user-defined procedural language. See <codeph><xref
                                href="./CREATE_LANGUAGE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                            /></codeph> for the procedural languages supported in Greenplum
                        Database. For backward compatibility, the name may be enclosed by single
                        quotes. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>IMMUTABLE</pt>
                    <pt>STABLE</pt>
                    <pt>VOLATILE</pt>
                    <pd>These attributes inform the query optimizer about the behavior of the
                        function. At most one choice may be specified. If none of these appear,
                            <codeph>VOLATILE</codeph> is the default assumption. Since Greenplum
                        Database currently has limited use of <codeph>VOLATILE</codeph> functions,
                        if a function is truly <codeph>IMMUTABLE</codeph>, you must declare it as so
                        to be able to use it without restrictions.</pd>
                    <pd><codeph>IMMUTABLE</codeph> indicates that the function cannot modify the
                        database and always returns the same result when given the same argument
                        values. It does not do database lookups or otherwise use information not
                        directly present in its argument list. If this option is given, any call of
                        the function with all-constant arguments can be immediately replaced with
                        the function value.</pd>
                    <pd><codeph>STABLE</codeph> indicates that the function cannot modify the
                        database, and that within a single table scan it will consistently return
                        the same result for the same argument values, but that its result could
                        change across SQL statements. This is the appropriate selection for
                        functions whose results depend on database lookups, parameter values (such
                        as the current time zone), and so on. Also note that the
                            <varname>current_timestamp</varname> family of functions qualify as
                        stable, since their values do not change within a transaction.</pd>
                    <pd><codeph>VOLATILE</codeph> indicates that the function value can change even
                        within a single table scan, so no optimizations can be made. Relatively few
                        database functions are volatile in this sense; some examples are
                            <codeph>random()</codeph>, <codeph>timeofday()</codeph>. But note that
                        any function that has side-effects must be classified volatile, even if its
                        result is quite predictable, to prevent calls from being optimized away; an
                        example is <codeph>setval()</codeph>.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>CALLED ON NULL INPUT</pt>
                    <pt>RETURNS NULL ON NULL INPUT</pt>
                    <pt>STRICT</pt>
                    <pd><codeph>CALLED ON NULL INPUT</codeph> (the default) indicates that the
                        function will be called normally when some of its arguments are null. It is
                        then the function author's responsibility to check for null values if
                        necessary and respond appropriately. <codeph>RETURNS NULL ON NULL
                            INPUT</codeph> or <codeph>STRICT</codeph> indicates that the function
                        always returns null whenever any of its arguments are null. If this
                        parameter is specified, the function is not executed when there are null
                        arguments; instead a null result is assumed automatically.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>[EXTERNAL] SECURITY INVOKER</pt>
                    <pt>[EXTERNAL] SECURITY DEFINER</pt>
                    <pd><codeph>SECURITY INVOKER</codeph> (the default) indicates that the function
                        is to be executed with the privileges of the user that calls it.
                            <codeph>SECURITY DEFINER</codeph> specifies that the function is to be
                        executed with the privileges of the user that created it. The key word
                            <codeph>EXTERNAL</codeph> is allowed for SQL conformance, but it is
                        optional since, unlike in SQL, this feature applies to all functions not
                        just external ones.</pd>
                </plentry>

                <plentry>
                    <pt>EXECUTE ON ANY</pt>
                    <pt>EXECUTE ON MASTER</pt>
                    <pt>EXECUTE ON ALL SEGMENTS</pt>
                    <pd>The <codeph>EXECUTE ON</codeph> attributes specify where (master or segment
                        instance) a function executes when it is invoked during the query execution
                        process.</pd>
                    <pd><codeph>EXECUTE ON ANY</codeph> (the default) indicates that the function
                        can be executed on the master, or any segment instance, and it returns the
                        same result regardless of where it is executed. Greenplum Database
                        determines where the function executes.</pd>
                    <pd><codeph>EXECUTE ON MASTER</codeph> indicates that the function must execute
                        only on the master instance. </pd>
                    <pd><codeph>EXECUTE ON ALL SEGMENTS</codeph> indicates that the function must
                        execute on all primary segment instances, but not the master, for each
                        invocation. The overall result of the function is the <codeph>UNION
                            ALL</codeph> of the results from all segment instances. </pd>
                    <pd>For information about using <codeph>EXECUTE ON</codeph> attributes, see
                            <xref href="#topic1/section6" format="dita">Notes</xref>.</pd>
                </plentry>

                <plentry>
                    <pt>COST <varname>execution_cost</varname></pt>
                    <pd>A positive number identifying the estimated execution cost for the function,
                        in <xref
                            href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/8.3/static/runtime-config-query.html#GUC-CPU-OPERATOR-COST"
                            scope="external" format="html">cpu_operator_cost</xref> units. If the
                        function returns a set, <varname>execution_cost</varname> identifies the
                        cost per returned row. If the cost is not specified, C-language and internal
                        functions default to 1 unit, while functions in other languages default to
                        100 units. The planner tries to evaluate the function less often when you
                        specify larger <varname>execution_cost</varname> values.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>configuration_parameter</varname></pt>
                    <pt><varname>value</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The <codeph>SET</codeph> clause applies a value to a session configuration
                        parameter when the function is entered. The configuration parameter is
                        restored to its prior value when the function exits. <codeph>SET FROM
                            CURRENT</codeph> applies the session's current value of the parameter
                        when the function is entered.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>definition</varname></pt>
                    <pd>A string constant defining the function; the meaning depends on the
                        language. It may be an internal function name, the path to an object file,
                        an SQL command, or text in a procedural language.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>obj_file, link_symbol</varname></pt>
                    <pd>This form of the <codeph>AS</codeph> clause is used for dynamically loadable
                        C language functions when the function name in the C language source code is
                        not the same as the name of the SQL function. The string
                            <varname>obj_file</varname> is the name of the file containing the
                        dynamically loadable object, and <varname>link_symbol</varname> is the name
                        of the function in the C language source code. If the link symbol is
                        omitted, it is assumed to be the same as the name of the SQL function being
                        defined. It is recommended to locate shared libraries either relative to
                            <codeph>$libdir</codeph> (which is located at
                            <codeph>$GPHOME/lib</codeph>) or through the dynamic library path (set
                        by the <codeph>dynamic_library_path</codeph> server configuration
                        parameter). This simplifies version upgrades if the new installation is at a
                        different location.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt><varname>describe_function</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The name of a callback function to execute when a query that calls this
                        function is parsed. The callback function returns a tuple descriptor that
                        indicates the result type.</pd>
                </plentry>
            </parml></section>
        <section id="section6"><title>Notes</title><p>Any compiled code (shared library files) for
                custom functions must be placed in the same location on every host in your Greenplum
                Database array (master and all segments). This location must also be in the
                    <codeph>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</codeph> so that the server can locate the files. It is
                recommended to locate shared libraries either relative to <codeph>$libdir</codeph>
                (which is located at <codeph>$GPHOME/lib</codeph>) or through the dynamic library
                path (set by the <codeph>dynamic_library_path</codeph> server configuration
                parameter) on all master segment instances in the Greenplum array.</p><p>The full
                SQL type syntax is allowed for input arguments and return value. However, some
                details of the type specification (such as the precision field for type
                    <varname>numeric</varname>) are the responsibility of the underlying function
                implementation and are not recognized or enforced by the <codeph>CREATE
                    FUNCTION</codeph> command. </p><p>Greenplum Database allows function
                overloading. The same name can be used for several different functions so long as
                they have distinct argument types. However, the C names of all functions must be
                different, so you must give overloaded C functions different C names (for example,
                use the argument types as part of the C names). </p><p>Two functions are considered
                the same if they have the same names and input argument types, ignoring any
                    <codeph>OUT</codeph> parameters. Thus for example these declarations
                conflict:</p><codeblock>CREATE FUNCTION foo(int) ...
CREATE FUNCTION foo(int, out text) ...</codeblock>
            <p>Functions that have different argument type lists are not considered to conflict at
                creation time, but if argument defaults are provided, they might conflict in use.
                For example, consider:</p><codeblock>CREATE FUNCTION foo(int) ...
CREATE FUNCTION foo(int, int default 42) ...</codeblock>
            <p>The call <codeph>foo(10)</codeph>, will fail due to the ambiguity about which
                function should be called.</p>
            <p>When repeated <codeph>CREATE FUNCTION</codeph> calls refer to the same object file,
                the file is only loaded once. To unload and reload the file, use the
                    <codeph>LOAD</codeph> command. </p><p>You must have the <codeph>USAGE</codeph>
                privilege on a language to be able to define a function using that language.</p>
            <p>It is often helpful to use dollar quoting to write the function definition string,
                rather than the normal single quote syntax. Without dollar quoting, any single
                quotes or backslashes in the function definition must be escaped by doubling them. A
                dollar-quoted string constant consists of a dollar sign (<codeph>$</codeph>), an
                optional tag of zero or more characters, another dollar sign, an arbitrary sequence
                of characters that makes up the string content, a dollar sign, the same tag that
                began this dollar quote, and a dollar sign. Inside the dollar-quoted string, single
                quotes, backslashes, or any character can be used without escaping. The string
                content is always written literally. For example, here are two different ways to
                specify the string "Dianne's horse" using dollar quoting:</p><codeblock>$$Dianne's horse$$
$SomeTag$Dianne's horse$SomeTag$</codeblock>
            <p>If a <codeph>SET</codeph> clause is attached to a function, the effects of a
                    <codeph>SET LOCAL</codeph> command executed inside the function for the same
                variable are restricted to the function; the configuration parameter's prior value
                is still restored when the function exits. However, an ordinary <codeph>SET</codeph>
                command (without <codeph>LOCAL</codeph>) overrides the <codeph>CREATE
                    FUNCTION</codeph>
                <codeph>SET</codeph> clause, much as it would for a previous <codeph>SET
                    LOCAL</codeph> command. The effects of such a command will persist after the
                function exits, unless the current transaction is rolled back.</p>
            <p>If a function with a <codeph>VARIADIC</codeph> argument is declared as
                    <codeph>STRICT</codeph>, the strictness check tests that the variadic array as a
                whole is non-null. PL/pgSQL will still call the function if the array has null
                elements.</p>
            <sectiondiv id="section7"><b>Using Functions with Queries on Distributed Data</b><p>In
                    some cases, Greenplum Database does not support using functions in a query where
                    the data in a table specified in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause is distributed
                    over Greenplum Database segments. As an example, this SQL query contains the
                    function
                    <codeph>func()</codeph>:</p><codeblock>SELECT func(a) FROM table1;</codeblock><p>The
                    function is not supported for use in the query if all of the following
                    conditions are met:</p><ul>
                    <li id="bs144942">The data of table <codeph>table1</codeph> is distributed over
                        Greenplum Database segments.</li>
                    <li id="bs144694">The function <codeph>func()</codeph> reads or modifies data
                        from distributed tables. </li>
                    <li id="bs145327">The function <codeph>func()</codeph> returns more than one row
                        or takes an argument (<codeph>a</codeph>) that comes from
                            <codeph>table1</codeph>.</li>
                </ul><p>If any of the conditions are not met, the function is supported.
                    Specifically, the function is supported if any of the following conditions
                    apply:</p><ul>
                    <li id="bs144699">The function <codeph>func()</codeph> does not access data from
                        distributed tables, or accesses data that is only on the Greenplum Database
                        master. </li>
                    <li id="bs144700">The table <codeph>table1</codeph> is a master only table.</li>
                    <li id="bs144701">The function <codeph>func()</codeph> returns only one row and
                        only takes input arguments that are constant values. The function is
                        supported if it can be changed to require no input arguments.</li>
                </ul></sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv><b>Using EXECUTE ON attributes</b><p>A function that executes queries to
                    access tables is only supported when a function is executed on the master. Such
                    functions should be defined with the <codeph>EXECUTE ON MASTER</codeph>
                    attribute. Otherwise, the function might return incorrect results when the
                    function is used in a complicated query. Without the attribute, planner
                    optimization might determine it would be beneficial to push the function
                    invocation to segment instances.</p>These are limitations for functions defined
                with the <codeph>EXECUTE ON MASTER</codeph> or <codeph>EXECUTE ON ALL
                    SEGMENTS</codeph> attribute:<ul id="ul_nlg_jky_fcb">
                    <li>The function must be a set-returning function.</li>
                    <li>The function cannot be in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause of a query.</li>
                    <li>The function cannot be in the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> list of a query with a
                            <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause.</li>
                    <li>A query that includes the function falls back from GPORCA to the legacy
                        query planner.</li>
                </ul></sectiondiv></section>
        <section id="section8"><title>Examples</title><p>A very simple addition
                function:</p><codeblock>CREATE FUNCTION add(integer, integer) RETURNS integer
    AS 'select $1 + $2;'
    LANGUAGE SQL
    IMMUTABLE
    RETURNS NULL ON NULL INPUT;</codeblock><p>Increment
                an integer, making use of an argument name, in PL/pgSQL:</p><codeblock>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION increment(i integer) RETURNS 
integer AS $$
        BEGIN
                RETURN i + 1;
        END;
$$ LANGUAGE plpgsql;</codeblock>
            <p>Increase the default segment host memory per query for a PL/pgSQL function:</p>
            <codeblock>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION function_with_query() RETURNS 
SETOF text AS $$
        BEGIN
                RETURN QUERY
                EXPLAIN ANALYZE SELECT * FROM large_table;
        END;
$$ LANGUAGE plpgsql
SET statement_mem='256MB';</codeblock>
            <p>Use polymorphic types to return an <codeph>ENUM</codeph> array:</p>
            <codeblock>CREATE TYPE rainbow AS ENUM('red','orange','yellow','green','blue','indigo','violet');
CREATE FUNCTION return_enum_as_array( anyenum, anyelement, anyelement ) 
    RETURNS TABLE (ae anyenum, aa anyarray) AS $$
    SELECT $1, array[$2, $3] 
$$ LANGUAGE SQL STABLE;

SELECT * FROM return_enum_as_array('red'::rainbow, 'green'::rainbow, 'blue'::rainbow);</codeblock><p>Return
                a record containing multiple output
                parameters:</p><codeblock>CREATE FUNCTION dup(in int, out f1 int, out f2 text)
    AS $$ SELECT $1, CAST($1 AS text) || ' is text' $$
    LANGUAGE SQL;

SELECT * FROM dup(42);</codeblock><p>You
                can do the same thing more verbosely with an explicitly named composite type:</p><codeblock>CREATE TYPE dup_result AS (f1 int, f2 text);
CREATE FUNCTION dup(int) RETURNS dup_result
    AS $$ SELECT $1, CAST($1 AS text) || ' is text' $$
    LANGUAGE SQL;

SELECT * FROM dup(42);</codeblock>
            <p>This function is defined with the <codeph>EXECUTE ON ALL SEGMENTS</codeph> to run on
                all primary segment instances. The <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command executes the
                function that returns the time it was run on each segment
                instance.<codeblock>CREATE FUNCTION run_on_segs (text) returns setof text as $$
  begin 
    return next ($1 || ' - ' || now()::text ); 
  end;
 $$ language plpgsql VOLATILE EXECUTE ON ALL SEGMENTS;

SELECT run_on_segs('my test');</codeblock></p></section>
        <section id="section9"><title>Compatibility</title><p><codeph>CREATE FUNCTION</codeph> is
                defined in SQL:1999 and later. The Greenplum Database version is similar but not
                fully compatible. The attributes are not portable, neither are the different
                available languages. </p><p>For compatibility with some other database systems,
                    <varname>argmode</varname> can be written either before or after
                    <varname>argname</varname>. But only the first way is standard-compliant. </p>
            <p>The SQL standard does not specify parameter defaults.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="section10"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref
                        href="ALTER_FUNCTION.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
                        <codeph><xref href="./DROP_FUNCTION.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                    /></codeph>, <codeph><xref href="./LOAD.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                    /></codeph></p></section>
    </body>
</topic>
