<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="cv20941">DROP FUNCTION</title><body><p id="sql_command_desc">Removes a function.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">DROP FUNCTION [IF EXISTS] name ( [ [argmode] [argname] argtype 
    [, ...] ] ) [CASCADE | RESTRICT]</codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>DROP FUNCTION</codeph> removes the definition of an existing
function. To execute this command the user must be the owner of the function.
The argument types to the function must be specified, since several different
functions may exist with the same name and different argument lists.</p></section><section id="section4"><title>Parameters</title><parml><plentry><pt>IF EXISTS</pt><pd>Do not throw an error if the function does not exist. A notice is
issued in this case. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>name</varname></pt><pd>The name (optionally schema-qualified) of an existing function.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>argmode</varname></pt><pd>The mode of an argument: either <codeph>IN</codeph>, <codeph>OUT</codeph>,
<codeph>INOUT</codeph>, or <codeph>VARIADIC</codeph>. If omitted, the default is IN. Note that <codeph>DROP
FUNCTION</codeph> does not actually pay any attention to <codeph>OUT</codeph>
arguments, since only the input arguments are needed to determine the
function's identity. So it is sufficient to list the <codeph>IN</codeph>,
 <codeph>INOUT</codeph>, and <codeph>VARIADIC</codeph> arguments. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>argname</varname></pt><pd>The name of an argument. Note that <codeph>DROP FUNCTION</codeph>
does not actually pay any attention to argument names, since only the
argument data types are needed to determine the function's identity.
</pd></plentry><plentry><pt><varname>argtype</varname></pt><pd>The data type(s) of the function's arguments (optionally schema-qualified),
if any.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>CASCADE</pt><pd>Automatically drop objects that depend on the function such as operators.
</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>RESTRICT</pt><pd>Refuse to drop the function if any objects depend on it. This is
the default.</pd></plentry></parml></section><section id="section5"><title>Examples</title><p>Drop the square root function: </p><codeblock>DROP FUNCTION sqrt(integer);</codeblock></section><section id="section6"><title>Compatibility</title><p>A <codeph>DROP FUNCTION</codeph> statement is defined in the SQL standard,
but it is not compatible with this command.</p></section><section id="section7"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref href="CREATE_FUNCTION.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="ALTER_FUNCTION.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p></section></body></topic>
