<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="ds20941">GRANT</title><body><p id="sql_command_desc">Defines access privileges.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">GRANT { {SELECT | INSERT | UPDATE | DELETE | REFERENCES | 
TRIGGER | TRUNCATE } [,...] | ALL [PRIVILEGES] }
    ON [TABLE] <varname>tablename</varname> [, ...]
    TO {<varname>rolename</varname> | PUBLIC} [, ...] [WITH GRANT OPTION]

GRANT { {USAGE | SELECT | UPDATE} [,...] | ALL [PRIVILEGES] }
    ON SEQUENCE <varname>sequencename</varname> [, ...]
    TO { <varname>rolename</varname> | PUBLIC } [, ...] [WITH GRANT OPTION]

GRANT { {CREATE | CONNECT | TEMPORARY | TEMP} [,...] | ALL 
[PRIVILEGES] }
    ON DATABASE <varname>dbname</varname> [, ...]
    TO {<varname>rolename</varname> | PUBLIC} [, ...] [WITH GRANT OPTION]

GRANT { EXECUTE | ALL [PRIVILEGES] }
    ON FUNCTION <varname>funcname</varname> ( [ [<varname>argmode</varname>] [<varname>argname</varname>] <varname>argtype</varname> [, ...] 
] ) [, ...]
    TO {<varname>rolename</varname> | PUBLIC} [, ...] [WITH GRANT OPTION]

GRANT { USAGE | ALL [PRIVILEGES] }
    ON LANGUAGE <varname>langname</varname> [, ...]
    TO {<varname>rolename</varname> | PUBLIC} [, ...] [WITH GRANT OPTION]

GRANT { {CREATE | USAGE} [,...] | ALL [PRIVILEGES] }
    ON SCHEMA <varname>schemaname</varname> [, ...]
    TO {<varname>rolename</varname> | PUBLIC} [, ...] [WITH GRANT OPTION]

GRANT { CREATE | ALL [PRIVILEGES] }
    ON TABLESPACE <varname>tablespacename</varname> [, ...]
    TO {<varname>rolename</varname> | PUBLIC} [, ...] [WITH GRANT OPTION]

GRANT <varname>parent_role</varname> [, ...] 
    TO <varname>member_role</varname> [, ...] [WITH ADMIN OPTION]

GRANT { SELECT | INSERT | ALL [PRIVILEGES] } 
    ON PROTOCOL <varname>protocolname</varname>
    TO <varname>username</varname></codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p>The <codeph>GRANT</codeph> command has two basic variants: one that
grants privileges on a database object (table, view, sequence, database,
function, procedural language, schema, or tablespace), and one that grants
membership in a role.</p><sectiondiv id="section4"><b>GRANT on Database Objects</b><p>This variant of the <codeph>GRANT</codeph> command gives specific privileges
on a database object to one or more roles. These privileges are added
to those already granted, if any. </p><p>The key word <codeph>PUBLIC</codeph> indicates that the privileges
are to be granted to all roles, including those that may be created later.
<codeph>PUBLIC</codeph> may be thought of as an implicitly defined group-level
role that always includes all roles. Any particular role will have the
sum of privileges granted directly to it, privileges granted to any role
it is presently a member of, and privileges granted to <codeph>PUBLIC</codeph>.
</p><p>If <codeph>WITH GRANT OPTION</codeph> is specified, the recipient
of the privilege may in turn grant it to others. Without a grant option,
the recipient cannot do that. Grant options cannot be granted to <codeph>PUBLIC</codeph>.
</p><p>There is no need to grant privileges to the owner of an object (usually
the role that created it), as the owner has all privileges by default.
The right to drop an object, or to alter its definition in any way is
not described by a grantable privilege; it is inherent in the owner,
and cannot be granted or revoked. The owner implicitly has all grant
options for the object, too.</p><p>Depending on the type of object, the initial default privileges may
include granting some privileges to <codeph>PUBLIC</codeph>. The default
is no public access for tables, schemas, and tablespaces; <codeph>CONNECT</codeph>
privilege and <codeph>TEMP</codeph> table creation privilege for databases;
<codeph>EXECUTE</codeph> privilege for functions; and <codeph>USAGE</codeph>
privilege for languages. The object owner may of course revoke these
privileges.</p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section5"><b>GRANT on Roles</b><p>This variant of the <codeph>GRANT</codeph> command grants membership
in a role to one or more other roles. Membership in a role is significant
because it conveys the privileges granted to a role to each of its members.
</p><p>If <codeph>WITH ADMIN OPTION</codeph> is specified, the member may
in turn grant membership in the role to others, and revoke membership
in the role as well. Database superusers can grant or revoke membership
in any role to anyone. Roles having <codeph>CREATEROLE</codeph> privilege
can grant or revoke membership in any role that is not a superuser.</p><p>Unlike the case with privileges, membership in a role cannot be granted
to <codeph>PUBLIC</codeph>.</p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section6"><b>GRANT on Protocols</b><p>After creating a custom protocol, specify <codeph>CREATE TRUSTED PROTOCOL</codeph>
to be able to allowing any user besides the owner to access it. If the
protocol is not trusted, you cannot give any other user permission to
use it to read or write data. After a <codeph>TRUSTED</codeph> protocol
is created, you can specify which other users can access it with the
<codeph>GRANT</codeph> command. </p><ul><li id="ds157703">To allow a user to create a readable external table with a trusted
            protocol<codeblock>GRANT SELECT ON PROTOCOL <varname>protocolname</varname> TO <varname>username</varname></codeblock></li><li id="ds157705">To allow a user to create a writable external table with a trusted
            protocol<codeblock>GRANT INSERT ON PROTOCOL <varname>protocolname</varname> TO <varname>username</varname></codeblock></li><li id="ds157707">To allow a user to create both readable and writable external table with a trusted
            protocol<codeblock>GRANT ALL ON PROTOCOL <varname>protocolname</varname> TO <varname>username</varname></codeblock></li></ul></sectiondiv></section><section id="section7"><title>Parameters</title><parml><plentry><pt>SELECT</pt><pd>Allows <codeph>SELECT</codeph> from any column of the specified table,
view, or sequence. Also allows the use of <codeph>COPY TO</codeph>.</pd> 
</plentry><plentry><pt>INSERT</pt><pd>Allows <codeph>INSERT</codeph> of a new row into the specified table.
Also allows <codeph>COPY FROM</codeph>.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>UPDATE</pt><pd>Allows <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> of any column of the specified table.
<codeph>SELECT ... FOR UPDATE</codeph> and <codeph>SELECT ... FOR SHARE</codeph>
also require this privilege (as well as the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> privilege).
For sequences, this privilege allows the use of the <codeph>nextval()</codeph>
and <codeph>setval()</codeph> functions.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>DELETE</pt><pd>Allows <codeph>DELETE</codeph> of a row from the specified table.
</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>REFERENCES</pt><pd>This keyword is accepted, although foreign key constraints are currently
not supported in Greenplum Database. To create a foreign key constraint,
it is necessary to have this privilege on both the referencing and referenced
tables.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>TRIGGER</pt><pd>Allows the creation of a trigger on the specified table.<note>Greenplum Database does not
              support triggers.</note></pd></plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>TRUNCATE</pt>
          <pd>
            <p>Allows <codeph>TRUNCATE</codeph> of all rows from the specified table. </p>
          </pd>
        </plentry><plentry><pt>CREATE</pt><pd>For databases, allows new schemas to be created within the database.</pd><pd>For schemas, allows new objects to be created within the schema.
To rename an existing object, you must own the object and have this privilege
for the containing schema.</pd><pd>For tablespaces, allows tables and indexes to be created within the
tablespace, and allows databases to be created that have the tablespace
as their default tablespace. (Note that revoking this privilege will
not alter the placement of existing objects.)</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>CONNECT</pt><pd>Allows the user to connect to the specified database. This privilege
is checked at connection startup (in addition to checking any restrictions
imposed by <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph>).</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>TEMPORARY</pt><pt>TEMP</pt><pd>Allows temporary tables to be created while using the database.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>EXECUTE</pt><pd>Allows the use of the specified function and the use of any operators
that are implemented on top of the function. This is the only type of
privilege that is applicable to functions. (This syntax works for aggregate
functions, as well.) </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>USAGE</pt><pd>For procedural languages, allows the use of the specified language
for the creation of functions in that language. This is the only type
of privilege that is applicable to procedural languages.</pd><pd>For schemas, allows access to objects contained in the specified
schema (assuming that the objects' own privilege requirements are also
met). Essentially this allows the grantee to look up objects within the
schema.</pd><pd>For sequences, this privilege allows the use of the 
<codeph>nextval()</codeph> function. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>ALL PRIVILEGES</pt><pd>Grant all of the available privileges at once. The <codeph>PRIVILEGES</codeph>
key word is optional in Greenplum Database, though it is required by
strict SQL. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>PUBLIC</pt><pd>A special group-level role that denotes that the privileges are to
be granted to all roles, including those that may be created later. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>WITH GRANT OPTION</pt><pd>The recipient of the privilege may in turn grant it to others.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>WITH ADMIN OPTION</pt><pd>The member of a role may in turn grant membership in the role to
others.</pd></plentry></parml></section><section id="section8"><title>Notes</title><p>Database superusers can access all objects regardless of object privilege
settings. One exception to this rule is view objects. Access to tables
referenced in the view is determined by permissions of the view owner
not the current user (even if the current user is a superuser).</p><p>If a superuser chooses to issue a <codeph>GRANT</codeph> or <codeph>REVOKE</codeph>
command, the command is performed as though it were issued by the owner
of the affected object. In particular, privileges granted via such a
command will appear to have been granted by the object owner. For role
membership, the membership appears to have been granted by the containing
role itself. </p><p><codeph>GRANT</codeph> and <codeph>REVOKE</codeph> can also be done
by a role that is not the owner of the affected object, but is a member
of the role that owns the object, or is a member of a role that holds
privileges <codeph>WITH GRANT OPTION</codeph> on the object. In this
case the privileges will be recorded as having been granted by the role
that actually owns the object or holds the privileges <codeph>WITH GRANT
OPTION</codeph>.</p><p>Granting permission on a table does not automatically extend permissions
to any sequences used by the table, including sequences tied to <codeph>SERIAL</codeph>
columns. Permissions on a sequence must be set separately. </p><p>Greenplum Database does not support granting or revoking privileges
for individual columns of a table. One possible workaround is to create
a view having just the desired columns and then grant privileges to that
view.</p><p>Use psql's <codeph>\z</codeph> meta-command to obtain information
about existing privileges for an object.</p></section><section id="section9"><title>Examples</title><p>Grant insert privilege to all roles on table <codeph>mytable</codeph>: </p><codeblock>GRANT INSERT ON mytable TO PUBLIC;</codeblock><p>Grant all available privileges to role <codeph>sally</codeph> on the view
        <codeph>topten</codeph>. Note that while the above will indeed grant all privileges if
        executed by a superuser or the owner of <codeph>topten</codeph>, when executed by someone
        else it will only grant those permissions for which the granting role has grant options.</p><codeblock>GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON topten TO sally;</codeblock><p>Grant membership in role <codeph>admins</codeph> to user <codeph>joe</codeph>: </p><codeblock>GRANT admins TO joe;</codeblock></section><section id="section10"><title>Compatibility</title><p>The <codeph>PRIVILEGES</codeph> key word in is required in the SQL standard,
but optional in Greenplum Database. The SQL standard does not support
setting the privileges on more than one object per command. </p><p>Greenplum Database allows an object owner to revoke his own ordinary privileges: for example, a
        table owner can make the table read-only to himself by revoking his own
          <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>,  <codeph>DELETE</codeph>, and
          <codeph>TRUNCATE</codeph> privileges. This is not possible according to the SQL standard.
        Greenplum Database treats the owner's privileges as having been granted by the owner to
        himself; therefore he can revoke them too. In the SQL standard, the owner's privileges are
        granted by an assumed <i>system</i> entity. </p><p>The SQL standard allows setting privileges for individual columns
within a table.</p><p>The SQL standard provides for a <codeph>USAGE</codeph> privilege on
other kinds of objects: character sets, collations, translations, domains.
</p><p>Privileges on databases, tablespaces, schemas, and languages are Greenplum
Database extensions.</p></section><section id="section11"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph><xref href="./REVOKE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p></section></body></topic>
