<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title id="eg20941">SELECT</title>
  <body>
    <p id="sql_command_desc">Retrieves rows from a table or view.</p>
    <section id="section2">
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">[ WITH [ RECURSIVE<sup>1</sup> ] <varname>with_query</varname> [, ...] ]
SELECT [ALL | DISTINCT [ON (<varname>expression</varname> [, ...])]]
  * | <varname>expression </varname>[[AS] <varname>output_name</varname>] [, ...]
  [FROM <varname>from_item</varname> [, ...]]
  [WHERE <varname>condition</varname>]
  [GROUP BY <varname>grouping_element</varname> [, ...]]
  [HAVING <varname>condition</varname> [, ...]]
  [WINDOW <varname>window_name</varname> AS (<varname>window_specification</varname>)]
  [{UNION | INTERSECT | EXCEPT} [ALL] <varname>select</varname>]
  [ORDER BY <varname>expression</varname> [ASC | DESC | USING <varname>operator</varname>] [NULLS {FIRST | LAST}] [, ...]]
  [LIMIT {<varname>count</varname> | ALL}]
  [OFFSET <varname>start</varname>]
  [FOR {UPDATE | SHARE} [OF <varname>table_name</varname> [, ...]] [NOWAIT] [...]]</codeblock>
      <p>where <varname>with_query:</varname> is:</p>
      <codeblock>  <varname>with_query_name</varname> [( <varname>column_name</varname> [, ...] )] AS ( <varname>select</varname> )</codeblock>
      <p>where <varname>grouping_element</varname> can be one of:</p>
      <codeblock>  ()
  <varname>expression</varname>
  ROLLUP (<varname>expression</varname> [,...])
  CUBE (<varname>expression</varname> [,...])
  GROUPING SETS ((<varname>grouping_element</varname> [, ...]))</codeblock>
      <p>where <varname>window_specification</varname> can be:</p>
      <codeblock>  [<varname>window_name</varname>]
  [PARTITION BY <varname>expression </varname>[, ...]]
  [ORDER BY <varname>expression</varname> [ASC | DESC | USING <varname>operator</varname>] [NULLS {FIRST | LAST}] [, ...]
     [{RANGE | ROWS} 
          { UNBOUNDED PRECEDING
          | <varname>expression</varname> PRECEDING
          | CURRENT ROW
          | BETWEEN <varname>window_frame_bound</varname> AND <varname>window_frame_bound</varname> }]]
                    where <varname>window_frame_bound</varname> can be one of:
                        UNBOUNDED PRECEDING
                        <varname>expression</varname> PRECEDING
                        CURRENT ROW
                        <varname>expression</varname> FOLLOWING
                        UNBOUNDED FOLLOWING</codeblock>
      <p>where <varname>from_item</varname> can be one of:</p>
      <codeblock>[ONLY] <varname>table_name</varname> [[AS] <varname>alias</varname> [( <varname>column_alias</varname> [, ...] )]]
(select) [AS] <varname>alias</varname> [( <varname>column_alias</varname> [, ...] )]<varname>
with_query_name</varname> [ [AS] <varname>alias</varname> [( <varname>column_alias</varname> [, ...] )]]
<varname>function_name</varname> ( [<varname>argument</varname> [, ...]] ) [AS] <varname>alias</varname>
             [( <varname>column_alias</varname> [, ...] 
                | <varname>column_definition</varname> [, ...] )]
<varname>function_name</varname> ( [<varname>argument</varname> [, ...]] ) AS 
              ( <varname>column_definition</varname> [, ...] )
<varname>from_item</varname> [NATURAL] <varname>join_type</varname> <varname>from_item</varname>
          [ON <varname>join_condition</varname> | USING ( <varname>join_column</varname> [, ...] )]</codeblock>
      <p><b>Note:</b>
        <sup>1</sup>The <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword is an experimental feature and is not
        recommended for production use.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section3">
      <title>Description</title>
      <p><codeph>SELECT</codeph> retrieves rows from zero or more tables. The general processing of
          <codeph>SELECT</codeph> is as follows: </p>
      <ol>
        <li>All queries in the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause are computed. These effectively serve as
          temporary tables that can be referenced in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> list. </li>
        <li id="eg138796">All elements in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> list are computed. (Each element
          in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> list is a real or virtual table.) If more than one element is
          specified in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> list, they are cross-joined together.</li>
        <li id="eg138832">If the <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause is specified, all rows that do not
          satisfy the condition are eliminated from the output.</li>
        <li id="eg138840">If the <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clause is specified, the output is
          divided into groups of rows that match on one or more of the defined grouping elements. If
          the <codeph>HAVING</codeph> clause is present, it eliminates groups that do not satisfy
          the given condition.</li>
        <li id="eg141787">If a window expression is specified (and optional <codeph>WINDOW</codeph>
          clause), the output is organized according to the positional (row) or value-based (range)
          window frame.</li>
        <li id="eg141798"><codeph>DISTINCT</codeph> eliminates duplicate rows from the result.
            <codeph>DISTINCT ON</codeph> eliminates rows that match on all the specified
          expressions. <codeph>ALL</codeph> (the default) will return all candidate rows, including
          duplicates.</li>
        <li id="eg138848">The actual output rows are computed using the <codeph>SELECT</codeph>
          output expressions for each selected row.</li>
        <li id="eg138856">Using the operators <codeph>UNION</codeph>, <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph>,
          and <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph>, the output of more than one <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement
          can be combined to form a single result set. The <codeph>UNION</codeph> operator returns
          all rows that are in one or both of the result sets. The <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph>
          operator returns all rows that are strictly in both result sets. The
            <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph> operator returns the rows that are in the first result set but
          not in the second. In all three cases, duplicate rows are eliminated unless
            <codeph>ALL</codeph> is specified.</li>
        <li id="eg138864">If the <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause is specified, the returned rows
          are sorted in the specified order. If <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> is not given, the rows are
          returned in whatever order the system finds fastest to produce.</li>
        <li id="eg138878">If the <codeph>LIMIT</codeph> or <codeph>OFFSET</codeph> clause is
          specified, the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement only returns a subset of the result
          rows.</li>
        <li id="eg138885">If <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph> or <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> is specified,
          the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement locks the entire table against concurrent
          updates.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>You must have <codeph>SELECT</codeph> privilege on a table to read its values. The use of
          <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph> or <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> requires <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>
        privilege as well.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section4">
      <title>Parameters</title>
      <sectiondiv>
        <b>The WITH Clause</b>
        <p>The optional <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause allows you to specify one or more subqueries
          that can be referenced by name in the primary query. The subqueries effectively act as
          temporary tables or views for the duration of the primary query. Each subquery can be a
            <codeph>SELECT</codeph>, or <codeph>VALUES</codeph> command. </p><p>A
            <varname>with_query_name</varname> without schema qualification must be specified for
          each query in the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause. Optionally, a list of column names can be
          specified; if the list of column names is omitted, the names are inferred from the
          subquery. The primary query and the <codeph>WITH</codeph> queries are all (notionally)
          executed at the same time. </p><p>The <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword can be enabled by
          setting the server configuration parameter <codeph>gp_recursive_cte_prototype</codeph> to
            <codeph>true</codeph>. For information about the parameter, see <xref
            href="../config_params/guc_config.xml#topic1"/>.<note type="warning">The
              <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword is an experimental feature and is not intended for
            use in a production environment. Experimental features are subject to change without
            notice in future releases.</note></p><p>If <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> is specified, it
          allows a subquery to reference itself by name. Such a subquery, the
            <varname>select</varname> portion of the <varname>with_query</varname> , must have the
          form</p><codeblock><varname>non_recursive_term</varname> UNION [ALL] <varname>recursive_term</varname></codeblock><p>The
          recursive self-reference must appear on the right-hand side of the <codeph>UNION
            [ALL]</codeph>. Only one recursive self-reference is permitted per query. </p><p>If the
            <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword is specified, the <codeph>WITH</codeph> queries need
          not be ordered: a query can reference another query that is later in the list. However,
          circular references, or mutual recursion, are not supported. </p><p>Without the
            <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword, <codeph>WITH</codeph> queries can only reference
          sibling <codeph>WITH</codeph> queries that are earlier in the <codeph>WITH</codeph>
          list.</p><p><codeph>WITH RECURSIVE</codeph> limitations. These items are not supported,<ul
            id="ul_b21_szt_n1b">
            <li>A recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause that contains the following in the
                <varname>recursive_term</varname>. <ul id="ul_c1b_nhf_p1b">
                <li>Subqueries with a self-reference</li>
                <li><codeph>DISTINCT</codeph> clause</li>
                <li><codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clause</li>
                <li>A window function</li>
              </ul></li>
            <li>A recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause where the
                <varname>with_query_name</varname> is a part of a set operation.</li>
          </ul></p><p>An example the set operation limitation. This query returns an error because
          the set operation <codeph>UNION</codeph> contains a reference to the table
            <codeph>foo</codeph>.
          <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE foo(i) AS (
    SELECT 1
  UNION ALL
    SELECT i+1 FROM (SELECT * FROM foo UNION SELECT 0) bar
)
SELECT * FROM foo LIMIT 5;</codeblock></p><p>This
          recursive CTE is allowed because the set operation <codeph>UNION</codeph> does not have a
          reference to the CTE
          <codeph>foo</codeph>.<codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE foo(i) AS (
    SELECT 1
  UNION ALL
    SELECT i+1 FROM (SELECT * FROM bar UNION SELECT 0) bar, foo
    WHERE foo.i = bar.a
)
SELECT * FROM foo LIMIT 5;</codeblock></p><p>See
            <xref href="../../admin_guide/query/topics/CTE-query.xml#topic_zhs_r1s_w1b"/><ph
            otherprops="pivotal"> in the <cite>Greenplum Database Administrator Guide</cite></ph>
          for additional information.</p>
      </sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section5">
        <b>The SELECT List</b>
        <p>The <codeph>SELECT</codeph> list (between the key words <codeph>SELECT</codeph> and
            <codeph>FROM</codeph>) specifies expressions that form the output rows of the
            <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement. The expressions can (and usually do) refer to columns
          computed in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause. </p>
        <p>Using the clause <codeph>[AS] </codeph>
          <varname>output_name</varname>, another name can be specified for an output column. This
          name is primarily used to label the column for display. It can also be used to refer to
          the column's value in <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> and <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clauses, but
          not in the <codeph>WHERE</codeph> or <codeph>HAVING</codeph> clauses; there you must write
          out the expression instead. The <codeph>AS</codeph> keyword is optional in most cases
          (such as when declaring an alias for column names, constants, function calls, and simple
          unary operator expressions). In cases where the declared alias is a reserved SQL keyword,
          the <varname>output_name</varname> must be enclosed in double quotes to avoid
          ambiguity.</p><p>An <varname>expression</varname> in the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> list can
          be a constant value, a column reference, an operator invocation, a function call, an
          aggregate expression, a window expression, a scalar subquery, and so on. A number of
          constructs can be classified as an expression but do not follow any general syntax rules.
          These generally have the semantics of a function or operator. For information about SQL
          value expressions and function calls, see "Querying Data" in the <i>Greenplum Database
            Administrator Guide</i>.</p><p>Instead of an expression, <codeph>*</codeph> can be
          written in the output list as a shorthand for all the columns of the selected rows. Also,
          you can write <codeph><varname>table_name</varname>.*</codeph> as a shorthand for the
          columns coming from just that table.</p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section6"><b>The FROM
          Clause</b><p>The <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause specifies one or more source tables for the
            <codeph>SELECT</codeph>. If multiple sources are specified, the result is the Cartesian
          product (cross join) of all the sources. But usually qualification conditions are added to
          restrict the returned rows to a small subset of the Cartesian product. The
            <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause can contain the following elements: </p><parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt><varname>table_name</varname></pt>
            <pd>The name (optionally schema-qualified) of an existing table or view. If
                <codeph>ONLY</codeph> is specified, only that table is scanned. If
                <codeph>ONLY</codeph> is not specified, the table and all its descendant tables (if
              any) are scanned.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt><varname>alias</varname></pt>
            <pd>A substitute name for the <codeph>FROM</codeph> item containing the alias. An alias
              is used for brevity or to eliminate ambiguity for self-joins (where the same table is
              scanned multiple times). When an alias is provided, it completely hides the actual
              name of the table or function; for example given <codeph>FROM foo AS f</codeph>, the
              remainder of the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> must refer to this <codeph>FROM</codeph> item
              as <codeph>f</codeph> not <codeph>foo</codeph>. If an alias is written, a column alias
              list can also be written to provide substitute names for one or more columns of the
              table.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt><varname>select</varname></pt>
            <pd>A sub-<codeph>SELECT</codeph> can appear in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause. This
              acts as though its output were created as a temporary table for the duration of this
              single <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command. Note that the sub-<codeph>SELECT</codeph> must
              be surrounded by parentheses, and an alias must be provided for it. A
                <codeph>VALUES</codeph> command can also be used here. See "Non-standard Clauses" in
              the <xref href="#topic1/section19" format="dita"/> section for limitations of using
              correlated sub-selects in Greenplum Database.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>
              <varname>with_query_name</varname>
            </pt>
            <pd>A <varname>with_query</varname> is referenced in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause by
              specifying its <varname>with_query_name</varname>, just as though the name were a
              table name. The <varname>with_query_name</varname> cannot contain a schema qualifier.
              An alias can be provided in the same way as for a table. </pd>
            <pd>The <varname>with_query</varname> hides a table of the same name for the purposes of
              the primary query. If necessary, you can refer to a table of the same name by
              qualifying the table name with the schema.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>
              <varname>function_name</varname>
            </pt>
            <pd>Function calls can appear in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause. (This is especially
              useful for functions that return result sets, but any function can be used.) This acts
              as though its output were created as a temporary table for the duration of this single
                <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command. An alias may also be used. If an alias is written,
              a column alias list can also be written to provide substitute names for one or more
              attributes of the function's composite return type. If the function has been defined
              as returning the record data type, then an alias or the key word <codeph>AS</codeph>
              must be present, followed by a column definition list in the form <codeph>(
                column_name data_type [, ... ] )</codeph>. The column definition list must match the
              actual number and types of columns returned by the function.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt><varname>join_type</varname></pt>
            <pd>One of:<ul id="ul_bwd_ft2_m4">
                <li id="eg139018"><b>[INNER] JOIN</b></li>
                <li id="eg139020"><b>LEFT [OUTER] JOIN</b></li>
                <li id="eg139022"><b>RIGHT [OUTER] JOIN</b></li>
                <li id="eg139024"><b>FULL [OUTER] JOIN</b></li>
                <li id="eg139026"><b>CROSS JOIN</b></li>
              </ul></pd>
            <pd>For the <codeph>INNER</codeph> and <codeph>OUTER</codeph> join types, a join
              condition must be specified, namely exactly one of <codeph>NATURAL</codeph>,
                <codeph>ON <varname>join_condition</varname></codeph>, or <codeph>USING (
                  <varname>join_column</varname> [, ...])</codeph>. See below for the meaning. For
                <codeph>CROSS JOIN</codeph>, none of these clauses may appear.</pd>
            <pd>A <codeph>JOIN</codeph> clause combines two <codeph>FROM</codeph> items. Use
              parentheses if necessary to determine the order of nesting. In the absence of
              parentheses, <codeph>JOIN</codeph>s nest left-to-right. In any case
                <codeph>JOIN</codeph> binds more tightly than the commas separating
                <codeph>FROM</codeph> items.</pd>
            <pd><codeph>CROSS JOIN</codeph> and <codeph>INNER JOIN</codeph> produce a simple
              Cartesian product, the same result as you get from listing the two items at the top
              level of <codeph>FROM</codeph>, but restricted by the join condition (if any).
                <codeph>CROSS JOIN</codeph> is equivalent to <codeph>INNER JOIN
                ON</codeph><codeph>(TRUE)</codeph>, that is, no rows are removed by qualification.
              These join types are just a notational convenience, since they do nothing you could
              not do with plain <codeph>FROM</codeph> and <codeph>WHERE</codeph>. </pd>
            <pd><codeph>LEFT OUTER JOIN</codeph> returns all rows in the qualified Cartesian product
              (i.e., all combined rows that pass its join condition), plus one copy of each row in
              the left-hand table for which there was no right-hand row that passed the join
              condition. This left-hand row is extended to the full width of the joined table by
              inserting null values for the right-hand columns. Note that only the
                <codeph>JOIN</codeph> clause's own condition is considered while deciding which rows
              have matches. Outer conditions are applied afterwards.</pd>
            <pd>Conversely, <codeph>RIGHT OUTER JOIN</codeph> returns all the joined rows, plus one
              row for each unmatched right-hand row (extended with nulls on the left). This is just
              a notational convenience, since you could convert it to a <codeph>LEFT OUTER
                JOIN</codeph> by switching the left and right inputs.</pd>
            <pd><codeph>FULL OUTER JOIN</codeph> returns all the joined rows, plus one row for each
              unmatched left-hand row (extended with nulls on the right), plus one row for each
              unmatched right-hand row (extended with nulls on the left).</pd>
          </plentry>
        </parml><parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt>ON <varname>join_condition</varname></pt>
            <pd><varname>join_condition</varname> is an expression resulting in a value of type
                <codeph>boolean</codeph> (similar to a <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause) that specifies
              which rows in a join are considered to match.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>USING (<varname>join_column</varname> [, ...])</pt>
            <pd>A clause of the form <codeph>USING ( a, b, ... )</codeph> is shorthand for
                <codeph>ON left_table.a = right_table.a AND left_table.b = right_table.b ...
              </codeph>. Also, <codeph>USING</codeph> implies that only one of each pair of
              equivalent columns will be included in the join output, not both.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>NATURAL</pt>
            <pd><codeph>NATURAL</codeph> is shorthand for a <codeph>USING</codeph> list that
              mentions all columns in the two tables that have the same names.</pd>
          </plentry>
        </parml></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section7"><b>The WHERE Clause</b><p>The optional
            <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause has the general
          form:</p><codeblock>WHERE <varname>condition</varname></codeblock><p>where
            <varname>condition</varname> is any expression that evaluates to a result of type
            <codeph>boolean</codeph>. Any row that does not satisfy this condition will be
          eliminated from the output. A row satisfies the condition if it returns true when the
          actual row values are substituted for any variable references. </p></sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv id="section8"><b>The GROUP BY Clause</b><p>The optional <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph>
          clause has the general
          form:</p><codeblock>GROUP BY <varname>grouping_element </varname>[, ...]</codeblock><p>where
            <varname>grouping_element</varname> can be one
            of:</p><codeblock>()
<varname>expression</varname>
ROLLUP (<varname>expression</varname> [,...])
CUBE (<varname>expression</varname> [,...])
GROUPING SETS ((<varname>grouping_element</varname> [, ...]))</codeblock><p><codeph>GROUP
            BY</codeph> will condense into a single row all selected rows that share the same values
          for the grouped expressions. <varname>expression</varname> can be an input column name, or
          the name or ordinal number of an output column (<codeph>SELECT</codeph> list item), or an
          arbitrary expression formed from input-column values. In case of ambiguity, a
            <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> name will be interpreted as an input-column name rather than
          an output column name.</p><p>Aggregate functions, if any are used, are computed across all
          rows making up each group, producing a separate value for each group (whereas without
            <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph>, an aggregate produces a single value computed across all the
          selected rows). When <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> is present, it is not valid for the
            <codeph>SELECT</codeph> list expressions to refer to ungrouped columns except within
          aggregate functions, since there would be more than one possible value to return for an
          ungrouped column.</p><p>Greenplum Database has the following additional OLAP grouping
          extensions (often referred to as <i>supergroups</i>):</p><parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt>ROLLUP</pt>
            <pd>A <codeph>ROLLUP</codeph> grouping is an extension to the <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph>
              clause that creates aggregate subtotals that roll up from the most detailed level to a
              grand total, following a list of grouping columns (or expressions).
                <codeph>ROLLUP</codeph> takes an ordered list of grouping columns, calculates the
              standard aggregate values specified in the <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clause, then
              creates progressively higher-level subtotals, moving from right to left through the
              list. Finally, it creates a grand total. A <codeph>ROLLUP</codeph> grouping can be
              thought of as a series of grouping sets. For example:</pd>
            <pd>
              <codeblock>GROUP BY ROLLUP (a,b,c) </codeblock>
            </pd>
            <pd>is equivalent to:</pd>
            <pd>
              <codeblock>GROUP BY GROUPING SETS( (a,b,c), (a,b), (a), () ) </codeblock>
            </pd>
            <pd>Notice that the <varname>n</varname> elements of a <codeph>ROLLUP</codeph> translate
              to <varname>n</varname>+1 grouping sets. Also, the order in which the grouping
              expressions are specified is significant in a <codeph>ROLLUP</codeph>.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>CUBE</pt>
            <pd>A <codeph>CUBE</codeph> grouping is an extension to the <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph>
              clause that creates subtotals for all of the possible combinations of the given list
              of grouping columns (or expressions). In terms of multidimensional analysis,
                <codeph>CUBE</codeph> generates all the subtotals that could be calculated for a
              data cube with the specified dimensions. For example:</pd>
            <pd>
              <codeblock>GROUP BY CUBE (a,b,c) </codeblock>
            </pd>
            <pd>is equivalent to:</pd>
            <pd>
              <codeblock>GROUP BY GROUPING SETS( (a,b,c), (a,b), (a,c), (b,c), (a), 
(b), (c), () ) </codeblock>
            </pd>
            <pd>Notice that <varname>n</varname> elements of a <codeph>CUBE</codeph> translate to 2n
              grouping sets. Consider using <codeph>CUBE</codeph> in any situation requiring
              cross-tabular reports. <codeph>CUBE</codeph> is typically most suitable in queries
              that use columns from multiple dimensions rather than columns representing different
              levels of a single dimension. For instance, a commonly requested cross-tabulation
              might need subtotals for all the combinations of month, state, and product.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>GROUPING SETS</pt>
            <pd>You can selectively specify the set of groups that you want to create using a
                <codeph>GROUPING SETS</codeph> expression within a <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clause.
              This allows precise specification across multiple dimensions without computing a whole
                <codeph>ROLLUP</codeph> or <codeph>CUBE</codeph>. For example:</pd>
            <pd>
              <codeblock>GROUP BY GROUPING SETS( (a,c), (a,b) )</codeblock>
            </pd>
            <pd>If using the grouping extension clauses <codeph>ROLLUP</codeph>,
                <codeph>CUBE</codeph>, or <codeph>GROUPING SETS</codeph>, two challenges arise.
              First, how do you determine which result rows are subtotals, and then the exact level
              of aggregation for a given subtotal. Or, how do you differentiate between result rows
              that contain both stored <codeph>NULL</codeph> values and "NULL" values created by the
                <codeph>ROLLUP</codeph> or <codeph>CUBE</codeph>. Secondly, when duplicate grouping
              sets are specified in the <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clause, how do you determine which
              result rows are duplicates? There are two additional grouping functions you can use in
              the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> list to help with this:<ul id="ul_vx1_3ml_m4">
                <li id="eg143759"><b>grouping(column [, ...])</b> — The <codeph>grouping</codeph>
                  function can be applied to one or more grouping attributes to distinguish
                  super-aggregated rows from regular grouped rows. This can be helpful in
                  distinguishing a "NULL" representing the set of all values in a super-aggregated
                  row from a <codeph>NULL</codeph> value in a regular row. Each argument in this
                  function produces a bit — either <codeph>1</codeph> or <codeph>0</codeph>, where
                    <codeph>1</codeph> means the result row is super-aggregated, and
                    <codeph>0</codeph> means the result row is from a regular grouping. The
                    <codeph>grouping</codeph> function returns an integer by treating these bits as
                  a binary number and then converting it to a base-10 integer.</li>
                <li id="eg143806"><b>group_id()</b> — For grouping extension queries that contain
                  duplicate grouping sets, the <codeph>group_id</codeph> function is used to
                  identify duplicate rows in the output. All <i>unique</i> grouping set output rows
                  will have a group_id value of 0. For each duplicate grouping set detected, the
                    <codeph>group_id</codeph> function assigns a group_id number greater than 0. All
                  output rows in a particular duplicate grouping set are identified by the same
                  group_id number. </li>
              </ul></pd>
          </plentry>
        </parml></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section9"><b>The WINDOW Clause</b><p>The
            <codeph>WINDOW</codeph> clause is used to define a window that can be used in the
            <codeph>OVER()</codeph> expression of a window function such as <codeph>rank</codeph> or
            <codeph>avg</codeph>. For
          example:</p><codeblock>SELECT vendor, rank() OVER (mywindow) FROM sale
GROUP BY vendor
WINDOW mywindow AS (ORDER BY sum(prc*qty));</codeblock><p>A
            <codeph>WINDOW</codeph> clause has this general
          form:</p><codeblock>WINDOW <varname>window_name</varname> AS (<varname>window_specification</varname>)</codeblock><p>where
            <varname>window_specification</varname> can be:</p><codeblock>[<varname>window_name</varname>]
[PARTITION BY <varname>expression </varname>[, ...]]
[ORDER BY <varname>expression</varname> [ASC | DESC | USING <varname>operator</varname>] [NULLS {FIRST | LAST}] [, ...]
    [{RANGE | ROWS} 
      { UNBOUNDED PRECEDING
      | <varname>expression</varname> PRECEDING
      | CURRENT ROW
      | BETWEEN <varname>window_frame_bound</varname> AND <varname>window_frame_bound</varname> }]]
             where <varname>window_frame_bound</varname> can be one of:
               UNBOUNDED PRECEDING
               <varname>expression</varname> PRECEDING
               CURRENT ROW
               <varname>expression</varname> FOLLOWING
               UNBOUNDED FOLLOWING</codeblock><parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt><varname>window_name</varname></pt>
            <pd>Gives a name to the window specification.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>PARTITION BY</pt>
            <pd>The <codeph>PARTITION BY</codeph> clause organizes the result set into logical
              groups based on the unique values of the specified expression. When used with window
              functions, the functions are applied to each partition independently. For example, if
              you follow <codeph>PARTITION BY</codeph> with a column name, the result set is
              partitioned by the distinct values of that column. If omitted, the entire result set
              is considered one partition.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>ORDER BY</pt>
            <pd>The <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause defines how to sort the rows in each partition
              of the result set. If omitted, rows are returned in whatever order is most efficient
              and may vary. <b>Note:</b> Columns of data types that lack a coherent ordering, such
              as <codeph>time</codeph>, are not good candidates for use in the <codeph>ORDER
                BY</codeph> clause of a window specification. Time, with or without time zone, lacks
              a coherent ordering because addition and subtraction do not have the expected effects.
              For example, the following is not generally true: <codeph>x::time &lt; x::time + '2
                hour'::interval</codeph></pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>ROWS | RANGE </pt>
            <pd>Use either a <codeph>ROWS</codeph> or <codeph>RANGE</codeph> clause to express the
              bounds of the window. The window bound can be one, many, or all rows of a partition.
              You can express the bound of the window either in terms of a range of data values
              offset from the value in the current row (<codeph>RANGE</codeph>), or in terms of the
              number of rows offset from the current row (<codeph>ROWS</codeph>). When using the
                <codeph>RANGE</codeph> clause, you must also use an <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph>
              clause. This is because the calculation performed to produce the window requires that
              the values be sorted. Additionally, the <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause cannot
              contain more than one expression, and the expression must result in either a date or a
              numeric value. When using the <codeph>ROWS</codeph> or <codeph>RANGE</codeph> clauses,
              if you specify only a starting row, the current row is used as the last row in the
              window.</pd>
            <pd><b>PRECEDING</b> — The <codeph>PRECEDING</codeph> clause defines the first row of
              the window using the current row as a reference point. The starting row is expressed
              in terms of the number of rows preceding the current row. For example, in the case of
                <codeph>ROWS</codeph> framing, <codeph>5 PRECEDING</codeph> sets the window to start
              with the fifth row preceding the current row. In the case of <codeph>RANGE</codeph>
              framing, it sets the window to start with the first row whose ordering column value
              precedes that of the current row by 5 in the given order. If the specified order is
              ascending by date, this will be the first row within 5 days before the current row.
                <codeph>UNBOUNDED PRECEDING</codeph> sets the first row in the window to be the
              first row in the partition.</pd>
            <pd><b>BETWEEN</b> — The <codeph>BETWEEN</codeph> clause defines the first and last row
              of the window, using the current row as a reference point. First and last rows are
              expressed in terms of the number of rows preceding and following the current row,
              respectively. For example, <codeph>BETWEEN 3 PRECEDING AND 5 FOLLOWING</codeph> sets
              the window to start with the third row preceding the current row, and end with the
              fifth row following the current row. Use <codeph>BETWEEN UNBOUNDED PRECEDING AND
                UNBOUNDED FOLLOWING</codeph> to set the first and last rows in the window to be the
              first and last row in the partition, respectively. This is equivalent to the default
              behavior if no <codeph>ROW</codeph> or <codeph>RANGE</codeph> clause is
              specified.</pd>
            <pd><b>FOLLOWING</b> — The <codeph>FOLLOWING</codeph> clause defines the last row of the
              window using the current row as a reference point. The last row is expressed in terms
              of the number of rows following the current row. For example, in the case of
                <codeph>ROWS</codeph> framing, <codeph>5 FOLLOWING</codeph> sets the window to end
              with the fifth row following the current row. In the case of <codeph>RANGE</codeph>
              framing, it sets the window to end with the last row whose ordering column value
              follows that of the current row by 5 in the given order. If the specified order is
              ascending by date, this will be the last row within 5 days after the current row. Use
                <codeph>UNBOUNDED FOLLOWING</codeph> to set the last row in the window to be the
              last row in the partition.</pd>
            <pd>If you do not specify a <codeph>ROW</codeph> or a <codeph>RANGE</codeph> clause, the
              window bound starts with the first row in the partition (<codeph>UNBOUNDED
                PRECEDING</codeph>) and ends with the current row (<codeph>CURRENT ROW</codeph>) if
                <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> is used. If an <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> is not specified,
              the window starts with the first row in the partition (<codeph>UNBOUNDED
                PRECEDING</codeph>) and ends with last row in the partition (<codeph>UNBOUNDED
                FOLLOWING</codeph>).</pd>
          </plentry>
        </parml></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section10"><b>The HAVING Clause</b><p>The optional
            <codeph>HAVING</codeph> clause has the general
          form:</p><codeblock>HAVING <varname>condition</varname></codeblock><p>where
            <varname>condition</varname> is the same as specified for the <codeph>WHERE</codeph>
          clause. <codeph>HAVING</codeph> eliminates group rows that do not satisfy the condition.
            <codeph>HAVING</codeph> is different from <codeph>WHERE</codeph>: <codeph>WHERE</codeph>
          filters individual rows before the application of <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph>, while
            <codeph>HAVING</codeph> filters group rows created by <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph>. Each
          column referenced in <varname>condition</varname> must unambiguously reference a grouping
          column, unless the reference appears within an aggregate function.</p><p>The presence of
            <codeph>HAVING</codeph> turns a query into a grouped query even if there is no
            <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clause. This is the same as what happens when the query
          contains aggregate functions but no <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clause. All the selected
          rows are considered to form a single group, and the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> list and
            <codeph>HAVING</codeph> clause can only reference table columns from within aggregate
          functions. Such a query will emit a single row if the <codeph>HAVING</codeph> condition is
          true, zero rows if it is not true. </p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section11"><b>The
          UNION Clause</b><p>The <codeph>UNION</codeph> clause has this general
          form:</p><codeblock><varname>select_statement</varname> UNION [ALL] <varname>select_statement</varname></codeblock><p>where
            <varname>select_statement</varname> is any <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement without an
            <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph>, <codeph>LIMIT</codeph>, <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph>, or
            <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> clause. (<codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> and <codeph>LIMIT</codeph>
          can be attached to a subquery expression if it is enclosed in parentheses. Without
          parentheses, these clauses will be taken to apply to the result of the
            <codeph>UNION</codeph>, not to its right-hand input expression.) </p><p>The
            <codeph>UNION</codeph> operator computes the set union of the rows returned by the
          involved <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statements. A row is in the set union of two result sets
          if it appears in at least one of the result sets. The two <codeph>SELECT</codeph>
          statements that represent the direct operands of the <codeph>UNION</codeph> must produce
          the same number of columns, and corresponding columns must be of compatible data
          types.</p><p>The result of <codeph>UNION</codeph> does not contain any duplicate rows
          unless the <codeph>ALL</codeph> option is specified. <codeph>ALL</codeph> prevents
          elimination of duplicates. (Therefore, <codeph>UNION ALL</codeph> is usually significantly
          quicker than <codeph>UNION</codeph>; use <codeph>ALL</codeph> when you can.)
          </p><p>Multiple <codeph>UNION</codeph> operators in the same <codeph>SELECT</codeph>
          statement are evaluated left to right, unless otherwise indicated by parentheses.
          </p><p>Currently, <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph> and <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> may not be
          specified either for a <codeph>UNION</codeph> result or for any input of a
            <codeph>UNION</codeph>. </p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section12"><b>The INTERSECT
          Clause</b><p>The <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph> clause has this general
          form:</p><codeblock><varname>select_statement</varname> INTERSECT [ALL] <varname>select_statement</varname></codeblock><p>where
            <varname>select_statement</varname> is any SELECT statement without an <codeph>ORDER
            BY</codeph>, <codeph>LIMIT</codeph>, <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph>, or <codeph>FOR
            SHARE</codeph> clause. </p><p>The <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph> operator computes the set
          intersection of the rows returned by the involved <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statements. A
          row is in the intersection of two result sets if it appears in both result sets.</p><p>The
          result of <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph> does not contain any duplicate rows unless the
            <codeph>ALL</codeph> option is specified. With <codeph>ALL</codeph>, a row that has
            <varname>m</varname> duplicates in the left table and <varname>n</varname> duplicates in
          the right table will appear min(<varname>m</varname>, <varname>n</varname>) times in the
          result set.</p><p>Multiple <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph> operators in the same
            <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement are evaluated left to right, unless parentheses
          dictate otherwise. <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph> binds more tightly than
            <codeph>UNION</codeph>. That is, <codeph>A UNION B INTERSECT C</codeph> will be read as
            <codeph>A UNION (B INTERSECT C)</codeph>. </p><p>Currently, <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph>
          and <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> may not be specified either for an
            <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph> result or for any input of an <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph>.
        </p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section13"><b>The EXCEPT Clause</b><p>The
            <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph> clause has this general
          form:</p><codeblock><varname>select_statement</varname> EXCEPT [ALL] <varname>select_statement</varname></codeblock><p>where
            <varname>select_statement</varname> is any <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement without an
            <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph>, <codeph>LIMIT</codeph>, <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph>, or
            <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> clause. </p><p>The <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph> operator computes
          the set of rows that are in the result of the left <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement but
          not in the result of the right one. </p><p>The result of <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph> does not
          contain any duplicate rows unless the <codeph>ALL</codeph> option is specified. With
            <codeph>ALL</codeph>, a row that has <varname>m</varname> duplicates in the left table
          and <varname>n</varname> duplicates in the right table will appear
            max(<varname>m-n</varname>,0) times in the result set. </p><p>Multiple
            <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph> operators in the same <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement are
          evaluated left to right, unless parentheses dictate otherwise. <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph>
          binds at the same level as <codeph>UNION</codeph>. </p><p>Currently, <codeph>FOR
            UPDATE</codeph> and <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> may not be specified either for an
            <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph> result or for any input of an <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph>.
        </p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section14"><b>The ORDER BY Clause</b><p>The optional
            <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause has this general
          form:</p><codeblock>ORDER BY <varname>expression</varname> [ASC | DESC | USING <varname>operator</varname>] [NULLS { FIRST | LAST}] [, ...]</codeblock><p>where
            <varname>expression</varname> can be the name or ordinal number of an output column
            (<codeph>SELECT</codeph> list item), or it can be an arbitrary expression formed from
          input-column values. </p><p>The <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause causes the result rows to
          be sorted according to the specified expressions. If two rows are equal according to the
          left-most expression, they are compared according to the next expression and so on. If
          they are equal according to all specified expressions, they are returned in an
          implementation-dependent order.</p><p>The ordinal number refers to the ordinal
          (left-to-right) position of the result column. This feature makes it possible to define an
          ordering on the basis of a column that does not have a unique name. This is never
          absolutely necessary because it is always possible to assign a name to a result column
          using the <codeph>AS</codeph> clause. </p><p>It is also possible to use arbitrary
          expressions in the <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause, including columns that do not appear
          in the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> result list. Thus the following statement is
          valid:</p><codeblock>SELECT name FROM distributors ORDER BY code;</codeblock><p>A
          limitation of this feature is that an <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause applying to the
          result of a <codeph>UNION</codeph>, <codeph>INTERSECT</codeph>, or <codeph>EXCEPT</codeph>
          clause may only specify an output column name or number, not an expression.</p><p>If an
            <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> expression is a simple name that matches both a result column
          name and an input column name, <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> will interpret it as the result
          column name. This is the opposite of the choice that <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> will make
          in the same situation. This inconsistency is made to be compatible with the SQL standard.
          </p><p>Optionally one may add the key word <codeph>ASC</codeph> (ascending) or
            <codeph>DESC</codeph> (descending) after any expression in the <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph>
          clause. If not specified, <codeph>ASC</codeph> is assumed by default. Alternatively, a
          specific ordering operator name may be specified in the <codeph>USING</codeph> clause.
            <codeph>ASC</codeph> is usually equivalent to <codeph>USING &lt;</codeph> and
            <codeph>DESC</codeph> is usually equivalent to <codeph>USING &gt;</codeph>. (But the
          creator of a user-defined data type can define exactly what the default sort ordering is,
          and it might correspond to operators with other names.) </p><p>If <codeph>NULLS
            LAST</codeph> is specified, null values sort after all non-null values; if <codeph>NULLS
            FIRST</codeph> is specified, null values sort before all non-null values. If neither is
          specified, the default behavior is <codeph>NULLS LAST</codeph> when <codeph>ASC</codeph>
          is specified or implied, and <codeph>NULLS FIRST</codeph> when <codeph>DESC</codeph> is
          specified (thus, the default is to act as though nulls are larger than non-nulls). When
            <codeph>USING</codeph> is specified, the default nulls ordering depends upon whether the
          operator is a less-than or greater-than operator.</p><p>Note that ordering options apply
          only to the expression they follow; for example <codeph>ORDER BY x, y DESC</codeph> does
          not mean the same thing as <codeph>ORDER BY x DESC, y
          DESC</codeph>.</p><p>Character-string data is sorted according to the locale-specific
          collation order that was established when the Greenplum Database system was
          initialized.</p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section15"><b>The DISTINCT Clause</b><p>If
            <codeph>DISTINCT</codeph> is specified, all duplicate rows are removed from the result
          set (one row is kept from each group of duplicates). <codeph>ALL</codeph> specifies the
          opposite: all rows are kept. <codeph>ALL</codeph> is the default. </p><p><codeph>DISTINCT
            ON ( <varname>expression</varname> [, ...] )</codeph> keeps only the first row of each
          set of rows where the given expressions evaluate to equal. The <codeph>DISTINCT
            ON</codeph> expressions are interpreted using the same rules as for <codeph>ORDER
            BY</codeph>. Note that the 'first row' of each set is unpredictable unless <codeph>ORDER
            BY</codeph> is used to ensure that the desired row appears first. For
          example:</p><codeblock>SELECT DISTINCT ON (location) location, time, report FROM 
weather_reports ORDER BY location, time DESC;</codeblock><p>retrieves
          the most recent weather report for each location. But if we had not used <codeph>ORDER
            BY</codeph> to force descending order of time values for each location, we would have
          gotten a report from an unpredictable time for each location.</p><p>The <codeph>DISTINCT
            ON</codeph> expression(s) must match the left-most <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph>
          expression(s). The <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause will normally contain additional
          expression(s) that determine the desired precedence of rows within each <codeph>DISTINCT
            ON</codeph> group.</p><p>When Greenplum Database processes queries that contain the
            <codeph>DISTINCT</codeph> clause, the queries are transformed into <codeph>GROUP
            BY</codeph> queries. In many cases, the transformation provides significant performance
          gains. However, when the number of distinct values is close to the total number of rows,
          the transformation might result in the generation of a multi-level grouping plan. In this
          case, there is an expected performance degradation because of the overhead introduced by
          the lower aggregation level.</p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section16"><b>The LIMIT
          Clause</b><p>The <codeph>LIMIT</codeph> clause consists of two independent
          sub-clauses:</p><codeblock>LIMIT {<varname>count</varname> | ALL}
OFFSET <varname>start</varname></codeblock><p>where
            <varname>count</varname> specifies the maximum number of rows to return, while
            <varname>start</varname> specifies the number of rows to skip before starting to return
          rows. When both are specified, start rows are skipped before starting to count the count
          rows to be returned. </p><p>When using <codeph>LIMIT</codeph>, it is a good idea to use an
            <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause that constrains the result rows into a unique order.
          Otherwise you will get an unpredictable subset of the query's rows — you may be asking for
          the tenth through twentieth rows, but tenth through twentieth in what ordering? You don't
          know what ordering unless you specify <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph>. </p><p>The query
          optimizer takes <codeph>LIMIT</codeph> into account when generating a query plan, so you
          are very likely to get different plans (yielding different row orders) depending on what
          you use for <codeph>LIMIT</codeph> and <codeph>OFFSET</codeph>. Thus, using different
            <codeph>LIMIT/OFFSET</codeph> values to select different subsets of a query result will
          give inconsistent results unless you enforce a predictable result ordering with
            <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph>. This is not a defect; it is an inherent consequence of the
          fact that SQL does not promise to deliver the results of a query in any particular order
          unless <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> is used to constrain the
        order.</p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section17"><b>The FOR UPDATE/FOR SHARE
          Clause</b><p>The <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph> clause has this
          form:</p><codeblock>FOR UPDATE [OF <varname>table_name</varname> [, ...]] [NOWAIT]</codeblock><p>The
          closely related <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> clause has this
            form:</p><codeblock>FOR SHARE [OF <varname>table_name</varname> [, ...]] [NOWAIT]</codeblock><p><codeph>FOR
            UPDATE</codeph> causes the tables accessed by the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement to
          be locked as though for update. This prevents the table from being modified or deleted by
          other transactions until the current transaction ends. That is, other transactions that
          attempt <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, <codeph>DELETE</codeph>, or <codeph>SELECT FOR
            UPDATE</codeph> of this table will be blocked until the current transaction ends. Also,
          if an <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, <codeph>DELETE</codeph>, or <codeph>SELECT FOR
            UPDATE</codeph> from another transaction has already locked a selected table,
            <codeph>SELECT FOR UPDATE</codeph> will wait for the other transaction to complete, and
          will then lock and return the updated table.</p><p>To prevent the operation from waiting
          for other transactions to commit, use the <codeph>NOWAIT</codeph> option. <codeph>SELECT
            FOR UPDATE NOWAIT</codeph> reports an error, rather than waiting, if a selected row
          cannot be locked immediately. Note that <codeph>NOWAIT</codeph> applies only to the
          row-level lock(s) — the required <codeph>ROW SHARE</codeph> table-level lock is still
          taken in the ordinary way. You can use the <codeph>NOWAIT</codeph> option of
            <codeph>LOCK</codeph> if you need to acquire the table-level lock without waiting (see
              <codeph><xref href="LOCK.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>).
            </p><p><codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> behaves similarly, except that it acquires a shared
          rather than exclusive lock on the table. A shared lock blocks other transactions from
          performing <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, <codeph>DELETE</codeph>, or <codeph>SELECT FOR
            UPDATE</codeph> on the table, but it does not prevent them from performing
            <codeph>SELECT FOR SHARE</codeph>.</p><p>If specific tables are named in <codeph>FOR
            UPDATE</codeph> or <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph>, then only those tables are locked; any
          other tables used in the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> are simply read as usual. A <codeph>FOR
            UPDATE</codeph> or <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> clause without a table list affects all
          tables used in the command. If <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph> or <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph>
          is applied to a view or subquery, it affects all tables used in the view or
          subquery.</p><codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph> or <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> do not apply to a
          <varname>with_query</varname> referenced by the primary query. If you want row locking to
        occur within a <varname>with_query</varname>, specify <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph> or
          <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> within the <varname>with_query</varname>.<p>Multiple
            <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph> and <codeph>FOR SHARE</codeph> clauses can be written if it
          is necessary to specify different locking behavior for different tables. If the same table
          is mentioned (or implicitly affected) by both <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph> and <codeph>FOR
            SHARE</codeph> clauses, then it is processed as <codeph>FOR UPDATE</codeph>. Similarly,
          a table is processed as <codeph>NOWAIT</codeph> if that is specified in any of the clauses
          affecting it.</p></sectiondiv></section>
    <section id="section18">
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>To join the table <codeph>films</codeph> with the table <codeph>distributors</codeph>: </p>
      <codeblock>SELECT f.title, f.did, d.name, f.date_prod, f.kind FROM 
distributors d, films f WHERE f.did = d.did</codeblock>
      <p>To sum the column <codeph>length</codeph> of all films and group the results by
          <codeph>kind</codeph>: </p>
      <codeblock>SELECT kind, sum(length) AS total FROM films GROUP BY kind;</codeblock>
      <p>To sum the column <codeph>length</codeph> of all films, group the results by
          <codeph>kind</codeph> and show those group totals that are less than 5 hours: </p>
      <codeblock>SELECT kind, sum(length) AS total FROM films GROUP BY kind 
HAVING sum(length) &lt; interval '5 hours';</codeblock>
      <p>Calculate the subtotals and grand totals of all sales for movie <codeph>kind</codeph> and
          <codeph>distributor</codeph>.</p>
      <codeblock>SELECT kind, distributor, sum(prc*qty) FROM sales
GROUP BY ROLLUP(kind, distributor)
ORDER BY 1,2,3;</codeblock>
      <p>Calculate the rank of movie distributors based on total sales:</p>
      <codeblock>SELECT distributor, sum(prc*qty), 
       rank() OVER (ORDER BY sum(prc*qty) DESC) 
FROM sale
GROUP BY distributor ORDER BY 2 DESC;</codeblock>
      <p>The following two examples are identical ways of sorting the individual results according
        to the contents of the second column (<codeph>name</codeph>):</p>
      <codeblock>SELECT * FROM distributors ORDER BY name;
SELECT * FROM distributors ORDER BY 2;</codeblock>
      <p>The next example shows how to obtain the union of the tables <codeph>distributors</codeph>
        and <codeph>actors</codeph>, restricting the results to those that begin with the letter
          <codeph>W</codeph> in each table. Only distinct rows are wanted, so the key word
          <codeph>ALL</codeph> is omitted: </p>
      <codeblock>SELECT distributors.name FROM distributors WHERE 
distributors.name LIKE 'W%' UNION SELECT actors.name FROM 
actors WHERE actors.name LIKE 'W%';</codeblock>
      <p>This example shows how to use a function in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause, both with and
        without a column definition list: </p>
      <codeblock>CREATE FUNCTION distributors(int) RETURNS SETOF distributors 
AS $$ SELECT * FROM distributors WHERE did = $1; $$ LANGUAGE 
SQL;
SELECT * FROM distributors(111);

CREATE FUNCTION distributors_2(int) RETURNS SETOF record AS 
$$ SELECT * FROM distributors WHERE did = $1; $$ LANGUAGE 
SQL;
SELECT * FROM distributors_2(111) AS (dist_id int, dist_name 
text);</codeblock>
      <p>This example uses a simple <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause:</p>
      <codeblock>WITH test AS (
  SELECT random() as x FROM generate_series(1, 3)
  )
SELECT * FROM test
UNION ALL
SELECT * FROM test; </codeblock>
      <p>This example uses the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause to display per-product sales totals in
        only the top sales regions. </p>
      <codeblock>WITH regional_sales AS 
    SELECT region, SUM(amount) AS total_sales
    FROM orders
    GROUP BY region
  ), top_regions AS (
    SELECT region
    FROM regional_sales
    WHERE total_sales > (SELECT SUM(total_sales) FROM
       regional_sales)
  )
SELECT region, product, SUM(quantity) AS product_units,
   SUM(amount) AS product_sales
FROM orders
WHERE region IN (SELECT region FROM top_regions) 
GROUP BY region, product;</codeblock>
      <p>The example could have been written without the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause but would have
        required two levels of nested sub-<codeph>SELECT</codeph> statements.</p>
      <p>This example uses the <codeph>WITH RECURSIVE</codeph> clause to find all subordinates
        (direct or indirect) of the employee Mary, and their level of indirectness, from a table
        that shows only direct subordinates:</p>
      <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE employee_recursive(distance, employee_name, manager_name) AS (
    SELECT 1, employee_name, manager_name
    FROM employee
    WHERE manager_name = 'Mary'
  UNION ALL
    SELECT er.distance + 1, e.employee_name, e.manager_name
    FROM employee_recursive er, employee e
    WHERE er.employee_name = e.manager_name
  )
SELECT distance, employee_name FROM employee_recursive;</codeblock>
      <p>The typical form of recursive queries: an initial condition, followed by <codeph>UNION
          [ALL]</codeph>, followed by the recursive part of the query. Be sure that the recursive
        part of the query will eventually return no tuples, or else the query will loop
        indefinitely. See <xref
          href="../../admin_guide/query/topics/CTE-query.xml#topic_zhs_r1s_w1b"/><ph
          otherprops="pivotal"> in the <cite>Greenplum Database Administrator Guide</cite></ph> for
        more examples.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section19"><title>Compatibility</title><p>The <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement is
        compatible with the SQL standard, but there are some extensions and some missing features.
        </p><sectiondiv id="section20"><b>Omitted FROM Clauses</b><p>Greenplum Database allows one
          to omit the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause. It has a straightforward use to compute the
          results of simple expressions. For example:</p><codeblock>SELECT 2+2;</codeblock><p>Some
          other SQL databases cannot do this except by introducing a dummy one-row table from which
          to do the <codeph>SELECT</codeph>. </p><p>Note that if a <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause is
          not specified, the query cannot reference any database tables. For compatibility with
          applications that rely on this behavior the <varname>add_missing_from</varname>
          configuration variable can be enabled.</p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section21"><b>The
          AS Key Word</b><p>In the SQL standard, the optional key word <codeph>AS</codeph> is just
          noise and can be omitted without affecting the meaning. The Greenplum Database parser
          requires this key word when renaming output columns because the type extensibility
          features lead to parsing ambiguities without it. <codeph>AS</codeph> is optional in
            <codeph>FROM</codeph> items, however. </p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section22"
          ><b>Namespace Available to GROUP BY and ORDER BY</b><p>In the SQL-92 standard, an
            <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> clause may only use result column names or numbers, while a
            <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clause may only use expressions based on input column names.
          Greenplum Database extends each of these clauses to allow the other choice as well (but it
          uses the standard's interpretation if there is ambiguity). Greenplum Database also allows
          both clauses to specify arbitrary expressions. Note that names appearing in an expression
          are always taken as input-column names, not as result-column names. </p><p>SQL:1999 and
          later use a slightly different definition which is not entirely upward compatible with
          SQL-92. In most cases, however, Greenplum Database interprets an <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph>
          or <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> expression the same way SQL:1999 does.
        </p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section23"><b>Nonstandard Clauses</b><p>The clauses
            <codeph>DISTINCT ON</codeph>, <codeph>LIMIT</codeph>, and <codeph>OFFSET</codeph> are
          not defined in the SQL standard.</p></sectiondiv><sectiondiv id="section24"><b>Limited Use
          of STABLE and VOLATILE Functions</b><p>To prevent data from becoming out-of-sync across
          the segments in Greenplum Database, any function classified as <codeph>STABLE</codeph> or
            <codeph>VOLATILE</codeph> cannot be executed at the segment database level if it
          contains SQL or modifies the database in any way. See <codeph><xref
              href="CREATE_FUNCTION.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph> for more
          information.</p></sectiondiv></section>
    <section id="section25">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p><codeph><xref href="EXPLAIN.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
