<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title id="eq20941">UPDATE</title>
  <body>
    <p id="sql_command_desc">Updates rows of a table.</p>
    <section id="section2">
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock id="sql_command_synopsis">[ WITH [ RECURSIVE ] <varname>with_query</varname> [, ...] ]
UPDATE [ONLY] <varname>table</varname> [[AS] <varname>alias</varname>]
   SET {<varname>column</varname> = {<varname>expression</varname> | DEFAULT} |
   (<varname>column</varname> [, ...]) = ({<varname>expression</varname> | DEFAULT} [, ...])} [, ...]
   [FROM <varname>fromlist</varname>]
   [WHERE <varname>condition </varname>| WHERE CURRENT OF <varname>cursor_name</varname> ]</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section3">
      <title>Description</title>
      <p><codeph>UPDATE</codeph> changes the values of the specified columns in all rows that
        satisfy the condition. Only the columns to be modified need be mentioned in the
          <codeph>SET</codeph> clause; columns not explicitly modified retain their previous
        values.</p>
      <p>By default, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> will update rows in the specified table and all its
        subtables. If you wish to only update the specific table mentioned, you must use the
          <codeph>ONLY</codeph> clause.</p>
      <p>There are two ways to modify a table using information contained in other tables in the
        database: using sub-selects, or specifying additional tables in the <codeph>FROM</codeph>
        clause. Which technique is more appropriate depends on the specific circumstances. </p>
      <p>If the <codeph>WHERE CURRENT OF</codeph> clause is specified, the row that is updated is
        the one most recently fetched from the specified cursor. </p>
      <p>The <codeph>WHERE CURRENT OF</codeph> clause is not supported with replicated tables.</p>
      <p>You must have the <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> privilege on the table, or at least on the
        column(s) that are listed to be updated. You must also have the <codeph>SELECT</codeph>
        privilege on any column whose values are read in the <varname>expression</varname>s or
          <varname>condition</varname>.</p>
      <note>As the default, Greenplum Database acquires an <codeph>EXCLUSIVE</codeph> lock on tables
        for <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> operations on heap tables. When the Global Deadlock Detector is
        enabled, the lock mode for <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> operations on heap tables is <codeph>ROW
          EXCLUSIVE</codeph>. See <xref href="../../admin_guide/dml.xml#topic_gdd" format="dita"
        />.</note>
      <sectiondiv id="section4">
        <b>Outputs</b>
        <p>On successful completion, an <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> command returns a command tag of the
          form:</p>
        <codeblock>UPDATE <varname>count</varname></codeblock>
        <p>where <varname>count</varname> is the number of rows updated. If <varname>count</varname>
          is 0, no rows matched the condition (this is not considered an error). </p>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
    <section id="section5">
      <title>Parameters</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><varname>with_query</varname></pt>
          <pd>The <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause allows you to specify one or more subqueries that can
            be referenced by name in the <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> query. </pd>
          <pd>For an <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> command that includes a <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause,
            the clause can only contain <codeph>SELECT</codeph> commands, the <codeph>WITH</codeph>
            clause cannot contain a data-modifying command (<codeph>INSERT</codeph>,
              <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, or <codeph>DELETE</codeph>). </pd>
          <pd>It is possible for the query (<codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement) to also contain a
              <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause. In such a case both sets of
              <varname>with_query</varname> can be referenced within the <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>
            query, but the second one takes precedence since it is more closely nested.</pd>
          <pd>See <xref href="../../admin_guide/query/topics/CTE-query.xml#topic_zhs_r1s_w1b"/> and
                <codeph><xref href="SELECT.xml#topic1"/></codeph> for details. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>ONLY</pt>
          <pd>If specified, update rows from the named table only. When not specified, any tables
            inheriting from the named table are also processed. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>table</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>The name (optionally schema-qualified) of an existing table. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>alias</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>A substitute name for the target table. When an alias is provided, it completely hides
            the actual name of the table. For example, given <codeph>UPDATE foo AS f</codeph>, the
            remainder of the <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> statement must refer to this table as
              <codeph>f</codeph> not <codeph>foo</codeph>. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>column</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>The name of a column in table. The column name can be qualified with a subfield name
            or array subscript, if needed. Do not include the table's name in the specification of a
            target column.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>expression</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>An expression to assign to the column. The expression may use the old values of this
            and other columns in the table.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>DEFAULT</pt>
          <pd>Set the column to its default value (which will be NULL if no specific default
            expression has been assigned to it).</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>fromlist</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>A list of table expressions, allowing columns from other tables to appear in the
              <codeph>WHERE</codeph> condition and the update expressions. This is similar to the
            list of tables that can be specified in the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause of a
              <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement. Note that the target table must not appear in the
              <varname>fromlist</varname>, unless you intend a self-join (in which case it must
            appear with an <varname>alias</varname> in the <varname>fromlist</varname>).</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>condition</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>An expression that returns a value of type boolean. Only rows for which this
            expression returns true will be updated.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>cursor_name</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>The name of the cursor to use in a <codeph>WHERE CURRENT OF</codeph> condition. The
            row to be updated is the one most recently fetched from the cursor. The cursor must be a
            non-grouping query on the <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> command target table. See
                <codeph><xref href="DECLARE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph> for
            more information about creating cursors. </pd>
          <pd><codeph>WHERE CURRENT OF</codeph> cannot be specified together with a Boolean
            condition. </pd>
          <pd>Note that <codeph>WHERE CURRENT OF</codeph> cannot be specified together with a
            Boolean condition. The <codeph>UPDATE...WHERE CURRENT OF</codeph> statement can only be
            executed on the server, for example in an interactive psql session or a script. Language
            extensions such as PL/pgSQL do not have support for updatable cursors.</pd>
          <pd>See <codeph><xref href="DECLARE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph> for
            more information about creating cursors.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>output_expression</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>An expression to be computed and returned by the <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> command after
            each row is updated. The expression may use any column names of the table or table(s)
            listed in <codeph>FROM</codeph>. Write <codeph>*</codeph> to return all columns. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>output_name</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>A name to use for a returned column.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section id="section6">
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p><codeph>SET</codeph> is not allowed on the Greenplum distribution key columns of a
        table.</p>
      <p>When a <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause is present, what essentially happens is that the target
        table is joined to the tables mentioned in the from list, and each output row of the join
        represents an update operation for the target table. When using <codeph>FROM</codeph> you
        should ensure that the join produces at most one output row for each row to be modified. In
        other words, a target row should not join to more than one row from the other table(s). If
        it does, then only one of the join rows will be used to update the target row, but which one
        will be used is not readily predictable.</p>
      <p>Because of this indeterminacy, referencing other tables only within sub-selects is safer,
        though often harder to read and slower than using a join.</p>
      <p>Executing <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> and <codeph>DELETE</codeph> commands directly on a
        specific partition (child table) of a partitioned table is not supported. Instead, execute
        these commands on the root partitioned table, the table created with the <codeph>CREATE
          TABLE</codeph> command.</p>
      <p>For a partitioned table, all the child tables are locked during the <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>
        operation when the Global Deadlock Detector is not enabled (the default). Only some of the
        leaf child tables are locked when the Global Deadlock Detector is enabled. For information
        about the Global Deadlock Detector, see <xref href="../../admin_guide/dml.xml#topic_gdd"
        />.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section7">
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>Change the word <codeph>Drama</codeph> to <codeph>Dramatic</codeph> in the column
          <codeph>kind</codeph> of the table <codeph>films</codeph>: </p>
      <codeblock>UPDATE films SET kind = 'Dramatic' WHERE kind = 'Drama';</codeblock>
      <p>Adjust temperature entries and reset precipitation to its default value in one row of the
        table <codeph>weather</codeph>: </p>
      <codeblock>UPDATE weather SET temp_lo = temp_lo+1, temp_hi = 
temp_lo+15, prcp = DEFAULT
WHERE city = 'San Francisco' AND date = '2016-07-03';</codeblock>
      <p>Use the alternative column-list syntax to do the same update:</p>
      <codeblock>UPDATE weather SET (temp_lo, temp_hi, prcp) = (temp_lo+1, 
temp_lo+15, DEFAULT)
WHERE city = 'San Francisco' AND date = '2016-07-03';</codeblock>
      <p>Increment the sales count of the salesperson who manages the account for Acme Corporation,
        using the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause syntax (assuming both tables being joined are
        distributed in Greenplum Database on the <codeph>id</codeph> column):</p>
      <codeblock>UPDATE employees SET sales_count = sales_count + 1 FROM 
accounts
WHERE accounts.name = 'Acme Corporation'
AND employees.id = accounts.id;</codeblock>
      <p>Perform the same operation, using a sub-select in the <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause:</p>
      <codeblock>UPDATE employees SET sales_count = sales_count + 1 WHERE id =
  (SELECT id FROM accounts WHERE name = 'Acme Corporation');</codeblock>
      <p>Attempt to insert a new stock item along with the quantity of stock. If the item already
        exists, instead update the stock count of the existing item. To do this without failing the
        entire transaction, use savepoints.</p>
      <codeblock>BEGIN;
-- other operations
SAVEPOINT sp1;
INSERT INTO wines VALUES('Chateau Lafite 2003', '24');
-- Assume the above fails because of a unique key violation,
-- so now we issue these commands:
ROLLBACK TO sp1;
UPDATE wines SET stock = stock + 24 WHERE winename = 'Chateau 
Lafite 2003';
-- continue with other operations, and eventually
COMMIT;</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section8">
      <title>Compatibility</title>
      <p>This command conforms to the SQL standard, except that the <codeph>FROM</codeph> clause is
        a Greenplum Database extension. </p>
      <p>According to the standard, the column-list syntax should allow a list of columns to be
        assigned from a single row-valued expression, such as a sub-select:</p>
      <codeblock>UPDATE accounts SET (contact_last_name, contact_first_name) =
    (SELECT last_name, first_name FROM salesmen
     WHERE salesmen.id = accounts.sales_id);</codeblock>
      <p>This is not currently implemented — the source must be a list of independent
        expressions.</p>
      <p>Some other database systems offer a <codeph>FROM</codeph> option in which the target table
        is supposed to be listed again within <codeph>FROM</codeph>. That is not how Greenplum
        Database interprets <codeph>FROM</codeph>. Be careful when porting applications that use
        this extension.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section9">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p><codeph><xref href="DECLARE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="DELETE.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="SELECT.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="INSERT.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
