<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_gzw_2wz_13b">
  <title>diskquota</title>
  <body>
    <p>The <codeph>diskquota</codeph> module allows Greenplum Database administrators to limit the
      amount of disk space used by schemas or roles in a database. </p>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_ofb_gb1_b3b">
    <title>Installing and Registering the Module</title>
    <body>
      <p>The <codeph>diskquota</codeph> module is installed when you install Greenplum Database.</p>
      <p>Before you can use the module, you must perform these steps:</p>
      <ol id="ol_pfb_gb1_b3b">
        <li>Create the <codeph>diskquota</codeph> database. The <codeph>diskquota</codeph> module
          uses this database to store the list of databases where the module is enabled.
          <codeblock>$ createdb diskquota;</codeblock></li>
        <li> Add the <codeph>diskquota</codeph> shared library to the Greenplum Database
            <codeph>shared_preload_libraries</codeph> server configuration parameter and restart
          Greenplum
          Database. Be sure to retain the previous setting of the configuration parameter.
          For example:<codeblock>$ gpconfig -s shared_preload_libraries
Values on all segments are consistent
GUC          : shared_preload_libraries
Master  value: auto_explain
Segment value: auto_explain
$ gpconfig -c shared_preload_libraries -v 'auto_explain,diskquota'
$ gpstop -ar</codeblock></li>
        <li> Register the <codeph>diskquota</codeph> extension in databases where you want to
          enforce disk usage quotas. <codeph>diskquota</codeph> can be registered in up to ten
          databases. <codeblock>$ psql -d testdb -c "CREATE EXTENSION diskquota"</codeblock></li>
        <li>If you register the <codeph>diskquota</codeph> extension in a database that already
          contains data, you must initialize the <codeph>diskquota</codeph> table size data by
          running the <codeph>diskquota.init_table_size_table()</codeph> UDF in the database. In a
          database with many files, this can take a long time. The <codeph>diskquota</codeph> module
          cannot be used until the initialization is
          complete.<codeblock>=# SELECT diskquota.init_table_size_table();</codeblock>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_ndp_4wy_c3b">
    <title>About the diskquota Module</title>
    <body>
      <p>A Greenplum Database superuser can set disk usage quotas for schemas and roles. A schema
        quota sets a limit on disk space used by all tables that belong to a schema. A role quota
        sets a limit on disk space used by all tables that are owned by a role.</p>
      <p>Diskquota processes running on the master and segment hosts check disk usage periodically
        and place schemas or roles on a denylist when they reach their quota. </p>
      <p>When a query plan has been generated for a query that would add data, and the schema or
        role is on the denylist, the query is cancelled before it can start. An error message
        reports the quota that has been exceeded. A query that does not add data, such as a simple
          <codeph>SELECT</codeph> query, is allowed to run even when the role or schema is on the
        denylist.</p>
      <p>Diskquota enforces <i>soft limits</i> for disk usage. Quotas are only checked before a
        query executes. If the quota is not exceeded when the query is about to run, the query is
        allowed to run, even if it causes the quota to be exceeded. </p>
      <p>There is some delay after a quota has been reached before the schema or role is added to
        the denylist. Other queries could add more data during the delay. The delay occurs because
          <codeph>diskquota</codeph> processes that calculate the disk space used by each table
        execute periodically with a pause between executions (two seconds by default). The delay
        also occurs when disk usage falls beneath a quota, due to operations such as
          <codeph>DROP</codeph>, <codeph>TRUNCATE</codeph>, or <codeph>VACUUM FULL</codeph> that
        remove data. Administrators can change the amount of time between disk space checks by
        setting the <codeph>diskquota.naptime</codeph> server configuration parameter.</p>
      <p>If a query is unable to run because the schema or role has been denylisted, an
        administrator can increase the exceeded quota to allow the query to execute. The
          <codeph>show_fast_schema_quota_view</codeph> and
          <codeph>show_fast_role_quota_view</codeph> views can be used to find the schemas or roles
        that have exceeded their limits.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_qfb_gb1_b3b">
    <title>Using the diskquota Module</title>
    <body>
      <section>
        <title>Setting Disk Quotas</title>
        <p>Use the <codeph>diskquota.set_schema_quota()</codeph> and
            <codeph>diskquota.set_role_quota()</codeph> user-defined functions in a database to set,
          update, or delete disk quota limits for schemas and roles in the database. The functions
          take two arguments: the schema or role name, and the quota to set. The quota can be
          specified in units of MB, GB, TB, or PB, for example '2TB'. </p>
        <p>The following example sets a 250GB quota for the <codeph>acct</codeph> schema:</p>
        <codeblock>$ SELECT diskquota.set_schema_quota('acct', '250GB');</codeblock>
        <p>This example sets a 500MB quota for the <codeph>nickd</codeph> role:</p>
        <codeblock>$ SELECT diskquota.set_role_quota(nickd, '500MB');</codeblock>
        <p>To change a quota, call the <codeph>diskquota.set_schema_quota()</codeph> or
            <codeph>diskquota.set_role_quota()</codeph> function again with the new quota value.</p>
        <p>To remove a quota, set the quota value to <codeph>'-1'</codeph>.</p>
      </section>
      <section><title>Displaying Disk Quotas and Disk Usage</title><p>The <codeph>diskquota</codeph>
          module provides two views to display active quotas and the current computed disk space
          used.</p>The <codeph>diskquota.show_fast_schema_quota_view</codeph> view lists active
        quotas for schemas in the current database. The <codeph>nspsize_in_bytes</codeph> column
        contains the calculated size for all tables that belong to the schema.
          <codeblock>=# <b>SELECT * FROM diskquota.show_fast_schema_quota_view;</b>
 schema_name | schema_oid | quota_in_mb | nspsize_in_bytes
-------------+------------+-------------+------------------
 acct        |      16561 |      256000 |           131072
 analytics   |      16519 |  1073741824 |        144670720
 eng         |      16560 |     5242880 |        117833728
 public      |       2200 |         250 |          3014656
(4 rows)</codeblock><p>The
            <codeph>diskquota.show_fast_role_quota_view</codeph> view lists the active quotas for
          roles in the current database. The <codeph>rolsize_in_bytes</codeph> column contains the
          calculated size for all tables that are owned by the
        role.</p><codeblock>=# <b>SELECT * FROM diskquota.show_fast_role_quota_view;</b>
 role_name | role_oid | quota_in_mb | rolsize_in_bytes
-----------+----------+-------------+------------------
 mdach     |    16558 |         500 |           131072
 adam      |    16557 |         300 |        117833728
 nickd     |    16577 |         500 |        144670720
(3 rows)</codeblock></section>
      <section><title>Setting the Delay Between Disk Usage Updates</title>The
          <codeph>diskquota.naptime</codeph> server configuration parameter specifies how frequently
        (in seconds) the table sizes are recalculated. The smaller the <codeph>naptime</codeph>
        value, the less delay in detecting changes in disk usage. This example sets the
          <codeph>naptime</codeph> to ten seconds.
        <codeblock>$ gpconfig -c diskquota.naptime -v 10</codeblock></section>
      <section>
        <title>Configuring diskquota Shared Memory</title>
        <p>The <codeph>diskquota</codeph> module uses shared memory to save the denylist and to save
          the active table list.</p>
        <p>The denylist shared memory can hold up to 1MiB of database objects that exceed the quota
          limit. If the denylist shared memory fills, data may be loaded into some schemas or roles
          after they have reached their quota limit. </p>
        <p>Active table shared memory holds up to 1MiB of active tables by default. Active tables
          are tables that may have changed sizes since <codeph>diskquota</codeph> last recalculated
          the table sizes. <codeph>diskquota</codeph> hook functions are called when the storage
          manager on each Greenplum Database segment creates, extends, or truncates a table file.
          The hook functions store the identity of the file in shared memory so that its file size
          can be recalculated the next time the table size data is refreshed. </p>
        <p>If the shared memory for active tables fills, <codeph>diskquota</codeph> may fail to
          detect a change in disk usage. The amount of active table shared memory can be adjusted by
          setting the <codeph>diskquota.max_active_tables</codeph> server configuration parameter.
          This example changes the active table shared memory to
          2MiB:<codeblock>$ gpconfig -c diskquota.max_active_tables -v '2MiB'</codeblock></p>
        <p>Shared memory is allocated when Greenplum Database starts up, so a server restart is
          required after you change the value of the  <codeph>diskquota.max_active_tables</codeph>
          parameter.</p>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_sfb_gb1_b3b">
    <title>Notes</title>
    <body>
      <p>The <codeph>diskquota</codeph> module can be enabled in up to ten databases. One diskquota
        worker process is created on the Greenplum Database master host for each diskquota-enabled
        database.</p>
      <p>The disk usage for a role is defined as the total of disk usage on all segments for all
        tables the role owns. Although a role is a cluster-level database object, the disk usage for
        roles is calculated separately for each database. </p>
      <p>The disk usage of a schema is defined as the total of disk usage on all segments for all
        tables in the schema. </p>
      <p>The disk usage for a table includes the table data, indexes, toast tables, and free space
        map. For append-optimized tables, the calculation includes the visibility map and index, and
        the block directory table.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>diskquota</codeph> module cannot detect a newly created table inside of an
        uncommitted transaction. The size of the new table is not included in the disk usage
        calculated for the corresponding schema or role until after the transaction has committed.
        Similarly, a table created using the <codeph>CREATE TABLE AS</codeph> command is not
        included in disk usage statistics until the command has completed.</p>
      <p>Deleting rows or running <codeph>VACUUM</codeph> on a table does not release disk space, so
        these operations cannot alone remove a schema or role from the <codeph>diskquota</codeph>
        denylist. The disk space used by a table can be reduced by running <codeph>VACUUM
          FULL</codeph> or <codeph>TRUNCATE TABLE</codeph>.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>diskquota</codeph> module supports high availability features provided by the
        background worker framework. The <codeph>diskquota</codeph> launcher process only runs on
        the active master node. The postmaster on the standby master does not start the
          <codeph>diskquota</codeph> launcher process when it is in standby mode. When the master is
        down and the administrator runs the <codeph><xref
            href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpactivatestandby.xml#topic1"/></codeph>
        command, the standby master changes its role to master and the <codeph>diskquota</codeph>
        launcher process is forked automatically. Using the <codeph>diskquota</codeph>-enabled
        database list in the <codeph>diskquota</codeph> database, the <codeph>diskquota</codeph>
        launcher creates the <codeph>diskquota</codeph> worker processes that manage disk quotas for
        each database.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_v2z_jrv_b3b">
    <title>Examples</title>
    <body>
      <p>This example demonstrates how to set up a schema quota and then observe diskquota behavior
        as data is added to the schema.</p>
      <ol id="ol_rfb_gb1_b3b">
        <li>Create a database named <codeph>test</codeph> and log in to
          it.<codeblock>$ <b>createdb test</b>
$ <b>psql -d test</b></codeblock></li>
        <li>Create the diskquota extension in the
          database.<codeblock>=# <b>CREATE EXTENSION diskquota;</b>
CREATE EXTENSION</codeblock></li>
        <li> Create the <codeph>s1</codeph>
          schema.<codeblock>=# <b>CREATE SCHEMA s1;</b>
CREATE SCHEMA</codeblock></li>
        <li>Set a 1MB disk quota for the <codeph>s1</codeph>
          schema.<codeblock>=# <b>SELECT diskquota.set_schema_quota('s1', '1MB');</b>
 set_schema_quota
------------------

(1 row)</codeblock></li>
        <li>The following commands create a table in the <codeph>s1</codeph> schema and insert a
          small amount of data into it. The schema has no data yet, so it is not on the denylist.
          <codeblock>=# <b>SET search_path TO s1;
SET
</b>=# <b>CREATE TABLE a(i int);</b>
CREATE TABLE
=# <b>INSERT INTO a SELECT generate_series(1,100);</b>
INSERT 0 100
</codeblock></li>
        <li>This command inserts a large amount of data, enough to exceed the 1MB quota that was set
          for the schema. Before the <codeph>INSERT</codeph> command, the <codeph>s1</codeph> schema
          is still not on the denylist, so this command should be allowed to run, even though it
          will exceed the limit set for the
          schema.<codeblock>=# <b>INSERT INTO a SELECT generate_series(1,10000000);</b>
INSERT 0 10000000
</codeblock></li>
        <li>This command attempts to insert a small amount of data. Because the previous command
          exceeded the schema's disk quota limit, the schema should be denylisted and any data
          loading command should be cancelled.
          <codeblock>=# <b>INSERT INTO a SELECT generate_series(1,100);</b>
ERROR:  schema's disk space quota exceeded with name:s1
</codeblock></li>
        <li>This command removes the quota from the <codeph>s1</codeph> schema by setting it to
            <codeph>-1</codeph> and again inserts a small amount of data. A 5-second sleep before
          the <codeph>INSERT</codeph> command ensures that the <codeph>diskquota</codeph> table size
          data is updated before the command is
          run.<codeblock>=# <b>SELECT diskquota.set_schema_quota('s1', '-1');</b>
 set_schema_quota
------------------

(1 row)
# Wait for 5 seconds to ensure the denylist is updated
#= <b>SELECT pg_sleep(5);</b>
#= <b>INSERT INTO a SELECT generate_series(1,100);</b>
INSERT 0 100
</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
