<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<dita>
  <topic id="topic_fstrm">
    <title>pageinspect</title>
    <body>
      <p>The <codeph>pageinspect</codeph> module provides functions for low level
         inspection of the contents of database pages. <codeph>pageinspect</codeph>
         is available only to Greenplum Database superusers.</p>
      <p>The Greenplum Database <codeph>pageinspect</codeph> module is based on the
        PostgreSQL <codeph>pageinspect</codeph> module. The Greenplum version of the
        module differs only in that it does not allow inspection of pages belonging to
        append-optimized or external relations.</p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic_reg">
      <title>Installing and Registering the Module</title>
      <body>
        <p>The <codeph>pageinspect</codeph> module is installed when you install
          Greenplum Database. Before you can use any of the functions defined in the
          module, you must register the <codeph>pageinspect</codeph> extension in
          each database in which you want to use the functions.
          <ph otherprops="pivotal">Refer to <xref href="../../install_guide/install_modules.xml"
            format="dita" scope="peer">Installing Additional Supplied Modules</xref>
          for more information.</ph></p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_info">
      <title>Module Documentation</title>
      <body>
        <p>See <codeph><xref href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/pageinspect.html"
            scope="external" format="html">pageinspect</xref></codeph> in the PostgreSQL
          documentation for detailed information about the individual functions in this module.</p>
        <note>For <codeph>pageinspect</codeph> functions that read data from a database, the
          function reads data only from the segment instance where the function is executed. For
          example, the <codeph>get_raw_page()</codeph> function returns a <codeph>block number out
            of range</codeph> error when you try to read data from a user-defined table on the
          Greenplum Database master because there is no data in the table on the master segment. The
          function will read data from a system catalog table on the master segment.</note>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</dita>
