<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic6">
   <title>pgAdmin 4 with Greenplum Database</title>
   <body>
      <p>If you prefer a graphic interface, use pgAdmin 4. This GUI client supports PostgreSQL
         databases with all standard pgAdmin 4 features, while adding support for some
         Greenplum-specific features. pgAdmin 4 is available for download at <xref
            href="https://www.pgadmin.org/docs/pgadmin4/1.x/" format="html" scope="external"
            />.<note>For limitations on using pgAdmin4 with Greenplum Database, refer to the
               <i>Greenplum Database Release Notes</i>.</note></p>
      <p>pgAdmin 4 supports the following Greenplum-specific features:</p>
      <ul>
         <li>Viewing Greenplum table DDL.</li>
         <li id="io147522">Append-optimized tables, including compressed append-optimized tables.
               <note>Only limited functionality for Greenplum partitioned tables is available with
               pgAdmin 4.</note>
         </li>
      </ul>
      <note>Graphical <codeph>EXPLAIN</codeph> features are currently not available with Greenplum
         Database.</note>
      <fig id="io149932">
         <title>pgAdmin 4 Dashboard View</title>
         <image href="../../graphics/pgAdmin4Dashbd.png" placement="break" width="679px"
            id="image_phx_vqr_hbb"/>
      </fig>
   </body>
   <topic id="topic7">
      <title>Installing pgAdmin 4</title>
      <body>
         <p>The installation package for pgAdmin 4 is available for download from the official
            pgAdmin 4 download site (<xref href="https://www.pgadmin.org" scope="external"
               format="html"/>). Installation instructions are included in the installation
            package.</p>
         <p>When configuring the server connection for Greenplum Database, retain the default
            Maintenance database of postgres, but specify gpadmin for the Username. When connected,
            Greenplum Database connections will be indicated by the Greenplum logo.</p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic9">
      <title>Viewing DDL Data with pgAdmin 4</title>
      <body>
         <p>You can use pgAdmin 4 to view Greenplum Database table DDL. </p>
         <p>To view the table DDL, simply drill down through the database information in the left
            navigation and select the desired table. Click on the <uicontrol>SQL</uicontrol> tab.
            The DDL will be displayed. You can also display DDL information for individual
            columns.</p>
         <fig id="io149084">
            <title>Graphical Query Plan in pgAdmin 4</title>
            <image href="../../graphics/pgAdmin4_showddl.png" placement="break" width="679px"
               id="image_wj1_4bm_3bb"/>
         </fig>
      </body>
   </topic>
</topic>
