<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<dita>
  <topic id="topic_fstrm">
    <title>Using the PgBouncer Connection Pooler </title>
    <shortdesc>The PgBouncer utility manages connection pools for PostgreSQL and Greenplum Database
      connections.</shortdesc>
    <body>
      <p>The Greenplum Database installation includes the PgBouncer connection pooling software. The
        following topics describe how to set up and use PgBouncer with Greenplum Database. See the
          <xref href="https://pgbouncer.github.io" format="html" scope="external">PgBouncer Web
          site</xref> for information about using PgBouncer with PostgreSQL.</p>
      <ul id="ul_off_zqj_5s">
        <li>
          <xref href="#topic_nzk_nqg_cs" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref href="#pgb_config" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref href="#topic_otc_snn_ts" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref href="#topic_m2h_5dj_5s" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li>
          <xref href="#topic_nfn_tvd_5s" format="dita"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Also, see reference information for PgBouncer in the <i>Greenplum Database Utility
          Guide</i>. </p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic_nzk_nqg_cs">
      <title>Overview</title>
      <body>
        <p>A database connection pool is a cache of database connections. Once a pool of connections
          is established, connection pooling eliminates the overhead of creating database
          connections, so clients connect much faster and the server load is reduced.</p>
        <p>The PgBouncer connection pooler, from the PostgreSQL community, is included with
          Greenplum Database. PgBouncer can manage connection pools for multiple databases, and
          databases may be on different Greenplum Database clusters or PostgreSQL backends.
          PgBouncer creates a pool for each database user and database combination. A pooled
          connection can only be reused for another connection request for the same user and
          database. </p>
        <p>The client application requires no software changes, but connects to the connection
          pool's host and port instead of the Greenplum Database master host and port. PgBouncer
          either creates a new database connection or reuses an existing connection. When the client
          disconnects, the connection is returned to the pool for re-use. </p>
        <p>PgBouncer supports the standard connection interface that PostgreSQL and Greenplum
          Database share. A client requesting a database connection provides the host name and port
          where PgBouncer is running, as well as the database name, username, and password.
          PgBouncer looks up the requested database (which may be an alias for the actual database)
          in its configuration file to find the host name, port, and database name for the database
          connection. The configuration file entry also determines how to authenticate the user and
          what database role will be used for the connection—a "forced user" can override the
          username provided with the client's connection request. </p>
        <p>PgBouncer requires an authentication file, a text file that contains a list of users and
          passwords. Passwords may be either clear text, MD5-encoded, or an LDAP/AD lookup string.
          You can also set up PgBouncer to query the destination database for users that are not in
          the authentication file. </p>
        <p>PgBouncer shares connections in one of three pool modes:<ul id="ul_jyx_rvg_cs">
            <li><i>Session pooling</i> – When a client connects, a connection is assigned to it as
              long as it remains connected. When the client disconnects, the connection is placed
              back into the pool.</li>
            <li><i>Transaction pooling</i> – A connection is assigned to a client for the duration
              of a transaction. When PgBouncer notices the transaction is done, the connection is
              placed back into the pool. This mode can be used only with applications that do not
              use features that depend upon a session. </li>
            <li><i>Statement pooling</i> – Statement pooling is like transaction pooling, but
              multi-statement transactions are not allowed. This mode is intended to enforce
              autocommit mode on the client and is targeted for PL/Proxy on PostgreSQL.</li>
          </ul></p>
        <p>A default pool mode can be set for the PgBouncer instance and the mode can be overridden
          for individual databases and users. </p>
        <p>By connecting to a virtual <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> database, you can monitor and
          manage PgBouncer using SQL-like commands. Configuration parameters can be changed without
          having to restart PgBouncer, and the configuration file can be reloaded to pick up
          changes.</p>
        <p>PgBouncer does not yet support SSL connections. If you want to encrypt traffic between
          clients and PgBouncer, you can use <xref href="https://www.stunnel.org" format="html"
            scope="external">stunnel</xref>, a free software utility that creates TLS-encrypted
          tunnels using the OpenSSL cryptography library. See <xref href="#topic_nfn_tvd_5s"
            format="dita"/> for directions.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="pgb_config">
      <title>Configuring and Starting PgBouncer</title>
      <body>
        <p>PgBouncer can be run on the Greenplum Database master or on another server. If you
          install PgBouncer on a separate server, you can easily switch clients to the standby
          master by updating the PgBouncer configuration file and reloading the configuration using
          the PgBouncer Administration Console. </p>
        <p>Follow these steps to set up PgBouncer.</p>
        <ol id="ol_xyn_qwg_cs">
          <li>Create a PgBouncer configuration file, for example <codeph>pgbouncer.ini</codeph>.
            Here is a simple configuration
              file:<codeblock>[databases]
template1 = host=127.0.0.1 port=5432 dbname=template1
mydb = host=127.0.0.1 port=5432 dbname=mydb

[pgbouncer]
pool_mode = session
listen_port = 6543
listen_addr = 127.0.0.1
auth_type = md5
auth_file = users.txt
logfile = pgbouncer.log
pidfile = pgbouncer.pid
admin_users = gpadmin</codeblock><p>The
              file is in the <codeph>.ini</codeph> file format and has three sections:
                <i>databases</i>, <i>pgbouncer</i>, and <i>users</i>. The databases section lists
              databases with their connection details. The pgbouncer section configures the
              PgBouncer instance. </p></li>
          <li>Create an authentication file. The name of the file must match the
              <codeph>auth_file</codeph> parameter in the <codeph>pgbouncer.ini</codeph> file,
              <codeph>users.txt</codeph> in this example. Each line contains a user name and
            password. The format of the password string matches the <codeph>auth_type</codeph>
            parameter in the PgBouncer configuration file. If the <codeph>auth_type</codeph>
            parameter is <codeph>plain</codeph>, the password string is a clear text password, for
            example: <codeblock>"gpadmin" "gpadmin1234"</codeblock><p>The <codeph>auth_type</codeph>
              in the following example is <codeph>md5</codeph>, so the authentication field must be
              MD5-encoded. The format for an MD5-encoded password
              is:<codeblock>"md5" + MD5(<varname>&lt;password>&lt;username></varname>)</codeblock></p><p>You
              can use the Linux <codeph>md5sum</codeph> command to calculate the MD5 string. For
              example, if the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> password is <codeph>admin1234</codeph> the
              following command prints the string for the password
              field:<codeblock>$ user=gpadmin; passwd=admin1234; echo -n md5; echo $passwd$user | md5sum
md53ce96652dedd8226c498e09ae2d26220</codeblock></p><p>And
              here is the MD5-encoded entry for the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user in the PgBouncer
              authentication file:</p><p>
              <codeblock>"gpadmin" "md53ce96652dedd8226c498e09ae2d26220"</codeblock>
            </p><p>To authenticate users against an LDAP or Active Directory server, the password
              field contains an LDAP lookup string. For
              example:</p><codeblock>"gpdbuser1" "ldap://10.0.0.11:10389/uid=gpdbuser1,ou=users,ou=system"</codeblock><p>For
              Active Directory, a user entry looks like this
              example:<codeblock>"gpdbuser2" "ldap://10.0.0.12:389/gpdbuser2"</codeblock>See <xref
                href="#topic_m2h_5dj_5s" format="dita"/> for the steps to configure PgBouncer to
              authenticate users with an LDAP server. </p><p>For details about the authentication
              file, see the "Authentication File Format" section of the PgBouncer reference in the
                <i>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</i>. </p></li>
          <li>Launch
              <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph>:<codeblock>$ $GPHOME/bin/pgbouncer -d pgbouncer.ini</codeblock><p>The
                <codeph>-d</codeph> or <codeph>--daemon</codeph> option runs PgBouncer as a
              background process. See the PgBouncer reference in the <i>Greenplum Database Utility
                Guide</i> for the <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> command syntax and its
            options.</p></li>
          <li>Update client applications to connect to <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> instead of
            directly to Greenplum Database server. To start <codeph>psql</codeph>, for
            example:<codeblock>$ psql -p 6543 -U <varname>someuser</varname> template1</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_lw4_rdm_g5">
      <title>Server Reset Query</title>
      <body>
        <p>When a connection is returned to the pool, it must be reset to the state of a newly
          created connection. PgBouncer accomplishes this by issuing a query before returning a
          connection to the pool. PostgreSQL 8.3 and later have the <codeph>DISCARD ALL</codeph>
          command for this purpose and it is the default reset query for the standard PgBouncer
          distribution. Greenplum Database does not support <codeph>DISCARD ALL</codeph> and if it
          is used an error is logged. </p>
        <p>A reset query can be specified by setting the <codeph>server_reset_query</codeph>
          parameter in the PgBouncer configuration file. For Greenplum Database with PgBouncer in
          session pooling mode, the <codeph>server_reset_query</codeph> parameter can be set to this
          query:<codeblock>RESET ALL; SET SESSION AUTHORIZATION DEFAULT</codeblock></p>
        <p>This is the default server reset query in the modified version of PgBouncer included with
          Greenplum Database 4.7.0 and later. Although the default differs from PgBouncer, it helps
          to ensure that the connection pool is transparent to Greenplum Database users and client
          applications do not have to be modified to use a connection pool. </p>
        <p>For more information about the <codeph>server_reset_query</codeph> parameter and the
          PgBouncer configuration file, see the PgBouncer reference in the <i>Greenplum Database
            Utility Guide</i>.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_otc_snn_ts">
      <title>Managing PgBouncer</title>
      <body>
        <p>PgBouncer has an administrative console, which is accessed by logging into the
            <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> virtual database. The console accepts SQL-like commands that
          allow you to monitor, reconfigure, and manage PgBouncer. </p>
        <p>Follow these steps to get started with the PgBouncer administrative console.</p>
        <ol id="ol_jwt_hyn_ts">
          <li>Log in to the <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> virtual database with
              <codeph>psql</codeph>:<codeblock>$ psql -p 6543 -U <varname>username</varname> pgbouncer</codeblock><p>The
              username must be set in the <codeph>admin_users</codeph> parameter in the
                <codeph>pgbouncer.ini</codeph> configuration file. You can also log in with the
              current Unix username if the <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> process is running with that
              user's UID.</p></li>
          <li>To see the available commands, run the <codeph>show help</codeph>
            command:<codeblock>pgbouncer=# show help;
NOTICE:  Console usage
DETAIL:
       SHOW HELP|CONFIG|DATABASES|POOLS|CLIENTS|SERVERS|VERSION
	SHOW STATS|FDS|SOCKETS|ACTIVE_SOCKETS|LISTS|MEM
	SHOW DNS_HOSTS|DNS_ZONES
	SET key = arg
	RELOAD
	PAUSE [&lt;db>]
	RESUME [&lt;db>]
	DISABLE &lt;db>
	ENABLE &lt;db>
	KILL &lt;db>
	SUSPEND
	SHUTDOWN</codeblock></li>
          <li>If you make changes to the <codeph>pgbouncer.ini</codeph> file, you can reload it with
            the <codeph>RELOAD</codeph> command:<codeblock>pgbouncer=# RELOAD;</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
        <section>
          <p>To map clients to server connections, use the <codeph>SHOW CLIENTS</codeph> and
              <codeph>SHOW SERVERS</codeph> views:</p>
          <ol id="ol_xgn_qfq_bt">
            <li>Use <codeph>ptr</codeph> and <codeph>link</codeph> to map the local client
              connection to the server connection.</li>
            <li>Use <codeph>addr</codeph> and <codeph>port</codeph> of the client connection to
              identify the TCP connection from the client.</li>
            <li>Use <codeph>local_addr</codeph> and <codeph>local_port</codeph> to identify the TCP
              connection to the server.</li>
          </ol>
        </section>
        <p>For complete documentation for all of the administration console commands, see the
          "PgBouncer Administration Console Commands" section of the PgBouncer reference in the
            <i>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</i>.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="id_mpv_d2q_bt">
      <title>Upgrading PgBouncer</title>
      <body>
        <p>You can upgrade PgBouncer without dropping connections. Just launch the new PgBouncer
          process with the <codeph>-R</codeph> option and the same configuration file:</p>
        <codeblock>$ pgbouncer -R -d config.ini</codeblock>
        <p>The <codeph>-R</codeph> (reboot) option causes the new process to connect to the console
          of the old process through a Unix socket and issue the following commands:</p>
        <codeblock>SUSPEND;
SHOW FDS;
SHUTDOWN;</codeblock>
        <p>When the new process sees that the old process is gone, it resumes the work with the old
          connections. This is possible because the <codeph>SHOW FDS</codeph> command sends actual
          file descriptors to the new process. If the transition fails for any reason, kill the new
          process and the old process will resume.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_m2h_5dj_5s">
      <title>Setting up LDAP Authentication with PgBouncer</title>
      <body>
        <p>You can authenticate Greenplum Database users against your LDAP or Active Directory
          service when using the PgBouncer connection pooler. When you have LDAP authentication
          working, you can secure client connections to PgBouncer by setting up stunnel, as
          described in <xref href="#topic_nfn_tvd_5s" format="dita"/>. </p>
        <p>Before you begin, you must have an LDAP or Active Directory server and a Greenplum
          Database cluster. <ol id="ol_c3q_g3j_5s">
            <li>Create Greenplum Database users in the LDAP/AD server, for example
                <codeph>gpdbuser1</codeph> and <codeph>gpdbuser2</codeph>.</li>
            <li>Create the corresponding Greenplum Database users in the
              database:<codeblock>createuser gpdbuser1
createuser gpdbuser2</codeblock></li>
            <li>Add the users to the Greenplum Database <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph>
              file:<codeblock>host     all         gpdbuser1              0.0.0.0/0     trust
host     all         gpdbuser2              0.0.0.0/0     trust
</codeblock></li>
            <li>Create a PgBouncer <filepath>config.ini</filepath> file with the following
              contents:<codeblock>[databases]
* = host=<varname>GPDB_host_addr</varname> port=<varname>GPDB_port</varname>

[pgbouncer]
listen_port = 6432
listen_addr = 0.0.0.0
auth_type = plain
auth_file = users.txt
logfile = pgbouncer.log
pidfile = pgbouncer.pid
ignore_startup_parameters=options
</codeblock></li>
            <li>Create the <codeph>users.txt</codeph> PgBouncer authentication file. The first field
              is the user name and the second is the LDAP or Active Directory lookup string for the
              user. For OpenLDAP or ApacheDS, for example, a user entry in the
                <filepath>users.txt</filepath> looks like
                this:<codeblock>"gpdbuser1" "ldap://10.0.0.11:10389/uid=gpdbuser1,ou=users,ou=system"</codeblock><p>For
                Active Directory, a user entry looks like this
                example:<codeblock>"gpdbuser1" "ldap://10.0.0.12:389/gpdbuser1"</codeblock></p></li>
            <li>Start PgBouncer with the <codeph>config.ini</codeph> file you
              created:<codeblock>$ pgbouncer -d config.ini</codeblock></li>
          </ol></p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_nfn_tvd_5s">
      <title>Securing PgBouncer Connections with stunnel</title>
      <body>
        <p>PgBouncer does not have SSL support, so connections between database clients and
          PgBouncer are not encrypted. To encrypt these connections, you can use <xref
            href="https://www.stunnel.org/index.html" format="html" scope="external">stunnel</xref>, a free
          software utility. stunnel is a proxy that uses the OpenSSL cryptographic library to add
          TLS encryption to network services. Newer versions of stunnel support the PostgreSQL libpq
          protocol, so Greenplum and PostgreSQL clients can use libpq SSL support to connect
          securely over the network to a stunnel instance set up as a proxy for PgBouncer. If you
          use a version of stunnel without libpq support, you need to set up a stunnel instance on
          both the client and PgBouncer host to create a secure tunnel over the network.</p>
        <p>On most platforms, you can install stunnel using the system package manager. For Windows,
          you can download an installer from <xref href="https://www.stunnel.org/index.html" format="html"
            scope="external">https://www.stunnel.org/index.html</xref>. You can also download and install stunnel
          from source if a packaged version is unavailable, if you want to upgrade to a newer
          version, or if you want to upgrade to a newer OpenSSL version. The next section provides
          steps to download, compile, and install OpenSSL and stunnel. </p>
        <p>For complete stunnel documentation, visit the <xref
            href="https://www.stunnel.org/docs.html" format="html" scope="external">stunnel
            documentation</xref> web site.</p>
        <section>
          <title>Installing stunnel From Source</title>
          <p>stunnel requires a version of the OpenSSL development package greater than 1.0. The
            following instructions download and build OpenSSL and stunnel for Red Hat or CentOS. Be
            sure to check <xref
              href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/static/auth-pg-hba-conf.html" format="html"
              scope="external">https://www.stunnel.org/index.html</xref> and <xref
              href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/static/auth-pg-hba-conf.html" format="html"
              scope="external">http://openssl.org</xref> for the latest versions. </p>
          <ol id="ol_flk_5y3_bt">
            <li>Set the <codeph>PREFIX</codeph> environment variable to the directory where you want
              to install stunnel, for example <filepath>/usr/local/stunnel</filepath> or
                <filepath>/home/gpadmin/stunnel</filepath>. If you choose to install stunnel in a
              system directory, you may need to run the <codeph>make install</codeph> commands as
              root.
              <codeblock>export PREFIX=<varname>/path/to/install_stunnel</varname></codeblock></li>
            <li>The following commands download, build, and install OpenSSL version
              1.0.2c:<codeblock>wget ftp://ftp.openssl.org/source/openssl-1.0.2c.tar.gz
tar xzf openssl-1.0.2c.tar.gz
cd openssl-1.0.2c
./Configure linux-x86_64 --prefix=$PREFIX shared no-asm
make
make install_sw
cd ..</codeblock></li>
            <li>Download, build, and install stunnel with the following
              commands:<codeblock>wget --no-check-certificate https://www.stunnel.org/downloads/stunnel-5.22.tar.gz
tar xzf stunnel-5.22.tar.gz
cd stunnel-5.22
LDFLAGS="-Wl,-rpath,'"'$$'"ORIGIN/../lib'"
./configure --prefix=$PREFIX --with-ssl=$PREFIX
make
make install</codeblock></li>
          </ol>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>Setting up Stunnel for PgBouncer</title>
          <p>Set up a stunnel instance as a proxy for PgBouncer. The stunnel instance accepts secure
            connections from database clients on its own port, decrypts the packets and forwards
            them to the PgBouncer instance on the same host (or on another host in a protected local
            network). PgBouncer results, including database results from connections managed by
            PgBouncer, are encrypted and returned over the network to the client. </p>
          <ol id="ol_gls_zwd_5s">
            <li>On the server running PgBouncer, create a directory for stunnel configuration files,
              for example <filepath>/home/gpadmin/stunnel</filepath>.</li>
            <li>Create a certificate and key file to use for authenticating. You can also use an
              existing certificate and key, or create a new pair with the following
                <codeph>openssl</codeph>
                command:<codeblock>$ openssl req -new -x509 -days 3650 -nodes -out stunnel.pem -keyout stunnel.key</codeblock><p>Move
                the <codeph>stunnel.key</codeph> and <codeph>stunnel.pem</codeph> files into your
                stunnel configuration directory. </p></li>
            <li>Create a stunnel configuration file, for example, <filepath>stunnel.conf</filepath>,
              with the following
                contents:<codeblock>
debug = info
socket = l:TCP_NODELAY=1
socket = r:TCP_NODELAY=1

debug = 7

cert = <varname>/PATH/TO/</varname>stunnel.pem
key = <varname>/PATH/TO/</varname>stunnel.key

[pg-server]
client=no
accept = 0.0.0.0:5433             # This is the SSL listening port
connect = <varname>PGHOST</varname>:<varname>PGPORT</varname>   # This is the PgBouncer listen port
protocol = pgsql
</codeblock><p>See
                the <xref href="https://www.stunnel.org/static/stunnel.html#CONFIGURATION-FILE"
                  format="html" scope="external">stunnel configuration file reference</xref> for
                additional configuration options. </p></li>
            <li>Run <codeph>stunnel</codeph> on the
              server:<codeblock>stunnel <varname>/path/to/stunnel-srv.conf</varname></codeblock></li>
            <li>On the client, connect to stunnel on its host and accept port. For
              example:<codeblock>psql -h <varname>pgbouncer-host</varname> -p <varname>stunnel-accept-port</varname> <varname>database-name</varname></codeblock></li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</dita>
