<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="pb141029">createuser</title><body><p id="client_util_desc">Creates a new database role.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock id="client_util_synopsis"><b>createuser</b> [<varname>connection-option</varname> ...] [<varname>role_attribute</varname> ...] [<b>-e</b>] <varname>role_name</varname>

<b>createuser</b> <b>-? | --help</b> 

<b>createuser</b> <b>-V | --version</b></codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p><codeph>createuser</codeph> creates a new Greenplum Database role. You must be a
                                superuser or have the <codeph>CREATEROLE</codeph> privilege to
                                create new roles. You must connect to the database as a superuser to
                                create new superusers.</p><p>Superusers can bypass all access permission checks within the database,
so superuser privileges should not be granted lightly. </p><p><codeph>createuser</codeph> is a wrapper around the SQL command <codeph>CREATE
ROLE</codeph>.</p></section><section id="section4"><title>Options</title><parml><plentry><pt>role_name</pt><pd>The name of the role to be created. This name must be different from all existing roles in this
                                                  Greenplum Database installation. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-c <varname>number</varname> | --connection-limit=<varname>number</varname></pt><pd>Set a maximum number of connections for the new role. The default
is to set no limit. </pd></plentry>
<plentry><pt>-d | --createdb</pt><pd>The new role will be allowed to create databases. </pd></plentry>
  <plentry><pt>-D | --no-createdb</pt><pd>The new role will not be allowed to create databases. This is the
    default.</pd></plentry>
<plentry><pt>-e | --echo</pt><pd>Echo the commands that <codeph>createuser</codeph> generates and
sends to the server. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-E | --encrypted</pt><pd>Encrypts the role's password stored in the database. If not specified,
the default password behavior is used. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-i | --inherit</pt><pd>The new role will automatically inherit privileges of roles it is
a member of. This is the default.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-I | --no-inherit</pt><pd>The new role will not automatically inherit privileges of roles it
is a member of. </pd></plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--interactive</pt>
          <pd>Prompt for the user name if none is specified on the command line, and also prompt for
            whichever of the options <codeph>-d</codeph>/<codeph>-D</codeph>,
              <codeph>-r</codeph>/<codeph>-R</codeph>, <codeph>-s</codeph>/<codeph>-S</codeph> is
            not specified on the command line.</pd>
        </plentry><plentry><pt>-l | --login</pt><pd>The new role will be allowed to log in to Greenplum Database. This is the default. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-L | --no-login</pt><pd>The new role will not be allowed to log in (a group-level role).</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-N | --unencrypted</pt><pd>Does not encrypt the role's password stored in the database. If
not specified, the default password behavior is used. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-P | --pwprompt</pt><pd>If given, <codeph>createuser</codeph> will issue a prompt for the
password of the new role. This is not necessary if you do not plan on
using password authentication. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-r | --createrole</pt><pd>The new role will be allowed to create new roles (<codeph>CREATEROLE</codeph>
privilege). </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-R | --no-createrole</pt><pd>The new role will not be allowed to create new roles. This is the default.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-s | --superuser</pt><pd>The new role will be a superuser. </pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-S | --no-superuser</pt><pd>The new role will not be a superuser. This is the default.</pd></plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-V | --version</pt>
          <pd>Print the <codeph>createuser</codeph> version and exit.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--replication</pt>
          <pd>The new user will have the <codeph>REPLICATION</codeph> privilege, which is described
            more fully in the documentation for <xref
              href="../../ref_guide/sql_commands/CREATE_ROLE.xml#topic1"/>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--no-replication</pt>
          <pd>The new user will not have the <codeph>REPLICATION</codeph> privilege, which is
            described more fully in the documentation for <xref
              href="../../ref_guide/sql_commands/CREATE_ROLE.xml#topic1"/>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-? | --help</pt>
          <pd>Show help about <codeph>createuser</codeph> command line arguments, and exit.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml><sectiondiv id="section5"><b>Connection Options</b><parml><plentry><pt>-h <varname>host</varname> | --host=<varname>host</varname></pt><pd>The host name of the machine on which the Greenplum master database
                                                  server is running. If not specified, reads from
                                                  the environment variable <codeph>PGHOST</codeph>
                                                  or defaults to localhost.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-p <varname>port</varname> | --port=<varname>port</varname></pt><pd>The TCP port on which the Greenplum master database server is
                                                  listening for connections. If not specified, reads
                                                  from the environment variable
                                                  <codeph>PGPORT</codeph> or defaults to 5432.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-U <varname>username</varname> | --username=<varname>username</varname></pt><pd>The database role name to connect as. If not specified, reads from
the environment variable <codeph>PGUSER</codeph> or defaults to the current
system role name.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-w | --no-password</pt><pd>Never issue a password prompt. If the server requires password authentication
and a password is not available by other means such as a <codeph>.pgpass</codeph>
file, the connection attempt will fail. This option can be useful in
batch jobs and scripts where no user is present to enter a password.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-W | --password</pt><pd>Force a password prompt.</pd></plentry></parml></sectiondiv></section><section id="section6"><title>Examples</title>
  <p>To create a role <codeph>joe</codeph> on the default database
        server:<codeblock>$ <b>createuser joe</b></codeblock></p><p>To create a role <codeph>joe</codeph> on the default database server with prompting for some
        additional attributes: </p><codeblock>$ <b>createuser --interactive joe</b>
Shall the new role be a superuser? (y/n) <b>n</b>
Shall the new role be allowed to create databases? (y/n) <b>n</b>
Shall the new role be allowed to create more new roles? (y/n) <b>n</b>
CREATE ROLE</codeblock><p>To create the same role <codeph>joe</codeph> using connection options, with attributes explicitly
        specified, and taking a look at the underlying command:</p><codeblock><b>createuser -h masterhost -p 54321 -S -D -R -e joe</b>
CREATE ROLE joe NOSUPERUSER NOCREATEDB NOCREATEROLE INHERIT 
LOGIN;
CREATE ROLE</codeblock><p>To create the role <codeph>joe</codeph> as a superuser, and assign password
          <codeph>admin123</codeph> immediately:</p><codeblock><b>createuser -P -s -e joe</b>
Enter password for new role: <b>admin123</b>
Enter it again: <b>admin123</b>
CREATE ROLE joe PASSWORD 'admin123' SUPERUSER CREATEDB 
CREATEROLE INHERIT LOGIN;
CREATE ROLE</codeblock><p>In the above example, the new password is not actually echoed when typed, but we show what was
        typed for clarity. However the password will appear in the echoed command, as illustrated if
        the <codeph>-e</codeph> option is used.</p></section><section id="section7">
                        <title>See Also</title>
                        <p><ph otherprops="op-print"><codeph>CREATE ROLE</codeph> in the
                                                <i>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</i></ph><ph
                                        otherprops="op-help"><codeph><xref
                                                  href="../../ref_guide/sql_commands/CREATE_ROLE.xml#topic1"
                                                /></codeph>,
                        <codeph><xref
                                                  href="dropuser.xml#topic1"/></codeph></ph></p>
                </section></body></topic>
