<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title id="os137116">pg_dump</title>
  <body>
    <p id="client_util_desc">Extracts a database into a single script file or other archive
      file.</p>
    <section id="section2">
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock id="client_util_synopsis"><b>pg_dump</b> [<varname>connection_option</varname> ...] [<varname>dump_option</varname> ...] <varname>dbname</varname></codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section3">
      <title>Description</title>
      <p><codeph>pg_dump</codeph> is a standard PostgreSQL utility for backing up a database, and is
        also supported in Greenplum Database. It creates a single (non-parallel) dump file. For
        routine backups of Greenplum Database, it is better to use the Greenplum Database backup
        utility, <codeph><xref href="../admin_utilities/gpcrondump.xml#topic1"/></codeph>, for the
        best performance.</p>
      <p>Use <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> if you are migrating your data to another database vendor's
        system, or to another Greenplum Database system with a different segment configuration (for
        example, if the system you are migrating to has greater or fewer segment instances). To
        restore, you must use the corresponding <xref href="./pg_restore.xml#topic1" type="topic"
          format="dita"/> utility (if the dump file is in archive format), or you can use a client
        program such as <codeph><xref href="psql.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>
        (if the dump file is in plain text format). </p>
      <p>Since <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> is compatible with regular PostgreSQL, it can be used to
        migrate data into Greenplum Database. The <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> utility in Greenplum
        Database is very similar to the PostgreSQL <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> utility, with the
        following exceptions and limitations:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="os142186">If using <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> to backup a Greenplum Database database,
          keep in mind that the dump operation can take a long time (several hours) for very large
          databases. Also, you must make sure you have sufficient disk space to create the dump
          file.</li>
        <li id="os142181">If you are migrating data from one Greenplum Database system to another,
          use the <codeph>--gp-syntax</codeph> command-line option to include the
            <codeph>DISTRIBUTED BY</codeph> clause in <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> statements. This
          ensures that Greenplum Database table data is distributed with the correct distribution
          key columns upon restore.</li>
      </ul>
      <p><codeph>pg_dump</codeph> makes consistent backups even if the database is being used
        concurrently. <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> does not block other users accessing the database
        (readers or writers). </p>
      <p>When used with one of the archive file formats and combined with
          <codeph>pg_restore</codeph>, <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> provides a flexible archival and
        transfer mechanism. <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> can be used to backup an entire database, then
          <codeph>pg_restore </codeph>can be used to examine the archive and/or select which parts
        of the database are to be restored. The most flexible output file format is the
          <varname>custom</varname> format (<codeph>-Fc</codeph>). It allows for selection and
        reordering of all archived items, and is compressed by default. The tar format
          (<codeph>-Ft</codeph>) is not compressed and it is not possible to reorder data when
        loading, but it is otherwise quite flexible. It can be manipulated with standard UNIX tools
        such as <codeph>tar</codeph>.</p>
      <note>The <codeph>--ignore-version</codeph> option is deprecated and will be removed in a
        future release.</note>
    </section>
    <section id="section4">
      <title>Options</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt>dbname</pt>
          <pd>Specifies the name of the database to be dumped. If this is not specified, the
            environment variable <codeph>PGDATABASE</codeph> is used. If that is not set, the user
            name specified for the connection is used.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <sectiondiv id="section5">
        <b>Dump Options</b>
        <parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-a | --data-only</pt>
            <pd>Dump only the data, not the schema (data definitions). This option is only
              meaningful for the plain-text format. For the archive formats, you may specify the
              option when you call <codeph><xref href="./pg_restore.xml#topic1" type="topic"
                  format="dita"/></codeph>. </pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-b | --blobs</pt>
            <pd>Include large objects in the dump. This is the default behavior except when
                <codeph>--schema</codeph>, <codeph>--table</codeph>, or
                <codeph>--schema-only</codeph> is specified, so the <codeph>-b</codeph> switch is
              only useful to add large objects to selective dumps. </pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-c | --clean</pt>
            <pd>Adds commands to the text output file to clean (drop) database objects prior to (the
              commands for) creating them. Note that objects are not dropped before the dump
              operation begins, but <codeph>DROP</codeph> commands are added to the DDL dump output
              files so that when you use those files to do a restore, the <codeph>DROP</codeph>
              commands are run prior to the <codeph>CREATE</codeph> commands. This option is only
              meaningful for the plain-text format. For the archive formats, you may specify the
              option when you call <codeph><xref href="./pg_restore.xml#topic1" type="topic"
                  format="dita"/></codeph>. </pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-C | --create</pt>
            <pd>Begin the output with a command to create the database itself and reconnect to the
              created database. (With a script of this form, it doesn't matter which database you
              connect to before running the script.) This option is only meaningful for the
              plain-text format. For the archive formats, you may specify the option when you call
                  <codeph><xref href="./pg_restore.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
              /></codeph>. </pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-d | --inserts</pt>
            <pd>Dump data as <codeph>INSERT</codeph> commands (rather than <codeph>COPY</codeph>).
              This will make restoration very slow; it is mainly useful for making dumps that can be
              loaded into non-PostgreSQL-based databases. Also, since this option generates a
              separate command for each row, an error in reloading a row causes only that row to be
              lost rather than the entire table contents. Note that the restore may fail altogether
              if you have rearranged column order. The <codeph>-D</codeph> option is safe against
              column order changes, though even slower. </pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-D | --column-inserts | --attribute-inserts</pt>
            <pd>Dump data as <codeph>INSERT</codeph> commands with explicit column names
                <codeph>(INSERT
                INTO</codeph><varname>table</varname><codeph>(</codeph><varname>column</varname><codeph>,
                ...) VALUES ...)</codeph>. This will make restoration very slow; it is mainly useful
              for making dumps that can be loaded into non-PostgreSQL-based databases. Also, since
              this option generates a separate command for each row, an error in reloading a row
              causes only that row to be lost rather than the entire table contents.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-E <varname>encoding</varname> | --encoding=<varname>encoding</varname></pt>
            <pd>Create the dump in the specified character set encoding. By default, the dump is
              created in the database encoding. (Another way to get the same result is to set the
                <codeph>PGCLIENTENCODING</codeph> environment variable to the desired dump
              encoding.)</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-f <varname>file</varname> | --file=<varname>file</varname></pt>
            <pd>Send output to the specified file. If this is omitted, the standard output is used.
            </pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-F p|c|t | --format=plain|custom|tar</pt>
            <pd>Selects the format of the output. format can be one of the following: </pd>
            <pd>p | plain — Output a plain-text SQL script file (the default). </pd>
            <pd>c | custom — Output a custom archive suitable for input into <codeph><xref
                  href="./pg_restore.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>. This is the
              most flexible format in that it allows reordering of loading data as well as object
              definitions. This format is also compressed by default. </pd>
            <pd>t | tar — Output a tar archive suitable for input into <codeph><xref
                  href="./pg_restore.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>. Using this
              archive format allows reordering and/or exclusion of database objects at the time the
              database is restored. It is also possible to limit which data is reloaded at restore
              time. </pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-i | --ignore-version</pt>
            <pd><note>This option is deprecated and will be removed in a future
              release.</note>Ignore version mismatch between <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> and the
              database server. <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> can dump from servers running previous
              releases of Greenplum Database (or PostgreSQL), but very old versions may not be
              supported anymore. Use this option if you need to override the version check.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-n <varname>schema</varname> | --schema=<varname>schema</varname></pt>
            <pd>Dump only schemas matching the schema pattern; this selects both the schema itself,
              and all its contained objects. When this option is not specified, all non-system
              schemas in the target database will be dumped. Multiple schemas can be selected by
              writing multiple <codeph>-n</codeph> switches. Also, the schema parameter is
              interpreted as a pattern according to the same rules used by
                <codeph>psql</codeph>'s<codeph> \d</codeph> commands, so multiple schemas can also
              be selected by writing wildcard characters in the pattern. When using wildcards, be
              careful to quote the pattern if needed to prevent the shell from expanding the
              wildcards.</pd>
            <pd>Note: When -n is specified, <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> makes no attempt to dump any
              other database objects that the selected schema(s) may depend upon. Therefore, there
              is no guarantee that the results of a specific-schema dump can be successfully
              restored by themselves into a clean database.<note>Non-schema objects such as blobs
                are not dumped when <codeph>-n</codeph> is specified. You can add blobs back to the
                dump with the <codeph>--blobs</codeph> switch.</note></pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-N <varname>schema</varname> | --exclude-schema=<varname>schema</varname></pt>
            <pd>Do not dump any schemas matching the schema pattern. The pattern is interpreted
              according to the same rules as for <codeph>-n</codeph>. <codeph>-N</codeph> can be
              given more than once to exclude schemas matching any of several patterns. When both
                <codeph>-n</codeph> and <codeph>-N</codeph> are given, the behavior is to dump just
              the schemas that match at least one <codeph>-n</codeph> switch but no
                <codeph>-N</codeph> switches. If <codeph>-N</codeph> appears without
                <codeph>-n</codeph>, then schemas matching <codeph>-N</codeph> are excluded from
              what is otherwise a normal dump.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-o | --oids</pt>
            <pd>Dump object identifiers (OIDs) as part of the data for every table. Use of this
              option is not recommended for files that are intended to be restored into Greenplum
              Database.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-O | --no-owner</pt>
            <pd>Do not output commands to set ownership of objects to match the original database.
              By default, <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> issues <codeph>ALTER OWNER</codeph> or
                <codeph>SET SESSION AUTHORIZATION</codeph> statements to set ownership of created
              database objects. These statements will fail when the script is run unless it is
              started by a superuser (or the same user that owns all of the objects in the script).
              To make a script that can be restored by any user, but will give that user ownership
              of all the objects, specify <codeph>-O</codeph>. This option is only meaningful for
              the plain-text format. For the archive formats, you may specify the option when you
              call <codeph><xref href="./pg_restore.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                /></codeph>.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-s | --schema-only</pt>
            <pd>Dump only the object definitions (schema), not data.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-S <varname>username</varname> | --superuser=<varname>username</varname></pt>
            <pd>Specify the superuser user name to use when disabling triggers. This is only
              relevant if <codeph>--disable-triggers</codeph> is used. It is better to leave this
              out, and instead start the resulting script as a superuser.<note>Greenplum Database
                does not support user-defined triggers.</note></pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-t <varname>table</varname> | --table=<varname>table</varname></pt>
            <pd>Dump only tables (or views or sequences) matching the table pattern. Specify the
              table in the format <codeph>schema.table</codeph>.</pd>
            <pd>Multiple tables can be selected by writing multiple <codeph>-t</codeph> switches.
              Also, the table parameter is interpreted as a pattern according to the same rules used
              by <codeph>psql</codeph>'s <codeph>\d</codeph> commands, so multiple tables can also
              be selected by writing wildcard characters in the pattern. When using wildcards, be
              careful to quote the pattern if needed to prevent the shell from expanding the
              wildcards. The <codeph>-n</codeph> and <codeph>-N</codeph> switches have no effect
              when <codeph>-t</codeph> is used, because tables selected by <codeph>-t</codeph> will
              be dumped regardless of those switches, and non-table objects will not be
                dumped.<note>When <codeph>-t</codeph> is specified, <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> makes
                no attempt to dump any other database objects that the selected table(s) may depend
                upon. Therefore, there is no guarantee that the results of a specific-table dump can
                be successfully restored by themselves into a clean database.<p>Also,
                    <codeph>-t</codeph> cannot be used to specify a child table partition. To dump a
                  partitioned table, you must specify the parent table name.</p></note></pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-T <varname>table</varname> | --exclude-table=<varname>table</varname></pt>
            <pd>Do not dump any tables matching the table pattern. The pattern is interpreted
              according to the same rules as for <codeph>-t</codeph>. <codeph>-T</codeph> can be
              given more than once to exclude tables matching any of several patterns. When both
                <codeph>-t</codeph> and <codeph>-T</codeph> are given, the behavior is to dump just
              the tables that match at least one <codeph>-t</codeph> switch but no
                <codeph>-T</codeph> switches. If <codeph>-T</codeph> appears without
                <codeph>-t</codeph>, then tables matching <codeph>-T</codeph> are excluded from what
              is otherwise a normal dump.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-v | --verbose</pt>
            <pd>Specifies verbose mode. This will cause <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> to output detailed
              object comments and start/stop times to the dump file, and progress messages to
              standard error.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-x | --no-privileges | --no-acl</pt>
            <pd>Prevent dumping of access privileges (<codeph>GRANT/REVOKE</codeph> commands).</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>--disable-dollar-quoting</pt>
            <pd>This option disables the use of dollar quoting for function bodies, and forces them
              to be quoted using SQL standard string syntax.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>--disable-triggers</pt>
            <pd>This option is only relevant when creating a data-only dump. It instructs
                <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> to include commands to temporarily disable triggers on the
              target tables while the data is reloaded. Use this if you have triggers on the tables
              that you do not want to invoke during data reload. The commands emitted for
                <codeph>--disable-triggers</codeph> must be done as superuser. So, you should also
              specify a superuser name with <codeph>-S</codeph>, or preferably be careful to start
              the resulting script as a superuser. This option is only meaningful for the plain-text
              format. For the archive formats, you may specify the option when you call
                  <codeph><xref href="./pg_restore.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                /></codeph>.<note>Greenplum Database does not support user-defined
              triggers.</note></pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>--no-tablespaces</pt>
            <pd>Do not output commands to select tablespaces. With this option, all objects will be
              created in whichever tablespace is the default during restore.</pd>
            <pd>This option is only meaningful for the plain-text format. For the archive formats,
              you can specify the option when you call <codeph>pg_restore</codeph>.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>--use-set-session-authorization</pt>
            <pd>Output SQL-standard <codeph>SET SESSION AUTHORIZATION</codeph> commands instead of
                <codeph>ALTER OWNER</codeph> commands to determine object ownership. This makes the
              dump more standards compatible, but depending on the history of the objects in the
              dump, may not restore properly. A dump using <codeph>SET SESSION
                AUTHORIZATION</codeph> will require superuser privileges to restore correctly,
              whereas <codeph>ALTER OWNER</codeph> requires lesser privileges.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>--gp-syntax | --no-gp-syntax </pt>
            <pd>Use <codeph>--gp-syntax</codeph> to dump Greenplum Database syntax in the
                <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> statements. This allows the distribution policy
                (<codeph>DISTRIBUTED BY</codeph> or <codeph>DISTRIBUTED RANDOMLY</codeph> clauses)
              of a Greenplum Database table to be dumped, which is useful for restoring into other
              Greenplum Database systems. The default is to include Greenplum Database syntax when
              connected to a Greenplum Database system, and to exclude it when connected to a
              regular PostgreSQL system.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-Z 0..9 | --compress=0..9</pt>
            <pd>Specify the compression level to use in archive formats that support compression.
              Currently only the <varname>custom</varname> archive format supports compression.</pd>
          </plentry>
        </parml>
      </sectiondiv>
      <sectiondiv id="section6">
        <b>Connection Options</b>
        <parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-h <varname>host</varname>| --host <varname>host</varname></pt>
            <pd>The host name of the machine on which the Greenplum Database master database server
              is running. If not specified, reads from the environment variable
                <codeph>PGHOST</codeph> or defaults to localhost.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-p <varname>port</varname>| --port <varname>port</varname></pt>
            <pd>The TCP port on which the Greenplum Database master database server is listening for
              connections. If not specified, reads from the environment variable
                <codeph>PGPORT</codeph> or defaults to 5432.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-U <varname>username</varname>| --username <varname>username</varname></pt>
            <pd>The database role name to connect as. If not specified, reads from the environment
              variable <codeph>PGUSER</codeph> or defaults to the current system role name.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-W | --password</pt>
            <pd>Force a password prompt.</pd>
          </plentry>
        </parml>
      </sectiondiv>
    </section>
    <section id="section7">
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p>When a data-only dump is chosen and the option <codeph>--disable-triggers</codeph> is used,
          <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> emits commands to disable triggers on user tables before
        inserting the data and commands to re-enable them after the data has been inserted. If the
        restore is stopped in the middle, the system catalogs may be left in the wrong state.</p>
      <p>Members of <codeph>tar</codeph> archives are limited to a size less than 8 GB. (This is an
        inherent limitation of the <codeph>tar</codeph> file format.) Therefore this format cannot
        be used if the textual representation of any one table exceeds that size. The total size of
        a tar archive and any of the other output formats is not limited, except possibly by the
        operating system.</p>
      <p>The dump file produced by <codeph>pg_dump</codeph> does not contain the statistics used by
        the optimizer to make query planning decisions. Therefore, it is wise to run
          <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> after restoring from a dump file to ensure good performance.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section8">
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>Dump a database called <codeph>mydb</codeph> into a SQL-script file:</p>
      <codeblock>pg_dump mydb &gt; db.sql</codeblock>
      <p>To reload such a script into a (freshly created) database named <codeph>newdb</codeph>: </p>
      <codeblock>psql -d newdb -f db.sql</codeblock>
      <p>Dump a Greenplum Database in tar file format and include distribution policy
        information:</p>
      <codeblock>pg_dump -Ft --gp-syntax mydb &gt; db.tar</codeblock>
      <p>To dump a database into a custom-format archive file: </p>
      <codeblock>pg_dump -Fc mydb &gt; db.dump</codeblock>
      <p>To reload an archive file into a (freshly created) database named <codeph>newdb</codeph>: </p>
      <codeblock>pg_restore -d newdb db.dump</codeblock>
      <p>To dump a single table named <codeph>mytab</codeph>: </p>
      <codeblock>pg_dump -t mytab mydb &gt; db.sql</codeblock>
      <p>To specify an upper-case or mixed-case name in <codeph>-t</codeph> and related switches,
        you need to double-quote the name; else it will be folded to lower case. But double quotes
        are special to the shell, so in turn they must be quoted. Thus, to dump a single table with
        a mixed-case name, you need something like:</p>
      <codeblock>pg_dump -t '"MixedCaseName"' mydb &gt; mytab.sql</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section9">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p><codeph><xref href="./pg_dumpall.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="pg_restore.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="psql.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
