<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic102">
  <title>Character Encoding</title>
  <body>
    <p>Character encoding systems consist of a code that pairs each character from a character set
      with something else, such as a sequence of numbers or octets, to facilitate data stransmission
      and storage. Greenplum Database supports a variety of character sets, including
      single-byte character sets such as the ISO 8859 series and multiple-byte character sets such
      as EUC (Extended UNIX Code), UTF-8, and Mule internal code. The server-side character set
      is defined during database initialization, UTF-8 is the default and can be changed. Clients
      can use all supported character sets transparently, but a few are not supported for use
      within the server as a server-side encoding. When loading or inserting data into Greenplum
      Database, Greenplum transparently converts the data from the specified client encoding into
      the server encoding. When sending data back to the client, Greenplum converts the data from
      the server character encoding into the specified client encoding.</p>
    <p>Data files must be in a character encoding recognized by Greenplum Database.
        <ph>See the <i>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</i> for the supported
        character sets. </ph>Data files that contain invalid or unsupported encoding sequences
      encounter errors when loading into Greenplum Database.</p>
    <note type="note">On data files generated on a Microsoft Windows operating system, run the
        <codeph>dos2unix</codeph> system command to remove any Windows-only characters before
      loading into Greenplum Database.</note>
    <note>If you <i>change</i> the <codeph>ENCODING</codeph> value in an existing
        <codeph>gpload</codeph> control file, you must manually drop any external tables that were
      creating using the previous <codeph>ENCODING</codeph> configuration. <codeph>gpload</codeph>
      does not drop and recreate external tables to use the new <codeph>ENCODING</codeph> if
        <codeph>REUSE_TABLES</codeph> is set to <codeph>true</codeph>.</note>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic103" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Changing the Client-Side Character Encoding</title>
    <body>
      <p>The client-side character encoding can be changed for a session by setting the
      server configuration parameter <codeph>client_encoding</codeph></p>
      <codeblock>SET client_encoding TO 'latin1';
</codeblock>
      <p>Change the client-side character encoding back to the default value:</p>
      <codeblock>RESET client_encoding;
</codeblock>
      <p>Show the current client-side character encoding setting:</p>
      <codeblock>SHOW client_encoding;
</codeblock>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
