<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic83">
   <title>Configuration File Format</title>
   <body>
      <p>The <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration file uses the YAML 1.1 document
                        format and implements a schema for defining the transformation parameters.
                        The configuration file must be a valid YAML document.</p>
      <p>The <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> program processes the document in order and
                        uses indentation (spaces) to determine the document hierarchy and
                        relationships of the sections to one another. The use of white space is
                        significant. Do not use white space for formatting and do not use tabs.</p>
      <p>The following is the basic structure of a configuration file.</p>
      <codeblock>---
VERSION:   1.0.0.1
TRANSFORMATIONS: 
transformation_name1:
TYPE:      input | output
COMMAND:   command
CONTENT:   data | paths
SAFE:      posix-regex
STDERR:    server | console
transformation_name2:
TYPE:      input | output
COMMAND:   command 
...</codeblock>
      <parml>
         <plentry id="p_version">
            <pt>VERSION</pt>
            <pd>Required. The version of the <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>
                                configuration file schema. The current version is 1.0.0.1.</pd>
         </plentry>
         <plentry id="p_transformations">
            <pt>TRANSFORMATIONS</pt>
            <pd>Required. Begins the transformation specification section. A
                                configuration file must have at least one transformation. When
                                    <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> receives a transformation request, it
                                looks in this section for an entry with the matching transformation
                                name. </pd>
         </plentry>
         <plentry id="p_type">
            <pt>TYPE</pt>
            <pd>Required. Specifies the direction of transformation. Values are
                                    <codeph>input</codeph> or <codeph>output</codeph>. <ul id="ul_f3p_j3q_34">
                  <li id="du198814">
                     <codeph>input</codeph>: <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> treats the standard output
                     of the transformation process as a stream of records to load into Greenplum Database.</li>
                  <li id="du198815">
                     <codeph>output</codeph>
                     <ph>: </ph>
                     <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> treats the standard input of the transformation
                     process as a stream of records from Greenplum Database to
                     transform and write to the appropriate output.</li>
               </ul>
            </pd>
         </plentry>
         <plentry id="p_command">
            <pt>COMMAND</pt>
            <pd>
               <p>Required. Specifies the command <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> will
                                    execute to perform the transformation. </p>
               <p>For input transformations, <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> invokes the command
                  specified in the <codeph>CONTENT</codeph> setting. The command is expected to open
                  the underlying file(s) as appropriate and produce one line of
                     <codeph>TEXT</codeph> for each row to load into Greenplum Database. The input transform determines whether the entire content should be converted
                  to one row or to multiple rows.</p>
               <p>For output transformations, <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> invokes
                                    this command as specified in the <codeph>CONTENT</codeph>
                                    setting. The output command is expected to open and write to the
                                    underlying file(s) as appropriate. The output transformation
                                    determines the final placement of the converted output.</p>
            </pd>
         </plentry>
         <plentry id="p_content">
            <pt>CONTENT</pt>
            <pd>
               <p>Optional. The values are <codeph>data</codeph> and
                                        <codeph>paths</codeph>. The default value is
                                        <codeph>data</codeph>.</p>
               <ul id="ul_wzg_43q_34">
                  <li id="du219653">When <codeph>CONTENT</codeph> specifies
                                            <codeph>data</codeph>, the text
                                            <codeph>%filename%</codeph> in the
                                            <codeph>COMMAND</codeph> section is replaced by the path
                                        to the file to read or write. </li>
                  <li id="du199214">When <codeph>CONTENT</codeph> specifies
                                            <codeph>paths</codeph>, the text
                                            <codeph>%filename%</codeph> in the
                                            <codeph>COMMAND</codeph> section is replaced by the path
                                        to the temporary file that contains the list of files to
                                        read or write. </li>
               </ul>
               <p>The following is an example of a <codeph>COMMAND</codeph> section
                                    showing the text <codeph>%filename%</codeph> that is
                                    replaced.</p>
               <p>
                  <codeblock>COMMAND: /bin/bash input_transform.sh %filename%</codeblock>
               </p>
            </pd>
         </plentry>
         <plentry id="p_safe">
            <pt>SAFE</pt>
            <pd>
               <p>Optional. A <codeph>POSIX </codeph>regular expression that the
                                    paths must match to be passed to the transformation. Specify
                                        <codeph>SAFE</codeph> when there is a concern about
                                    injection or improper interpretation of paths passed to the
                                    command. The default is no restriction on paths.</p>
            </pd>
         </plentry>
         <plentry id="p_stderr">
            <pt>STDERR</pt>
            <pd>
               <p>Optional. The values are <codeph>server</codeph> and
                                        <codeph>console</codeph>.</p>
               <p>This setting specifies how to handle standard error output from the
                  transformation. The default, <codeph>server</codeph>, specifies that
                     <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> will capture the standard error output from the
                  transformation in a temporary file and send the first 8k of that file to Greenplum Database as an error message. The error message will appear as a
                  SQL error. <codeph>Console</codeph> specifies that <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> does
                  not redirect or transmit the standard error output from the transformation. </p>
            </pd>
         </plentry>
      </parml>
   </body>
</topic>
