<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic68">
    <title>Defining a File-Based Writable External Table</title>
    <body>
        <p>Writable external tables that output data to files use the Greenplum parallel file server program,
                <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>, or the Hadoop Distributed File System interface,
                <codeph>gphdfs</codeph>. </p>
        <p>Use the <codeph>CREATE WRITABLE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> command to define the external
            table and specify the location and format of the output files. <ph>See <xref
                    href="../../external/g-using-the-greenplum-parallel-file-server--gpfdist-.xml#topic13"
                /> for instructions on setting up <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> for use with an
                external table and <xref
                    href="../../external/g-using-hadoop-distributed-file-system--hdfs--tables.xml#topic19"
                /> for instructions on setting up <codeph>gphdfs</codeph> for use with an external
                table.</ph></p>
        <ul>
            <li id="du175508">With a writable external table using the <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>
                protocol, the Greenplum segments send their data to
                    <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>, which writes the data to the named file.
                    <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> must run on a host that the Greenplum segments can access over the network.
                    <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> points to a file location on the output host and
                writes data received from the Greenplum segments to the
                file. To divide the output data among multiple files, list multiple
                    <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> URIs in your writable external table definition.</li>
            <li id="du218710">A writable external web table sends data to an application as a stream
                of data. For example, unload data from Greenplum Database and send it
                to an application that connects to another database or ETL tool to load the data
                elsewhere. Writable external web tables use the <codeph>EXECUTE</codeph> clause to
                specify a shell command, script, or application to run on the segment hosts and
                accept an input stream of data. See <xref
                    href="g-defining-a-command-based-writable-external-web-table.xml#topic71"/> for
                more information about using <codeph>EXECUTE</codeph> commands in a writable
                external table definition.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>You can optionally declare a distribution policy for your writable external tables. By
            default, writable external tables use a random distribution policy. If the source table
            you are exporting data from has a hash distribution policy, defining the same
            distribution key column(s) for the writable external table improves unload performance
            by eliminating the requirement to move rows over the interconnect. If you unload data
            from a particular table, you can use the <codeph>LIKE</codeph> clause to copy the column
            definitions and distribution policy from the source table.</p>
    </body>
</topic>
