<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic71">
   <title>Defining a Command-Based Writable External Web Table</title>
   <body>
      <p>You can define writable external web tables to send output rows to an application or
         script. The application must accept an input stream, reside in the same location on all of
         the Greenplum segment hosts, and be executable by the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user. All
         segments in the Greenplum system run the application or script, whether or not a segment
         has output rows to process.</p>
      <p>Use <codeph>CREATE WRITABLE EXTERNAL WEB TABLE</codeph> to define the external table and
         specify the application or script to run on the segment hosts. Commands execute from within
         the database and cannot access environment variables (such as <codeph>$PATH</codeph>). Set
         environment variables in the <codeph>EXECUTE</codeph> clause of your writable external
         table definition. For example:</p>
      <p>
         <codeblock>=# CREATE WRITABLE EXTERNAL WEB TABLE output (output text) 
    EXECUTE 'export PATH=$PATH:/home/<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>
            /programs;
    myprogram.sh' 
    FORMAT 'TEXT'
    DISTRIBUTED RANDOMLY;
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>The following Greenplum Database variables are available for use in OS commands executed by
         a web or writable external table. Set these variables as environment variables in the shell
         that executes the command(s). They can be used to identify a set of requests made by an
         external table statement across the Greenplum Database array of hosts and segment
         instances.</p>
      <table id="du224024">
         <title>External Table EXECUTE Variables</title>
         <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
            <thead>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">Variable</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">Description</entry>
               </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_CID</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">Command count of the transaction executing the external
                     table statement.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_DATABASE</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The database in which the external table definition
                     resides.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_DATE</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The date on which the external table command ran.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_MASTER_HOST</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The host name of the Greenplum master host from which the
                     external table statement was dispatched.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_MASTER_PORT</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The port number of the Greenplum master instance from which
                     the external table statement was dispatched.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_QUERY_STRING</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The SQL command (DML or SQL query) executed by Greenplum
                     Database.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_SEG_DATADIR</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The location of the data directory of the segment instance
                     executing the external table command.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_SEG_PG_CONF</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The location of the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file of
                     the segment instance executing the external table command.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_SEG_PORT</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The port number of the segment instance executing the
                     external table command.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_SEGMENT_COUNT</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The total number of primary segment instances in the
                     Greenplum Database system.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_SEGMENT_ID</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The ID number of the segment instance executing the external
                     table command (same as <codeph>dbid</codeph> in
                        <codeph>gp_segment_configuration</codeph>).</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_SESSION_ID</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The database session identifier number associated with the
                     external table statement.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_SN</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">Serial number of the external table scan node in the query
                     plan of the external table statement.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_TIME</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The time the external table command was executed.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_USER </entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The database user executing the external table
                     statement.</entry>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <entry colname="col1">$GP_XID</entry>
                  <entry colname="col2">The transaction ID of the external table statement.</entry>
               </row>
            </tbody>
         </tgroup>
      </table>
   </body>
</topic>
