<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic93">
   <title>Example 2 - IRS MeF XML Files (In demo Directory)</title>
   <body>
      <p>This example demonstrates loading a sample IRS Modernized eFile tax return
                        using a Joost STX transformation. The data is in the form of a complex XML
                        file.</p>
      <p>The U.S. Internal Revenue Service (IRS) made a significant commitment to XML
                        and specifies its use in its Modernized e-File (MeF) system. In MeF, each
                        tax return is an XML document with a deep hierarchical structure that
                        closely reflects the particular form of the underlying tax code. </p>
      <p>XML, XML Schema and stylesheets play a role in their data representation and business
      workflow. The actual XML data is extracted from a ZIP file attached to a MIME "transmission
      file" message. For more information about MeF, see <xref
        href="https://www.irs.gov/uac/modernized-e-file-overview" scope="external" format="html"
        >Modernized e-File (Overview)</xref> on the IRS web site.</p>
      <p>The sample XML document, <i>RET990EZ_2006.xml</i>, is about 350KB in size
                        with two elements:</p>
      <ul>
         <li id="du202262">ReturnHeader</li>
         <li id="du202263">ReturnData</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The &lt;ReturnHeader&gt; element contains general details about the tax
                        return such as the taxpayer's name, the tax year of the return, and the
                        preparer. The &lt;ReturnData&gt; element contains multiple sections with
                        specific details about the tax return and associated schedules. </p>
      <p>The following is an abridged sample of the XML file.</p>
      <codeblock>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt; 
&lt;Return returnVersion="2006v2.0"
   xmlns="https://www.irs.gov/efile" 
   xmlns:efile="https://www.irs.gov/efile"
   xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.irs.gov/efile"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"&gt; 
   &lt;ReturnHeader binaryAttachmentCount="1"&gt;
     &lt;ReturnId&gt;AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA&lt;/ReturnId&gt;
     &lt;Timestamp&gt;1999-05-30T12:01:01+05:01&lt;/Timestamp&gt;
     &lt;ReturnType&gt;990EZ&lt;/ReturnType&gt;
     &lt;TaxPeriodBeginDate&gt;2005-01-01&lt;/TaxPeriodBeginDate&gt;
     &lt;TaxPeriodEndDate&gt;2005-12-31&lt;/TaxPeriodEndDate&gt;
     &lt;Filer&gt;
       &lt;EIN&gt;011248772&lt;/EIN&gt;
       ... more data ...
     &lt;/Filer&gt;
     &lt;Preparer&gt;
       &lt;Name&gt;Percy Polar&lt;/Name&gt;
       ... more data ...
     &lt;/Preparer&gt;
     &lt;TaxYear&gt;2005&lt;/TaxYear&gt;
   &lt;/ReturnHeader&gt;
   ... more data ..
</codeblock>
      <p>The goal is to import all the data into a Greenplum database.
      First, convert the XML document into text with newlines "escaped", with two columns:
        <codeph>ReturnId</codeph> and a single column on the end for the entire MeF tax return. For
      example:</p>
      <p>
         <codeblock>AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA|&lt;Return returnVersion="2006v2.0"... 
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>Load the data into Greenplum Database.</p>
   </body>
</topic>