<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic55">
    <title>Handling Load Errors</title>
    <body>
        <p>Readable external tables are most commonly used to select data to load into regular
            database tables. You use the <codeph>CREATE TABLE AS SELECT</codeph> or <codeph>INSERT
                INTO </codeph>commands to query the external table data. By default, if the data
            contains an error, the entire command fails and the data is not loaded into the target
            database table. </p>
        <p>The <codeph>SEGMENT REJECT LIMIT</codeph> clause allows you to isolate format errors in
            external table data and to continue loading correctly formatted rows. Use
                <codeph>SEGMENT REJECT LIMIT </codeph>to set an error threshold, specifying the
            reject limit <codeph>count</codeph> as number of <codeph>ROWS</codeph> (the default) or
            as a <codeph>PERCENT</codeph> of total rows (1-100).</p>
        <p>The entire external table operation is aborted, and no rows are processed, if the number
            of error rows reaches the <codeph>SEGMENT REJECT LIMIT</codeph>. The limit of error rows
            is per-segment, not per entire operation. The operation processes all good rows, and it
            discards and optionally logs formatting errors for erroneous rows, if the number of
            error rows does not reach the <codeph>SEGMENT REJECT
                LIMIT</codeph>.</p>
        <p>The <codeph>LOG ERRORS</codeph> clause allows you to keep error rows for further
            examination. For information about the <codeph>LOG ERRORS</codeph> clause, see the
                <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> command in the <cite>Greenplum Database
                Reference Guide</cite>.</p>
        <p>When you set <codeph>SEGMENT REJECT LIMIT</codeph>, Greenplum scans the external data in
            single row error isolation mode. Single row error isolation mode applies to external
            data rows with format errors such as extra or missing attributes, attributes of a wrong
            data type, or invalid client encoding sequences. Greenplum does not check constraint
            errors, but you can filter constraint errors by limiting the <codeph>SELECT</codeph>
            from an external table at runtime. For example, to eliminate duplicate key errors:</p>
        <codeblock>=# INSERT INTO table_with_pkeys 
    SELECT DISTINCT * FROM external_table;
</codeblock>
        <note>When loading data with the <codeph>COPY</codeph> command or an
            external table, the value of the server configuration parameter
                <codeph>gp_initial_bad_row_limit</codeph> limits the initial number of rows that are
            processed that are not formatted properly. The default is to stop processing if the
            first 1000 rows contain formatting errors. See the <cite>Greenplum Database Reference
                Guide</cite> for information about the parameter.</note>
    </body>
</topic>
