<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic66">
    <title>Optimizing Data Load and Query Performance</title>
    <body>
        <p>Use the following tips to help optimize your data load and subsequent query
            performance.</p>
        <ul>
            <li id="du218161">Drop indexes before loading data into existing tables. <p>Creating an
                    index on pre-existing data is faster than updating it incrementally as each row
                    is loaded. You can temporarily increase the
                        <codeph>maintenance_work_mem</codeph> server configuration parameter to help
                    speed up <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph> commands, though load performance is
                    affected. Drop and recreate indexes only when there are no active users on the
                    system. </p></li>
            <li id="du218152">Create indexes last when loading data into new tables. Create the
                table, load the data, and create any required indexes. </li>
            <li id="du168719">Run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> after loading data. If you significantly
                altered the data in a table, run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> or <codeph>VACUUM
                    ANALYZE</codeph> to update table statistics for the query optimizer. Current
                statistics ensure that the optimizer makes the best decisions during query planning
                and avoids poor performance due to inaccurate or nonexistent statistics.</li>
            <li id="du168720">Run <codeph>VACUUM</codeph> after load errors. If the load operation
                does not run in single row error isolation mode, the operation stops at the first
                error. The target table contains the rows loaded before the error occurred. You
                cannot access these rows, but they occupy disk space. Use the
                    <codeph>VACUUM</codeph> command to recover the wasted space.</li>
        </ul>
    </body>
</topic>
