<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic65">
    <title>Running COPY in Single Row Error Isolation Mode</title>
    <body>
        <p>By default, <codeph>COPY</codeph> stops an operation at the first error: if the data
            contains an error, the operation fails and no data loads. If you run <codeph>COPY
                FROM</codeph> in <i>single row error isolation mode</i>, Greenplum skips rows that
            contain format errors and loads properly formatted rows. Single row error isolation mode
            applies only to rows in the input file that contain format errors. If the data contains
            a constraint error such as violation of a <codeph>NOT NULL</codeph>,
                <codeph>CHECK</codeph>, or <codeph>UNIQUE</codeph> constraint, the operation fails
            and no data loads.</p>
        <p>Specifying <codeph>SEGMENT REJECT LIMIT</codeph> runs the <codeph>COPY</codeph> operation
            in single row error isolation mode. Specify the acceptable number of error rows on each
            segment, after which the entire <codeph>COPY FROM</codeph> operation fails and no rows
            load. The error row count is for each Greenplum Database segment, not for the entire
            load operation. </p>
        <p>If the <codeph>COPY</codeph> operation does not reach the error limit, Greenplum loads
            all correctly-formatted rows and discards the error rows. Use the <codeph>LOG
                ERRORS</codeph> clause to capture data formatting errors internally in Greenplum
            Database. For example:</p>
        <example>
            <codeblock>=&gt; COPY country FROM '/data/gpdb/country_data' 
   WITH DELIMITER '|' LOG ERRORS
   SEGMENT REJECT LIMIT 10 ROWS;</codeblock>
        </example>
        <p>See <xref href="g-viewing-bad-rows-in-the-error-table-or-error-log.xml#topic58"/> for
            information about investigating error rows. </p>
    </body>
</topic>
