<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic18">
    <title>Troubleshooting gpfdist</title>
    <body>
        <p>The segments access <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> at runtime. Ensure that the Greenplum segment hosts have network access to
                <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>. <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> is a web server: test
            connectivity by running the following command from each host in the Greenplum array (segments and master):</p>
        <p>
            <codeblock>$ wget http://<i>gpfdist_hostname</i>:<i>port</i>/<i>filename</i>
         </codeblock>
        </p>
        <p>The <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> definition must have the correct host name,
            port, and file names for <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>. Specify file names and paths
            relative to the directory from which <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> serves files (the
            directory path specified when <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> started). See <xref
                href="g-creating-external-tables---examples.xml#topic44"/>.</p>
        <p>If you start <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> on your system and IPv6 networking is disabled,
                <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> displays this warning message when testing for an IPv6
            port.</p>
        <codeblock>[WRN gpfdist.c:2050] Creating the socket failed
</codeblock>
        <p>If the corresponding IPv4 port is available, <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> uses that port
            and the warning for IPv6 port can be ignored. To see information about the ports that
                <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> tests, use the <codeph>-V</codeph> option.</p>
        <p>For information about IPv6 and IPv4 networking, see your operating system
            documentation.</p>
        <p>When reading or writing data with the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> or
                <codeph>gfdists</codeph> protocol, the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> utility rejects HTTP
            requests that do not include <codeph>X-GP-PROTO</codeph> in the request header. If
                <codeph>X-GP-PROTO</codeph> is not detected in the header request
                <codeph>gpfist</codeph> returns a 400 error in the status line of the HTTP response
            header: <codeph>400 invalid request (no gp-proto)</codeph>.</p>
        <p>Greenplum Database includes <codeph>X-GP-PROTO</codeph> in the HTTP request header to
            indicate that the request is from Greenplum Database. </p>
    </body>
</topic>
