<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic43">
   <title>Using a Custom Protocol</title>
   <body>
      <p>Greenplum Database provides protocols such as <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>,
            <codeph>http</codeph>, and <codeph>file</codeph> for accessing data over a network, or
         you can author a custom protocol. You can use the standard data formats,
            <codeph>TEXT</codeph> and <codeph>CSV</codeph>, or a custom data format with custom
         protocols.</p>
      <p>You can create a custom protocol whenever the available built-in protocols do not suffice
         for a particular need. For example, you could connect Greenplum Database in parallel to another
         system directly, and stream data from one to the other without the need to materialize the
         data on disk or use an intermediate process such as <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>. </p>
      <ol>
         <li id="du226058">Author the send, receive, and (optionally) validator functions in C, with
            a predefined API. These functions are compiled and registered with the Greenplum
            Database. For an example custom protocol, see <xref
               href="g-example-custom-data-access-protocol.xml#topic103"/>. </li>
         <li id="du226065">After writing and compiling the read and write functions into a shared
            object (.so), declare a database function that points to the .so file and function
            names. <p>The following examples use the compiled import and export
               code.</p><codeblock>CREATE FUNCTION myread() RETURNS integer
as '$libdir/gpextprotocol.so', 'myprot_import'
LANGUAGE C STABLE;
CREATE FUNCTION mywrite() RETURNS integer
as '$libdir/gpextprotocol.so', 'myprot_export'
LANGUAGE C STABLE;
</codeblock><p>The
               format of the optional validator function is:</p><p>
               <codeblock>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION myvalidate() RETURNS void 
AS '$libdir/gpextprotocol.so', 'myprot_validate' 
LANGUAGE C STABLE; 
</codeblock>
            </p>
         </li>
         <li id="du226078">Create a protocol that accesses these functions.
               <codeph>Validatorfunc</codeph> is
            optional.<codeblock>CREATE TRUSTED PROTOCOL myprot(
writefunc='mywrite',
readfunc='myread', 
validatorfunc='myvalidate');</codeblock>
         </li>
         <li id="du226083">Grant access to any other users, as
            necessary.<codeblock>GRANT ALL ON PROTOCOL myprot TO otheruser;
</codeblock>
         </li>
         <li id="du226085">Use the protocol in readable or writable external tables.<p>
               <codeblock>CREATE WRITABLE EXTERNAL TABLE ext_sales(LIKE sales)
LOCATION ('myprot://&lt;meta&gt;/&lt;meta&gt;/…')
FORMAT 'TEXT';
CREATE READABLE EXTERNAL TABLE ext_sales(LIKE sales)
LOCATION('myprot://&lt;meta&gt;/&lt;meta&gt;/…')
FORMAT 'TEXT';
</codeblock>
            </p>
         </li>
      </ol>
      <p>Declare custom protocols with the SQL command <codeph>CREATE TRUSTED PROTOCOL</codeph>,
         then use the <codeph>GRANT</codeph> command to grant access to your users. For example:</p>
      <ul>
         <li id="du201414">Allow a user to create a readable external table with a trusted
            protocol<codeblock>GRANT SELECT ON PROTOCOL <i>&lt;protocol name&gt;</i> TO <i>&lt;user name&gt;</i>;</codeblock>
         </li>
         <li id="du201461">Allow a user to create a writable external table with a trusted
            protocol<codeblock>GRANT INSERT ON PROTOCOL <i>&lt;protocol name&gt;</i> TO <i>&lt;user name&gt;</i>;</codeblock>
         </li>
         <li id="du201474">Allow a user to create readable and writable external tables with a
            trusted
            protocol<codeblock>GRANT ALL ON PROTOCOL <i>&lt;protocol name&gt;</i> TO <i>&lt;user name&gt;</i>;</codeblock>
         </li>
      </ul>
   </body>
</topic>
