<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic75">
   <title>Transforming External Data with gpfdist and gpload</title>
   <shortdesc>The <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> parallel file server allows you to set up transformations
      that enable Greenplum Database external tables to read and write files in formats that are not
      supported with the <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> command's <codeph>FORMAT</codeph>
      clause. An <i>input</i> transformation reads a file in the foreign data format and outputs
      rows to <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> in the CSV or other text format specified in the external
      table's <codeph>FORMAT</codeph> clause. An <i>output</i> transformation receives rows from
         <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> in text format and converts them to the foreign data
      format.</shortdesc>
   <body>
      <p>This topic describes the tasks to set up data transformations that work with
            <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> to read or write external data files with formats that
         Greenplum Database does not support. </p>
      <ul id="ul_xlm_13m_pbb">
         <li><xref href="#topic_mdl_thm_pbb" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic_el5_k12_pbb" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic77" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic78" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic80" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic83" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic91" format="dita"/></li>
      </ul>
   </body>
   <topic id="topic_mdl_thm_pbb">
      <title>About gpfdist Transformations</title>
      <body>
         <p>To set up a transformation for a data format, you provide an executable command that
               <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> can call with the name of the file containing data. For
            example, you could write a shell script that runs an XSLT transformation on an XML file
            to output rows with columns delimited with a vertical bar (<codeph>|</codeph>) character
            and rows delimited with linefeeds. </p>
         <p>Transformations are configured in a YAML-formatted configuration file passed to
               <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> on the command line. </p>
         <p>If you want to load the external data into a table in the Greenplum database, you can
            use the <codeph>gpload</codeph> utility to automate the tasks to create an external
            table, run <codeph>gpfdist</codeph>, and load the transformed data into the database
            table.</p>
         <p>Accessing data in external XML files from within the database is a common example
            requiring transformation. The following diagram shows <i>gpfdist</i> performing a
            transformation on XML files on an ETL server.</p>
         <fig id="du185408">
            <title>External Tables using XML Transformations</title>
            <image href="../../graphics/ext-tables-xml.png" placement="break" id="image_xbp_whm_pbb"/>
         </fig>
         <p>Following are the high-level steps to set up a <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> transformation
            for external data files. The process is illustrated with an XML example. </p>
         <ol id="ol_d4f_4wf_pbb">
            <li><xref href="#topic_el5_k12_pbb" format="dita">Determine the transformation
                  schema</xref>.</li>
            <li><xref href="#topic77" format="dita">Write a transformation</xref>.</li>
            <li><xref href="#topic78" format="dita">Write the gpfdist configuration
               file</xref>.</li>
            <li><xref href="#topic80" format="dita">Transfer the data</xref>.</li>
         </ol>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic_el5_k12_pbb">
      <title>Determine the Transformation Schema</title>
      <body>
         <p>To prepare for the transformation project:</p>
         <ol id="ol_fl5_k12_pbb">
            <li> Determine the goal of the project, such as indexing data, analyzing data, combining
               data, and so on. </li>
            <li> Examine the source files and note the file structure and element names.</li>
            <li> Choose the elements to import and decide if any other limits are appropriate.</li>
         </ol>
         <p>For example, the following XML file, <i>prices.xml</i>, is a simple XML file that
            contains price records. Each price record contains two fields: an item number and a
            price.</p>
         <codeblock>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" ?&gt;
&lt;prices&gt;
  &lt;pricerecord&gt;
    &lt;itemnumber&gt;708421&lt;/itemnumber&gt;
    &lt;price&gt;19.99&lt;/price&gt;
  &lt;/pricerecord&gt;
  &lt;pricerecord&gt;
    &lt;itemnumber&gt;708466&lt;/itemnumber&gt;
    &lt;price&gt;59.25&lt;/price&gt;
  &lt;/pricerecord&gt;
  &lt;pricerecord&gt;
    &lt;itemnumber&gt;711121&lt;/itemnumber&gt;
    &lt;price&gt;24.99&lt;/price&gt;
  &lt;/pricerecord&gt;
&lt;/prices&gt;
</codeblock>
         <p>The goal of this transformation is to import all the data into a Greenplum Database
            readable external table with an integer <codeph>itemnumber</codeph> column and a decimal
               <codeph>price</codeph> column.</p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic77">
      <title>Write a Transformation</title>
      <body>
         <p>The transformation specifies what to extract from the data. You can use any authoring
            environment and language appropriate for your project. For XML transformations choose
            from technologies such as XSLT, Joost (STX), Java, Python, or Perl, based on the goals
            and scope of the project.</p>
         <p>In the price example, the next step is to transform the XML data into a two-column
            delimited text format.</p>
         <p>
            <codeblock>708421|19.99
708466|59.25
711121|24.99
</codeblock>
         </p>
         <p>The following STX transform, called <i>input_transform.stx</i>, performs the data
            transformation.</p>
         <codeblock>&lt;?xml version="1.0"?&gt;
&lt;stx:transform version="1.0"
   xmlns:stx="http://stx.sourceforge.net/2002/ns"
   pass-through="none"&gt;
  &lt;!-- declare variables --&gt;
  &lt;stx:variable name="itemnumber"/&gt;
  &lt;stx:variable name="price"/&gt;
  &lt;!-- match and output prices as columns delimited by | --&gt;
  &lt;stx:template match="/prices/pricerecord"&gt;
    &lt;stx:process-children/&gt;
    &lt;stx:value-of select="$itemnumber"/&gt;    
&lt;stx:text&gt;|&lt;/stx:text&gt;
    &lt;stx:value-of select="$price"/&gt;      &lt;stx:text&gt;
&lt;/stx:text&gt;
  &lt;/stx:template&gt;
  &lt;stx:template match="itemnumber"&gt;
    &lt;stx:assign name="itemnumber" select="."/&gt;
  &lt;/stx:template&gt;
  &lt;stx:template match="price"&gt;
    &lt;stx:assign name="price" select="."/&gt;
  &lt;/stx:template&gt;
&lt;/stx:transform&gt;
</codeblock>
         <p>This STX transform declares two temporary variables, <codeph>itemnumber</codeph> and
               <codeph>price</codeph>, and the following rules. </p>
         <ol id="ol_u5s_l12_pbb">
            <li id="du186530">When an element that satisfies the XPath expression
                  <codeph>/prices/pricerecord</codeph> is found, examine the child elements and
               generate output that contains the value of the <codeph>itemnumber</codeph> variable,
               a <codeph>|</codeph> character, the value of the price variable, and a newline.</li>
            <li id="du186531">When an <codeph>&lt;itemnumber&gt;</codeph> element is found, store
               the content of that element in the variable <codeph>itemnumber</codeph>.</li>
            <li id="du186677">When a &lt;price&gt; element is found, store the content of that
               element in the variable <codeph>price</codeph>.</li>
         </ol>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic78">
      <title>Write the gpfdist Configuration File</title>
      <body>
         <p>The <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration is specified as a YAML 1.1 document. It
            contains rules that <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> uses to select a transformation to apply
            when loading or extracting data. </p>
         <p>This example <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration contains the following items that
            are required for the <i>prices.xml</i> transformation scenario:</p>
         <ul id="ul_lct_m12_pbb">
            <li id="du219363">the <codeph>config.yaml</codeph> file defining
                  <codeph>TRANSFORMATIONS</codeph>
            </li>
            <li id="du219364">the <codeph>input_transform.sh</codeph> wrapper script, referenced in
               the <codeph>config.yaml</codeph> file</li>
            <li id="du219365">the <codeph>input_transform.stx</codeph> joost transformation, called
               from <codeph>input_transform.sh</codeph></li>
         </ul>
         <p>Aside from the ordinary YAML rules, such as starting the document with three dashes
               (<codeph>---</codeph>), a <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration must conform to
            the following restrictions:</p>
         <ol id="ol_mct_m12_pbb">
            <li id="du186770">A <codeph>VERSION</codeph> setting must be present with the value
                  <codeph>1.0.0.1</codeph>.</li>
            <li id="du186771">A <codeph>TRANSFORMATIONS</codeph> setting must be present and contain
               one or more mappings.</li>
            <li id="du186772">Each mapping in the <codeph>TRANSFORMATION</codeph> must contain:<ul
                  id="ul_ass_j31_34">
                  <li id="du186773">a <codeph>TYPE</codeph> with the value 'input' or 'output'</li>
                  <li id="du186774">a <codeph>COMMAND</codeph> indicating how the transformation is
                     run.</li>
               </ul>
            </li>
            <li id="du186775">Each mapping in the <codeph>TRANSFORMATION</codeph> can contain
               optional <codeph>CONTENT</codeph>, <codeph>SAFE</codeph>, and <codeph>STDERR</codeph>
               settings.</li>
         </ol>
         <p>The following <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration, called
               <codeph>config.yaml</codeph>, applies to the prices example. The initial indentation
            on each line is significant and reflects the hierarchical nature of the specification.
            The transformation name <codeph>prices_input</codeph> in the following example will be
            referenced later when creating the table in SQL.</p>
         <codeblock>---
VERSION: 1.0.0.1
TRANSFORMATIONS:
  prices_input:
    TYPE:     input
    COMMAND:  /bin/bash input_transform.sh %filename%
</codeblock>
         <p>The <codeph>COMMAND</codeph> setting uses a wrapper script called
               <codeph>input_transform.sh</codeph> with a <codeph>%filename%</codeph> placeholder.
            When <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> runs the <codeph>prices_input</codeph> transform, it
            invokes <codeph>input_transform.sh</codeph> with <codeph>/bin/bash</codeph> and replaces
            the <codeph>%filename%</codeph> placeholder with the path to the input file to
            transform. The wrapper script called <codeph>input_transform.sh</codeph> contains the
            logic to invoke the STX transformation and return the output.</p>
         <p>If Joost is used, the Joost STX engine must be installed.</p>
         <codeblock>#!/bin/bash
# input_transform.sh - sample input transformation, 
# demonstrating use of Java and Joost STX to convert XML into
# text to load into Greenplum Database.
# java arguments:
#   -jar joost.jar         joost STX engine
#   -nodecl                  don't generate a &lt;?xml?&gt; declaration
#   $1                        filename to process
#   input_transform.stx    the STX transformation
#
# the AWK step eliminates a blank line joost emits at the end
java \
    -jar joost.jar \
    -nodecl \
    $1 \
    input_transform.stx \
 | awk 'NF&gt;0
</codeblock>
         <p>The <codeph>input_transform.sh</codeph> file uses the Joost STX engine with the AWK
            interpreter. The following diagram shows the process flow as <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>
            runs the transformation.</p>
         <image href="../../graphics/02-pipeline.png" placement="break" width="462px" height="190px"
            id="image_nct_m12_pbb"/>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic80">
      <title>Transfer the Data</title>
      <body>
         <p>Create the target database tables with SQL statements based on the appropriate
            schema.</p>
         <p>There are no special requirements for Greenplum Database tables that hold loaded data.
            In the prices example, the following command creates the <codeph>prices</codeph> table,
            where the data is to be loaded.</p>
         <codeblock>CREATE TABLE prices (
  itemnumber integer,       
  price       decimal        
) 
DISTRIBUTED BY (itemnumber);
</codeblock>
         <p>Next, use one of the following approaches to transform the data with
               <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>.</p>
         <ul id="ul_jfr_h32_pbb">
            <li id="du224442">
               <codeph>gpload</codeph> supports only input transformations, but in many cases is
               easier to implement. </li>
            <li id="du224443">
               <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> with <codeph>INSERT INTO SELECT FROM</codeph> supports both
               input and output transformations, but exposes details that <codeph>gpload</codeph>
               automates for you.</li>
         </ul>
      </body>
      <topic id="topic81">
         <title>Transforming with gpload</title>
         <body>
            <p>The Greenplum Database <codeph>gpload</codeph> utility orchestrates a data load
               operation using the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> parallel file server and a
               YAML-formatted configuration file. <codeph>gpload</codeph> automates these tasks:</p>
            <ul id="ul_rt1_jnk_pbb">
               <li>Creates a readable external table in the database.</li>
               <li>Starts <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> instances with the configuration file that
                  contains the transformation. </li>
               <li>Runs <codeph>INSERT INTO <varname>table_name</varname> SELECT FROM
                        <varname>external_table</varname></codeph> to load the data.</li>
               <li>Removes the external table definition.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>Transforming data with <codeph>gpload</codeph> requires that the settings
                  <codeph>TRANSFORM</codeph> and <codeph>TRANSFORM_CONFIG</codeph> appear in the
                  <codeph>INPUT</codeph> section of the <codeph>gpload</codeph> control file.</p>
            <p>For more information about the syntax and placement of these settings in the
                  <codeph>gpload</codeph> control file, see the <i>Greenplum Database Reference
                  Guide</i>.</p>
            <ul id="ul_sy3_l32_pbb">
               <li id="du187470">
                  <codeph>TRANSFORM_CONFIG</codeph> specifies the name of the
                     <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration file.</li>
               <li id="du200069">The <codeph>TRANSFORM</codeph> setting indicates the name of the
                  transformation that is described in the file named in
                     <codeph>TRANSFORM_CONFIG</codeph>.</li>
            </ul>
            <codeblock>---
VERSION: 1.0.0.1
DATABASE: ops
USER: gpadmin
GPLOAD:
  INPUT:
    - TRANSFORM_CONFIG: config.yaml
    - TRANSFORM: prices_input
    - SOURCE:
        FILE: prices.xml</codeblock>
            <p>The transformation name must appear in two places: in the <codeph>TRANSFORM</codeph>
               setting of the <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration file and in the
                  <codeph>TRANSFORMATIONS</codeph> section of the file named in the
                  <codeph>TRANSFORM_CONFIG</codeph> section.</p>
            <p>In the <codeph>gpload</codeph> control file, the optional parameter
                  <codeph>MAX_LINE_LENGTH</codeph> specifies the maximum length of a line in the XML
               transformation data that is passed to <codeph>gpload</codeph>.</p>
            <p>The following diagram shows the relationships between the <codeph>gpload</codeph>
               control file, the <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration file, and the XML data
               file.</p>
            <image href="../../graphics/03-gpload-files.jpg" placement="break" width="415px"
               height="258px" id="image_ty3_l32_pbb"/>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="topic82">
         <title>Transforming with gpfdist and INSERT INTO SELECT FROM</title>
         <body>
            <p>With this load method, you perform each of the tasks that <codeph>gpload</codeph>
               automates. You start <codeph>gpfdist</codeph>, create an external table, load the
               data, and clean up by dropping the table and stopping <codeph>gpfdist</codeph>.</p>
            <p>Specify the transformation in the <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> definition's
                  <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause. For example, the transform is shown in bold in
               the following command. (Run <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> first, using the command
                  <codeph>gpfdist -c config.yaml</codeph>).</p>
            <codeblock>CREATE READABLE EXTERNAL TABLE prices_readable (LIKE prices)
   LOCATION ('gpfdist://hostname:8080/prices.xml<b>#transform=prices_input</b>')
   FORMAT 'TEXT' (DELIMITER '|')
   LOG ERRORS SEGMENT REJECT LIMIT 10;
</codeblock>
            <p>In the command above, change <codeph>hostname</codeph> to your hostname.
                  <codeph>prices_input</codeph> comes from the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph>
               configuration file.</p>
            <p>The following query then loads the data into the <codeph>prices</codeph> table.</p>
            <codeblock>INSERT INTO prices SELECT * FROM prices_readable;</codeblock>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="topic83">
         <title>Configuration File Format</title>
         <body>
            <p>The <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration file uses the YAML 1.1 document format
               and implements a schema for defining the transformation parameters. The configuration
               file must be a valid YAML document.</p>
            <p>The <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> program processes the document in order and uses
               indentation (spaces) to determine the document hierarchy and relationships of the
               sections to one another. The use of white space is significant. Do not use white
               space for formatting and do not use tabs.</p>
            <p>The following is the basic structure of a configuration file.</p>
            <codeblock>---
VERSION:   1.0.0.1
TRANSFORMATIONS: 
  transformation_name1:
    TYPE:      input | output
    COMMAND:   command
    CONTENT:   data | paths
    SAFE:      posix-regex
    STDERR:    server | console
  transformation_name2:
    TYPE:      input | output
    COMMAND:   command 
...</codeblock>
            <parml>
               <plentry id="p_version">
                  <pt>VERSION</pt>
                  <pd>Required. The version of the <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> configuration file
                     schema. The current version is 1.0.0.1.</pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry id="p_transformations">
                  <pt>TRANSFORMATIONS</pt>
                  <pd>Required. Begins the transformation specification section. A configuration
                     file must have at least one transformation. When <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>
                     receives a transformation request, it looks in this section for an entry with
                     the matching transformation name. </pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry id="p_type">
                  <pt>TYPE</pt>
                  <pd>Required. Specifies the direction of transformation. Values are
                        <codeph>input</codeph> or <codeph>output</codeph>. <ul id="ul_f3p_j3q_34">
                        <li id="du198814">
                           <codeph>input</codeph>: <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> treats the standard
                           output of the transformation process as a stream of records to load into
                           Greenplum Database.</li>
                        <li id="du198815">
                           <codeph>output</codeph>
                           <ph>: </ph>
                           <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> treats the standard input of the
                           transformation process as a stream of records from Greenplum Database to
                           transform and write to the appropriate output.</li>
                     </ul>
                  </pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry id="p_command">
                  <pt>COMMAND</pt>
                  <pd>
                     <p>Required. Specifies the command <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> will execute to
                        perform the transformation. </p>
                     <p>For input transformations, <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> invokes the command
                        specified in the <codeph>CONTENT</codeph> setting. The command is expected
                        to open the underlying file(s) as appropriate and produce one line of
                           <codeph>TEXT</codeph> for each row to load into Greenplum Database. The
                        input transform determines whether the entire content should be converted to
                        one row or to multiple rows.</p>
                     <p>For output transformations, <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> invokes this command
                        as specified in the <codeph>CONTENT</codeph> setting. The output command is
                        expected to open and write to the underlying file(s) as appropriate. The
                        output transformation determines the final placement of the converted
                        output.</p>
                  </pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry id="p_content">
                  <pt>CONTENT</pt>
                  <pd>
                     <p>Optional. The values are <codeph>data</codeph> and <codeph>paths</codeph>.
                        The default value is <codeph>data</codeph>.</p>
                     <ul id="ul_wzg_43q_34">
                        <li id="du219653">When <codeph>CONTENT</codeph> specifies
                              <codeph>data</codeph>, the text <codeph>%filename%</codeph> in the
                              <codeph>COMMAND</codeph> section is replaced by the path to the file
                           to read or write. </li>
                        <li id="du199214">When <codeph>CONTENT</codeph> specifies
                              <codeph>paths</codeph>, the text <codeph>%filename%</codeph> in the
                              <codeph>COMMAND</codeph> section is replaced by the path to the
                           temporary file that contains the list of files to read or write. </li>
                     </ul>
                     <p>The following is an example of a <codeph>COMMAND</codeph> section showing
                        the text <codeph>%filename%</codeph> that is replaced.</p>
                     <p>
                        <codeblock>COMMAND: /bin/bash input_transform.sh %filename%</codeblock>
                     </p>
                  </pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry id="p_safe">
                  <pt>SAFE</pt>
                  <pd>
                     <p>Optional. A <codeph>POSIX</codeph> regular expression that the paths must
                        match to be passed to the transformation. Specify <codeph>SAFE</codeph> when
                        there is a concern about injection or improper interpretation of paths
                        passed to the command. The default is no restriction on paths.</p>
                  </pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry id="p_stderr">
                  <pt>STDERR</pt>
                  <pd>
                     <p>Optional. The values are <codeph>server</codeph> and
                           <codeph>console</codeph>.</p>
                     <p>This setting specifies how to handle standard error output from the
                        transformation. The default, <codeph>server</codeph>, specifies that
                           <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> will capture the standard error output from
                        the transformation in a temporary file and send the first 8k of that file to
                        Greenplum Database as an error message. The error message will appear as an
                        SQL error. <codeph>Console</codeph> specifies that
                           <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> does not redirect or transmit the standard
                        error output from the transformation. </p>
                  </pd>
               </plentry>
            </parml>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic91">
      <title>XML Transformation Examples</title>
      <body>
         <p>The following examples demonstrate the complete process for different types of XML data
            and STX transformations. Files and detailed instructions associated with these examples
            are in the GitHub repo <codeph>github.com://greenplum-db/gpdb</codeph> in the
                  <codeph><xref
                  href="https://github.com/greenplum-db/gpdb/blob/master/gpMgmt/demo/gpfdist_transform"
                  format="html" scope="external">gpMgmt/demo/gpfdist_transform</xref></codeph>
            directory. Read the README file in the <i>Before You Begin</i> section before you run
            the examples. The README file explains how to download the example data file used in the
            examples.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="topic32">
         <title>Command-based External Web Tables</title>
         <body>
            <p>The output of a shell command or script defines command-based web table data. Specify
               the command in the <codeph>EXECUTE</codeph> clause of <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL WEB
                  TABLE</codeph>. The data is current as of the time the command runs. The
                  <codeph>EXECUTE</codeph> clause runs the shell command or script on the specified
               master, and/or segment host or hosts. The command or script must reside on the hosts
               corresponding to the host(s) defined in the <codeph>EXECUTE</codeph> clause.</p>
            <p>By default, the command is run on segment hosts when active segments have output rows
               to process. For example, if each segment host runs four primary segment instances
               that have output rows to process, the command runs four times per segment host. You
               can optionally limit the number of segment instances that execute the web table
               command. All segments included in the web table definition in the <codeph>ON</codeph>
               clause run the command in parallel.</p>
            <p>The command that you specify in the external table definition executes from the
               database and cannot access environment variables from <codeph>.bashrc</codeph> or
                  <codeph>.profile</codeph>. Set environment variables in the
                  <codeph>EXECUTE</codeph> clause. For example:</p>
            <p>
               <codeblock>=# CREATE EXTERNAL WEB TABLE output (output text)
    EXECUTE 'PATH=/home/gpadmin/programs; export PATH; myprogram.sh' 
    FORMAT 'TEXT';
</codeblock>
            </p>
            <p>Scripts must be executable by the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user and reside in the
               same location on the master or segment hosts.</p>
            <p>The following command defines a web table that runs a script. The script runs on each
               segment host where a segment has output rows to process. </p>
            <p>
               <codeblock>=# CREATE EXTERNAL WEB TABLE log_output 
    (linenum int, message text) 
    EXECUTE '/var/load_scripts/get_log_data.sh' ON HOST 
    FORMAT 'TEXT' (DELIMITER '|');
</codeblock>
            </p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="topic93">
         <title>IRS MeF XML Files (In demo Directory)</title>
         <body>
            <p>This example demonstrates loading a sample IRS Modernized eFile tax return using a
               Joost STX transformation. The data is in the form of a complex XML file.</p>
            <p>The U.S. Internal Revenue Service (IRS) made a significant commitment to XML and
               specifies its use in its Modernized e-File (MeF) system. In MeF, each tax return is
               an XML document with a deep hierarchical structure that closely reflects the
               particular form of the underlying tax code. </p>
            <p>XML, XML Schema and stylesheets play a role in their data representation and business
               workflow. The actual XML data is extracted from a ZIP file attached to a MIME
               "transmission file" message. For more information about MeF, see <xref
                  href="https://www.irs.gov/uac/modernized-e-file-overview" scope="external"
                  format="html">Modernized e-File (Overview)</xref> on the IRS web site.</p>
            <p>The sample XML document, <i>RET990EZ_2006.xml</i>, is about 350KB in size with two
               elements:</p>
            <ul id="ul_egs_y42_pbb">
               <li id="du202262">ReturnHeader</li>
               <li id="du202263">ReturnData</li>
            </ul>
            <p>The &lt;ReturnHeader&gt; element contains general details about the tax return such
               as the taxpayer's name, the tax year of the return, and the preparer. The
               &lt;ReturnData&gt; element contains multiple sections with specific details about the
               tax return and associated schedules. </p>
            <p>The following is an abridged sample of the XML file.</p>
            <codeblock>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt; 
&lt;Return returnVersion="2006v2.0"
   xmlns="https://www.irs.gov/efile" 
   xmlns:efile="https://www.irs.gov/efile"
   xsi:schemaLocation="https://www.irs.gov/efile"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"&gt; 
   &lt;ReturnHeader binaryAttachmentCount="1"&gt;
     &lt;ReturnId&gt;AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA&lt;/ReturnId&gt;
     &lt;Timestamp&gt;1999-05-30T12:01:01+05:01&lt;/Timestamp&gt;
     &lt;ReturnType&gt;990EZ&lt;/ReturnType&gt;
     &lt;TaxPeriodBeginDate&gt;2005-01-01&lt;/TaxPeriodBeginDate&gt;
     &lt;TaxPeriodEndDate&gt;2005-12-31&lt;/TaxPeriodEndDate&gt;
     &lt;Filer&gt;
       &lt;EIN&gt;011248772&lt;/EIN&gt;
       ... more data ...
     &lt;/Filer&gt;
     &lt;Preparer&gt;
       &lt;Name&gt;Percy Polar&lt;/Name&gt;
       ... more data ...
     &lt;/Preparer&gt;
     &lt;TaxYear&gt;2005&lt;/TaxYear&gt;
   &lt;/ReturnHeader&gt;
   ... more data ..
</codeblock>
            <p>The goal is to import all the data into a Greenplum database. First, convert the XML
               document into text with newlines "escaped", with two columns:
                  <codeph>ReturnId</codeph> and a single column on the end for the entire MeF tax
               return. For example:</p>
            <p>
               <codeblock>AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA|&lt;Return returnVersion="2006v2.0"... 
</codeblock>
            </p>
            <p>Load the data into Greenplum Database.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="topic94">
         <title>WITSML™ Files (In demo Directory)</title>
         <body>
            <p>This example demonstrates loading sample data describing an oil rig using a Joost STX
               transformation. The data is in the form of a complex XML file downloaded from
               energistics.org.</p>
            <p>The Wellsite Information Transfer Standard Markup Language (WITSML™) is an oil
               industry initiative to provide open, non-proprietary, standard interfaces for
               technology and software to share information among oil companies, service companies,
               drilling contractors, application vendors, and regulatory agencies. For more
               information about WITSML™, see <xref href="http://www.energistics.org/"
                  scope="external" format="html">http://www.energistics.org/</xref>.</p>
            <p>The oil rig information consists of a top level <codeph>&lt;rigs&gt;</codeph> element
               with multiple child elements such as <codeph>&lt;documentInfo&gt;,
                  &lt;rig&gt;</codeph>, and so on. The following excerpt from the file shows the
               type of information in the <codeph>&lt;rig&gt;</codeph> tag.</p>
            <codeblock>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;?xml-stylesheet href="../stylesheets/rig.xsl" type="text/xsl" media="screen"?&gt;
&lt;rigs 
 xmlns="http://www.energistics.org/schemas/131" 
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.energistics.org/schemas/131 ../obj_rig.xsd" 
 version="1.3.1.1"&gt;
 &lt;documentInfo&gt;
 ... misc data ...
 &lt;/documentInfo&gt;
 &lt;rig uidWell="W-12" uidWellbore="B-01" uid="xr31"&gt;
     &lt;nameWell&gt;6507/7-A-42&lt;/nameWell&gt;
     &lt;nameWellbore&gt;A-42&lt;/nameWellbore&gt;
     &lt;name&gt;Deep Drill #5&lt;/name&gt;
     &lt;owner&gt;Deep Drilling Co.&lt;/owner&gt;
     &lt;typeRig&gt;floater&lt;/typeRig&gt;
     &lt;manufacturer&gt;Fitsui Engineering&lt;/manufacturer&gt;
     &lt;yearEntService&gt;1980&lt;/yearEntService&gt;
     &lt;classRig&gt;ABS Class A1 M CSDU AMS ACCU&lt;/classRig&gt;
     &lt;approvals&gt;DNV&lt;/approvals&gt;
 ... more data ...</codeblock>
            <p>The goal is to import the information for this rig into Greenplum Database. </p>
            <p>The sample document, <i>rig.xml</i>, is about 11KB in size. The input does not
               contain tabs so the relevant information can be converted into records delimited with
               a pipe (|).</p>
            <p>
               <codeph>W-12|6507/7-A-42|xr31|Deep Drill #5|Deep Drilling Co.|John
                  Doe|John.Doe@example.com|</codeph>
            </p>
            <p>With the columns:</p>
            <ul id="ul_ids_bp2_pbb">
               <li>
                  <codeph>well_uid text</codeph>, -- e.g. W-12 </li>
               <li>
                  <codeph>well_name text</codeph>, -- e.g. 6507/7-A-42 </li>
               <li>
                  <codeph>rig_uid text</codeph>, -- e.g. xr31 </li>
               <li>
                  <codeph>rig_name text</codeph>, -- e.g. Deep Drill #5 </li>
               <li>
                  <codeph>rig_owner text</codeph>, -- e.g. Deep Drilling Co. </li>
               <li>
                  <codeph>rig_contact text</codeph>, -- e.g. John Doe </li>
               <li>
                  <codeph>rig_email text</codeph>, -- e.g. John.Doe@example.com </li>
               <li>
                  <codeph>doc xml</codeph>
               </li>
            </ul>
            <p>Then, load the data into Greenplum Database.</p>
         </body>
      </topic>
   </topic>
</topic>
