<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="io138244">Accessing the Database</title>
  <shortdesc>This topic describes the various client tools you can use to connect to Greenplum
    Database, and how to establish a database session.</shortdesc>
  <topic id="topic2" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="io140159">Establishing a Database Session</title>
    <shortdesc>Greenplum Database supports interactive client programs and connections from
      applications through PostgreSQL-compatible database connectivity libraries.</shortdesc>
    <body>
      <p>Users can connect to Greenplum Database using a PostgreSQL-compatible client program, such
        as <codeph>psql</codeph>. Users and administrators <i>always</i> connect to Greenplum
        Database through the <i>master</i>; the segments cannot accept client connections.</p>
      <p>In order to establish a connection to the Greenplum Database master, you will need to know
        the following connection information and configure your client program accordingly.</p>
      <table id="io140729">
        <title>Connection Parameters</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2*"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="1*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Connection Parameter</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Description</entry>
              <entry colname="col3">Environment Variable</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Application name</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">The application name that is connecting to the database. The
                default value, held in the <codeph>application_name</codeph> connection parameter is
                  <i>psql</i>.</entry>
              <entry colname="col3">
                <codeph>$PGAPPNAME</codeph>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Database name</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">The name of the database to which you want to connect. For a
                newly initialized system, use the <codeph>postgres</codeph> database to connect for
                the first time.</entry>
              <entry colname="col3">
                <codeph>$PGDATABASE</codeph>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Host name</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">The host name of the Greenplum Database master. The default host
                is the local host. </entry>
              <entry colname="col3">
                <codeph>$PGHOST</codeph>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Port</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">The port number that the Greenplum Database master instance is
                running on. The default is 5432.</entry>
              <entry colname="col3">
                <codeph>$PGPORT</codeph>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">User name</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">The database user (role) name to connect as. This is not
                necessarily the same as your OS user name. Check with your Greenplum administrator
                if you are not sure what you database user name is. Note that every Greenplum
                Database system has one superuser account that is created automatically at
                initialization time. This account has the same name as the OS name of the user who
                initialized the Greenplum system (typically <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>).</entry>
              <entry colname="col3">
                <codeph>$PGUSER</codeph>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic3" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="io140721">Supported Client Applications</title>
    <shortdesc>The PostgreSQL<codeph>psql</codeph> interactive client is included with Greenplum
      Database. Third party clients are also available.</shortdesc>
    <body>
      <p>Users can connect to Greenplum Database using various client applications:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="io141965">A number of <xref href="#topic4" type="topic" format="dita"/> are provided
          with your Greenplum installation. The <codeph>psql</codeph> client application provides an
          interactive command-line interface to Greenplum Database. </li>
        <li id="io155276"><xref href="#topic6" type="topic" format="dita"/> is an  updated version
          of the popular management tool pgAdmin. Since version 1.10.0, the pgAdmin client available
          from PostgreSQL Tools includes support for  some Greenplum-specific features. Installation
          packages are available for download from the <xref
            href="https://www.pgadmin.org/download/" scope="external" format="html"><ph>pgAdmin
              download site</ph></xref>.</li>
        <li id="io141985">Using standard <xref href="#topic12" type="topic" format="dita"/>, such as
          ODBC and JDBC, users can create their own client applications that interface to Greenplum
          Database. Because Greenplum Database is based on PostgreSQL, it uses the standard
          PostgreSQL database drivers.</li>
        <li id="io141996">Most <xref href="#topic13" type="topic" format="dita"/> that use standard
          database interfaces, such as ODBC and JDBC, can be configured to connect to Greenplum
          Database.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic4" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="io140725">Greenplum Database Client Applications</title>
      <body>
        <p>Greenplum Database comes installed with a number of client applications located in
            <codeph>$GPHOME/bin</codeph> of your Greenplum Database master host installation. The
          following are the most commonly used client applications:</p>
        <table id="io142026">
          <title>Commonly used client applications</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="110pt"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="266pt"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">Name</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">Usage</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">
                  <codeph>createdb</codeph>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="col2">create a new database</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">
                  <codeph>createlang</codeph>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="col2">define a new procedural language</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">
                  <codeph>createuser</codeph>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="col2">define a new database role</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">
                  <codeph>dropdb</codeph>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="col2">remove a database</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">
                  <codeph>droplang</codeph>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="col2">remove a procedural language</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">
                  <codeph>dropuser</codeph>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="col2">remove a role</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">
                  <codeph>psql</codeph>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="col2">PostgreSQL interactive terminal</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">
                  <codeph>reindexdb</codeph>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="col2">reindex a database</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">
                  <codeph>vacuumdb</codeph>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="col2">garbage-collect and analyze a database</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <p>When using these client applications, you must connect to a database through the
          Greenplum master instance. You will need to know the name of your target database, the
          host name and port number of the master, and what database user name to connect as. This
          information can be provided on the command-line using the options <codeph>-d</codeph>,
            <codeph>-h</codeph>, <codeph>-p</codeph>, and <codeph>-U</codeph> respectively. If an
          argument is found that does not belong to any option, it will be interpreted as the
          database name first.</p>
        <p>All of these options have default values which will be used if the option is not
          specified. The default host is the local host. The default port number is 5432. The
          default user name is your OS system user name, as is the default database name. Note that
          OS user names and Greenplum Database user names are not necessarily the same. </p>
        <p id="io141912">If the default values are not correct, you can set the environment
          variables <codeph>PGDATABASE</codeph>, <codeph>PGHOST</codeph>, <codeph>PGPORT</codeph>,
          and <codeph>PGUSER</codeph> to the appropriate values, or use a
            <codeph>psql</codeph><codeph>~/.pgpass</codeph> file to contain frequently-used
          passwords. For information about Greenplum Database environment variables, see the
            <i>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</i>. For information about psql, see the
            <i>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</i>.</p>
      </body>
      <topic id="topic5" xml:lang="en">
        <title id="io141913">Connecting with psql</title>
        <body>
          <p>Depending on the default values used or the environment variables you have set, the
            following examples show how to access a database via <codeph>psql</codeph>:</p>
          <p>
            <codeblock>$ psql -d gpdatabase -h master_host -p 5432 -U <codeph>gpadmin</codeph></codeblock>
            <codeblock>$ psql gpdatabase</codeblock>
            <codeblock>$ psql</codeblock>
          </p>
          <p>If a user-defined database has not yet been created, you can access the system by
            connecting to the <codeph>postgres</codeph> database. For
            example:<codeblock>$ psql postgres</codeblock></p>
          <p>After connecting to a database, <codeph>psql</codeph> provides a prompt with the name
            of the database to which <codeph>psql</codeph> is currently connected, followed by the
            string <codeph>=&gt;</codeph> (or <codeph>=#</codeph> if you are the database
            superuser). For example:</p>
          <p>
            <codeblock>gpdatabase=&gt;</codeblock>
          </p>
          <p>At the prompt, you may type in SQL commands. A SQL command must end with a
              <codeph>;</codeph> (semicolon) in order to be sent to the server and executed. For
            example:</p>
          <p>
            <codeblock>=&gt; SELECT * FROM mytable;</codeblock>
          </p>
          <p>See the <i>Greenplum Reference Guide</i> for information about using the
              <codeph>psql</codeph> client application and SQL commands and syntax.</p>
        </body>
      </topic>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic6" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="io140208">pgAdmin 4</title>
      <body>
        <p>If you prefer a graphic interface, use pgAdmin 4. This GUI client supports PostgreSQL
          databases with all standard pgAdmin 4 features, while adding support for some
          Greenplum-specific features. </p>
        <p>pgAdmin 4 supports the following Greenplum-specific features:</p>
        <ul id="ul_dc4_g15_3bb">
          <li>Viewing Greenplum table DDL.</li>
          <li id="io147522">Append-optimized tables, including compressed append-optimized tables.
              <note>Only limited functionality for Greenplum partitioned tables is available with
              pgAdmin 4.</note></li>
        </ul>
      </body>
      <topic id="topic7" xml:lang="en">
        <title>Installing pgAdmin 4</title>
        <body>
          <p>The installation package for pgAdmin 4 is available for download from the official
            pgAdmin 4 download site (<xref href="https://www.pgadmin.org" scope="external"
              format="html"/>). Installation instructions are included in the installation
            package.</p>
        </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="topic8" xml:lang="en">
        <title>Documentation for pgAdmin 4</title>
        <body>
          <p>For general help on the features of the pgAdmin graphical interface or PostgreSQL,
            select one of the entries from the <b>Help</b> dropdown menu.</p>
        </body>
      </topic>
      <topic id="topic9" xml:lang="en">
        <title>Viewing DDL Data with pgAdmin 4</title>
        <body>
          <p>This topic highlights a Greenplum Database task you can perform with pgAdmin 4: viewing
            Greenplum Database table DDL.</p>
        </body>
      </topic>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic12" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="io149542">Database Application Interfaces</title>
      <body>
        <p>You may want to develop your own client applications that interface to Greenplum
          Database. PostgreSQL provides a number of database drivers for the most commonly used
          database application programming interfaces (APIs), which can also be used with Greenplum
          Database. These drivers are not packaged with the Greenplum Database base distribution.
          Each driver is an independent PostgreSQL development project and must be downloaded,
          installed and configured to connect to Greenplum Database. The following drivers are
          available:</p>
        <table id="io140349">
          <title>Greenplum Database Interfaces</title>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="1*"/>
            <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="3*"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">API</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">PostgreSQL Driver</entry>
                <entry colname="col3">Download Link</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">ODBC</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">pgodbc</entry>
                <entry colname="col3">Available in the Greenplum Database Connectivity package,
                  which can be downloaded from <xref href="https://network.pivotal.io"
                    scope="external" format="html"><ph>Pivotal Network</ph></xref>.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">JDBC</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">pgjdbc</entry>
                <entry colname="col3">Available in the <i>Greenplum Database Connectivity</i>
                  package, which can be downloaded from <xref
                    href="https://network.pivotal.io" scope="external" format="html"
                      ><ph>Pivotal Network</ph></xref>.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">Perl DBI</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">pgperl</entry>
                <entry colname="col3">
                  <xref href="http://pgfoundry.org/projects/pgperl"
                    scope="external" format="html">http://pgfoundry.org/projects/pgperl</xref>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="col1">Python DBI</entry>
                <entry colname="col2">pygresql</entry>
                <entry colname="col3">
                  <xref href="http://www.pygresql.org/" scope="external" format="html"
                    >http://www.pygresql.org</xref>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <p>General instructions for accessing a Greenplum Database with an API are:</p>
        <ol>
          <li id="io140287">Download your programming language platform and respective API from the
            appropriate source. For example, you can get the Java development kit (JDK) and JDBC API
            from Sun.</li>
          <li id="io140288">Write your client application according to the API specifications. When
            programming your application, be aware of the SQL support in Greenplum Database so you
            do not include any unsupported SQL syntax. See the <i>Greenplum Database Reference
              Guide</i> for more information.</li>
        </ol>
        <p>Download the appropriate PostgreSQL driver and configure connectivity to your Greenplum
          Database master instance. Greenplum provides a client tools package that contains the
          supported database drivers for Greenplum Database. Download the client tools packagefrom
            <xref href="https://network.pivotal.io" scope="external" format="html"
              ><ph>Pivotal Network </ph></xref>and documentation from <xref
            href="http://gpdb.docs.pivotal.io" scope="external" format="html"><ph>Pivotal
              Documentation</ph></xref>. </p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic13" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="io140178">Third-Party Client Tools</title>
      <body>
        <p id="io140183">Most third-party extract-transform-load (ETL) and business intelligence
          (BI) tools use standard database interfaces, such as ODBC and JDBC, and can be configured
          to connect to Greenplum Database. Greenplum has worked with the following tools on
          previous customer engagements and is in the process of becoming officially certified</p>
        <ul>
          <li id="io142400">Business Objects</li>
          <li id="io142404">Microstrategy</li>
          <li id="io142405">Informatica Power Center</li>
          <li id="io142406">Microsoft SQL Server Integration Services (SSIS) and Reporting Services
            (SSRS)</li>
          <li id="io142412">Ascential Datastage</li>
          <li id="io142423">SAS</li>
          <li id="io142432">Cognos</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Greenplum Professional Services can assist users in configuring their chosen third-party
          tool for use with Greenplum Database.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic14" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="io140185">Troubleshooting Connection Problems</title>
    <body>
      <p id="io140978">A number of things can prevent a client application from successfully
        connecting to Greenplum Database. This topic explains some of the common causes of
        connection problems and how to correct them.</p>
      <table id="io140982">
        <title>Common connection problems</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="1*"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="4*"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Problem</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">Solution</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">No <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> entry for host or
                user</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">To enable Greenplum Database to accept remote client
                connections, you must configure your Greenplum Database master instance so that
                connections are allowed from the client hosts and database users that will be
                connecting to Greenplum Database. This is done by adding the appropriate entries to
                the <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> configuration file (located in the master
                instance's data directory). For more detailed information, see <xref
                  href="../client_auth.xml#topic2" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Greenplum Database is not running</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">If the Greenplum Database master instance is down, users will
                not be able to connect. You can verify that the Greenplum Database system is up by
                running the <codeph>gpstate</codeph> utility on the Greenplum master host.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Network problems<p>Interconnect timeouts</p></entry>
              <entry colname="col2">If users connect to the Greenplum master host from a remote
                client, network problems can prevent a connection (for example, DNS host name
                resolution problems, the host system is down, and so on.). To ensure that network
                problems are not the cause, connect to the Greenplum master host from the remote
                client host. For example: <codeph>ping <i>hostname</i></codeph>. <p id="io141723">If
                  the system cannot resolve the host names and IP addresses of the hosts involved in
                  Greenplum Database, queries and connections will fail. For some operations,
                  connections to the Greenplum Database master use <codeph>localhost</codeph> and
                  others use the actual host name, so you must be able to resolve both. If you
                  encounter this error, first make sure you can connect to each host in your
                  Greenplum Database array from the master host over the network. In the
                    <codeph>/etc/hosts</codeph> file of the master and all segments, make sure you
                  have the correct host names and IP addresses for all hosts involved in the
                  Greenplum Database array. The <codeph>127.0.0.1</codeph> IP must resolve to
                    <codeph>localhost</codeph>.</p></entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="col1">Too many clients already</entry>
              <entry colname="col2">By default, Greenplum Database is configured to allow a maximum
                of 250 concurrent user connections on the master and 750 on a segment. A connection
                attempt that causes that limit to be exceeded will be refused. This limit is
                controlled by the <codeph>max_connections</codeph> parameter in the
                  <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> configuration file of the Greenplum Database
                master. If you change this setting for the master, you must also make appropriate
                changes at the segments.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
