<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ddb-plugin">
  <title>Using the DD Boost Storage Plugin with gpbackup, gprestore, and gpbackup_manager</title>
  <body>
    <note>The DD Boost storage plugin is available only with the commercial release of Tanzu Greenplum
      Backup and Restore.</note>
    <p>Dell EMC Data Domain Boost (DD Boost) is Dell EMC software that can be used with the
          <xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpbackup.xml">gpbackup</xref> and
          <xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gprestore.xml">gprestore</xref>
      utilities to perform faster backups to the Dell EMC Data Domain storage appliance. You can
      also replicate a backup on a separate, remote Data Domain system for disaster recovery with
      gpbackup or <xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpbackup_manager.xml">gpbackup_manager</xref>.
      For information about replication, see <xref href="replication-ddb.xml"/>.</p>
    <p>To use the DD Boost storage plugin application, you first create a configuration file to
      specify the location of the plugin, the DD Boost login, and the backup location. When you run
        <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> or <codeph>gprestore</codeph>, you specify the configuration file
      with the option <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>. For information about the configuration
      file, see <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-plugin-config" format="dita"/>.</p>
    <p>If you perform a backup operation with the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> option
        <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>, you must also specify the <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>
      option when you restore the backup with <codeph>gprestore</codeph>. </p>
    <section id="ddb-plugin-config">
      <title>DD Boost Storage Plugin Configuration File Format</title>
      <p>The configuration file specifies the absolute path to the Greenplum Database DD Boost
        storage plugin executable, DD Boost connection credentials, and Data Domain location. The
        configuration file is required only on the master host. The DD Boost storage plugin
        application must be in the same location on every Greenplum Database host. </p>
      <p>The DD Boost storage plugin configuration file uses the <xref
          href="http://yaml.org/spec/1.1/" scope="external" format="html">YAML 1.1</xref> document
        format and implements its own schema for specifying the DD Boost information. </p>
      <p>The configuration file must be a valid YAML document. The <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> and
          <codeph>gprestore</codeph> utilities process the configuration file document in order and
        use indentation (spaces) to determine the document hierarchy and the relationships of the
        sections to one another. The use of white space is significant. White space should not be
        used simply for formatting purposes, and tabs should not be used at all.</p>
      <p>This is the structure of a DD Boost storage plugin configuration file.</p>
      <codeblock>executablepath: &lt;absolute-path-to-gpbackup_ddboost_plugin>
options: 
  hostname: "&lt;data-domain-host>"
  username: "&lt;ddboost-ID>"
  password_encryption: "on" | "off"       
  password: "&lt;ddboost-pwd>"
  storage_unit: "&lt;data-domain-id>"
  directory: "&lt;data-domain-dir>"
  replication: "on" | "off"
  replication_streams: integer
  remote_hostname: "&lt;remote-dd-host>"
  remote_username: "&lt;remote-ddboost-ID>"
  remote_password_encryption "on" | "off"
  remote_password: "&lt;remote-dd-pwd>"
  remote_storage_unit: "&lt;remote-dd-ID>"
  remote_directory: "&lt;remote-dd-dir>"</codeblock>
      <parml id="ddb-exe-path">
        <plentry id="plugin-exe">
          <pt>executablepath</pt>
          <pd>Required. Absolute path to the plugin executable. For example, the Greenplum
            Database installation location is <codeph>$GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_ddboost_plugin</codeph>.
            The plugin must be in the same location on every Greenplum Database host.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="ddb-options">
          <pt>options</pt>
          <pd>Required. Begins the DD Boost storage plugin options section.<parml>
              <plentry id="ddb-host">
                <pt>hostname</pt>
                <pd>Required. The IP address or hostname of the host. There is a 30-character limit.
                </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-user">
                <pt>username</pt>
                <pd>Required. The Data Domain Boost user name. There is a 30-character limit.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-pwd-encrypt">
                <pt>password_encryption</pt>
                <pd>Optional. Specifies whether the <codeph>password</codeph> option value is
                  encrypted. Default value is <codeph>off</codeph>. Use the <xref
                      href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpbackup_manager.xml#topic1"/>
                  <codeph>encrypt-password</codeph> command to encrypt the plain-text password for
                  the DD Boost user. If the <codeph>replication</codeph> option is
                    <codeph>on</codeph>, <codeph>gpbackup_manager</codeph> also encrypts the remote
                  Data Domain user's password. Copy the encrypted password(s) from the
                    <codeph>gpbackup_manager</codeph> output to the <codeph>password</codeph>
                  options in the configuration file.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-pwd">
                <pt>password</pt>
                <pd>Required. The passcode for the DD Boost user to access the Data Domain storage
                  unit. If the <codeph>password_encryption</codeph> option is <codeph>on</codeph>,
                  this is an encrypted password.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-s-unit">
                <pt>storage-unit</pt>
                <pd>Required. A valid storage unit name for the Data Domain system that is used for
                  backup and restore operations.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-dir">
                <pt>directory</pt>
                <pd>Required. The location for the backup files, configuration files, and global
                  objects on the Data Domain system. The location on the system is
                    <codeph>/&lt;</codeph><varname>data-domain-dir</varname>> in the storage unit of
                  the system.</pd>
                <pd>During a backup operation, the plugin creates the directory location if it does
                  not exist in the storage unit and stores the backup in this directory
                      <codeph>/&lt;<varname>data-domain-dir</varname>>/<varname>YYYYMMDD</varname>/<varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname>/</codeph>.
                </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-replication">
                <pt>replication</pt>
                <pd>Optional. Enables or disables backup replication with DD Boost managed file
                  replication when <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> performs a backup operation. Value is
                  either <codeph>on</codeph> or <codeph>off</codeph>. Default value is
                    <codeph>off</codeph>, backup replication is disabled. When the value is
                    <codeph>on</codeph>, the DD Boost plugin replicates the backup on the Data
                  Domain system that you specify with the <codeph>remote_*</codeph> options. </pd>
                <pd>The <codeph>replication</codeph> option and <codeph>remote_*</codeph> options
                  are ignored when performing a restore operation with <codeph>gprestore</codeph>.
                  The <codeph>remote_*</codeph> options are ignored if <codeph>replication</codeph>
                  is <codeph>off</codeph>.</pd>
                <pd>This option is ignored when you perform replication with the
                    <codeph>gpbackup_manager replicate-backup</codeph> command. For information
                  about replication,see <xref href="replication-ddb.xml"/>.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-replication_streams">
                <pt>replication_streams</pt>
                <pd>Optional. Used with the <codeph>gpbackup_manager replicate-backup</codeph>
                  command, ignored otherwise. Specifies the maximum number of Data Domain I/O
                  streams that can be used when replicating a backup set on a remote Data Domain
                  server from the Data Domain server that contains the backup. Default value is
                  1.</pd>
                <pd>This option is ignored when you perform replication with
                    <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>. The default value is used.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-host">
                <pt>remote_hostname</pt>
                <pd>Required when performing replication. The IP address or hostname of the Data
                  Domain system that is used for remote backup storage. There is a 30-character
                  limit. </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-user">
                <pt>remote_username</pt>
                <pd>Required when performing replication. The Data Domain Boost user name that
                  accesses the remote Data Domain system. There is a 30-character limit.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-pwd-encrypt">
                <pt>remote_password_encryption</pt>
                <pd>Optional when performing replication. Specifies whether the
                    <codeph>remote_password</codeph> option value is encrypted. The default value is
                    <codeph>off</codeph>. To set up password encryption use the <xref
                      href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpbackup_manager.xml#topic1"
                      >gpbackup_manager</xref>
                  <codeph>encrypt-password</codeph> command to encrypt the plain-text passwords for
                  the DD Boost user. If the <codeph>replication</codeph> parameter is
                    <codeph>on</codeph>, <codeph>gpbackup_manager</codeph> also encrypts the remote
                  Data Domain user's password. Copy the encrypted passwords from the
                    <codeph>gpbackup_manager</codeph> output to the password options in the
                  configuration file. </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-pwd">
                <pt>remote_password</pt>
                <pd>Required when performing replication. The passcode for the DD Boost user to
                  access the Data Domain storage unit on the remote system. If the
                    <codeph>remote_password_encryption</codeph> option is <codeph>on</codeph>, this
                  is an encrypted password.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-s-unit">
                <pt>remote_storage_unit</pt>
                <pd>Required when performing replication. A valid storage unit name for the remote
                  Data Domain system that is used for backup replication.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-dir">
                <pt>remote_directory</pt>
                <pd>Required when performing replication. The location for the replicated backup
                  files, configuration files, and global objects on the remote Data Domain system.
                  The location on the system is
                    <codeph>/&lt;</codeph><varname>remote-dd-dir</varname>> in the storage unit of
                  the remote system.</pd>
                <pd>During a backup operation, the plugin creates the directory location if it does
                  not exist in the storage unit of the remote Data Domain system and stores the
                  replicated backup in this directory
                      <codeph>/&lt;<varname>remote-dd-dir</varname>>/<varname>YYYYMMDD</varname>/<varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname>/</codeph>.
                </pd>
              </plentry>
            </parml></pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section id="ddb_examples">
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>This is an example DD Boost storage plugin configuration file that is used in the next
          <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> example command. The name of the file is
          <codeph>ddboost-test-config.yaml</codeph>.</p>
      <codeblock>executablepath: $GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_ddboost_plugin
options: 
  hostname: "192.0.2.230"
  username: "test-ddb-user"
  password: "asdf1234asdf"
  storage_unit: "gpdb-backup"
  directory: "test/backup"</codeblock>
      <p>This <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> example backs up the database demo using the DD Boost
        storage plugin. The absolute path to the DD Boost storage plugin configuration file is
          <codeph>/home/gpadmin/ddboost-test-config.yml</codeph>.<codeblock>gpbackup --dbname demo --single-data-file --plugin-config /home/gpadmin/ddboost-test-config.yaml</codeblock></p>
      <p>The DD Boost storage plugin writes the backup files to this directory of the Data Domain
        storage unit <codeph>gpdb-backup</codeph>. </p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>/test/backup/&lt;YYYYMMDD>/&lt;YYYYMMDDHHMMSS>/</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>This is an example DD Boost storage plugin configuration file that enables
        replication.<codeblock>executablepath: $GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_ddboost_plugin
options:
  hostname: "192.0.2.230"
  username: "test-ddb-user"
  password: "asdf1234asdf"
  storage_unit: "gpdb-backup"
  directory: "test/backup"
  replication: "on"
  remote_hostname: "192.0.3.20"
  remote_username: "test-dd-remote"
  remote_password: "qwer2345erty"
  remote_storage_unit: "gpdb-remote"
  remote_directory: "test/replication"</codeblock></p>
      <p>To restore from the replicated backup in the previous example, you can run
          <codeph>gprestore</codeph> with the DD Boost storage plugin and specify a configuration
        file with this
        information.<codeblock>executablepath: $GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_ddboost_plugin
options:
  hostname: "192.0.3.20"
  remote_username: "test-dd-remote"
  remote_password: "qwer2345erty"
  storage_unit: "gpdb-remote"
  directory: "test/replication"</codeblock></p>
    </section>
    <section id="ddboost_notes">
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p>Dell EMC DD Boost is integrated with Tanzu Greenplum and requires a DD Boost
        license. Open source Greenplum Database cannot use the DD Boost software, but can back up to
        a Dell EMC Data Domain system mounted as an NFS share on the Greenplum master and segment
        hosts.</p>
      <p>When you perform a backup with the DD Boost storage plugin, the plugin stores the backup
        files in this location in the Data Domain storage unit. </p>
      <codeblock>&lt;directory>/backups/&lt;datestamp>/&lt;timestamp></codeblock>
      <p>Where &lt;<varname>directory</varname>> is the location you specified in the DD Boost
        configuration file, and &lt;<varname>datestamp</varname>> and
          &lt;<varname>timestamp</varname>> are the backup date and time stamps. </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
