<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="restore-new-target" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="kk174264">Backup Process and Locks</title>
  <body>
    <p>During backups, the <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> utility locks the <i>pg_class</i> system
      table and the tables that are backed up. Locking the <i>pg_class</i> table with an
        <codeph>EXCLUSIVE</codeph> lock ensures that no tables are added, deleted, or altered until
        <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> locks tables that are to be backed up with <codeph>ACCESS
        SHARE</codeph> locks.</p>
    <p>The steps below describe the process <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> follows to dump databases,
      including what happens before locks are placed, while locks are held, and after locks are
      removed.</p>
    <p>If more than one database is specified, this process is executed for each database in
      sequence. </p>
    <ul id="ul_lm4_1bp_4x">
      <li><codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> parses the command-line arguments and verifies that options
        and arguments are properly specified.</li>
      <li>If any of the following filter options are specified, <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> prepares
        filters to determine the set of tables to back up. Otherwise, all tables are included in the
          backup.<ul id="ul_sjc_gvp_4x">
          <li><codeph>-s <i>schema_name</i></codeph> – Includes all the tables qualified by the
            specified schema.</li>
          <li><codeph>-S <i>schema_name</i></codeph> – Excludes all tables qualified by the
            specified schema.</li>
          <li><codeph>--schema-file=<i>filename</i></codeph> – Includes all the tables qualified by
            the schema listed in <i>filename</i>.</li>
          <li><codeph>--exclude-schema-file=<i>filename</i></codeph> – Excludes all tables qualified
            by the schema listed in <i>filename</i>.</li>
          <li><codeph>-t <i>schema.table_name</i></codeph> – Dumps the specified table.</li>
          <li><codeph>-T <i>schema.table_name</i></codeph> – Excludes the specified table.</li>
          <li><codeph>--table-file=<i>filename</i></codeph> – Dumps the tables specified in
              <i>filename</i>.</li>
          <li><codeph>--exclude-table-file=<i>filename</i></codeph> – Dumps all tables except tables
            specified in <i>filename</i>.</li>
        </ul></li>
      <li><codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> verifies the backup targets:<ul id="ul_wgz_kpc_px">
          <li>Verifies that the database exists.</li>
          <li>Verifies that specified tables or schemas to be dumped exist.</li>
          <li>Verifies that the current primary for each segment is up. </li>
          <li>Verifies that the backup directory exists and is writable for the master and each
            segment. </li>
          <li>Verifies that sufficient disk space is available to back up each segment. Note that if
            more than one segment is backed up to the same disk volume, this disk space check cannot
            ensure there is space available for all segments. </li>
        </ul></li>
      <li>Places an <codeph>EXCLUSIVE</codeph> lock on the catalog table <codeph>pg_class</codeph>.
        The lock permits only concurrent read operations on a table. While the lock is on the
        catalog table, relations such as tables, indexes, and views cannot be created, altered, or
        dropped in the database. <p><codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> starts a thread to watch for a lock
          file (<codeph><i>dump_dir</i>/gp_lockfile_<i>timestamp</i></codeph>) to appear, signaling
          the parallel backup on the segments has completed.</p></li>
      <li><codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> locks tables that are to be backed up with an <codeph>ACCESS
          SHARE</codeph> lock. <p>An <codeph>ACCESS SHARE</codeph> lock only conflicts with an
            <codeph>ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</codeph> lock. The following SQL statements acquire an
            <codeph>ACCESS EXCLUSIVE</codeph> lock: <ul id="ul_lj2_hpn_1p">
            <li><codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>CLUSTER</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>DROP TABLE</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>REINDEX</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>TRUNCATE</codeph></li>
            <li><codeph>VACUUM FULL</codeph></li>
          </ul></p></li>
      <li>Threads are created and dispatched for the master and segments to perform the database
        dump. </li>
      <li>When the threads have acquired <codeph>ACCESS SHARED</codeph> locks on all the required
        tables, the <codeph><i>dump_dir</i>/gp_lockfile_<i>timestamp</i></codeph> lock file is
        created, signaling <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> to release the <codeph>EXCLUSIVE</codeph>
        lock on the <i>pg_class</i> catalog table, while tables are being backed up.</li>
      <li><codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> checks the status files for each primary segment for any
        errors to report. If a dump fails and the <codeph>-r</codeph> flag was specified, the backup
        is rolled back.</li>
      <li>The <codeph>ACCESS SHARE</codeph> locks on the target tables are released.</li>
      <li>If the backup succeeded and a post-dump script was specified with the -R option,
          <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> runs the script now. </li>
      <li><codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> reports the backup status, sends email if configured, and
        saves the backup status in the <codeph>public.gpcrondump_history</codeph> table in the
        database. </li>
    </ul>
  </body>
</topic>
