<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic26" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Using Named Pipes</title>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum Database allows the use of named pipes with <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> and
        <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> to back up and restore Greenplum databases. When backing up a
      database with regular files, the files that contain the backup information are placed in
      directories on the Greenplum Database segments. If segment hosts do not have enough local disk
      space available to backup to files, you can use named pipes to back up to non-local storage,
      such as storage on another host on the network or to a backup appliance. </p>
    <p>Backing up with named pipes is not supported if the <codeph>--ddboost</codeph> option is
      specified.</p>
    <section id="kk180388">
      <p><b>To back up a Greenplum database using named pipes</b></p>
      <ol id="ol_alv_vgb_tt">
        <li id="kk180389">Run the <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> command with options
            <codeph>-K timestamp</codeph> and <codeph>--list-backup-files</codeph>. <p>This creates
            two text files that contain the names of backup files, one per line. The file names
            include the <codeph>timestamp</codeph> you specified with the <codeph>-K
              timestamp</codeph> option and have the suffixes <codeph>_pipes</codeph> and
              <codeph>_regular_files</codeph>. For example:
            </p><p><codeblock>gp_dump_20150519160000_pipes 
gp_dump_20150519160000_regular_files</codeblock>The
            file names listed in the <codeph>_pipes</codeph> file are to be created as named pipes.
            The file names in the <codeph>_regular_files</codeph> file should not be created as
            named pipes. <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> and <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> use the
            information in these files during backup and restore operations.</p></li>
        <li id="kk180226">Create named pipes on all Greenplum Database segments using the file names
          in the generated <codeph>_pipes</codeph> file.</li>
        <li>Redirect the output of each named pipe to the destination process or file object. </li>
        <li id="kk180227">Run <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> to back up the database using the named
            pipes.<p>To create a complete set of Greenplum Database backup files, the files listed
            in the <codeph>_regular_files</codeph> file must also be backed up.</p></li>
      </ol>
      <p><b>To restore a database that used named pipes during backup</b></p>
      <ol>
        <li>Direct the contents of each backup file to the input of its named pipe, for example
            <codeph>cat <varname>filename</varname> > <varname>pipename</varname></codeph>, if the
          backup file is accessible as a local file object. </li>
        <li id="kk180234">Run the <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> command to restore the database using
          the named pipes.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic27" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Example</title>
    <body>
      <p>This example shows how to back up a database over the network using named pipes and the
        netcat (<codeph>nc</codeph>) Linux command. The segments write backup files to the inputs of
        the named pipes. The outputs of the named pipes are piped through <codeph>nc</codeph>
        commands, which make the files available on TCP ports. Processes on other hosts can then
        connect to the segment hosts at the designated ports to receive the backup files. This
        example requires that the <codeph>nc</codeph> package is installed on all Greenplum
        hosts.</p>
      <ol id="ol_p2x_fws_cs">
        <li>Enter the following <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> command to generate the lists of backup
          files for the <codeph>testdb</codeph> database in the <codeph>/backups</codeph> directory. <p>
            <codeblock>$ gpcrondump -x testdb -K 20150519160000 --list-backup-files -u /backups
</codeblock>
          </p></li>
        <li>View the files that <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> created in the
            <filepath>/backup</filepath>
          directory:<codeblock>$ ls -lR /backups
/backups:
total 4
drwxrwxr-x 3 gpadmin gpadmin 4096 May 19 21:49 db_dumps

/backups/db_dumps:
total 4
drwxrwxr-x 2 gpadmin gpadmin 4096 May 19 21:49 20150519

/backups/db_dumps/20150519:
total 8
-rw-rw-r-- 1 gpadmin gpadmin 256 May 19 21:49 gp_dump_20150519160000_pipes
-rw-rw-r-- 1 gpadmin gpadmin 391 May 19 21:49 gp_dump_20150519160000_regular_files</codeblock></li>
        <li>View the contents of the <filepath>_pipes</filepath> file.
          <codeblock>$ cat /backups/db_dumps/20150519/gp_dump_20150519160000_pipes 
sdw1:/backups/db_dumps/20150519/gp_dump_0_2_20150519160000.gz
sdw2:/backups/db_dumps/20150519/gp_dump_1_3_20150519160000.gz
mdw:/backups/db_dumps/20150519/gp_dump_-1_1_20150519160000.gz
mdw:/backups/db_dumps/20150519/gp_dump_-1_1_20150519160000_post_data.gz
</codeblock></li>
        <li>Create the specified named pipes on the Greenplum Database segments. Also set up a
          reader for the named pipe.
            <codeblock>gpssh -h sdw1
[sdw1] mkdir -p /backups/db_dumps/20150519/
[sdw1] mkfifo /backups/db_dumps/20150519/gp_dump_0_2_20150519160000.gz
[sdw1] cat /backups/db_dumps/20150519/gp_dump_0_2_20150519160000.gz | nc -l 21000 
[sdw1] exit
</codeblock><p>Complete
            these steps for each of the named pipes listed in the <codeph>_pipes</codeph> file. Be
            sure to choose an available TCP port for each file.</p></li>
        <li>On the destination hosts, receive the backup files with commands like the
          following:<codeblock>nc sdw1 21000 > gp_dump_0_2_20150519160000.gz
</codeblock>
        </li>
        <li>Run <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> to begin the
          backup:<codeblock>gpcrondump -x testdb -K 20150519160000 -u /backups
</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
      <p>To restore a database with named pipes, reverse the direction of the backup files by
        sending the contents of the backup files to the inputs of the named pipes and run the
          <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> command:
          <codeblock>gpdbrestore -x testdb -t 20150519160000 -u /backups
</codeblock><codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph>
        reads from the named pipes' outputs. </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
