<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_edj_hrv_ft">
  <title>Backup and Restore Options</title>
  <body>
    <p>The Greenplum Database backup and restore utilities support various locations for backup
      files:</p>
    <ul id="ul_gy1_tzc_gt">
      <li>With the <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> utility, backup files may be saved in the default
        location, the <codeph>db_dumps</codeph> subdirectory of the master and each segment, or
        saved to a different directory specified with the <codeph>gpcrondump -u</codeph>
        option.</li>
      <li>Both the <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> and <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> utilities have
        integrated support for Dell EMC Data Domain Boost and Veritas NetBackup systems.</li>
      <li>Backup files can be saved through named pipes to any network accessible location.</li>
      <li>Backup files saved to the default location may be moved to an archive server on the
        network. This allows performing the backup at the highest transfer rates (when segments
        write the backup data to fast local disk arrays) and then freeing up disk space by moving
        the files to remote storage. </li>
    </ul>
    <p>You can create dumps containing selected database objects:<ul id="ul_tzq_5zc_gt">
        <li>You can backup tables belonging to one or more schema you specify on the command line or
          in a text file. </li>
        <li>You can specify schema to exclude from the backup, as command-line options or in a list
          provided in a text file. </li>
        <li>You can backup a specified set of tables listed on the command line or in a text file.
          The table and schema options cannot be used together in a single backup.</li>
        <li>In addition to database objects, <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> can backup the
          configuration files <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph>, <codeph>pg_ident.conf</codeph>, and
            <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph>, and global database objects, such as roles and
          tablespaces.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>You can create incremental backups:</p>
    <ul id="ul_h3g_fxz_qt">
      <li>An incremental backup contains only append-optimized and column-oriented tables that have
        changed since the most recent incremental or full backup.</li>
      <li>For partitioned append-optimized tables, only changed append-optimized/column-oriented
        table partitions are backed up. </li>
      <li>Incremental backups include all heap tables.</li>
      <li>Use the <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph>
        <codeph>--incremental</codeph> flag to specify an incremental backup.</li>
      <li>Restoring an incremental backup requires a full backup and all subsequent incremental
        backups, up to the backup you are restoring.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>The <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> utility offers many options:<ul id="ul_djz_g1d_gt">
        <li>By default, <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> restores data to the database it was backed up
          from. </li>
        <li>The <codeph>--redirect</codeph> flag allows you to restore a backup to a different
          database. </li>
        <li>The restored database can be dropped and recreated, but the default is to restore into
          an existing database.</li>
        <li>Selected tables can be restored from a backup by listing the tables on the command line
          or by listing them in a text file and specifying the text file on the command line.</li>
        <li>You can restore a database from backup files moved to an archive server. The backup
          files are copied back into place on the master host and each segment host and then
          restored to the database.</li>
      </ul></p>
  </body>
</topic>
