<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ur2_fsn_ndb">
  <title>Using the S3 Storage Plugin with gpbackup and gprestore</title>
  <body>
    <p>The S3 storage plugin application lets you use an Amazon Simple Storage Service (Amazon S3)
      location to store and retrieve backups when you run <codeph><xref
          href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpbackup.xml">gpbackup</xref></codeph> and <codeph><xref
          href="../../utility_guide/ref/gprestore.xml">gprestore</xref></codeph>. Amazon S3 provides
      secure, durable, highly-scalable object storage. The S3 plugin streams the backup data from a
      named pipe (FIFO) directly to the S3 bucket without generating local disk I/O.</p>
    <p>The S3 storage plugin can also connect to an Amazon S3 compatible service such as <xref
        href="https://www.emc.com/en-us/storage/ecs/index.htm" format="html" scope="external">Dell
        EMC Elastic Cloud Storage</xref> (ECS) and <xref href="https://www.minio.io/" format="html"
        scope="external">Minio</xref>.</p>
    <section>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <p>Using Amazon S3 to back up and restore data requires an Amazon AWS account with access to
        the Amazon S3 bucket. These are the Amazon S3 bucket permissions required for backing up and
        restoring data:<ul id="ul_hh5_3mn_h4b">
          <li><systemoutput>Upload/Delete</systemoutput> for the S3 user ID that uploads the
            files</li>
          <li><systemoutput>Open/Download</systemoutput> and <systemoutput>View</systemoutput> for
            the S3 user ID that accesses the files</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>For information about Amazon S3, see <xref href="https://aws.amazon.com/s3/" format="html"
          scope="external">Amazon S3</xref>. For information about Amazon S3 regions and endpoints,
        see <xref href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/rande.html#s3_region"
          format="html" scope="external">AWS service endpoints</xref>. For information about S3
        buckets and folders, see the <xref href="https://aws.amazon.com/documentation/s3/"
          format="html" scope="external">Amazon S3 documentation</xref>. </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Installing the S3 Storage Plugin</title>
    </section>
    <p><ph otherprops="pivotal">The S3 storage plugin is included with the Tanzu Greenplum Backup
        and Restore release. Use the latest S3 plugin release with the latest Tanzu Backup and
        Restore, to avoid any incompatibilities. </ph></p>
    <p><ph otherprops="oss-only">Open Source Greenplum Backup and Restore customers may get the
        utility from <xref href="https://github.com/greenplum-db/gpbackup-s3-plugin" format="html"
          scope="external">gpbackup-s3-plugin</xref>. Build the utility following the steps in <xref
          href=" https://github.com/greenplum-db/gpbackup-s3-plugin#building-and-installing-binaries"
          format="html" scope="external">Building and Installing the S3 plugin</xref>.</ph></p>
    <p>The S3 storage plugin application must be in the same location on every Greenplum Database
      host, for example <codeph>$GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_s3_plugin</codeph>. The S3 storage plugin
      requires a configuration file, installed only on the master host.</p>
    <section><title>Using the S3 Storage Plugin</title><p>To use the S3 storage plugin application,
        specify the location of the plugin, the S3 login credentials, and the backup location in a
        configuration file. For information about the configuration file, see <xref
          href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-plugin-config" format="dita"/>. </p><p>When running
          <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> or <codeph>gprestore</codeph>, specify the configuration file
        with the option
      <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>.</p><codeblock>gpbackup --dbname &lt;database-name> --plugin-config /&lt;path-to-config-file>/&lt;s3-config-file>.yaml</codeblock>
      When you perform a backup operation using <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> with the
        <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph> option, you must also specify the
        <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph> option when restoring with <codeph>gprestore</codeph>.
        <codeblock>gprestore --timestamp &lt;YYYYMMDDHHMMSS> --plugin-config /&lt;path-to-config-file>/&lt;s3-config-file>.yaml</codeblock><p>The
        S3 plugin stores the backup files in the S3 bucket, in a location similar to:
        </p><codeblock>&lt;<varname>folder</varname>>/backups/&lt;<varname>datestamp</varname>>/&lt;<varname>timestamp</varname>></codeblock><p>Where
          <varname>folder</varname> is the location you specified in the S3 configuration file, and
          <varname>datestamp</varname> and <varname>timestamp</varname> are the backup date and time
        stamps. </p><p>The S3 storage plugin logs are in
            <codeph>&lt;gpadmin_home>/gpAdmin/gpbackup_s3_plugin_<varname>timestamp</varname>.log</codeph>
        on each Greenplum host system. The <varname>timestamp</varname> format is
          <codeph>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</codeph>.</p><b> Example</b><p>This is an example S3 storage plugin
        configuration file, named <codeph>s3-test-config.yaml</codeph>, that is used in the next
          <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> example
        command.</p><codeblock>executablepath: $GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_s3_plugin
options: 
  region: us-west-2
  aws_access_key_id: test-s3-user
  aws_secret_access_key: asdf1234asdf
  bucket: gpdb-backup
  folder: test/backup3</codeblock><p>This
          <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> example backs up the database demo using the S3 storage plugin
        with absolute path
        <codeph>/home/gpadmin/s3-test</codeph>.<codeblock>gpbackup --dbname demo --plugin-config /home/gpadmin/s3-test/s3-test-config.yaml</codeblock></p><p>The
        S3 storage plugin writes the backup files to this S3 location in the AWS region us-west-2. </p><p>
        <codeblock>gpdb-backup/test/backup3/backups/<varname>YYYYMMDD</varname>/<varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname>/</codeblock>
      </p></section>
    <p>This example restores a specific backup set defined by the <codeph>20201206233124</codeph>
      timestamp, using the S3 plugin configuration file. </p>
    <codeblock>gprestore --timestamp 20201206233124 --plugin-config /home/gpadmin/s3-test/s3-test-config.yaml</codeblock>
    <section id="s3-plugin-config">
      <title>S3 Storage Plugin Configuration File Format</title>
      <p>The configuration file specifies the absolute path to the Greenplum Database S3 storage
        plugin executable, connection credentials, and S3 location. </p><p>The S3 storage plugin
        configuration file uses the <xref href="http://yaml.org/spec/1.1/" scope="external"
          format="html">YAML 1.1</xref> document format and implements its own schema for specifying
        the location of the Greenplum Database S3 storage plugin, connection credentials, and S3
        location and login information. </p><p>The configuration file must be a valid YAML document.
        The <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> and <codeph>gprestore</codeph> utilities process the control
        file document in order and use indentation (spaces) to determine the document hierarchy and
        the relationships of the sections to one another. The use of white space is significant.
        White space should not be used simply for formatting purposes, and tabs should not be used
        at all.</p><p>This is the structure of a S3 storage plugin configuration file.</p>
      <codeblock><xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-exe-path" format="dita">executablepath</xref>: &lt;<varname>absolute-path-to-gpbackup_s3_plugin</varname>>
<xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-options" format="dita">options</xref>: 
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-region" format="dita">region</xref>: &lt;<varname>aws-region</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-endpoint" format="dita">endpoint</xref>: &lt;<varname>S3-endpoint</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-id" format="dita">aws_access_key_id</xref>: &lt;<varname>aws-user-id</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-key" format="dita">aws_secret_access_key</xref>: &lt;<varname>aws-user-id-key</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-bucket" format="dita">bucket</xref>: &lt;<varname>s3-bucket</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-location" format="dita">folder</xref>: &lt;<varname>s3-location</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-encryption" format="dita">encryption</xref>: [on|off]
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/concurrent_requests" format="dita">backup_max_concurrent_requests</xref>: [int]
    # default value is 6
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/multipart_chunksize" format="dita">backup_multipart_chunksize</xref>: [string] 
    # default value is 10MB
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/concurrent_requests" format="dita">restore_max_concurrent_requests</xref>: [int]
    # default value is 6
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/multipart_chunksize" format="dita">restore_multipart_chunksize</xref>: [string] 
    # default value is 10MB
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/http-proxy" format="dita">http_proxy</xref>:
        <varname>http://&lt;your_username>:&lt;your_secure_password>@proxy.example.com:proxy_port</varname></codeblock>
      <note>The S3 storage plugin does not support filtered restore operations and the associated
          <codeph>restore_subset</codeph> plugin configuration property.</note>
      <parml id="s3-exe-path">
        <plentry>
          <pt>executablepath</pt>
          <pd>Required. Absolute path to the plugin executable. For example, the Tanzu Greenplum
            installation location is <codeph>$GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_s3_plugin</codeph>. The plugin
            must be in the same location on every Greenplum Database host.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="s3-options">
          <pt>options</pt>
          <pd>Required. Begins the S3 storage plugin options section.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="s3-region">
          <pt>region</pt>
          <pd>Required for AWS S3. If connecting to an S3 compatible service, this option is not
            required.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="s3-endpoint">
          <pt>endpoint</pt>
          <pd>Required for an S3 compatible service. Specify this option to connect to an S3
            compatible service such as ECS. The plugin connects to the specified S3 endpoint
            (hostname or IP address) to access the S3 compatible data store. </pd>
          <pd>If this option is specified, the plugin ignores the <codeph>region</codeph> option and
            does not use AWS to resolve the endpoint. When this option is not specified, the plugin
            uses the <codeph>region</codeph> to determine AWS S3 endpoint. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="s3-id">
          <pt>aws_access_key_id</pt>
          <pd>Optional. The S3 ID to access the S3 bucket location that stores backup files. </pd>
          <pd>If this parameter is not specified, S3 authentication uses information from the
            session environment. See <codeph><xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-key" format="dita"
                >aws_secret_access_key</xref></codeph></pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="s3-key">
          <pt>aws_secret_access_key</pt>
          <pd>Required only if you specify <codeph>aws_access_key_id</codeph>. The S3 passcode for
            the S3 ID to access the S3 bucket location. <p>If <codeph>aws_access_key_id</codeph> and
                <codeph>aws_secret_access_key</codeph> are not specified in the configuration file,
              the S3 plugin uses S3 authentication information from the system environment of the
              session running the backup operation. The S3 plugin searches for the information in
              these sources, using the first available source.</p><ol id="ol_t5l_txj_z4b">
              <li>The environment variables <codeph>AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID</codeph> and
                  <codeph>AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY</codeph>.</li>
              <li>The authentication information set with the AWS CLI command <codeph>aws
                  configure</codeph>.</li>
              <li>The credentials of the Amazon EC2 IAM role if the backup is run from an EC2
                instance.</li>
            </ol></pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="s3-bucket">
          <pt>bucket</pt>
          <pd>Required. The name of the S3 bucket in the AWS region or S3 compatible data store. The
            bucket must exist. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="s3-location">
          <pt>folder</pt>
          <pd>Required. The S3 location for backups. During a backup operation, the plugin creates
            the S3 location if it does not exist in the S3 bucket. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="s3-encryption">
          <pt>encryption</pt>
          <pd>Optional. Enable or disable use of Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) when connecting to an S3
            location. Default value is <codeph>on</codeph>, use connections that are secured with
            SSL. Set this option to <codeph>off</codeph> to connect to an S3 compatible service that
            is not configured to use SSL. </pd>
          <pd>Any value other than <codeph>off</codeph> is treated as <codeph>on</codeph>. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="concurrent_requests">
          <pt>backup_max_concurrent_requests</pt>
          <pd>Optional. The segment concurrency level for a file artifact within a single
            backup/upload request. The default value is set to 6. Use this parameter in conjuction
            with the <codeph>gpbackup --jobs</codeph> flag, to increase your overall backup
            concurrency. </pd>
          <pd>Example: In a 4 node cluster, with 12 segments (3 per node), if the
              <codeph>--jobs</codeph> flag is set to 10, there could be 120 concurrent backup
            requests. With the <codeph>backup_max_concurrent_requests</codeph> parameter set to 6,
            the total S3 concurrent upload threads during a single backup session would reach 720
            (120 x 6). </pd>
          <pd>
            <note>If the upload artifact is 10MB (see <codeph><xref
                  href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/multipart_chunksize" format="dita"
                  >backup_multipart_chunksize</xref></codeph>), the
                <codeph>backup_max_concurrent_requests</codeph> parameter would not take effect
              since the file is smaller than the chunk size.</note>
          </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="multipart_chunksize">
          <pt>backup_multipart_chunksize</pt>
          <pd>Optional. The file chunk size of the S3 multipart upload request in Megabytes (for
            example 20MB), Gigabytes (for example 1GB), or bytes (for example 1048576B). The default
            value is 10MB and the minimum value is 5MB (or 5242880B). Use this parameter along with
            the <codeph>--jobs </codeph>flag and the <codeph>backup_max_concurrent_requests</codeph>
            parameter to fine tune your backups. Set the chunksize based on your individual segment
            file size. S3 supports up to 10,000 max total partitions for a single file upload. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>restore_max_concurrent_requests</pt>
          <pd>Optional. The level of concurrency for downloading a file artifact within a single
            restore request. The default value is set to 6. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>restore_multipart_chunksize</pt>
          <pd>Optional. The file chunk size of the S3 multipart download request in Megabytes (for
            example 20MB), Gigabytes (for example 1GB), or bytes (for example 1048576B). The default
            value is 10MB. Use this parameter along with the
              <codeph>restore_max_concurrent_requests</codeph> parameter to fine tune your
            restores.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="http-proxy">
          <pt>http_proxy</pt>
          <pd>Optional. Allow AWS S3 access via a proxy server. The parameter should contain the
            proxy url in the form of
              <codeph>http://username:password@proxy.example.com:proxy_port</codeph> or
              <codeph>http://proxy.example.com:proxy_port</codeph>. </pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
