<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="backup-veritas">
  <title>Backing Up Databases with Veritas NetBackup</title>
  <body id="body_ebt_kzy_3p">
    <p>For Greenplum Database on Red Hat Enterprise Linux, you can configure Greenplum Database to
      perform backup and restore operations with Veritas NetBackup. You configure Greenplum Database
      and NetBackup and then run a Greenplum Database <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> or
        <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> command. The following topics describe how to set up NetBackup
      and back up or restore Greenplum Databases. </p>
    <ul id="ul_zyz_fyy_3p">
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic_lpr_bcz_3p" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic_nq4_m1z_3p" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic_mlb_1bz_3p" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic_vwm_v1z_3p" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic_t1d_qbz_3p" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic_myv_lbz_3p" format="dita"/>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_lpr_bcz_3p">
    <title>About NetBackup Software</title>
    <body>
      <p>NetBackup includes the following server and client software:</p>
      <ul id="ul_pm1_dcz_3p">
        <li>The NetBackup master server manages NetBackup backups, archives, and restores. The
          master server is responsible for media and device selection for NetBackup. </li>
        <li>NetBackup Media servers are the NetBackup device hosts that provide additional storage
          by allowing NetBackup to use the storage devices that are attached to them.</li>
        <li>NetBackup client software that resides on the Greenplum Database hosts that contain data
          to be backed up. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>See the <cite>Veritas NetBackup Getting Started Guide</cite> for information about
        NetBackup.</p>
      <p otherprops="pivotal">See the Release Notes for information about compatible NetBackup
        versions for this release of Pivotal Greenplum Database.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_nq4_m1z_3p">
    <title>Limitations</title>
    <body>
      <ul id="ul_fdn_q1z_3p">
        <li>NetBackup is not compatible with DDBoost. Both NetBackup and DDBoost cannot be used in a
          single back up or restore operation. </li>
        <li>For incremental back up sets, a full backup and associated incremental backups, the
          backup set must be on a single device. For example, a backup set must all be on a
          NetBackup system. The backup set cannot have some backups on a NetBackup system and others
          on the local file system or a Data Domain system. </li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_mlb_1bz_3p">
    <title>Configuring Greenplum Database Hosts for NetBackup</title>
    <body>
      <section>
        <p>You install and configure NetBackup client software on the Greenplum Database master host
          and all segment hosts. The NetBackup client software must be able to communicate with the
          NetBackup server software.</p>
        <ol id="ol_ojl_gbz_3p">
          <li>Install the NetBackup client software on Greenplum Database hosts. See the NetBackup
            installation documentation for information on installing NetBackup clients on UNIX
            systems.</li>
          <li>Set parameters in the NetBackup configuration file
              <codeph>/usr/openv/netbackup/bp.conf</codeph> on the Greenplum Database master and
            segment hosts. Set the following parameters on each Greenplum Database host. <table
              frame="all" id="table_sll_gbz_3p">
              <title>NetBackup bp.conf parameters for Greenplum Database</title>
              <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colnum="1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colnum="2" colwidth="2.15*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row>
                    <entry>Parameter</entry>
                    <entry>Description</entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>SERVER</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>Host name of the NetBackup Master Server</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>MEDIA_SERVER</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>Host name of the NetBackup Media Server</entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><codeph>CLIENT_NAME</codeph></entry>
                    <entry>Host name of the Greenplum Database Host</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table><p>See the <cite>Veritas NetBackup Administrator's Guide</cite> for information
              about the <filepath>bp.conf</filepath> file. </p></li>
          <li>Set the <codeph>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</codeph> environment variable for Greenplum Database
            hosts to use NetBackup client. Greenplum Database installs NetBackup SDK library files
            that are used with the NetBackup client. To configure Greenplum Database to use the
            library files that correspond to the version of the NetBackup client that is installed
            on the hosts, add the following line to the file
              <codeph>$GPHOME/greenplum_path.sh</codeph>:<codeblock>LD_LIBRARY_PATH=$GPHOME/lib/nbu<varname>NN</varname>/lib:$LD_LIBRARY_PATH </codeblock><p>Replace
              the <varname>NN</varname> with the NetBackup client version that is installed on the
              host (for example, use 77 for NetBackup 7.7.x). </p><p>The
                <codeph>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</codeph> line should be added before this line in
                <codeph>$GPHOME/greenplum_path.sh</codeph>:</p><codeblock>export LD_LIBRARY_PATH</codeblock></li>
          <li>Execute this command to remove the current <codeph>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</codeph>
            value:<codeblock>unset LD_LIBRARY_PATH</codeblock></li>
          <li>Execute this command to update the environment variables for Greenplum
            Database:<codeblock>source $GPHOME/greenplum_path.sh</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section>
        <p>See the <cite>Veritas NetBackup Administrator's Guide</cite> for information about
          configuring NetBackup servers.</p>
        <ol id="ol_yml_gbz_3p">
          <li>Ensure that the Greenplum Database hosts are listed as NetBackup clients for the
            NetBackup server. <p>In the NetBackup Administration Console, the information for the
              NetBackup clients, Media Server, and Master Server is in the <uicontrol>NetBackup
                Management</uicontrol> node within the <uicontrol>Host Properties</uicontrol> node.
            </p></li>
          <li>Configure a NetBackup storage unit. The storage unit must be configured to point to a
            writable disk location.<p>In the NetBackup Administration Console, the information for
              NetBackup storage units is in <uicontrol>NetBackup Management</uicontrol> node within
              the <uicontrol>Storage</uicontrol> node. </p></li>
          <li>Configure a NetBackup backup policy and schedule within the policy. <p>In the
              NetBackup Administration Console, the <uicontrol>Policy</uicontrol> node below the
                <uicontrol>Master Server</uicontrol> node is where you create a policy and a
              schedule for the policy. </p><ul id="ul_w4l_gbz_3p">
              <li>In the <uicontrol>Policy Attributes</uicontrol> tab, these values are required for
                Greenplum Database:<p>The value in the <uicontrol>Policy type</uicontrol> field must
                  be DataStore</p><p>The value in the <uicontrol>Policy storage</uicontrol> field is
                  the storage unit created in the previous step.</p><p>The value in <uicontrol>Limit
                    jobs per policy</uicontrol> field must be at least 3. </p></li>
              <li>In the <uicontrol>Policy Schedules</uicontrol> tab, create a NetBackup schedule
                for the policy. </li>
            </ul></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_vwm_v1z_3p">
    <title>Configuring NetBackup for Greenplum Database</title>
    <body>
      <p>See the <cite>Veritas NetBackup Administrator's Guide</cite> for information about
        configuring NetBackup servers.</p>
      <ol id="ol_xqz_x1z_3p">
        <li>Ensure that the Greenplum Database hosts are listed as NetBackup clients for the
          NetBackup server. <p>In the NetBackup Administration Console, the information for the
            NetBackup clients, Media Server, and Master Server is in <uicontrol>NetBackup
              Management</uicontrol> node within the <uicontrol>Host Properties</uicontrol> node.
          </p></li>
        <li>Configure a NetBackup storage unit. The storage unit must be configured to point to a
          writable disk location.<p>In the NetBackup Administration Console, the information for
            NetBackup storage units is in <uicontrol>NetBackup Management</uicontrol> node within
            the <uicontrol>Storage</uicontrol> node. </p></li>
        <li>Configure a NetBackup backup policy and schedule within the policy. <p>In the NetBackup
            Administration Console, the <uicontrol>Policy</uicontrol> node below the
              <uicontrol>Master Server</uicontrol> node is where you create a policy and a schedule
            for the policy. </p><ul id="ul_xrz_x1z_3p">
            <li>In the <uicontrol>Policy Attributes</uicontrol> tab, these values are required for
              Greenplum Database:<p>The value in the <uicontrol>Policy type</uicontrol> field must
                be DataStore</p><p>The value in the <uicontrol>Policy storage</uicontrol> field is
                the storage unit created in the previous step.</p><p>The value in <uicontrol>Limit
                  jobs per policy</uicontrol> field must be at least 3. </p></li>
            <li>In the <uicontrol>Policy Schedules</uicontrol> tab, create a NetBackup schedule for
              the policy. </li>
          </ul></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_t1d_qbz_3p">
    <title>Performing a Back Up or Restore with NetBackup </title>
    <body>
      <p>The Greenplum Database <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> and <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph>
        utilities support options to back up or restore data to a NetBackup storage unit. When
        performing a back up, Greenplum Database transfers data files directly to the NetBackup
        storage unit. No backup data files are created on the Greenplum Database hosts. The backup
        metadata files are both stored on the hosts and backed up to the NetBackup storage unit. </p>
      <p>When performing a restore, the files are retrieved from the NetBackup server, and then
        restored. </p>
      <p>Following are the <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> utility options for NetBackup:</p>
      <pre>--netbackup-service-host <varname>netbackup_master_server</varname>
--netbackup-policy <varname>policy_name</varname>
--netbackup-schedule <varname>schedule_name</varname>
--netbackup-block-size <varname>size</varname> (optional)
--netbackup-keyword <varname>keyword</varname> (optional) </pre>
      <p>The <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> utility provides the following options for NetBackup:</p>
      <pre>--netbackup-service-host <varname>netbackup_master_server</varname>
--netbackup-block-size <varname>size</varname> (optional)</pre>
      <note>When performing a restore operation from NetBackup, you must specify the backup
        timestamp with the <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> utility <codeph>-t</codeph> option.</note>
      <p>The policy name and schedule name are defined on the NetBackup master server. See <xref
          href="#topic_vwm_v1z_3p" format="dita"/> for information about policy name and schedule
        name. See the <cite>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</cite> for information about the
        Greenplum Database utilities. </p>
      <note>You must run the <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> or <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> command
        during a time window defined for the NetBackup schedule. </note>
      <p>During a back up or restore operation, a separate NetBackup job is created for the
        following types of Greenplum Database data: </p>
      <ul id="ul_s5b_ybz_3p">
        <li>Segment data for each segment instance</li>
        <li>C database data</li>
        <li>Metadata</li>
        <li>Post data for the master </li>
        <li>State files Global objects (<codeph>gpcrondump -G</codeph> option)</li>
        <li>Configuration files for master and segments (<codeph>gpcrondump -g</codeph> option)</li>
        <li>Report files (<codeph>gpcrondump -h</codeph> option)</li>
      </ul>
      <p>In the NetBackup Administration Console, the Activity Monitor lists NetBackup jobs. For
        each job, the job detail displays Greenplum Database backup information. </p>
      <note>When backing up or restoring a large amount of data, set the NetBackup
          <codeph>CLIENT_READ_TIMEOUT</codeph> option to a value that is at least twice the expected
        duration of the operation (in seconds). The <codeph>CLIENT_READ_TIMEOUT</codeph> default
        value is <codeph>300</codeph> seconds (5 minutes). <p>For example, if a backup takes 3
          hours, set the <codeph>CLIENT_READ_TIMEOUT</codeph> to <codeph>21600</codeph> (2 x 3 x 60
          x 60). You can use the NetBackup <codeph>nbgetconfig</codeph> and
            <codeph>nbsetconfig</codeph> commands on the NetBackup server to view and change the
          option value.</p><p>For information about <codeph>CLIENT_READ_TIMEOUT</codeph> and the
            <codeph>nbgetconfig</codeph>, and <codeph>nbsetconfig</codeph> commands, see the
          NetBackup documentation.</p></note>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_myv_lbz_3p">
    <title>Example NetBackup Back Up and Restore Commands</title>
    <body>
      <p>This <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> command backs up the database <i>customer</i> and
        specifies a NetBackup policy and schedule that are defined on the NetBackup master server
          <codeph>nbu_server1</codeph>. A block size of 1024 bytes is used to transfer data to the
        NetBackup server.
        <codeblock>gpcrondump -x customer --netbackup-service-host=nbu_server1 \
   --netbackup-policy=gpdb_cust --netbackup-schedule=gpdb_backup \
   --netbackup-block-size=1024</codeblock></p>
      <p>This <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> command restores Greenplum Database data from the data
        managed by NetBackup master server <codeph>nbu_server1</codeph>. The option <codeph>-t
          20170530090000</codeph> specifies the timestamp generated by <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph>
        when the backup was created. The <codeph>-e</codeph> option specifies that the target
        database is dropped before it is restored.</p>
      <codeblock>gpdbrestore -t 20170530090000 -e --netbackup-service-host=nbu_server1</codeblock>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
