<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic88">
   <title>Using gpbackup and gprestore with BoostFS</title>
   <body>
      <p>You can use the Greenplum Database <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> and <codeph>gprestore</codeph>
         utilities with the Data Domain DD Boost File System Plug-In (BoostFS) to access a Data
         Domain system. BoostFS leverages DD Boost technology and helps reduce bandwidth usage, can
         improve backup-times, offers load-balancing and in-flight encryption, and supports the Data
         Domain multi-tenancy feature set.</p>
      <p>You install the BoostFS plug-in on the Greenplum Database host systems to provide access to
         a Data Domain system as a standard file system mount point. With direct access to a BoostFS
         mount point, <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> and <codeph>gprestore</codeph> can leverage the
         storage and network efficiencies of the DD Boost protocol for backup and recovery.</p>
      <p>For information about configuring BoostFS, you can download the <cite>BoostFS for Linux
            Configuration Guide</cite> from the Dell support site <xref
            href="https://www.dell.com/support" format="html" scope="external"
            >https://www.dell.com/support</xref> (requires login). After logging into the support
         site, you can find the guide by searching for "<userinput>BoostFS for Linux Configuration
            Guide</userinput>". You can limit your search results by choosing to list only
            <userinput>Manuals &amp; Documentation</userinput> as resources. </p>
      <p>To back up or restore with BoostFS, you include the option <codeph>--backup-dir</codeph>
         with the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> or <codeph>gprestore</codeph> command to access the Data
         Domain system.</p>
   </body>
   <topic id="topic_zp4_mvv_bdb">
      <title>Installing BoostFS</title>
      <body>
         <p>Download the latest BoostFS RPM from the Dell support site <xref
               href="https://www.dell.com/support" format="html" scope="external"
               >https://www.dell.com/support</xref> (requires login).</p>
         <p>After logging into the support site, you can find the RPM by searching for
               "<userinput>boostfs</userinput>". You can limit your search results by choosing to
            list only <userinput>Downloads &amp; Drivers</userinput> as resources. To list the most
            recent RPM near the top of your search results, sort your results by descending
            date.</p>
         <p>The RPM supports both RHEL and SuSE.</p>
         <p>These steps install BoostFS and create a mounted directory that accesses a Data Domain
            system. </p>
         <p>Perform the steps on all Greenplum Database hosts. The mounted directory you create must
            be the same on all hosts.</p>
         <ol id="ol_d2g_4rv_bdb">
            <li>Copy the BoostFS RPM to the host and install the RPM.<p>After installation, the
                  DDBoostFS package files are located under
               <codeph>/opt/emc/boostfs</codeph>.</p></li>
            <li>Set up the BoostFS lockbox with the storage unit with the <codeph>boostfs</codeph>
               utility. Enter the Data Domain user password at the
                  prompts.<codeblock>/opt/emc/boostfs/bin/boostfs lockbox set -d &lt;<varname>Data_Domain_IP</varname>> -s &lt;<varname>Storage_Unit</varname>> -u &lt;<varname>Data_Domain_User</varname>></codeblock><p>The
                        <codeph>&lt;<varname>Storage_Unit</varname>></codeph> is the Data Domain
                  storage unit ID. The &lt;<varname>Data_Domain_User</varname>> is a Data Domain
                  user with access to the storage unit.</p></li>
            <li>Create the directory in the location you want to mount
               BoostFS.<codeblock>mkdir &lt;<varname>path_to_mount_directory</varname>></codeblock></li>
            <li>Mount the Data Domain storage unit with the <codeph>boostfs</codeph> utility. Use
               the <codeph>mount</codeph> option <codeph>-allow-others=true</codeph> to allow other
               users to write to the BoostFS mounted file system.
               <codeblock>/opt/emc/boostfs/bin/boostfs mount &lt;<varname>path_to_mount_directory</varname>> -d $&lt;<varname>Data_Domain_IP</varname>> -s &lt;<varname>Storage_Unit</varname>> -o allow-others=true</codeblock></li>
            <li>Confirm that the mount was successful by running this
               command.<codeblock>mountpoint &lt;<varname>mounted_directory</varname>></codeblock>The
               command lists the directory as a mount
               point.<codeblock>&lt;<varname>mounted_directory</varname>> is a mountpoint</codeblock></li>
         </ol>
         <p>You can now run <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> and <codeph>gprestore</codeph> with the
               <codeph>--backup-dir</codeph> option to back up a database to
                  <codeph>&lt;<varname>mounted_directory</varname>></codeph> on the Data Domain
            system and restore data from the Data Domain system. </p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic_t4z_tvv_bdb">
      <title>Backing Up and Restoring with BoostFS </title>
      <body>
         <p>These are required <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> options when backing up data to a Data
            Domain system with BoostFS.<ul id="ul_h3t_pcb_cdb">
               <li><codeph>--backup-dir</codeph> - Specify the mounted Data Domain storage
                  unit.</li>
               <li><codeph>--no-compression</codeph> - Disable compression. Data compression
                  interferes with DD Boost data de-duplication.</li>
               <li><codeph>--single-data-file</codeph> - Create a single data file on each segment
                  host. A single data file avoids a BoostFS stream limitation.</li>
            </ul></p>
         <p>When you use <codeph>gprestore</codeph> to restore a backup from a Data Domain system
            with BoostFS, you must specify the mounted Data Domain storage unit with the option
               <codeph>--backup-dir</codeph>.</p>
         <p>When you use the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> option <codeph>--single-data-file</codeph>,
            you cannot specify the <codeph>--jobs</codeph> option to perform a parallel restore
            operation with <codeph>gprestore</codeph>.</p>
         <p>This example <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> command backs up the database
               <codeph>test</codeph>. The example assumes that the directory
               <codeph>/boostfs-test</codeph> is the mounted Data Domain storage unit.
            <codeblock>$ gpbackup --dbname test --backup-dir /boostfs-test/ --single-data-file --no-compression</codeblock></p>
         <p>These commands drop the database <codeph>test</codeph> and restore the database from the
            backup.
            <codeblock>$ dropdb test
$ gprestore --backup-dir /boostfs-test/ --timestamp 20171103153156 --create-db</codeblock></p>
         <p>The value <codeph>20171103153156</codeph> is the timestamp of the
               <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> backup set to restore. For information about how
               <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> uses timesamps when creating backups, see <xref
               href="backup-gpbackup.xml"/>. For information about the <codeph>-timestamp</codeph>
            option, see <xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gprestore.xml"
               >gprestore</xref>.</p>
      </body>
   </topic>
</topic>
