<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="automate-gpcrondump" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="kk155437">Backing Up with gpcrondump</title>
  <body>
    <p>Use <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> to backup databases, data, and objects such as database roles
      and server configuration files. </p>
    <p>The <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> utility dumps the contents of a Greenplum database to SQL
      script files on the master and each segment. The script files can then be used to restore the
      database.</p>
    <p>The master backup files contain SQL commands to create the database schema. The segment data
      dump files contain SQL statements to load the data into the tables. The segment dump files are
      compressed using <codeph>gzip</codeph>. Optionally, the server configuration files
        <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph>, <codeph>pg_ident.conf</codeph>, and
        <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> and global data such as roles and tablespaces can be included
      in a backup.</p>
    <p>The <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> utility has one required flag, <codeph>-x</codeph>, which
      specifies the database to
      dump:<codeblock>gpcrondump -x <varname>mydb</varname></codeblock>This performs a full backup
      of the specified database to the default locations.</p>
    <note>By default, the utility creates the <codeph>public.gpcrondump_history</codeph> table that
      contains details of the database dump. If the <codeph>public</codeph> schema has been deleted
      from the database, you must specify the <codeph>-H</codeph> option to prevent
        <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> from returning an error when it attempts to create the
      table.</note>
    <p>By default, <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> creates the backup files in the data directory on the
      master and each segment instance in the
        <codeph><varname>data_directory</varname>/db_dumps</codeph> directory. You can specify a
      different backup location using the <codeph>-u</codeph> flag. For example, the following
      command will save backup files to the <codeph>/backups</codeph>
      directory:<codeblock>gpcrondump <varname>mydb</varname> -u <varname>/backups</varname></codeblock>
      The <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> utility creates the <codeph>db_dumps</codeph> subdirectory in
      the specified directory. If there is more than one primary segment per host, all of the
      segments on the host write their backup files to the same directory. This differs from the
      default, where each segment writes backups to its own data directory. This can be used to
      consolidate backups to a single directory or mounted storage device. </p>
    <p>In the <codeph>db_dumps</codeph> directory, backups are saved to a directory in the format
        <i>YYYYMMDD</i>, for example
        <codeph><varname>data_directory</varname>/db_dumps/20151012</codeph> for a backup created on
      October 12, 2015. The backup file names in the directory contain a full timestamp for the
      backup in the format <i>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</i>, for example
        <codeph>gp_dump_0_2_20151012195916.gz</codeph>. The <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> command
      uses the most recent backup by default but you can specify an earlier backup to restore. </p>
    <p>The utility creates backup files with this file name format.</p>
    <p><codeblock><varname>prefix_</varname>gp_dump_<varname>content</varname>_<varname>dbid</varname>_<varname>timestamp</varname></codeblock>The
        <codeph>content</codeph> and <codeph>dbid</codeph> are identifiers for the Greenplum
      Database segment instances that are assigned by Greenplum Database. For information about the
      identifiers, see the Greenplum Database system catalog table <i>gp_id</i> in the
        <cite>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</cite>. </p>
    <p>If you include the <codeph>-g</codeph> option, <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> saves the
      configuration files with the backup. These configuration files are dumped in the master or
      segment data directory to
        <codeph>db_dumps/YYYYMMDD/config_files_<varname>timestamp</varname>.tar</codeph>. If
        <codeph>--ddboost</codeph> is specified, the backup is located on the default storage unit
      in the directory specified by <codeph>--ddboost-backupdir</codeph> when the Data Domain Boost
      credentials were set. The <codeph>-G</codeph> option backs up global objects such as roles and
      tablespaces to a file in the master backup directory named
          <codeph>gp_global_-1_1_<varname>timestamp</varname></codeph>. </p>
    <p>If <codeph>--ddboost</codeph> is specified, the backup is located on the default storage unit
      in the directory specified by <codeph>--ddboost-backupdir</codeph> when the Data Domain Boost
      credentials were set.</p>
    <p>There are many more <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> options available to configure backups. Refer
      to the <i>Greenplum Utility Reference Guide</i> for information about all of the available
      options. See <xref href="backup-ddboost.xml#topic17"/> for details of backing up with Data
      Domain Boost. </p>
    <note type="warning">Backing up a database with <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> while simultaneously
      running <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph> might cause <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> to
        fail.<p>Backing up a database with <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> while simultaneously running
        DDL commands might cause issues with locks. You might see either the DDL command or
          <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph> waiting to acquire locks.</p></note>
  </body>
</topic>
