<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ur2_fsn_ndb">
  <title>Using the S3 Storage Plugin with gpbackup and gprestore</title>
  <body>
    <p>The S3 storage plugin application lets you use an Amazon Simple Storage Service (Amazon S3)
      location to store and retrieve backups when you run <codeph><xref
          href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpbackup.xml">gpbackup</xref></codeph> and
          <codeph><xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gprestore.xml"
        >gprestore</xref></codeph>. Amazon S3 provides secure, durable, highly-scalable object
      storage.</p>
    <p>The S3 storage plugin can also connect to an Amazon S3 compatible service such as <xref
        href="https://www.emc.com/en-us/storage/ecs/index.htm" format="html" scope="external">Dell
        EMC Elastic Cloud Storage</xref> (ECS) and <xref href="https://www.minio.io/" format="html"
        scope="external">Minio</xref>.</p>
    <p>To use the S3 storage plugin application, you specify the location of the plugin and the S3
      login and backup location in a configuration file. When you run <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> or
        <codeph>gprestore</codeph>, you specify the configuration file with the option
        <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>. For information about the configuration file, see <xref
        href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-plugin-config" format="dita"/>.</p>
    <p>If you perform a backup operation with the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> option
        <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>, you must also specify the <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>
      option when you restore the backup with <codeph>gprestore</codeph>. </p>
    <section id="s3-plugin-config">
      <title>S3 Storage Plugin Configuration File Format</title>
      <p>The configuration file specifies the absolute path to the Greenplum Database S3 storage
        plugin executable, connection credentials, and S3 location. </p>
      <p>The S3 storage plugin configuration file uses the <xref href="http://yaml.org/spec/1.1/"
          scope="external" format="html">YAML 1.1</xref> document format and implements its own
        schema for specifying the location of the Greenplum Database S3 storage plugin, connection
        credentials, and S3 location and login information. </p>
      <p>The configuration file must be a valid YAML document. The <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> and
          <codeph>gprestore</codeph> utilities process the control file document in order and use
        indentation (spaces) to determine the document hierarchy and the relationships of the
        sections to one another. The use of white space is significant. White space should not be
        used simply for formatting purposes, and tabs should not be used at all.</p>
      <p>This is the structure of a S3 storage plugin configuration file.</p>
      <codeblock><xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-exe-path" format="dita">executablepath</xref>: &lt;<varname>absolute-path-to-gpbackup_s3_plugin</varname>>
<xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-options" format="dita">options</xref>: 
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-region" format="dita">region</xref>: &lt;<varname>aws-region</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-endpoint" format="dita">endpoint</xref>: &lt;<varname>S3-endpoint</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-id" format="dita">aws_access_key_id</xref>: &lt;<varname>aws-user-id</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-key" format="dita">aws_secret_access_key</xref>: &lt;<varname>aws-user-id-key</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-bucket" format="dita">bucket</xref>: &lt;<varname>s3-bucket</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-location" format="dita">folder</xref>: &lt;<varname>s3-location</varname>>
  <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3-encryption" format="dita">encryption</xref>: [on|off]</codeblock>
      <parml id="s3-exe-path">
        <plentry>
          <pt>executablepath</pt>
          <pd>Required. Absolute path to the plugin executable. For example, the Pivotal Greenplum
            Database installation location is <codeph>$GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_s3_plugin</codeph>. The
            plugin must be in the same location on every Greenplum Database host.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="s3-options">
          <pt>options</pt>
          <pd>Required. Begins the S3 storage plugin options section.<parml>
              <plentry id="s3-region">
                <pt>region</pt>
                <pd>Required for AWS S3. If connecting to an S3 compatible service, this option is
                  not required.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="s3-endpoint">
                <pt>endpoint</pt>
                <pd>Required for an S3 compatible service. Specify this option to connect to an S3
                  compatible service such as ECS. The plugin connects to the specified S3 endpoint
                  (hostname or IP address) to access the S3 compatible data store. </pd>
                <pd>If this option is specified, the plugin ignores the <codeph>region</codeph>
                  option and does not use AWS to resolve the endpoint. When this option is not
                  specified, the plugin uses the <codeph>region</codeph> to determine AWS S3
                  endpoint. </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="s3-id">
                <pt>aws_access_key_id</pt>
                <pd>Optional. The S3 ID to access the S3 bucket location that stores backup files. </pd>
                <pd>If this parameter is not specified, S3 authentication information from the
                  session environment is used. See <xref href="#topic_ur2_fsn_ndb/s3_notes"
                    format="dita"/>.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="s3-key">
                <pt>aws_secret_access_key</pt>
                <pd>Required only if you specify <codeph>aws_access_key_id</codeph>. The S3 passcode
                  for the S3 ID to access the S3 bucket location.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="s3-bucket">
                <pt>bucket</pt>
                <pd>Required. The name of the S3 bucket in the AWS region or S3 compatible data
                  store. The bucket must exist. </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="s3-location">
                <pt>folder</pt>
                <pd>Required. The S3 location for backups. During a backup operation, the plugin
                  creates the S3 location if it does not exist in the S3 bucket. </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="s3-encryption">
                <pt>encryption</pt>
                <pd>Optional. Enable or disable use of Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) when connecting to
                  an S3 location. Default value is <codeph>on</codeph>, use connections that are
                  secured with SSL. Set this option to <codeph>off</codeph> to connect to an S3
                  compatible service that is not configured to use SSL. </pd>
                <pd>Any value other than <codeph>off</codeph> is treated as <codeph>on</codeph>.
                </pd>
              </plentry>
            </parml></pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Example</title>
      <p>This is an example S3 storage plugin configuration file that is used in the next
          <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> example command. The name of the file is
          <codeph>s3-test-config.yaml</codeph>.</p>
      <codeblock>executablepath: $GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_s3_plugin
options: 
  region: us-west-2
  aws_access_key_id: test-s3-user
  aws_secret_access_key: asdf1234asdf
  bucket: gpdb-backup
  folder: test/backup3</codeblock>
      <p>This <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> example backs up the database demo using the S3 storage
        plugin. The absolute path to the S3 storage plugin configuration file is
          <codeph>/home/gpadmin/s3-test</codeph>.<codeblock>gpbackup --dbname demo --plugin-config /home/gpadmin/s3-test-config.yaml</codeblock></p>
      <p>The S3 storage plugin writes the backup files to this S3 location in the AWS region
        us-west-2. </p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>gpdb-backup/test/backup3/backups/<varname>YYYYMMDD</varname>/<varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname>/</codeblock>
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="s3_notes">
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p>The S3 storage plugin application must be in the same location on every Greenplum Database
        host. The configuration file is required only on the master host.</p>
      <p>When you perform a backup with the S3 storage plugin, the plugin stores the backup files in
        this location in the S3 bucket. </p>
      <codeblock>&lt;<varname>folder</varname>>/backups/&lt;<varname>datestamp</varname>>/&lt;<varname>timestamp</varname>></codeblock>
      <p>Where <varname>folder</varname> is the location you specified in the S3 configuration file,
        and <varname>datestamp</varname> and <varname>timestamp</varname> are the backup date and
        time stamps. </p>
      <p>Using Amazon S3 to back up and restore data requires an Amazon AWS account with access to
        the Amazon S3 bucket. These are the Amazon S3 bucket permissions required for backing up and
        restoring data.<ul id="ul_qsv_yh5_ndb">
          <li><systemoutput>Upload/Delete</systemoutput> for the S3 user ID that uploads the
            files</li>
          <li><systemoutput>Open/Download</systemoutput> and <systemoutput>View</systemoutput> for
            the S3 user ID that accesses the files</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>If <codeph>aws_access_key_id</codeph> and <codeph>aws_secret_access_key</codeph> are not
        specified in the configuration file, the S3 plugin uses S3 authentication information from
        the system environment of the session running the backup operation. The S3 plugin searches
        for the information in these sources, using the first available source.</p>
      <ol id="ul_mkl_y1l_cgb">
        <li>The environment variables <codeph>AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID</codeph> and
            <codeph>AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY</codeph>.</li>
        <li>The authentication information set with the AWS CLI command <codeph>aws
            configure</codeph>.</li>
        <li>The credentials of the Amazon EC2 IAM role if the backup is run from an EC2
          instance.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>For information about Amazon S3, see <xref href="https://aws.amazon.com/s3/" format="html"
          scope="external">Amazon S3</xref>.<ul id="ul_g2h_2qn_ndb">
          <li>For information about Amazon S3 regions and endpoints, see <xref
              href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/rande.html#s3_region" format="html"
              scope="external"
              >http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/rande.html#s3_region</xref>.</li>
          <li>For information about S3 buckets and folders, see the Amazon S3 documentation <xref
              href="https://aws.amazon.com/documentation/s3/" format="html" scope="external"
              >https://aws.amazon.com/documentation/s3/</xref>. </li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
