<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_ddb-plugin" otherprops="pivotal">
  <title>Using the DD Boost Storage Plugin with gpbackup and gprestore</title>
  <body>
    <note>The DD Boost storage plugin is available only in the commercial release of Pivotal
      Greenplum Database.</note>
    <p>Dell EMC Data Domain Boost (DD Boost) is Dell EMC software that can be used with the
          <codeph><xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpbackup.xml"
        >gpbackup</xref></codeph> and <codeph><xref
          href="../../utility_guide/ref/gprestore.xml">gprestore</xref></codeph>
      utilities to perform faster backups to the Dell EMC Data Domain storage appliance. You can
      also replicate a backup on a separate, remote Data Domain system for disaster recovery.</p>
    <p>To use the DD Boost storage plugin application, you first create a configuration file to
      specify the location of the plugin, the DD Boost login, and the backup location. When you run
        <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> or <codeph>gprestore</codeph>, you specify the configuration file
      with the option <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>. For information about the configuration
      file, see <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-plugin-config" format="dita"/>.</p>
    <p>If you perform a backup operation with the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> option
        <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>, you must also specify the <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>
      option when you restore the backup with <codeph>gprestore</codeph>. </p>
    <p>To replicate a backup set on a separate Data Domain system for disaster recovery, add the
      backup replication options to the configuration file. Set the <codeph>replication</codeph>
      option to <codeph>on</codeph> and add the options that the plugin uses to access the remote
      Data Domain system that stores the replicated backup. During the backup operation, the DD
      Boost storage plugin replicates the backup set on the remote Data Domain system with DD Boost
      managed file replication. </p>
    <p>To restore data from a replicated backup, you can use <codeph>gprestore</codeph> with the DD
      Boost storage plugin and specify the location of the backup in the DD Boost configuration
      file. </p>
    <section id="ddb-plugin-config">
      <title>DD Boost Storage Plugin Configuration File Format</title>
      <p>The configuration file specifies the absolute path to the Greenplum Database DD Boost
        storage plugin executable, DD Boost connection credentials, and Data Domain location. </p>
      <p>The DD Boost storage plugin configuration file uses the <xref
          href="http://yaml.org/spec/1.1/" scope="external" format="html">YAML 1.1</xref> document
        format and implements its own schema for specifying the DD Boost information. </p>
      <p>The configuration file must be a valid YAML document. The <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> and
          <codeph>gprestore</codeph> utilities process the configuration file document in order and
        use indentation (spaces) to determine the document hierarchy and the relationships of the
        sections to one another. The use of white space is significant. White space should not be
        used simply for formatting purposes, and tabs should not be used at all.</p>
      <p>This is the structure of a DD Boost storage plugin configuration file.</p>
      <codeblock><xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/plugin-exe" format="dita">executablepath</xref>: &lt;<varname>absolute-path-to-gpbackup_ddboost_plugin</varname>>
<xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-options" format="dita">options</xref>: 
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-host" format="dita">hostname</xref>: "&lt;<varname>data-domain-host</varname>>"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-user" format="dita">username</xref>: "&lt;<varname>ddboost-ID</varname>>"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-pwd" format="dita">password</xref>: "&lt;<varname>ddboost-pwd</varname>>"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-s-unit" format="dita">storage_unit</xref>: "&lt;<varname>data-domain-id</varname>>"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-dir" format="dita">directory</xref>: "&lt;<varname>data-domain-dir</varname>>"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-replication" format="dita">replication</xref>: "on" | "off"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-remote-host" format="dita">remote_hostname</xref>: "&lt;<varname>remote-dd-host</varname>>"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-remote-user" format="dita">remote_username</xref>: "&lt;<varname>remote-ddboost-ID</varname>>"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-remote-pwd" format="dita">remote_password</xref>: "&lt;<varname>remote-dd-pwd</varname>>"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-remote-s-unit" format="dita">remote_storage_unit</xref>: "&lt;<varname>remote-dd-ID</varname>>"
  <xref href="#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-remote-dir" format="dita">remote_directory</xref>: "&lt;<varname>remote-dd-dir</varname>>"</codeblock>
      <parml id="ddb-exe-path">
        <plentry id="plugin-exe">
          <pt>executablepath</pt>
          <pd>Required. Absolute path to the plugin executable. For example, the Pivotal Greenplum
            Database installation location is <codeph>$GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_ddboost_plugin</codeph>.
            The plugin must be in the same location on every Greenplum Database host.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="ddb-options">
          <pt>options</pt>
          <pd>Required. Begins the DD Boost storage plugin options section.<parml>
              <plentry id="ddb-host">
                <pt>hostname</pt>
                <pd>Required. The IP address or hostname of the host. There is a 30-character limit.
                </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-user">
                <pt>username</pt>
                <pd>Required. The Data Domain Boost user name. There is a 30-character limit.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-pwd">
                <pt>password</pt>
                <pd>Required. The passcode for the DD Boost user to access the Data Domain storage
                  unit.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-s-unit">
                <pt>storage-unit</pt>
                <pd>Required. A valid storage unit name for the Data Domain system that is used for
                  backup and restore operations.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-dir">
                <pt>directory</pt>
                <pd>Required. The location for the backup files, configuration files, and global
                  objects on the Data Domain system. The location on the system is
                    <codeph>/&lt;</codeph><varname>data-domain-dir</varname>> in the storage unit of
                  the system.</pd>
                <pd>During a backup operation, the plugin creates the directory location if it does
                  not exist in the storage unit and stores the backup in this directory
                      <codeph>/&lt;<varname>data-domain-dir</varname>>/<varname>YYYYMMDD</varname>/<varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname>/</codeph>.
                </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-replication">
                <pt>replication</pt>
                <pd>Optional. Enables or disables backup replication with DD Boost managed file
                  replication when <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> performs a backup operation. Value is
                  either <codeph>on</codeph> or <codeph>off</codeph>. Default value is
                    <codeph>off</codeph>, backup replication is disabled. When the value is
                    <codeph>on</codeph>, the DD Boost plugin replicates the backup on the Data
                  Domain system that you specify with the <codeph>remote_*</codeph> options. </pd>
                <pd>The <codeph>replication</codeph> option and <codeph>remote_*</codeph> options
                  are ignored when performing a restore operation with <codeph>gprestore</codeph>.
                  The <codeph>remote_*</codeph> options are ignored if <codeph>replication</codeph>
                  is <codeph>off</codeph>.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-host">
                <pt>remote_hostname</pt>
                <pd>Required if <codeph>replication</codeph> is <codeph>on</codeph>. The IP address
                  or hostname of the Data Domain system that is used for remote backup storage.
                  There is a 30-character limit. </pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-user">
                <pt>remote_username</pt>
                <pd>Required if <codeph>replication</codeph> is <codeph>on</codeph>. The Data Domain
                  Boost user name that accesses the remote Data Domain system. There is a
                  30-character limit.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-pwd">
                <pt>remote_password</pt>
                <pd>Required if <codeph>replication</codeph> is <codeph>on</codeph>. The passcode
                  for the DD Boost user to access the Data Domain storage unit on the remote
                  system.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-s-unit">
                <pt>remote_storage-unit</pt>
                <pd>Required if <codeph>replication</codeph> is <codeph>on</codeph>. A valid storage
                  unit name for the remote Data Domain system that is used for backup
                  replication.</pd>
              </plentry>
              <plentry id="ddb-remote-dir">
                <pt>remote_directory</pt>
                <pd>Required if <codeph>replication</codeph> is <codeph>on</codeph>. The location
                  for the replicated backup files, configuration files, and global objects on the
                  remote Data Domain system. The location on the system is
                    <codeph>/&lt;</codeph><varname>remote-dd-dir</varname>> in the storage unit of
                  the remote system.</pd>
                <pd>During a backup operation, the plugin creates the directory location if it does
                  not exist in the storage unit of the remote Data Domain system and stores the
                  replicated backup in this directory
                      <codeph>/&lt;<varname>remote-dd-dir</varname>>/<varname>YYYYMMDD</varname>/<varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname>/</codeph>.
                </pd>
              </plentry>
            </parml></pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Example</title>
      <p>This is an example DD Boost storage plugin configuration file that is used in the next
          <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> example command. The name of the file is
          <codeph>ddboost-test-config.yaml</codeph>.</p>
      <codeblock>executablepath: $GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_ddboost_plugin
options: 
  hostname: "192.0.2.230"
  username: "test-ddb-user"
  password: "asdf1234asdf"
  storage_unit: "gpdb-backup"
  directory: "test/backup"</codeblock>
      <p>This <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> example backs up the database demo using the DD Boost
        storage plugin. The absolute path to the DD Boost storage plugin configuration file is
          <codeph>/home/gpadmin/ddboost-test-config.yml</codeph>.<codeblock>gpbackup --dbname demo --single-data-file --plugin-config /home/gpadmin/ddboost-test-config.yaml</codeblock></p>
      <p>The DD Boost storage plugin writes the backup files to this directory of the Data Domain
        storage unit <codeph>gpdb-backup</codeph>. </p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>/test/backup/<varname>YYYYMMDD</varname>/<varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname>/</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>This is an example DD Boost storage plugin configuration file that enables
        replication.<codeblock>executablepath: $GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_ddboost_plugin
options:
  hostname: "192.0.2.230"
  username: "test-ddb-user"
  password: "asdf1234asdf"
  storage_unit: "gpdb-backup"
  directory: "test/backup"
  replication: "on"
  remote_hostname: "192.0.3.20"
  remote_username: "test-dd-remote"
  remote_password: "qwer2345erty"
  remote_storage_unit: "gpdb-remote"
  remote_directory: "test/replication"</codeblock></p>
      <p>To restore from the replicated backup in the previous example, you can run
          <codeph>gprestore</codeph> with the DD Boost storage plugin and specify a configuration
        file with this
        information.<codeblock>executablepath: $GPHOME/bin/gpbackup_ddboost_plugin
options:
  hostname: "192.0.3.20"
  remote_username: "test-dd-remote"
  remote_password: "qwer2345erty"
  storage_unit: "gpdb-remote"
  directory: "test/replication"</codeblock></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p>Dell EMC DD Boost is integrated with Pivotal Greenplum Database and requires a DD Boost
        license. Open source Greenplum Database cannot use the DD Boost software, but can back up to
        a Dell EMC Data Domain system mounted as an NFS share on the Greenplum master and segment
        hosts.</p>
      <p>The DD Boost storage plugin application must be in the same location on every Greenplum
        Database host. The configuration file is required only on the master host.</p>
      <p>When you perform a backup with the DD Boost storage plugin, the plugin stores the backup
        files in this location in the Data Domain storage unit. </p>
      <codeblock>&lt;<varname>directory</varname>>/backups/&lt;<varname>datestamp</varname>>/&lt;<varname>timestamp</varname>></codeblock>
      <p>Where &lt;<varname>directory</varname>> is the location you specified in the DD Boost
        configuration file, and &lt;<varname>datestamp</varname>> and
          &lt;<varname>timestamp</varname>> are the backup date and time stamps. </p>
      <p>When performing a backup operation with replication, the Data Domain system where the
        backup is stored must have access to the remote Data Domain system where the replicated
        backup is stored. </p>
      <p>Performing a backup operation with replication increases the time required to perform a
        backup. The backup set is copied to the local Data Domain system, and then replicated on the
        remote Data Domain system using DD Boost managed file replication. The backup operation
        completes after the backup set is replicated on the remote system.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
