<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_isj_khw_sbs" otherprops="pivotal">
  <title>Migrating Data with gpcopy</title>
  <shortdesc>This topic describes how to use the <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility to transfer data
    between databases in different Greenplum Database clusters.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> is a high-performance utility that can copy metadata and data from
      one Greenplum database to another Greenplum database. You can migrate the entire contents of a
      database, or just selected tables. The source and destination databases must be in different
      clusters, and the clusters can have different Greenplum Database versions. For example, you
      can use <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> to migrate data from a version 4.x Greenplum Database to
      version 5.x.</p>
    <p>The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> interface includes options to transfer one or more full
      databases, or one or more database tables. A full database transfer includes the database
      schema, table data, indexes, views, roles, user-defined functions, resource queues, and
      resource groups. If a copied table or database does not exist in the destination cluster,
        <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> creates it automatically, along with indexes as necessary.</p>
    <p>Configuration files, including <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> and
        <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph>, must be transferred manually by an administrator. Extensions
      installed in the database with <codeph>gppkg</codeph>, such as MADlib and programming language
      extensions, must be installed in the destination database by an administrator. </p>
    <p><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> uses many of the same command-line options as the earlier
        <codeph>gptransfer</codeph> utility. <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> provides several improvements
      as compared to <codeph>gptransfer</codeph>:<ul id="ul_ibs_vsp_zdb">
        <li><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> performs significantly faster than <codeph>gptransfer</codeph>
          when copying large amounts of data.</li>
        <li><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> provides more detailed reporting and summary information about
          all aspects of the copy operation.</li>
        <li>
          <p><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> allows the source table data to change while the data is being
            copied. A lock is not acquired on the source table when data is copied. </p>
        </li>
        <li>The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility includes the
            <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> option to help migrate data from one Pivotal
          Greenplum Database system to another on the same hardware, requiring minimal free space
          available.</li>
      </ul></p></body>
    <topic id="topic_psq_dsp_zdb">
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <body>
      <p>The source and destination Greenplum Database systems must already exist, have network
        access between all hosts, and have master host and primary segment hosts in both systems.
        Each system must be configured with the same number of segments.</p>
      <p><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> is dependent on the <codeph>pg_dump</codeph>,
          <codeph>pg_dumpall</codeph>, and <codeph>psql</codeph> utilities installed with Greenplum
        Database. In most cases, you run <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> from a Greenplum Database cluster,
        so the dependencies are automatically met. If you need to run <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> on a
        remote server, such as an ETL system, copy  the <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> binary and install a
        compatible <xref href="https://network.pivotal.io/products/pivotal-gpdb" scope="external"
          >Greenplum Clients</xref> package to meet the <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> dependencies.</p>
      <p><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> supports migrating data from a Greenplum Database 4.3.26 or later
        cluster to a Greenplum Database 5.9 or later cluster. However Greenplum Database 4.3.26 and
        later do not include the actual <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility. You must manually copy the
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility from your version 5.9 or later cluster into the older
        version cluster to migrate data.. For
        example:<codeblock>$ cp /usr/local/greenplum-db-5.8.0/bin/gpcopy /usr/local/greenplum-db-4.3.26.0/bin/</codeblock></p>
    </body>
  </topic>
    <topic id="topic_qwl_2rp_zdb">
      <title>Limitations for the Source and Destination Systems</title>
      <body>
      <p><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> cannot copy data from one database to another in the same Greenplum
        Database system. The destination system must be a separate Greenplum Database cluster.</p>
        <p dir="ltr" id="docs-internal-guid-872b07d9-60bd-1131-d5a6-3fb4dc225771">The
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility supports copying only between source and destination
        Greenplum Database systems with the same number of segments. If you need to transfer data to
        a Greenplum Database system having a different number of segments, you must use
          <codeph>gptransfer</codeph> instead. See <xref href="gptransfer.xml#topic_gptransfer"
        />.</p>
        <p>If you are copying data between Greenplum Database clusters having different versions,
        each cluster must have <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> installed locally. <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> is
        installed with Pivotal Greenplum Database starting with versions 5.9.0 and 4.3.26.0.</p>
        <p><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> transfers data from user databases only; the
            <codeph>postgres</codeph>, <codeph>template0</codeph>, and <codeph>template1</codeph>
          databases cannot be transferred. Administrators must transfer configuration files manually
          and install extensions into the destination database with <codeph>gppkg</codeph>.</p>
        <p><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> cannot copy a row that is larger than 1GB in size.</p>
        <p>When transferring data between databases, you can run only one instance of
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> at a time.  Running multiple, concurrent instances of
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> is not supported.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_ay1_frp_zdb">
      <title>Configuring Parallel Jobs</title>
      <body>
        <p>The degree of parallelism when running <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> is determined the option
          <codeph>--jobs</codeph>. The option controls the number processes that
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> runs in parallel. The default is 4. The range is from 1 to 64. </p>
      <p>The <codeph>--jobs</codeph> value, <varname>n</varname>, produces
            <codeph>2*<varname>n</varname>+1</codeph> database connections. For example, the default
          <codeph>--jobs</codeph> value of 4 creates 9 connections.</p>
        <p>If you increase this option, ensure that the Greenplum Database systems are configured
        with a sufficient maximum concurrent connection value to accommodate the
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> connections and any other concurrent connections (such as user
        connections) that you require. See the Greenplum Database server configuration parameter
          <codeph>max_connections</codeph>.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_nd3_2sp_zdb">
    <title>Validating Copied Data</title>
    <body>
      <p>By default, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> does not validate the data transferred. You can request
        validation using the <codeph>--validate=<i>type</i></codeph> option. You must include
            <codeph>--validate=<i>type</i></codeph> if you specify the
          <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> option. The validation <i>type</i> can be one of
        the following:<ul id="ul_hf1_k21_xdb">
          <li><codeph>count</codeph> - compares the row counts between the source and destination
            tables.</li>
          <li><codeph>md5xor</codeph> - validates by selecting all rows of the source and
            destination tables, converting all columns in a row to text, and then calculating the
            md5 value of each row.  <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> then performs an XOR over the MD5 values
            to ensure that all rows were successfully copied for the table.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <note>Avoid using <codeph>--append</codeph> with either validation option. If you use
          <codeph>--append</codeph> and the source table already includes rows, then either
        validation method will fail due to the different number of rows in the source and
        destination tables. </note>
    </body>
  </topic>
    <topic id="topic_ytw_2sp_zdb">
    <title>Addressing Failed Data Transfers</title>
    <body>
      <p>When <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> encounters errors and quits or is cancelled by the user,
        current copy operations on tables in the destination database are rolled back. Copy
        operations that have completed are not rolled back. </p>
      <p>If an error occurs during the process of copying a table, or table validation fails,
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> continues copying the other specified tables. After
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> finishes, it displays a list of tables where errors occurred or
        validation failed and displays a <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> command. You can use the provided
        command to retry copying the failed tables. </p>
      <p>The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility logs messages in log file
            <codeph>gpcopy_<varname>date</varname>.log</codeph> in the
          <codeph>~/gpAdminLogs</codeph> directory on the master host. If you run multiple
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> commands on the same day, the utility appends messages to that
        day's log file. </p>
      <p>After <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> completes, it displays a summary of the operations performed.
        If the utility fails to copy tables, they are highlighted in summary, and there is a
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> command provided in summary for user to just copy the failed
        tables. The information is displayed at the command prompt and in the
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> log file. </p>
      <p>After resolving the issues that caused the copy operations to fail, you can run the
        provided command to copy the tables that failed in the previous <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>
        command. </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_ekp_rmp_zdb">
    <title>Performing a Basic Data Migration</title>
    <body>
      <p>Follow this procedure to migrate data from one Greenplum Database system to another with
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>:<ol id="ol_zc4_b34_b2b">
          <li>Start both the source and destination clusters.</li>
          <li>Perform a full database backup in the source Greenplum Database system. See <xref
              href="backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_yrr_hqw_sbb"/>.</li>
          <li>While Greenplum Database 4.3.26 and later support migration with
              <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>, Greenplum Database 4.3.x does not include the
              <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility. If you are migrating from a version 4.3.x system,
            Pivotal recommends that you copy the utility from your Greenplum Database 5.x
            installation to the 4.3.x installation. For
            example:<codeblock>$ cp /usr/local/greenplum-db-5.8.0/bin/gpcopy /usr/local/greenplum-db-4.3.26.0/bin/</codeblock></li>
          <li>As a best practice, source the <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> file in the source
            Greenplum Database 4.3.x installation, so that you execute <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> from
            the source system. For
            example:<codeblock>$ source /usr/local/greenplum-db-4.3.26.0/greenplum_path.sh</codeblock></li>
          <li>Use <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> with the <codeph>--full</codeph> option to migrate your
            data to the destination system. A full migration automatically copies all database
            objects including tables, es, views, roles, functions, user defined types (UDT),
            resource queues, and resource groups for all user defined databases. Include the
              <codeph>--drop</codeph> to drop any destination tables that may already exist
            (recreating es as necessary). For example:
              <codeblock>gpcopy --source-host mytest --source-port 1234 --source-user gpuser \
    --dest-host demohost --dest-port 1234 --dest-user gpuser \
    --full --drop --validate count</codeblock><p>With
              the above command, the utility drops tables in the destination database
                (<codeph>--drop</codeph> option) and uses the row count of the source and
              destination tables to validate the data transfer (<codeph>--validate count</codeph>
              option). The other <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> options specify the source and destination
              Greenplum Database system master hosts, ports, and the User ID to use to connect to
              the Greenplum Database systems.<note>While the example command performs a full system
                copy, consider migrating only portions of the your data at a time, so that you can
                reduce downtime while addressing table errors or validation failures that may occur
                during the copy operation.</note></p></li>
          <li>The <systemoutput>gpcopy</systemoutput> utility does not copy configuration files such
            as <systemoutput>postgresql.conf</systemoutput> and
              <systemoutput>pg_hba.conf</systemoutput>. You must set up the destination system
            configuration as necessary to match the source system.</li>
          <li>The <systemoutput>gpcopy</systemoutput> utility does not copy external objects such as
            Greenplum Database extensions, third party jar files, and shared object files. You must
            recreate these external objects as necessary to match the source system. </li>
          <li>Greenplum Database 5.x removes automatic implicit casts between the text type and other
            data types. After you migrate from Greenplum Database version 4.3.x to version 5.x, this
            change in behavior may impact existing applications and queries. Refer to <xref
              href="../../install_guide/43x_to_5x.xml" format="dita" scope="peer">About Implicit
              Text Casting in Greenplum Database</xref> in the <cite>Greenplum Database Installation
              Guide</cite> for information, including a discussion about supported and unsupported
            workarounds.</li>
          <li>After migrating data you may need to modify SQL scripts, administration scripts, and
            user-defined functions as necessary to account for changes in Greenplum Database version
            5.x. Look for <b>Upgrade Action Required</b> entries in the <xref scope="external"
              format="html" href="https://gpdb.docs.pivotal.io/latest/relnotes/">Pivotal Greenplum
              5.x Release Notes</xref> for features that may necessitate post-migration tasks.</li>
        </ol></p>
      <p>See the <xref href="../../utility_guide/admin_utilities/gpcopy.xml">gpcopy reference
          page</xref>
        <ph otherprops="op-print">in the <cite>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</cite>
        </ph>for complete syntax and usage information. </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_pyc_hpp_zdb">
    <title>Migrating Data Between Clusters that Share Hardware</title>
    <body>
      <p>In order to migrate data between two clusters on the same hardware, you should have enough
        free disk space to accommodate over 5 times the original data set. This enables you to
        maintain 2 full copies of the primary and mirror data sets (on the source and destination
        systems), plus the original backup data in ASCII format. </p>
      <p>If you attempt to migrate on the same system but you run out of disk space, the
          <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility provides the <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph>
        option to help you complete the operation with only a minimum of free disk space. The
          <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> option instructs the utility to truncate each
        source table after successfully copying the table data to the destination cluster and
        validating that the copy succeeded.</p>
      <p>If you choose to use <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph>, consider the following:<ul
          id="ul_g5k_22q_zdb">
          <li>Using the <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> option does not allow for an easy
            rollback to the source system to its original condition if errors occur or validation
            checks fail during the <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> operation. Table errors or validation
            failures during the <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> operation can leave some tables remaining in
            the source cluster, while other tables may be empty (having been truncated after being
            copied to the new cluster). Back up all source data before using <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>
            with <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph>.</li>
          <li>Migrating data with <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> still requires an amount
            of free disk space equal to the sum of the largest tables that you will migrate in a
            single batch using <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>. For example, with a <codeph>--jobs</codeph>
            setting of 5, you must ensure that you have free space equal to the sum of the 5 largest
            tables copied in the batch. The procedure below provides sample commands to determine
            the largest table sizes.</li>
          <li>You must use the <codeph>--validate</codeph> option with
              <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> to ensure that data is successfully copied
            before source tables are truncated.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>If you attempt to use the instructions in <xref href="#topic_ekp_rmp_zdb" format="dita"/>
        to migrate systems that use the same hardware, but you do not have the required free
          space:<ol id="ul_zdm_bm4_b2b">
          <li>Start both the source and destination clusters. </li>
          <li>Perform a full database backup in the source Greenplum Database system. See <xref
              href="backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_yrr_hqw_sbb"/>.</li>
          <li>Determine if you have enough free space to migrate your data using
              <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph>. Migrating data "in-place" requires an amount
            of free disk space equal to the sum of the largest tables that you will migrate in a
            single batch using <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>. For example, if you want to use a
              <codeph>--jobs</codeph> setting of 5, ensure that you have free space equal to the sum
            of the 5 largest tables copied in the batch. <p>The following query lists the largest 5
              tables in your source system; modify the query as needed depending on the
                <codeph>--jobs</codeph> setting you intend to
              use:<codeblock>gpadmin=# SELECT n.nspname, c.relname, c.relstorage, pg_relation_size(c.oid)
FROM 
pg_class c JOIN pg_namespace n ON (c.relnamespace=n.oid)
JOIN pg_catalog.gp_distribution_policy p ON (c.oid = p.localoid)
WHERE
n.nspname NOT IN ('gpexpand', 'pg_bitmap', 'information_schema', 'gp_toolkit')
AND n.nspname NOT LIKE 'pg_temp_%%' AND c.relstorage &lt;> 'v'
ORDER BY 4 DESC LIMIT 5;
</codeblock></p><p>Either
              free enough disk space to cover the sum of the table sizes shown in the above query,
              or consider using a smaller <codeph>--jobs</codeph> value to reduce the free space
              requirements.</p></li>
          <li>While Greenplum Database 4.3.26 and later support migration with
              <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>, Greenplum Database 4.3.x does not include the
              <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility. If you are migrating from a version 4.3.x system,
            Pivotal recommends that you copy the utility from your Greenplum Database 5.x
            installation to the 4.3.x installation. For
            example:<codeblock>$ cp /usr/local/greenplum-db-5.8.0/bin/gpcopy /usr/local/greenplum-db-4.3.26.0/bin/</codeblock></li>
          <li>As a best practice, source the <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> file in the source
            Greenplum Database 4.3.x installation, so that you execute <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> from
            the source system. For
            example:<codeblock>$ source /usr/local/greenplum-db-4.3.26.0/greenplum_path.sh</codeblock></li>
          <li>Use a <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> with the <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> and
              <codeph>--validate</codeph> options to migrate your data to the destination system. A
            full migration automatically copies all database objects including tables, es, views,
            roles, functions, user defined types (UDT), resource queues, and resource groups for all
            user defined databases. Include the <codeph>--drop</codeph> to drop any destination
            tables that may already exist (recreating es as necessary). The
              <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> truncates each source table, only after
            copying and validating the table data in the destination system. For example:
              <codeblock>gpcopy --source-host my_host --source-port 1234 --source-user gpuser \
--dest-host my_host --dest-port 1235 --dest-user gpuser --full --drop \
-truncate-source-after --analyze --validate count</codeblock><p>The
              above command performs a full database copy, first dropping tables in the destination
              database (<codeph>--drop</codeph> option) if they already exist.
                <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> truncates each table in the source system only after
              successfully copying and validating the table data in the destination system. The
              other <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> options specify the source and destination Greenplum
              Database system master hosts, ports, and the User ID to use to connect to the
              Greenplum Database systems.<note>While the example command performs a full system
                copy, consider migrating only portions of the your data at a time, so that you can
                reduce downtime while addressing table errors or validation failures that may occur
                during the copy operation.</note></p></li>
          <li>The <systemoutput>gpcopy</systemoutput> utility does not copy configuration files such
            as <systemoutput>postgresql.conf</systemoutput> and
              <systemoutput>pg_hba.conf</systemoutput>. You must set up the destination system
            configuration as necessary to match the source system.</li>
          <li>The <systemoutput>gpcopy</systemoutput> utility does not copy external objects such as
            Greenplum Database extensions, third party jar files, and shared object files. You must
            recreate these external objects as necessary to match the source system. </li>
          <li>Greenplum Database 5.x removes automatic implicit casts between the text type and other
            data types. After you migrate from Greenplum Database version 4.3.x to version 5.x, this
            change in behavior may impact existing applications and queries. Refer to <xref
              href="../../install_guide/43x_to_5x.xml" format="dita" scope="peer">About Implicit
              Text Casting in Greenplum Database</xref> in the <cite>Greenplum Database Installation
              Guide</cite> for information, including a discussion about supported and unsupported
            workarounds.</li>
          <li>After migrating data you may need to modify SQL scripts, administration scripts, and
            user-defined functions as necessary to account for changes in Greenplum Database version
            5.x. Look for <b>Upgrade Action Required</b> entries in the <xref scope="external"
              format="html" href="https://gpdb.docs.pivotal.io/latest/relnotes/">Pivotal Greenplum
              5.x Release Notes</xref> for features that may necessitate post-migration tasks.</li>
        </ol></p>
      <p>See the <xref href="../../utility_guide/admin_utilities/gpcopy.xml">gpcopy reference
          page</xref>
        <ph otherprops="op-print">in the <cite>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</cite>
        </ph>for complete syntax and usage information. </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
