<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="restore-parallel" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="kk156079">Restoring a Database Using gpdbrestore</title>
  <body>
    <p>The <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> utility restores a database from backup files created by
        <codeph>gpcrondump</codeph>. </p>
    <p>The <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> requires one of the following options to identify the backup
      set to restore:<ul id="ul_p1x_n3c_rt">
        <li><codeph>-t <varname>timestamp</varname></codeph> – restore the backup with the specified
          timestamp.</li>
        <li><codeph>-b <varname>YYYYYMMDD</varname>
          </codeph> – restore dump files for the specified date in the <codeph>db_dumps</codeph>
          subdirectories on the segment data directories. </li>
        <li><codeph>-s <varname>database_name</varname></codeph> – restore the latest dump files for
          the specified database found in the segment data directories.</li>
        <li><codeph>-R <varname>hostname:path</varname></codeph> – restore the backup set located in
          the specified directory of a remote host.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>To restore an incremental backup, you need a complete set of backup files—a full backup and
      any required incremental backups. You can use the <codeph>--list-backups</codeph> option to
      list the full and incremental backup sets required for an incremental backup specified by
      timestamp. For
      example:<codeblock>$ gpdbrestore -t 20151013195916 --list-backup</codeblock></p>
    <p>You can restore a backup to a different database using the <codeph>--redirect
        <i>database</i></codeph> option. The database is created if it does not exist. The following
      example restores the most recent backup of the <codeph>mydb</codeph> database to a new
      database named
      <codeph>mydb_snapshot</codeph>:<codeblock>$ gpdbrestore -s grants --redirect grants_snapshot</codeblock></p>
    <p>You can also restore a backup to a different Greenplum Database system. See
        <xref href="restore-diff-system.xml#restore-new-target"/> for information about this
      option.</p>
    <section id="kk167020">
      <title>To restore from an archive host using gpdbrestore</title>
      <p>You can restore a backup saved on a host outside of the Greenplum cluster using the
          <codeph>-R</codeph> option. Although the Greenplum Database software does not have to be
        installed on the remote host, the remote host must have a <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> account
        configured with passwordless ssh access to all hosts in the Greenplum cluster. This is
        required because each segment host will use scp to copy its segment backup file from the
        archive host. See <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> in the <i>Greenplum Database Utility
          Guide</i> for help adding the remote host to the cluster. </p>
      <p>This procedure assumes that the backup set was moved off the Greenplum array to another
        host in the network.</p>
      <ol id="ol_t3x_mlv_ft">
        <li id="kk167022">Ensure that the archive host is reachable from the Greenplum master
          host:<codeblock>$ ping <varname>archive_host</varname></codeblock></li>
        <li>Ensure that you can ssh into the remote host with the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> account
          and no password. <codeblock>$ ssh gpadmin@<varname>archive_host</varname></codeblock></li>
        <li>Ensure that you can ping the master host from the archive
          host:<codeblock>$ ping mdw</codeblock></li>
        <li id="kk170774">Ensure that the restore's target database exists. For
          example:<codeblock>$ createdb database_name</codeblock></li>
        <li id="kk167026">From the master, run the <codeph>gpdbrestore</codeph> utility. The
            <codeph>-R</codeph> option specifies the host name and path to a complete backup
            set:<codeblock>$ gpdbrestore -R <i>archive_host</i>:/gpdb/backups/archive/20120714 -e <varname>dbname</varname></codeblock><p>Omit
            the <codeph>-e <varname>dbname</varname></codeph> option if the database has already
            been created.</p></li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
