<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title id="eb20941">Configuring Proxies for the Greenplum Interconnect</title>
  <shortdesc>You can configure a Greenplum system to use proxies for interconnect communication to
    reduce the use of connections and ports during query processing.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>The Greenplum <i>interconnect</i> (the networking layer) refers to the inter-process
      communication between segments and the network infrastructure on which this communication
      relies. For information about the Greenplum architecture and interconnect, see <xref
        href="../intro/arch_overview.xml" format="dita"/>. </p>
    <p>In general, when running a query, a QD (query dispatcher) on the Greenplum master creates
      connections to one or more QE (query executor) processes on segments, and a QE can create
      connections to other QEs. For a description of Greenplum query processing and parallel query
      processing, see <xref href="../query/topics/parallel-proc.xml"/>.</p>
    <p>By default, connections between the QD on the master and QEs on segment instances and between
      QEs on different segment instances require a separate network port. You can configure a
      Greenplum system to use proxies when Greenplum communicates between the QD and QEs and between
      QEs on different segment instances. The interconnect proxies require only one network
      connection for Greenplum internal communication between two segment instances, so it consumes
      fewer connections and ports than <codeph>TCP</codeph> mode, and has better performance than
        <codeph>UDPIFC</codeph> mode in a high-latency network. </p>
    <p>To enable interconnect proxies for the Greenplum system, set these system configuration
        parameters.<ul id="ul_vqk_34f_4mb">
        <li>List the proxy ports with the parameter <codeph><xref
              href="../../ref_guide/config_params/guc-list.xml#gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses"
              format="dita"/></codeph>. You must specify a proxy port for the master, standby
          master, and all segment instances.</li>
        <li>Set the parameter <codeph><xref
              href="../../ref_guide/config_params/guc-list.xml#gp_interconnect_type" format="dita"
            /></codeph> to <codeph>proxy</codeph>.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <note>When expanding a Greenplum Database system, you must disable interconnect proxies before
      adding new hosts and segment instances to the system, and you must update the
        <codeph>gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses</codeph> parameter with the newly-added segment
      instances before you re-enable interconnect proxies. </note>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_z4l_lcg_4mb">
    <title>Example</title>
    <body>
      <p>This example sets up a Greenplum system to use proxies for the Greenplum interconnect when
        running queries. The example sets the <codeph><xref
            href="../../ref_guide/config_params/guc-list.xml#gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses"
            format="dita"/></codeph> parameter and tests the proxies before setting the
            <codeph><xref href="../../ref_guide/config_params/guc-list.xml#gp_interconnect_type"
            format="dita"/></codeph> parameter for the Greenplum system.<ul id="ul_mtf_wsm_4mb">
          <li><xref href="#topic_z4l_lcg_4mb/set_proxy_address" format="dita">Setting the
              Interconnect Proxy Addresses</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="#topic_z4l_lcg_4mb/test_proxy" format="dita">Testing the Interconnect
              Proxies</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="#topic_z4l_lcg_4mb/set_gpdb_proxy" format="dita">Setting Interconnect
              Proxies for the System</xref></li>
        </ul></p>
      <section id="set_proxy_address">
        <title>Setting the Interconnect Proxy Addresses</title>
        <p>Set the <codeph>gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses</codeph> parameter to specify the proxy
          ports for the master and segment instances. The syntax for the value has the following
          format and you must specify the parameter value as a single-quoted string.</p>
        <codeblock>&lt;db_id>:&lt;cont_id>:&lt;seg_ip>:&lt;port>[,&lt;dbid>:&lt;segid>:&lt;ip>:&lt;port> ... ]</codeblock>
        <p>For the master, standby master, and segment instance, the first three fields,
            <varname>db_id</varname>, <varname>cont_id</varname>, and <varname>seg_ip</varname> can
          be found in the <codeph><xref
              href="../../ref_guide/system_catalogs/gp_segment_configuration.xml"
              >gp_segment_configuration</xref></codeph> catalog table. The fourth field,
            <varname>port</varname>, is the proxy port for the Greenplum master or a segment
            instance.<ul id="ul_hxd_2qm_4mb">
            <li><varname>db_id</varname> is the <codeph>dbid</codeph> column in the catalog
              table.</li>
            <li><varname>cont_id</varname> is the <codeph>content</codeph> column in the catalog
              table.</li>
            <li><varname>seg_ip</varname> is the IP address corresponding to the
                <codeph>address</codeph> column in the catalog table. If the
                <codeph>address</codeph> is a hostname, use the IP address of the hostname.</li>
            <li><varname>port</varname> is the TCP/IP port for the segment instance proxy that you
              specify.</li>
          </ul></p>
        <p>This is an example PL/Python function that displays or sets the segment instance proxy
          port values for the <codeph>gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses</codeph> parameter. To create
          and run the function, you must enable PL/Python in the database with the <codeph>CREATE
            EXTENSION plpythonu</codeph> command.</p>
        <codeblock>--
-- A PL/Python function to setup the interconnect proxy addresses.
-- Requires the Python modules os and socket.
--
-- Usage:
--   select my_setup_ic_proxy(-1000, '');              -- display IC proxy values for segments
--   select my_setup_ic_proxy(-1000, 'update proxy');  -- update the gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses parameter
--
-- The first argument, "delta", is used to calculate the proxy port with this formula:
--
--   proxy_port = postmaster_port + delta
--
-- The second argument, "action", is used to update the gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses parameter.
-- The parameter is not updated unless "action" is 'update proxy'.
-- Note that running  "gpstop -u" is required for the update to take effect. 
-- A Greenplum system restart will also work.
--
create or replace function my_setup_ic_proxy(delta int, action text)
returns table(dbid smallint, content smallint, ip text, port int) as $$
    import os
    import socket

    results = []
    value = ''

    segs = plpy.execute('''SELECT dbid, content, port, address
                              FROM gp_segment_configuration
                            ORDER BY 1''')
    for seg in segs:
        dbid = seg['dbid']
        content = seg['content']
        port = seg['port']
        address = seg['address']

        # lookup ip of the address
        ip = socket.gethostbyname(address)

        # decide the proxy port
        port = port + delta

        # append to the result list
        results.append((dbid, content, ip, port))

        # build the value for the GUC
        if value:
            value += ','
        value += '{}:{}:{}:{}'.format(dbid, content, ip, port)

    if action.lower() == 'update proxy':
        os.system('''gpconfig --skipvalidation -c gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses -v "'{}'"'''.format(value))
        plpy.notice('''the settings are applied, please reload with 'gpstop -u' to take effect.''')
    else:
        plpy.notice('''if the settings are correct, re-run with 'update proxy' to apply.''')
    return results
$$ language plpythonu execute on master;</codeblock>
        <note>When you run the function, you should connect to the database using the Greenplum
          interconnect type <codeph>UDPIFC</codeph> or <codeph>TCP</codeph>. This example uses
            <codeph>psql</codeph> to connect to the database <codeph>mytest</codeph> with the
          interconnect type
          <codeph>UDPIFC</codeph>.<codeblock>PGOPTIONS="-c gp_interconnect_type=udpifc" psql -d mytest</codeblock></note>
        <p>Running this command lists the segment instance values for the
            <codeph>gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses</codeph> parameter.
          <codeblock>select my_setup_ic_proxy(-1000, '');</codeblock></p>
        <p>This command runs the function to set the
          parameter.<codeblock>select my_setup_ic_proxy(-1000, 'update proxy');</codeblock></p>
        <p>As an alternative, you can run the <codeph><xref
              href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpconfig.xml">gpconfig</xref></codeph> utility to set
          the <codeph>gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses</codeph> parameter. To set the value as a
          string, the value is a single-quoted string that is enclosed in double quotes. The example
          Greenplum system consists of a master and a single segment instance. </p>
        <codeblock>gpconfig --skipvalidation -c gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses -v "'1:-1:192.168.180.50:35432,2:0:192.168.180.54:35000'"</codeblock>
        <p>After setting the <codeph>gp_interconnect_proxy_addresses</codeph> parameter, reload the
            <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file with the <codeph>gpstop -u</codeph> command. This
          command does not stop and restart the Greenplum system.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="test_proxy">
        <title>Testing the Interconnect Proxies</title>
        <p>To test the proxy ports configured for the system, you can set the
            <codeph>PGOPTIONS</codeph> environment variable when you start a <codeph>psql</codeph>
          session in a command shell. This command sets the environment variable to enable
          interconnect proxies, starts <codeph>psql</codeph>, and logs into the database
            <codeph>mytest</codeph>.</p>
        <codeblock>PGOPTIONS="-c gp_interconnect_type=proxy" psql -d mytest</codeblock>
        <p>You can run queries in the shell to test the system. For example, you can run a query
          that accesses all the primary segment instances. This query displays the segment IDs and
          number of rows on the segment instance from the table
          <codeph>sales</codeph>.<codeblock># SELECT gp_segment_id, COUNT(*) FROM sales GROUP BY gp_segment_id ;</codeblock></p>
      </section>
      <section id="set_gpdb_proxy">
        <title>Setting Interconnect Proxies for the System</title>
        <p>After you have tested the interconnect proxies for the system, set the server
          configuration parameter for the system with the <codeph>gpconfig</codeph> utility.</p>
        <p>
          <codeblock>gpconfig -c  gp_interconnect_type -v proxy</codeblock>
        </p>
        <p>Reload the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file with the <codeph>gpstop -u</codeph>
          command. This command does not stop and restart the Greenplum system.</p>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
