<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<dita>
  <topic id="topic_lph_p1k_2hb">
    <title>Replicating Backups</title>
    <body>
      <p>You can use <xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpbackup.xml"
          >gpbackup</xref> or <xref
            href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpbackup_manager.xml">gpbackup_manager</xref>
        with the DD Boost storage plugin to replicate a backup from one Data Domain system to a
        second, remote, Data Domain system for disaster recovery. You can replicate a backup as part
        of the backup process, or replicate an existing backup set as a separate operation. Both
        methods require a <xref href="backup-ddboost-plugin.xml#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb-plugin-config"
          >DD Boost configuration file</xref> that includes options that specify Data Domain system
        locations and DD Boost configuration. The DD Boost storage plugin replicates the backup set
        on the remote Data Domain system with DD Boost managed file replication. </p>
      <p>When replicating a backup, the Data Domain system where the backup is stored must have
        access to the remote Data Domain system where the replicated backup is stored. </p>
      <p>To restore data from a replicated backup, use <xref
            href="../../utility_guide/ref/gprestore.xml">gprestore</xref> with the DD Boost
        storage plugin. In the configuration file, specify the location of the backup in the DD
        Boost configuration file. </p>
      <p>For example configuration files, see <xref
          href="backup-ddboost-plugin.xml#topic_ddb-plugin/ddb_examples"/> in <xref
          href="backup-ddboost-plugin.xml"/>.</p>
      <section><title>Replicate a Backup as Part of the Backup Process</title><p>Use the
            <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> utility to replicate a backup set as part of the backup
          process.</p><p>To enable replication during a back up, add the backup replication options
          to the configuration file. Set the configuration file <codeph>replication</codeph> option
          to <codeph>on</codeph> and add the options that the plugin uses to access the remote Data
          Domain system that stores the replicated backup.</p><p>When using
            <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>, the <codeph>replication</codeph> option must be set to
            <codeph>on</codeph>. </p><p>The configuration file <codeph>replication_streams</codeph>
          option is ignored, the default value is used. </p>Performing a backup operation with
        replication increases the time required to perform a backup. The backup set is copied to the
        local Data Domain system, and then replicated on the remote Data Domain system using DD
        Boost managed file replication. The backup operation completes after the backup set is
        replicated on the remote system.</section>
      <section>
        <title>Replicate an Existing Backup </title>
        <p>Use the <codeph>gpbackup_manager replicate-backup</codeph> command to replicate an
          existing backup set that is on a Data Domain system and was created by
            <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>.</p>
        <p>When you run <codeph>backup_manager replicate-backup</codeph>, specify a DD Boost
          configuration file that contains the same type of information that is in the configuration
          file used to replicate a backup set with <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>. </p>
        <p>When using the <codeph>gpbackup_manager replicate-backup</codeph> command, the
          configuration file <codeph>replication</codeph> option is ignored. The command always
          attempts to replicate a back up.</p>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
</dita>
