<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="kg138244">Starting and Stopping Greenplum Database</title>
  <shortdesc>In a Greenplum Database DBMS, the database server instances (the master and all
    segments) are started or stopped across all of the hosts in the system in such a way that they
    can work together as a unified DBMS. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Because a Greenplum Database system is distributed across many machines, the process for
      starting and stopping a Greenplum Database system is different than the process for starting
      and stopping a regular PostgreSQL DBMS.</p>
    <p>Use the <codeph>gpstart</codeph> and <codeph>gpstop</codeph> utilities to start and stop
      Greenplum Database, respectively. These utilities are located in the
        <filepath>$GPHOME/bin</filepath> directory on your Greenplum Database master host.</p>
    <note type="important">Do not issue a <codeph>kill</codeph> command to end any Postgres process.
      Instead, use the database command <codeph>pg_cancel_backend()</codeph>. <p>Issuing a
          <codeph>kill -9</codeph> or <codeph>kill -11</codeph> can introduce database corruption
        and prevent root cause analysis from being performed.</p></note>
    <p>For information about <codeph>gpstart</codeph> and <codeph>gpstop</codeph>, see the
        <cite>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</cite>.</p>
  </body>
  <task id="task_hkd_gzv_fp">
    <title>Starting Greenplum Database</title>
    <shortdesc>Start an initialized Greenplum Database system by running the
        <codeph>gpstart</codeph> utility on the master instance.</shortdesc>
    <taskbody>
      <context>Use the <codeph>gpstart</codeph> utility to start a Greenplum Database system that
        has already been initialized by the <codeph>gpinitsystem</codeph> utility, but has been
        stopped by the <codeph>gpstop</codeph> utility. The <codeph>gpstart</codeph> utility starts
        Greenplum Database by starting all the Postgres database instances on the Greenplum Database
        cluster. <codeph>gpstart</codeph> orchestrates this process and performs the process in
        parallel.</context>
      <steps-unordered id="steps-unordered_ot5_ntk_gp">
        <step>
          <cmd>Run <codeph>gpstart</codeph> on the master host to start Greenplum Database:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>$ gpstart</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
      </steps-unordered>
    </taskbody>
  </task>
  <task id="task_gpdb_restart">
    <title>Restarting Greenplum Database</title>
    <shortdesc>Stop the Greenplum Database system and then restart it.</shortdesc>
    <taskbody>
      <context>The <codeph>gpstop</codeph> utility with the <codeph>-r</codeph> option can stop and
        then restart Greenplum Database after the shutdown completes. </context>
      <steps-unordered id="steps-unordered_c51_ntk_gp">
        <step>
          <cmd>To restart Greenplum Database, enter the following command on the master host:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>$ gpstop -r</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
      </steps-unordered>
    </taskbody>
  </task>
  <task id="task_upload_config">
    <title>Reloading Configuration File Changes Only</title>
    <shortdesc>Reload changes to Greenplum Database configuration files without interrupting the
      system.</shortdesc>
    <taskbody>
      <context>The <codeph>gpstop</codeph> utility can reload changes to the
          <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath> configuration file and to <i>runtime</i> parameters in
        the master <filepath>postgresql.conf</filepath> file and <filepath>pg_hba.conf</filepath>
        file without service interruption. Active sessions pick up changes when they reconnect to
        the database. Many server configuration parameters require a full system restart
          (<codeph>gpstop -r</codeph>) to activate. For information about server configuration
        parameters, see the <cite>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</cite>.</context>
      <steps-unordered id="steps-unordered_n3k_mtk_gp">
        <step>
          <cmd>Reload configuration file changes without shutting down the system using the
              <codeph>gpstop</codeph> utility:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>$ gpstop -u</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
      </steps-unordered>
    </taskbody>
  </task>
  <task id="task_maint_mode">
    <title>Starting the Master in Maintenance Mode</title>
    <shortdesc>Start only the master to perform maintenance or administrative tasks without
      affecting data on the segments. </shortdesc>
    <taskbody>
      <context><ph otherprops="pivotal">Maintenance mode should only be used with direction from
          Pivotal Technical Support. </ph>For example, you could connect to a database only on the
        master instance in maintenance mode and edit system catalog settings. For more information
        about system catalog tables, see the <cite>Greenplum Database Reference
        Guide</cite>.</context>
      <steps id="steps_gnq_3rk_gp">
        <step>
          <cmd>Run <codeph>gpstart</codeph> using the <option>-m</option> option:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>$ gpstart -m</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>Connect to the master in maintenance mode to do catalog maintenance. For
            example:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock id="kg155401">$ PGOPTIONS='-c gp_role=utility' psql postgres</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>After completing your administrative tasks, stop the master in utility mode. Then,
            restart it in production mode.</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>$ gpstop -mr</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
          <info>
            <note type="warning">
              <p>Incorrect use of maintenance mode connections can result in an inconsistent system
                state. Only Technical Support should perform this operation.</p>
            </note>
          </info>
        </step>
      </steps>
    </taskbody>
  </task>
  <task id="task_gpdb_stop">
    <title id="kg156168">Stopping Greenplum Database</title>
    <taskbody>
      <context>The <codeph>gpstop</codeph> utility stops or restarts your Greenplum Database system
        and always runs on the master host. When activated, <codeph>gpstop</codeph> stops all
          <codeph>postgres</codeph> processes in the system, including the master and all segment
        instances. The <codeph>gpstop</codeph> utility uses a default of up to 64 parallel worker
        threads to bring down the Postgres instances that make up the Greenplum Database cluster.
        The system waits for any active transactions to finish before shutting down. To stop
        Greenplum Database immediately, use fast mode.</context>
      <steps-unordered>
        <step>
          <cmd>To stop Greenplum Database:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>$ gpstop</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
        </step>
        <step>
          <cmd>To stop Greenplum Database in fast mode:</cmd>
          <stepxmp>
            <codeblock>$ gpstop -M fast</codeblock>
          </stepxmp>
          <stepresult>By default, you are not allowed to shut down Greenplum Database if there are any
      client connections to the database. Use the <codeph>-M fast</codeph> option to roll
      back all in progress transactions and terminate any connections before shutting down.</stepresult>
        </step>
      </steps-unordered>
    </taskbody>
  </task>
  <topic id="topic13">
    <title>Stopping Client Processes</title>
    <body>
      <p>Greenplum Database launches a new backend process for each client connection. A Greenplum Database user with <codeph>SUPERUSER</codeph> privileges can cancel and terminate these client backend processes.</p>
      <p>Canceling a backend process with the <codeph>pg_cancel_backend()</codeph> function ends a specific queued or active client query. Terminating a backend process with the <codeph>pg_terminate_backend()</codeph> function terminates a client connection to a database.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>pg_cancel_backend()</codeph> function has two signatures:<ul>
        <li><codeph>pg_cancel_backend( pid int4 )</codeph></li>
        <li><codeph>pg_cancel_backend( pid int4, msg text )</codeph></li>
      </ul></p>
      <p>The <codeph>pg_terminate_backend()</codeph> function has two similar signatures:<ul>
        <li><codeph>pg_terminate_backend( pid int4 )</codeph></li>
        <li><codeph>pg_terminate_backend( pid int4, msg text )</codeph></li>
      </ul></p>
      <p>If you provide a <codeph>msg</codeph>, Greenplum Database includes the text in the cancel
        message returned to the client. <codeph>msg</codeph> is limited to 128 bytes; Greenplum
        Database truncates anything longer.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>pg_cancel_backend()</codeph> and <codeph>pg_terminate_backend()</codeph>
        functions return <codeph>true</codeph> if successful, and <codeph>false</codeph>
        otherwise.</p>
      <p>To cancel or terminate a backend process, you must first identify the process ID of the
        backend. You can obtain the process ID from the <codeph>pid</codeph> column of the
          <codeph>pg_stat_activity</codeph> view. For example, to view the process information
        associated with all running and queued queries:
        <codeblock>=# SELECT usename, pid, waiting, state, query, datname
     FROM pg_stat_activity;</codeblock></p>
      <p>Sample partial query output:</p>
      <codeblock> usename |  pid     | waiting | state  |         query          | datname
---------+----------+---------+--------+------------------------+---------
  sammy  |   31861  |    f    | idle   | SELECT * FROM testtbl; | testdb
  billy  |   31905  |    t    | active | SELECT * FROM topten;  | testdb</codeblock>
      <p>Use the output to identify the process id (<codeph>pid</codeph>) of the query or client
        connection. </p>
      <p>For example, to cancel the waiting query identified in the sample output above and include
          <codeph>'Admin canceled long-running query.'</codeph> as the message returned to the
        client:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>=# SELECT pg_cancel_backend(31905 ,'Admin canceled long-running query.');
ERROR:  canceling statement due to user request: "Admin canceled long-running query."</codeblock>
      </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
