<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic_zhs_r1s_w1b">
  <title>WITH Queries (Common Table Expressions)</title>
  <shortdesc>The <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause provides a way to use subqueries or perform a data
    modifying operation in a larger <codeph>SELECT</codeph> query. You can also use the
      <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause in an <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, or
      <codeph>DELETE</codeph> command. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>See <xref href="#topic_xyn_dgh_5gb" format="dita"/> for information about using
        <codeph>SELECT</codeph> in a <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause.</p>
    <p>See <xref href="#topic_zg3_bgh_5gb" format="dita"/>, for information about using
        <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, or <codeph>DELETE</codeph> in a
        <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause. </p>
    <note>These are limitations for using a <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause.<ul id="ul_rfx_brf_wgb">
        <li>For a <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command that includes a <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause, the
          clause can contain at most a single clause that modifies table data
            (<codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, or <codeph>DELETE</codeph>
          command).</li>
        <li>For a data-modifying command (<codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, or
            <codeph>DELETE</codeph>) that includes a <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause, the clause can
          only contain a <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command, the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause cannot
          contain a data-modifying command.</li>
      </ul></note>
    <p>By default, the <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword for the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause is
      enabled. <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> can be disabled by setting the server configuration
      parameter <codeph><xref
          href="../../../ref_guide/config_params/guc-list.xml#gp_recursive_cte"/></codeph>
      to <codeph>false</codeph>.</p>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_xyn_dgh_5gb">
    <title>SELECT in a WITH Clause</title>
    <body>
      <p>The subqueries, which are often referred to as Common Table Expressions or CTEs, can be
        thought of as defining temporary tables that exist just for the query. These examples show
        the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause being used with a <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command. The
        example <codeph>WITH</codeph> clauses can be used the same way with <codeph>INSERT</codeph>,
          <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, or <codeph>DELETE</codeph>. In each case, the
          <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause effectively provides temporary tables that can be referred to
        in the main command.</p>
      <p>A <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command in the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause is evaluated only
        once per execution of the parent query, even if it is referred to more than once by the
        parent query or sibling <codeph>WITH</codeph> clauses. Thus, expensive calculations that are
        needed in multiple places can be placed within a <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause to avoid
        redundant work. Another possible application is to prevent unwanted multiple evaluations of
        functions with side-effects. However, the other side of this coin is that the optimizer is
        less able to push restrictions from the parent query down into a <codeph>WITH</codeph> query
        than an ordinary sub-query. The <codeph>WITH</codeph> query will generally be evaluated as
        written, without suppression of rows that the parent query might discard afterwards.
        However, evaluation might stop early if the references to the query demand only a limited
        number of rows.</p>
      <p> One use of this feature is to break down complicated queries into simpler parts. This
        example query displays per-product sales totals in only the top sales regions:</p>
      <codeblock>WITH regional_sales AS (
     SELECT region, SUM(amount) AS total_sales
     FROM orders
     GROUP BY region
  ), top_regions AS (
     SELECT region
     FROM regional_sales
     WHERE total_sales > (SELECT SUM(total_sales)/10 FROM regional_sales)
  )
SELECT region,
    product,
    SUM(quantity) AS product_units,
    SUM(amount) AS product_sales
FROM orders
WHERE region IN (SELECT region FROM top_regions)
GROUP BY region, product;
</codeblock>
      <p>The query could have been written without the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause, but would have
        required two levels of nested sub-SELECTs. It is easier to follow with the
          <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause.</p>
      <p>When the optional <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword is enabled, the <codeph>WITH</codeph>
        clause can accomplish things not otherwise possible in standard SQL. Using
          <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph>, a query in the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause can refer to its
        own output. This is a simple example that computes the sum of integers from 1 through
        100:</p>
      <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE t(n) AS (
    VALUES (1)
  UNION ALL
    SELECT n+1 FROM t WHERE n &lt; 100
)
SELECT sum(n) FROM t;
</codeblock>
      <p>The general form of a recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause (a <codeph>WITH</codeph>
        clause that uses a the <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword) is a <i>non-recursive term</i>,
        followed by a <codeph>UNION</codeph> (or <codeph>UNION ALL</codeph>), and then a
          <i>recursive term</i>, where only the <i>recursive term</i> can contain a reference to the
        query output.
        <codeblock><varname>non_recursive_term</varname> UNION [ ALL ] <varname>recursive_term</varname></codeblock></p>
      <p>A recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> query that contains a <codeph> UNION [ ALL ]</codeph> is
        executed as follows:</p>
      <ol id="ol_a3s_r1s_w1b">
        <li>Evaluate the non-recursive term. For <codeph>UNION</codeph> (but not <codeph>UNION
            ALL</codeph>), discard duplicate rows. Include all remaining rows in the result of the
          recursive query, and also place them in a temporary <i>working table</i>.</li>
        <li>As long as the working table is not empty, repeat these steps:<ol id="ol_b3s_r1s_w1b">
            <li>Evaluate the recursive term, substituting the current contents of the working table
              for the recursive self-reference. For <codeph>UNION</codeph> (but not <codeph>UNION
                ALL</codeph>), discard duplicate rows and rows that duplicate any previous result
              row. Include all remaining rows in the result of the recursive query, and also place
              them in a temporary <i>intermediate table</i>.</li>
            <li>Replace the contents of the <i>working table</i> with the contents of the
                <i>intermediate table</i>, then empty the <i>intermediate table</i>.</li>
          </ol></li>
      </ol>
      <note>Strictly speaking, the process is iteration not recursion, but
          <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> is the terminology chosen by the SQL standards
        committee.</note>
      <p>Recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> queries are typically used to deal with hierarchical or
        tree-structured data. An example is this query to find all the direct and indirect sub-parts
        of a product, given only a table that shows immediate inclusions:</p>
      <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE included_parts(sub_part, part, quantity) AS (
    SELECT sub_part, part, quantity FROM parts WHERE part = 'our_product'
  UNION ALL
    SELECT p.sub_part, p.part, p.quantity
    FROM included_parts pr, parts p
    WHERE p.part = pr.sub_part
  )
SELECT sub_part, SUM(quantity) as total_quantity
FROM included_parts
GROUP BY sub_part ;
</codeblock>
      <p>When working with recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> queries, you must ensure that the
        recursive part of the query eventually returns no tuples, or else the query loops
        indefinitely. In the example that computes the sum of integers, the working table contains a
        single row in each step, and it takes on the values from 1 through 100 in successive steps.
        In the 100th step, there is no output because of the <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause, and the
        query terminates.</p>
      <p>For some queries, using <codeph>UNION</codeph> instead of <codeph>UNION ALL</codeph> can
        ensure that the recursive part of the query eventually returns no tuples by discarding rows
        that duplicate previous output rows. However, often a cycle does not involve output rows
        that are complete duplicates: it might be sufficient to check just one or a few fields to
        see if the same point has been reached before. The standard method for handling such
        situations is to compute an array of the visited values. For example, consider the following
        query that searches a table graph using a link field:</p>
      <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE search_graph(id, link, data, depth) AS (
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, 1
        FROM graph g
      UNION ALL
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, sg.depth + 1
        FROM graph g, search_graph sg
        WHERE g.id = sg.link
)
SELECT * FROM search_graph;
</codeblock>
      <p>This query loops if the link relationships contain cycles. Because the query requires a
          <codeph>depth</codeph> output, changing <codeph>UNION ALL</codeph> to
          <codeph>UNION</codeph> does not eliminate the looping. Instead the query needs to
        recognize whether it has reached the same row again while following a particular path of
        links. This modified query adds two columns, <codeph>path</codeph> and
          <codeph>cycle</codeph>, to the loop-prone query:</p>
      <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE search_graph(id, link, data, depth, path, cycle) AS (
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, 1,
          ARRAY[g.id],
          false
        FROM graph g
      UNION ALL
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, sg.depth + 1,
          path || g.id,
          g.id = ANY(path)
        FROM graph g, search_graph sg
        WHERE g.id = sg.link AND NOT cycle
)
SELECT * FROM search_graph;
</codeblock>
      <p>Aside from detecting cycles, the array value of <codeph>path</codeph> is useful in its own
        right since it represents the path taken to reach any particular row.</p>
      <p>In the general case where more than one field needs to be checked to recognize a cycle, an
        array of rows can be used. For example, if we needed to compare fields <codeph>f1</codeph>
        and <codeph>f2</codeph>:</p>
      <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE search_graph(id, link, data, depth, path, cycle) AS (
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, 1,
          ARRAY[ROW(g.f1, g.f2)],
          false
        FROM graph g
      UNION ALL
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, sg.depth + 1,
          path || ROW(g.f1, g.f2),
          ROW(g.f1, g.f2) = ANY(path)
        FROM graph g, search_graph sg
        WHERE g.id = sg.link AND NOT cycle
)
SELECT * FROM search_graph;
</codeblock>
      <note type="tip">Omit the <codeph>ROW()</codeph> syntax in the case where only one field needs
        to be checked to recognize a cycle. This uses a simple array rather than a composite-type
        array, gaining efficiency.</note>
      <note type="tip">The recursive query evaluation algorithm produces its output in breadth-first
        search order. You can display the results in depth-first search order by making the outer
        query <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> a path column constructed in this way.</note>
      <p>A helpful technique for testing a query when you are not certain if it might loop
        indefinitely is to place a <codeph>LIMIT</codeph> in the parent query. For example, this
        query would loop forever without the <codeph>LIMIT</codeph> clause:</p>
      <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE t(n) AS (
    SELECT 1
  UNION ALL
    SELECT n+1 FROM t
)
SELECT n FROM t LIMIT 100;</codeblock>
      <p>The technique works because the recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> implementation evaluates
        only as many rows of a <codeph>WITH</codeph> query as are actually fetched by the parent
        query. Using this technique in production is not recommended, because other systems might
        work differently. Also, the technique might not work if the outer query sorts the recursive
          <codeph>WITH</codeph> results or join the results to another table.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_zg3_bgh_5gb">
    <title>Data-Modifying Statements in a WITH clause</title>
    <body>
      <p>For a <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command, you can use the data-modifying commands
          <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, or <codeph>DELETE</codeph> in a
          <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause. This allows you to perform several different operations in
        the same query. </p>
      <p>A data-modifying statement in a <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause is executed exactly once, and
        always to completion, independently of whether the primary query reads all (or indeed any)
        of the output. This is different from the rule when using <codeph>SELECT</codeph> in a
          <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause, the execution of a <codeph>SELECT</codeph> continues only as
        long as the primary query demands its output.</p>
      <p>This simple CTE query deletes rows from <codeph>products</codeph>. The
          <codeph>DELETE</codeph> in the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause deletes the specified rows
        from products, returning their contents by means of its <codeph>RETURNING</codeph>
        clause.</p>
      <codeblock>WITH deleted_rows AS (
    DELETE FROM products
    WHERE
        "date" >= '2010-10-01' AND
        "date" &lt; '2010-11-01'
    RETURNING *
)
SELECT * FROM deleted_rows;</codeblock>
      <p>Data-modifying statements in a <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause must have
          <codeph>RETURNING</codeph> clauses, as shown in the previous example. It is the output of
        the <codeph>RETURNING</codeph> clause, not the target table of the data-modifying statement,
        that forms the temporary table that can be referred to by the rest of the query. If a
        data-modifying statement in a <codeph>WITH</codeph> lacks a <codeph>RETURNING</codeph>
        clause, an error is returned. </p>
      <p>If the optional <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword is enabled, recursive self-references in
        data-modifying statements are not allowed. In some cases it is possible to work around this
        limitation by referring to the output of a recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph>. For example,
        this query would remove all direct and indirect subparts of a product.</p>
      <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE included_parts(sub_part, part) AS (
    SELECT sub_part, part FROM parts WHERE part = 'our_product'
  UNION ALL
    SELECT p.sub_part, p.part
    FROM included_parts pr, parts p
    WHERE p.part = pr.sub_part
  )
DELETE FROM parts
  WHERE part IN (SELECT part FROM included_parts);</codeblock>
      <p>The sub-statements in a <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause are executed concurrently with each
        other and with the main query. Therefore, when using a data-modifying statement in a
          <codeph>WITH</codeph>, the statement is executed in a <i>snapshot</i>. The effects of the
        statement are not visible on the target tables. The <codeph>RETURNING</codeph> data is the
        only way to communicate changes between different <codeph>WITH</codeph> sub-statements and
        the main query. In this example, the outer <codeph>SELECT</codeph> returns the original
        prices before the action of the <codeph>UPDATE</codeph> in the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause. </p>
      <codeblock>WITH t AS (
    UPDATE products SET price = price * 1.05
    RETURNING *
)
SELECT * FROM products;</codeblock>
      <p>In this example the outer <codeph>SELECT</codeph> returns the updated data.</p>
      <codeblock>WITH t AS (
    UPDATE products SET price = price * 1.05
    RETURNING *
)
SELECT * FROM t;</codeblock>
      <p>Updating the same row twice in a single statement is not supported. The effects of such a
        statement will not be predictable. Only one of the modifications takes place, but it is not
        easy (and sometimes not possible) to predict which modification occurs. </p>
      <p>Any table used as the target of a data-modifying statement in a <codeph>WITH</codeph>
        clause must not have a conditional rule, or an <codeph>ALSO</codeph> rule, or an
          <codeph>INSTEAD</codeph> rule that expands to multiple statements.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
