<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic_zhs_r1s_w1b">
  <title>WITH Queries (Common Table Expressions)</title>
  <shortdesc>The <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause of the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command provides a way
    to write subqueries for use in a larger <codeph>SELECT</codeph> query. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>The subqueries, which are often referred to as Common Table Expressions or CTEs, can be
      thought of as defining temporary tables that exist just for the query. One use of this feature
      is to break down complicated queries into simpler parts. This example query displays
      per-product sales totals in only the top sales regions:</p>
    <codeblock>WITH regional_sales AS (
     SELECT region, SUM(amount) AS total_sales
     FROM orders
     GROUP BY region
  ), top_regions AS (
     SELECT region
     FROM regional_sales
     WHERE total_sales > (SELECT SUM(total_sales)/10 FROM regional_sales)
  )
SELECT region,
    product,
    SUM(quantity) AS product_units,
    SUM(amount) AS product_sales
FROM orders
WHERE region IN (SELECT region FROM top_regions)
GROUP BY region, product;
</codeblock>
    <p>The query could have been written without the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause, but would have
      required two levels of nested sub-SELECTs. It is easier to follow with the
        <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause.</p>
    <p>The <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword can be enabled by setting the server configuration
      parameter <codeph>gp_recursive_cte_prototype</codeph> to <codeph>on</codeph>.<note
        type="warning">The <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword is an experimental feature and is not
        intended for use in a production environment. Experimental features are subject to change
        without notice in future releases.</note></p>
    <p>The optional <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph> keyword changes <codeph>WITH</codeph> accomplishes
      things not otherwise possible in standard SQL. Using <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph>, a query in
      the <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause can refer to its own output. This is a simple example that
      computes the sum the integers from 1 through 100:</p>
    <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE t(n) AS (
    VALUES (1)
  UNION ALL
    SELECT n+1 FROM t WHERE n &lt; 100
)
SELECT sum(n) FROM t;
</codeblock>
    <p>The required form of a recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> clause is a <i>non-recursive term</i>,
      followed by a <codeph>UNION</codeph> (or <codeph>UNION ALL</codeph>), and then a <i>recursive
        term</i>, where only the <i>recursive term</i> can contain a reference to the query output.
      <codeblock><varname>non_recursive_term</varname> UNION [ ALL ] <varname>recursive_term</varname></codeblock></p>
    <p>A recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> query is executed as follows:</p>
    <ol id="ol_a3s_r1s_w1b">
      <li>Evaluate the non-recursive term. For <codeph>UNION</codeph> (but not <codeph>UNION
          ALL</codeph>), discard duplicate rows. Include all remaining rows in the result of the
        recursive query, and also place them in a temporary <i>working table</i>.</li>
      <li>As long as the working table is not empty, repeat these steps:<ol id="ol_b3s_r1s_w1b">
          <li>Evaluate the recursive term, substituting the current contents of the working table
            for the recursive self-reference. For <codeph>UNION</codeph> (but not <codeph>UNION
              ALL</codeph>), discard duplicate rows and rows that duplicate any previous result row.
            Include all remaining rows in the result of the recursive query, and also place them in
            a temporary <i>intermediate table</i>.</li>
          <li>Replace the contents of the <i>working table</i> with the contents of the
              <i>intermediate table</i>, then empty the <i>intermediate table</i>.</li>
        </ol></li>
    </ol>
    <note>Strictly speaking, the process is iteration not recursion, but <codeph>RECURSIVE</codeph>
      is the terminology chosen by the SQL standards committee.</note>
    <p>Recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> queries are typically used to deal with hierarchical or
      tree-structured data. An example is this query to find all the direct and indirect sub-parts
      of a product, given only a table that shows immediate inclusions:</p>
    <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE included_parts(sub_part, part, quantity) AS (
    SELECT sub_part, part, quantity FROM parts WHERE part = 'our_product'
  UNION ALL
    SELECT p.sub_part, p.part, p.quantity
    FROM included_parts pr, parts p
    WHERE p.part = pr.sub_part
  )
SELECT sub_part, SUM(quantity) as total_quantity
FROM included_parts
GROUP BY sub_part
</codeblock>
    <p>When working with recursive <codeph>WITH</codeph> queries, you must ensure that the recursive
      part of the query eventually returns no tuples, or else the query loops indefinitely. In the
      example that computes the sum the integers, the working table contains a single row in each
      step, and it takes on the values from 1 through 100 in successive steps. In the 100th step,
      there is no output because of the <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clause, and the query terminates.</p>
    <p>For some queries, using <codeph>UNION</codeph> instead of <codeph>UNION ALL</codeph> can
      ensure that the recursive part of the query eventually returns no tuples by discarding rows
      that duplicate previous output rows. However, often a cycle does not involve output rows that
      are complete duplicates: it might sufficient to check just one or a few fields to see if the
      same point has been reached before. The standard method for handling such situations is to
      compute an array of the visited values. For example, consider the following query that
      searches a table graph using a link field:</p>
    <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE search_graph(id, link, data, depth) AS (
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, 1
        FROM graph g
      UNION ALL
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, sg.depth + 1
        FROM graph g, search_graph sg
        WHERE g.id = sg.link
)
SELECT * FROM search_graph;
</codeblock>
    <p>This query loops if the link relationships contain cycles. Because the query requires a
        <codeph>depth</codeph> output, changing <codeph>UNION ALL</codeph> to <codeph>UNION</codeph>
      does not eliminate the looping. Instead the query needs to recognize whether it has reached
      the same row again while following a particular path of links. This modified query adds two
      columns <codeph>path</codeph> and <codeph>cycle</codeph> to the loop-prone query:</p>
    <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE search_graph(id, link, data, depth, path, cycle) AS (
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, 1,
          ARRAY[g.id],
          false
        FROM graph g
      UNION ALL
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, sg.depth + 1,
          path || g.id,
          g.id = ANY(path)
        FROM graph g, search_graph sg
        WHERE g.id = sg.link AND NOT cycle
)
SELECT * FROM search_graph;
</codeblock>
    <p>Aside from detecting cycles, the array value of <codeph>path</codeph> is useful in its own
      right since it represents the path taken to reach any particular row.</p>
    <p>In the general case where more than one field needs to be checked to recognize a cycle, an
      array of rows can be used. For example, if we needed to compare fields <codeph>f1</codeph> and
        <codeph>f2</codeph>:</p>
    <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE search_graph(id, link, data, depth, path, cycle) AS (
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, 1,
          ARRAY[ROW(g.f1, g.f2)],
          false
        FROM graph g
      UNION ALL
        SELECT g.id, g.link, g.data, sg.depth + 1,
          path || ROW(g.f1, g.f2),
          ROW(g.f1, g.f2) = ANY(path)
        FROM graph g, search_graph sg
        WHERE g.id = sg.link AND NOT cycle
)
SELECT * FROM search_graph;
</codeblock>
    <note type="tip">Omit the <codeph>ROW()</codeph> syntax in the case where only one field needs
      to be checked to recognize a cycle. This uses a simple array rather than a composite-type
      array to be used, gaining efficiency.</note>
    <note type="tip">The recursive query evaluation algorithm produces its output in breadth-first
      search order. You can display the results in depth-first search order by making the outer
      query <codeph>ORDER BY</codeph> a path column constructed in this way.</note>
    <p>A helpful technique for testing a query when you are not certain if it might loop
      indefinitely is to place a <codeph>LIMIT</codeph> in the parent query. For example, this query
      would loop forever without the <codeph>LIMIT</codeph> clause:</p>
    <codeblock>WITH RECURSIVE t(n) AS (
    SELECT 1
  UNION ALL
    SELECT n+1 FROM t
)
SELECT n FROM t LIMIT 100;</codeblock>
    <p>The technique works because the recursvie <codeph>WITH</codeph> implementation evaluates only
      as many rows of a <codeph>WITH</codeph> query as are actually fetched by the parent query.
      Using this technique in production is not recommended, because other systems might work
      differently. Also, the technique might not work if the outer query sorts the recursive
        <codeph>WITH</codeph> results or join the results to another table.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
