<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title>Enabling and Disabling GPORCA</title>
  <abstract>
    <shortdesc>By default, Greenplum Database uses GPORCA instead of the Postgres Planner.
      Server configuration parameters enable or disable GPORCA.</shortdesc>
  </abstract>
  <body>
    <p>Although GPORCA is on by default, you can configure GPORCA usage at the system, database,
      session, or query level using the <cmdname>optimizer</cmdname> parameter. Refer to one of the
      following sections if you want to change the default behavior:<ul id="ul_frw_y51_kr">
        <li><xref href="#topic_byp_lqk_br" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_pzr_3db_3r" format="dita"/></li>
        <li><xref href="#topic_lx4_vqk_br" format="dita"/></li>
      </ul></p>
    <note>You can disable the ability to enable or disable GPORCA with the
      server configuration parameter <cmdname>optimizer_control</cmdname>. For information about the
      server configuration parameters, see the <cite>Greenplum Database Reference
        Guide</cite>.</note>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_byp_lqk_br">
    <title>Enabling GPORCA for a System</title>
    <body>
      <p>Set the server configuration parameter <cmdname>optimizer</cmdname> for the Greenplum Database system.</p>
      <ol id="ol_a5s_2sl_vp">
        <li>Log into the Greenplum Database master host as <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>,
          the Greenplum Database administrator.</li>
        <li>Set the values of the server configuration parameters. These Greenplum Database
          <cmdname>gpconfig</cmdname> utility commands sets the value of the parameters to
            <codeph>on</codeph>:<codeblock>$ gpconfig -c optimizer -v on --masteronly</codeblock></li>
        <li>Restart Greenplum Database. This Greenplum Database
          <cmdname>gpstop</cmdname> utility command reloads the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph>
          files of the master and segments without shutting down Greenplum Database.
          <codeblock>gpstop -u</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_pzr_3db_3r">
    <title>Enabling GPORCA for a Database</title>
    <body>
      <p>Set the server configuration parameter <cmdname>optimizer</cmdname> for individual Greenplum databases with the <cmdname>ALTER DATABASE</cmdname>
        command. For example, this command enables GPORCA for the database
          <i>test_db</i>.<codeblock>> ALTER DATABASE test_db SET OPTIMIZER = ON ;</codeblock></p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_lx4_vqk_br">
    <title>Enabling GPORCA for a Session or a Query</title>
    <body>
      <p>You can use the <cmdname>SET</cmdname> command to set <cmdname>optimizer</cmdname> server
        configuration parameter for a session. For example, after you use the
          <cmdname>psql</cmdname> utility to connect to Greenplum Database, this
          <cmdname>SET</cmdname> command enables GPORCA:<codeblock>> set optimizer = on ;</codeblock></p>
      <p>To set the parameter for a specific query, include the <cmdname>SET</cmdname> command prior
        to running the query.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
