<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title>Considerations when Using GPORCA</title>
  <abstract>
    <shortdesc> To execute queries optimally with GPORCA, query criteria to consider. </shortdesc>
  </abstract>
  <body>
    <p>Ensure the following criteria are met:<ul id="ul_bpd_4rb_kr">
        <li>The table does not contain multi-column partition keys.</li>
        <li>The multi-level partitioned table is a uniform multi-level partitioned table. See <xref
            href="query-piv-uniform-part-tbl.xml#topic1"/>.</li>
        <li>The server configuration parameter <codeph>optimizer_enable_master_only_queries</codeph>
          is set to <codeph>on</codeph> when running against master only tables such as the system
          table <i>pg_attribute</i>. For information about the parameter, see the <cite>Greenplum
            Database Reference Guide</cite>.<note>Enabling this parameter decreases performance of
            short running catalog queries. To avoid this issue, set this parameter only for a
            session or a query. </note></li>
        <li>Statistics have been collected on the root partition of a partitioned table.</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>If the partitioned table contains more than 20,000 partitions, consider a redesign of the
      table schema. </p>
    <p>These server configuration parameters affect GPORCA query processing.</p>
    <ul id="ul_jt3_nnq_1y">
      <li><codeph>optimizer_cte_inlining_bound</codeph> controls the amount of inlining performed
        for common table expression (CTE) queries (queries that contain a <codeph>WHERE</codeph>
        clause).</li>
      <li><codeph>optimizer_force_multistage_agg</codeph> forces GPORCA to choose a 3 stage
        aggregate plan for a scalar distinct qualified aggregate. </li>
      <li><codeph>optimizer_force_three_stage_scalar_dqa</codeph> forces GPORCA to choose a plan
        with multistage aggregates when such a plan alternative is generated. </li>
      <li><codeph>optimizer_join_order</codeph> sets the query optimization level for join ordering
        by specifying which types of join ordering alternatives to evaluate.</li>
      <li><codeph>optimizer_join_order_threshold</codeph> specifies the maximum number of join
        children for which GPORCA uses the dynamic programming-based join ordering algorithm.</li>
      <li><codeph>optimizer_nestloop_factor</codeph> controls nested loop join cost factor to apply
        to during query optimization.</li>
      <li><codeph>optimizer_parallel_union</codeph> controls the amount of parallelization that
        occurs for queries that contain a <codeph>UNION</codeph> or <codeph>UNION ALL</codeph>
        clause. When the value is <codeph>on</codeph>, GPORCA can generate a query plan the child
        operations of a <codeph>UNION</codeph> or <codeph>UNION ALL</codeph> operation execute in
        parallel on segment instances. </li>
      <li><codeph>optimizer_sort_factor</codeph> controls the cost factor that GPORCA applies to
        sorting operations during query optimization. The cost factor can be adjusted for queries
        when data skew is present. </li>
    </ul>
    <p>These server configuration parameters control the display and logging of information.</p>
    <ul id="ul_t3j_fhw_xz">
      <li><codeph>optimizer_print_missing_stats</codeph> controls the display of column information
        about columns with missing statistics for a query (default is <codeph>true</codeph>)</li>
      <li><codeph>optimizer_print_optimization_stats</codeph> controls the logging of GPORCA query
        optimization metrics for a query (default is <codeph>off</codeph>)</li>
    </ul>
    <p> For information about the parameters, see the <cite>Greenplum Database Reference
        Guide</cite>.</p>
    <p>GPORCA generates minidumps to describe the optimization context for a given query. <ph
        otherprops="pivotal"
        >The minidump files are used by Pivotal support to analyze Greenplum
        Database issues. </ph>The information in the file is not in a format that can be easily used
      for debugging or troubleshooting. The minidump file is located under the master data directory
      and uses the following naming format:</p>
    <p>
      <codeph>Minidump_<varname>date</varname>_<varname>time</varname>.mdp</codeph>
    </p>
    <p>For information about the minidump file, see the server configuration parameter
        <codeph>optimizer_minidump</codeph> in the <cite>Greenplum Database Reference
      Guide</cite>.</p>
    <p>When the <codeph>EXPLAIN ANALYZE</codeph> command uses GPORCA, the <codeph>EXPLAIN</codeph>
      plan shows only the number of partitions that are being eliminated. The scanned partitions are
      not shown. To show the name of the scanned partitions in the segment logs set the server
      configuration parameter <codeph>gp_log_dynamic_partition_pruning</codeph> to
        <codeph>on</codeph>. This example <codeph>SET</codeph> command enables the parameter.</p>
    <p>
      <codeblock>SET gp_log_dynamic_partition_pruning = on;</codeblock>
    </p>
  </body>
</topic>
