<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title>Enabling GPORCA</title>
  <abstract>
    <shortdesc>To GPORCA, you set Greenplum Database server
      configuration parameters.</shortdesc>
  </abstract>
  <body>
    <ul id="ul_o5l_tqk_br">
      <li><xref format="dita" href="#topic_r5d_hv1_kr">Set the
            <codeph>optimizer_analyze_root_partition</codeph> parameter to
          <codeph>on</codeph></xref> to enable statistics collection for the root partition of a
        partitioned table.</li>
      <li>Set the <cmdname>optimizer</cmdname> parameter to <codeph>on</codeph> to enable GPORCA. You can set the parameter at these levels:<ul id="ul_frw_y51_kr">
          <li><xref href="#topic_byp_lqk_br" format="dita">A Greenplum Database
              system</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="#topic_pzr_3db_3r" format="dita">A specific Greenplum database</xref></li>
          <li><xref href="#topic_lx4_vqk_br" format="dita">A session or query</xref></li>
        </ul></li>
    </ul>
    <note>You can disable the ability to enable or disable GPORCA with the
      server configuration parameter <cmdname>optimizer_control</cmdname>. For information about the
      server configuration parameters, see the <cite>Greenplum Database Reference
        Guide</cite>.</note>
    <note type="important">If you intend to execute queries on partitioned tables with GPORCA enabled, you must collect statistics on the partitioned table root partition
      with the <cmdname>ANALYZE ROOTPARTITION</cmdname> command. The command <codeph>ANALYZE
        ROOTPARTITION</codeph> collects statistics on the root partition of a partitioned table
      based on the data in the table. Statistics are not collected on the leaf partitions, leaf
      partition data is only sampled. If you specify a list of column names for a partitioned table,
      the statistics for the columns and the root partition are collected. For information on the
        <cmdname>ANALYZE</cmdname> command, see the <cite>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</cite>.<p>You can also use the Greenplum Database utility <codeph>analyzedb</codeph> to update table statistics. The
          Greenplum Database utility <codeph>analyzedb</codeph> can update statistics
        for multiple tables in parallel. The utility can also check table statistics and update
        statistics only if the statistics are not current or do not exist. For information about the
          <codeph>analyzedb</codeph> utility, see the <cite>Greenplum Database Utility
          Guide</cite>.</p><p>As part of routine database maintenance, Refresh statistics on
        the root partition when there are significant changes to leaf partition data.</p></note>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_r5d_hv1_kr">
    <title>Setting the optimizer_analyze_root_partition Parameter</title>
    <body>
      <p>When the configuration parameter <codeph>optimizer_analyze_root_partition</codeph> is set
        to <codeph>on</codeph>, root partition statistics will be collected when
          <cmdname>ANALYZE</cmdname> is run on a partitioned table. Root partition statistics are
        required by GPORCA.</p>
      <ol id="ol_n22_hv1_kr">
        <li>Log into the Greenplum Database master host as <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>,
          the Greenplum Database administrator.</li>
        <li>Set the values of the server configuration parameters. These Greenplum Database
          <cmdname>gpconfig</cmdname> utility commands sets the value of the parameters to
            <codeph>on</codeph>:<codeblock>$ gpconfig -c optimizer_analyze_root_partition -v on --masteronly</codeblock></li>
        <li>Restart Greenplum Database. This Greenplum Database
          <cmdname>gpstop</cmdname> utility command reloads the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph>
          files of the master and segments without shutting down Greenplum Database.
          <codeblock>gpstop -u</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_byp_lqk_br">
    <title>Enabling GPORCA for a System</title>
    <body>
      <p>Set the server configuration parameter <cmdname>optimizer</cmdname> for the Greenplum Database system.</p>
      <ol id="ol_a5s_2sl_vp">
        <li>Log into the Greenplum Database master host as <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>,
          the Greenplum Database administrator.</li>
        <li>Set the values of the server configuration parameters. These Greenplum Database
          <cmdname>gpconfig</cmdname> utility commands sets the value of the parameters to
            <codeph>on</codeph>:<codeblock>$ gpconfig -c optimizer -v on --masteronly</codeblock></li>
        <li>Restart Greenplum Database. This Greenplum Database
          <cmdname>gpstop</cmdname> utility command reloads the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph>
          files of the master and segments without shutting down Greenplum Database.
          <codeblock>gpstop -u</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_pzr_3db_3r">
    <title>Enabling GPORCA for a Database</title>
    <body>
      <p>Set the server configuration parameter <cmdname>optimizer</cmdname> for individual Greenplum databases with the <cmdname>ALTER DATABASE</cmdname>
        command. For example, this command enables GPORCA for the database
          <i>test_db</i>.<codeblock>> ALTER DATABASE test_db SET OPTIMIZER = ON ;</codeblock></p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_lx4_vqk_br">
    <title>Enabling GPORCA for a Session or a Query</title>
    <body>
      <p>You can use the <cmdname>SET</cmdname> command to set <cmdname>optimizer</cmdname> server
        configuration parameter for a session. For example, after you use the
          <cmdname>psql</cmdname> utility to connect to Greenplum Database, this
          <cmdname>SET</cmdname> command enables GPORCA:<codeblock>> set optimizer = on ;</codeblock></p>
      <p>To set the parameter for a specific query, include the <cmdname>SET</cmdname> command prior
        to running the query.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
