<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Preparing and Adding Hosts</title>
  <shortdesc>Verify your new host systems are ready for integration into the existing Greenplum
    system. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>To prepare new host systems for expansion, install the Greenplum Database software binaries,
      exchange the required SSH keys, and run performance tests. </p>
    <p>Run performance tests first on the new hosts and then all hosts. Run the tests on all hosts
      with the system offline so user activity does not distort results.</p>
    <p>Generally, you should run performance tests when an administrator modifies host networking or
      other special conditions in the system. For example, if you will run the expanded system on
      two network clusters, run tests on each cluster.</p>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic18" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="no159311">Adding New Hosts to the Trusted Host Environment</title>
    <body>
      <p>New hosts must exchange SSH keys with the existing hosts to enable Greenplum administrative
        utilities to connect to all segments without a password prompt. Perform the key exchange
        process twice with the <codeph><xref
            href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpssh-exkeys.xml">gpssh-exkeys</xref></codeph>
        utility.</p>
      <p>First perform the process as <codeph>root</codeph>, for administration convenience, and
        then as the user <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>, for management utilities. Perform the following
        tasks in order:</p>
      <ol>
        <li id="no160532">
          <xref href="#topic18/no160715" type="section" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="no160536">
          <xref href="#topic18/no160595" type="section" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="no160713">
          <xref href="#topic18/sshexch_gpadmin" type="section" format="dita"/>
        </li>
      </ol>
      <note type="note">The Greenplum Database segment host naming convention is
          <codeph>sdwN</codeph> where <codeph>sdw</codeph> is a prefix and <codeph>N</codeph> is an
        integer ( <codeph>sdw1</codeph>, <codeph>sdw2</codeph> and so on). For hosts with multiple
        interfaces, the convention is to append a dash (<codeph>-</codeph>) and number to the host
        name. For example, <codeph>sdw1-1</codeph> and <codeph>sdw1-2</codeph> are the two interface
        names for host <codeph>sdw1</codeph>. </note>
      <section id="no160715">
        <title>To exchange SSH keys as root</title>
        <ol id="ol_k3b_xjr_g4">
          <li id="no182144">Create a host file with the existing host names in your array and a
            separate host file with the new expansion host names. For existing hosts, you can use
            the same host file used to set up SSH keys in the system. In the files, list all hosts
            (master, backup master, and segment hosts) with one name per line and no extra lines or
            spaces. Exchange SSH keys using the configured host names for a given host if you use a
            multi-NIC configuration. In this example, <codeph>mdw</codeph> is configured with a
            single NIC, and <codeph>sdw1</codeph>, <codeph>sdw2</codeph>, and <codeph>sdw3</codeph>
            are configured with 4
            NICs:<codeblock>mdw
sdw1-1
sdw1-2
sdw1-3
sdw1-4
sdw2-1
sdw2-2
sdw2-3
sdw2-4
sdw3-1
sdw3-2
sdw3-3
sdw3-4</codeblock></li>
          <li id="no175582">Log in as <codeph>root</codeph> on the master host, and source the
              <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> file from your Greenplum
            installation.<codeblock>$ su - 
# source /usr/local/greenplum-db/greenplum_path.sh</codeblock></li>
          <li id="no160584">Run the <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> utility referencing the host list
            files. For
            example:<codeblock># gpssh-exkeys -e /home/gpadmin/<i>existing_hosts_file</i> -x 
/home/gpadmin/<i>new_hosts_file</i></codeblock></li>
          <li id="no160589"><codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> checks the remote hosts and performs the
            key exchange between all hosts. Enter the <codeph>root</codeph> user password when
            prompted. For
            example:<codeblock>***Enter password for root@<i>hostname</i>: <i>&lt;root_password&gt;</i></codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section id="no160595">
        <title>To create the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user</title>
        <ol id="ol_amb_xjr_g4">
          <li id="no160603">Use <codeph><xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpssh.xml"
                >gpssh</xref></codeph> to create the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user on all the new
            segment hosts (if it does not exist already). Use the list of new hosts you created for
            the key exchange. For
            example:<codeblock># gpssh -f <i>new_hosts_file</i> '/usr/sbin/useradd <i>gpadmin</i> -d 
/home/<i>gpadmin</i> -s /bin/bash'</codeblock></li>
          <li id="no160614">Set a password for the new <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user. On Linux, you
            can do this on all segment hosts simultaneously using <codeph>gpssh</codeph>. For
            example:<codeblock># gpssh -f <i>new_hosts_file</i> 'echo <i>gpadmin_password</i> | passwd 
gpadmin --stdin'</codeblock></li>
          <li id="no160642">Verify the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user has been created by looking for
            its home
            directory:<codeblock># gpssh -f <i>new_hosts_file</i> ls -l /home</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
      <section id="sshexch_gpadmin">
        <title>To exchange SSH keys as the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user</title>
        <ol id="ol_lpb_xjr_g4">
          <li id="no162532">Log in as <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> and run the
              <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> utility referencing the host list files. For
            example:<codeblock># gpssh-exkeys -e /home/gpadmin/<i>existing_hosts_file</i> -x 
/home/gpadmin/<i>new_hosts_file</i></codeblock></li>
          <li id="no160664"><codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> will check the remote hosts and perform
            the key exchange between all hosts. Enter the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user password
            when prompted. For
            example:<codeblock>***Enter password for gpadmin@<i>hostname</i>: <i>&lt;gpadmin_password&gt;</i></codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic20" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="no159219">Validating Disk I/O and Memory Bandwidth</title>
    <body>
      <p>Use the <codeph><xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpcheckperf.xml"
            >gpcheckperf</xref></codeph> utility to test disk I/O and memory bandwidth. </p>
      <section id="no159247">
        <title>To run gpcheckperf</title>
        <ol>
          <li id="no159250">Run the <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> utility using the host file for new
            hosts. Use the <codeph>-d</codeph> option to specify the file systems you want to test
            on each host. You must have write access to these directories. For
            example:<codeblock>$ gpcheckperf -f <i>new_hosts_file</i> -d /data1 -d /data2 -v </codeblock></li>
          <li id="no159252">The utility may take a long time to perform the tests because it is
            copying very large files between the hosts. When it is finished, you will see the
            summary results for the Disk Write, Disk Read, and Stream tests.</li>
        </ol>
        <p>For a network divided into subnets, repeat this procedure with a separate host file for
          each subnet.</p>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic21" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Integrating New Hardware into the System</title>
    <body>
      <p>Before initializing the system with the new segments, shut down the system with
          <codeph>gpstop</codeph> to prevent user activity from skewing performance test results.
        Then, repeat the performance tests using host files that include <i>all</i> hosts, existing
        and new.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
