<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Expanding a Greenplum System</title>
  <shortdesc>To scale up performance and storage capacity, expand your Greenplum Database system by
    adding hosts to the system. In general, adding nodes to a Greenplum cluster achieves a linear scaling 
    of performance and storage capacity. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Data warehouses typically grow over time as additional data is gathered and the retention
      periods increase for existing data. At times, it is necessary to increase database capacity to
      consolidate different data warehouses into a single database. Additional computing capacity
      (CPU) may also be needed to accommodate newly added analytics projects. Although it is wise to
      provide capacity for growth when a system is initially specified, it is not generally possible
      to invest in resources long before they are required. Therefore, you should expect to execute
      a database expansion project periodically. </p>
    <p>Because of the Greenplum MPP architecture, when you add resources to the system, the capacity
      and performance are the same as if the system had been originally implemented with the added
      resources. Unlike data warehouse systems that require substantial downtime in order to dump
      and restore the data, expanding a Greenplum Database system is a phased process with minimal
      downtime. Regular and ad hoc workloads can continue while data is redistributed and
      transactional consistency is maintained. The administrator can schedule the distribution
      activity to fit into ongoing operations and can pause and resume as needed. Tables can be
      ranked so that datasets are redistributed in a prioritized sequence, either to ensure that
      critical workloads benefit from the expanded capacity sooner, or to free disk space needed to
      redistribute very large tables.</p>
    <p>The expansion process uses standard Greenplum Database operations so it is transparent and
      easy for administrators to troubleshoot. Segment mirroring and any replication mechanisms in
      place remain active, so fault-tolerance is uncompromised and disaster recovery measures remain
      effective. </p>
  </body>
</topic>
