<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic28" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="expand-redistribute">Redistributing Tables</title>
  <shortdesc>Redistribute tables to balance existing data over the newly expanded cluster. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>After creating an expansion schema, you can redistribute tables across the entire system with
          <codeph><xref href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpexpand.xml"
        >gpexpand</xref></codeph>. Plan to run this during low-use hours when the utility's CPU
      usage and table locks have minimal impact on operations. Rank tables to redistribute the
      largest or most critical tables first.</p>
    <note>When redistributing data, Greenplum Database must be running in production mode. Greenplum
      Database cannot be in restricted mode or in master mode. The <codeph><xref
          href="../../utility_guide/ref/gpstart.xml">gpstart</xref></codeph> options
        <codeph>-R</codeph> or <codeph>-m</codeph> cannot be specified to start Greenplum
      Database.</note>
    <p>While table redistribution is underway, any new tables or partitions created are distributed
      across all segments exactly as they would be under normal operating conditions. Queries can
      access all segments, even before the relevant data is redistributed to tables on the new
      segments. The table or partition being redistributed is locked and unavailable for read or
      write operations. When its redistribution completes, normal operations resume.</p>
    <ul id="ul_qt5_xbv_mr">
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic29" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic30" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li>
        <xref href="#topic31" format="dita"/>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic29" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="no161370">Ranking Tables for Redistribution</title>
    <body>
      <p>For large systems, you can control the table redistribution order. Adjust tables'
          <codeph>rank</codeph> values in the expansion schema to prioritize heavily-used tables and
        minimize performance impact. Available free disk space can affect table ranking; see <xref
          href="expand-planning.xml#topic11" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</p>
      <p>To rank tables for redistribution by updating <codeph>rank</codeph> values in <i><xref
            href="../../ref_guide/system_catalogs/gp_expansion_tables.xml"
            >gpexpand.status_detail</xref></i>, connect to Greenplum Database using
          <codeph>psql</codeph> or another supported client. Update <i>gpexpand.status_detail</i>
        with commands such as:</p>
      <codeblock>=&gt; UPDATE gpexpand.status_detail SET rank=10;

=&gt; UPDATE gpexpand.status_detail SET rank=1 WHERE fq_name = 'public.lineitem';
=&gt; UPDATE gpexpand.status_detail SET rank=2 WHERE fq_name = 'public.orders';</codeblock>
      <p>These commands lower the priority of all tables to <codeph>10</codeph> and then assign a
        rank of <codeph>1</codeph> to <codeph>lineitem</codeph> and a rank of <codeph>2</codeph> to
          <codeph>orders</codeph>. When table redistribution begins, <codeph>lineitem</codeph> is
        redistributed first, followed by <codeph>orders</codeph> and all other tables in
          <i>gpexpand.status_detail</i>. To exclude a table from redistribution, remove the table
        from the <i>gpexpand.status_detail</i> table. </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic30" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Redistributing Tables Using gpexpand</title>
    <body>
      <section id="no162282">
        <title>To redistribute tables with gpexpand</title>
        <ol>
          <li id="no162285">Log in on the master host as the user who will run your Greenplum
            Database system, for example, <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>.</li>
          <li id="no162763">Run the <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> utility. You can use the
              <codeph>-d</codeph> or <codeph>-e</codeph> option to define the expansion session time
            period. For example, to run the utility for up to 60 consecutive
              hours:<codeblock>$ gpexpand -d 60:00:00</codeblock><p>The utility redistributes tables
              until the last table in the schema completes or it reaches the specified duration or
              end time. <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> updates the status and time in <i><xref
                  href="../../ref_guide/system_catalogs/gp_expansion_status.xml"
                  >gpexpand.status</xref></i> when a session starts and finishes.</p></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic31" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Monitoring Table Redistribution</title>
    <body>
      <p>You can query the expansion schema during the table redistribution process. The view
            <i><xref href="../../ref_guide/system_catalogs/gpexpand_expansion_progress.xml"
            >gpexpand.expansion_progress</xref></i> provides a current progress summary, including
        the estimated rate of table redistribution and estimated time to completion. You can query
        the table <i><xref href="../../ref_guide/system_catalogs/gp_expansion_tables.xml"
            >gpexpand.status_detail</xref></i> for per-table status information.</p>
      <p>See also <xref href="expand-initialize.xml#topic_wkv_kkd_chb"/> for information about
        monitoring the overall expansion progress with the <codeph>gpstate</codeph> utility.</p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic32" xml:lang="en">
      <title>Viewing Expansion Status</title>
      <body>
        <p>After the first table completes redistribution, <i>gpexpand.expansion_progress</i>
          calculates its estimates and refreshes them based on all tables' redistribution rates.
          Calculations restart each time you start a table redistribution session with
            <codeph>gpexpand</codeph>. To monitor progress, connect to Greenplum Database using
            <codeph>psql</codeph> or another supported client; query
            <i>gpexpand.expansion_progress</i> with a command like the following:</p>
        <p>
          <codeblock>=# SELECT * FROM gpexpand.expansion_progress;
             name             |         value
------------------------------+-----------------------
 Bytes Left                   | 5534842880
 Bytes Done                   | 142475264
 Estimated Expansion Rate     | 680.75667095996092 MB/s
 Estimated Time to Completion | 00:01:01.008047
 Tables Expanded              | 4
 Tables Left                  | 4
(6 rows)</codeblock>
        </p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic33" xml:lang="en">
      <title>Viewing Table Status</title>
      <body>
        <p>The table <i>gpexpand.status_detail</i> stores status, time of last update, and more
          facts about each table in the schema. To see a table's status, connect to Greenplum
          Database using <codeph>psql</codeph> or another supported client and query
            <i>gpexpand.status_detail</i>:</p>
        <p>
          <codeblock>=&gt; SELECT status, expansion_started, source_bytes FROM
gpexpand.status_detail WHERE fq_name = 'public.sales';
  status   |     expansion_started      | source_bytes
-----------+----------------------------+--------------
 COMPLETED | 2017-02-20 10:54:10.043869 |   4929748992
(1 row)</codeblock>
        </p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</topic>
