<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="about_monitoring">
  <title>About Management and Monitoring Utilities</title>
  <shortdesc>Greenplum Database provides standard command-line utilities for performing common
    monitoring and administration tasks. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum command-line utilities are located in the
        <filepath><varname>$GPHOME</varname>/bin</filepath> directory and are executed on the master
      host. Greenplum provides utilities for the following administration tasks:</p>
    <ul id="ul_mtm_tsv_fp">
      <li>Installing Greenplum Database on an array</li>
      <li>Initializing a Greenplum Database System</li>
      <li>Starting and stopping Greenplum Database</li>
      <li>Adding or removing a host</li>
      <li>Expanding the array and redistributing tables among new segments</li>
      <li>Managing recovery for failed segment instances</li>
      <li>Managing failover and recovery for a failed master instance</li>
      <li>Backing up and restoring a database (in parallel)</li>
      <li>Loading data in parallel</li>
      <li>Transferring data between Greenplum databases</li>
      <li>System state reporting</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Pivotal provides an optional system monitoring and management tool, Greenplum Command
      Center, which administrators can install and enable with Greenplum Database.
      Greenplum Command Center depends upon a dedicated database in Greenplum Database,
      named <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph>, which is used to collect and store system metrics.
      Data collection agents on the segments send their data to the Greenplum master at
      regular intervals (typically every 15 seconds).</p>
    <p> Greenplum Database includes a <codeph>gpperfmon_install</codeph> management utility,
      which creates the <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph> database and enables the data
      collection agents. Users can query the <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph> database to see
      query and system metrics. </p>
    <p>Administrators can install Greenplum Command Center, available separately from
      Greenplum Database, to provide a graphical web-based user interface for viewing the
      system metrics and to perform additional system management tasks. For more
      information about Greenplum Command Center, see the <xref
        href="https://gpcc.docs.pivotal.io" format="html" scope="external">Greenplum
        Command Center documentation</xref>.</p>
    <image href="../graphics/cc_arch_gpdb.png" id="image_mt4_ltv_fp"/>
  </body>
</topic>
