<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="about_monitoring">
  <title>About Management and Monitoring Utilities</title>
  <shortdesc>Greenplum Database provides standard command-line utilities for performing common
    monitoring and administration tasks. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum command-line utilities are located in the
        <filepath><varname>$GPHOME</varname>/bin</filepath> directory and are executed on the master
      host. Greenplum provides utilities for the following administration tasks:</p>
    <ul id="ul_mtm_tsv_fp">
      <li>Installing Greenplum Database on an array</li>
      <li>Initializing a Greenplum Database System</li>
      <li>Starting and stopping Greenplum Database</li>
      <li>Adding or removing a host</li>
      <li>Expanding the array and redistributing tables among new segments</li>
      <li>Managing recovery for failed segment instances</li>
      <li>Managing failover and recovery for a failed master instance</li>
      <li>Backing up and restoring a database (in parallel)</li>
      <li>Loading data in parallel</li>
      <li>Transferring data between Greenplum databases</li>
      <li>System state reporting</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Greenplum provides an optional system monitoring and management tool that administrators can
      install and enable with Greenplum Database. Greenplum Command Center uses data collection
      agents on each segment host to collect and store Greenplum system metrics in a dedicated
      database. Segment data collection agents send their data to the Greenplum master at regular
      intervals (typically every 15 seconds). Users can query the Command Center database to see
      query and system metrics. Greenplum Command Center has a graphical web-based user interface
      for viewing system metrics, which administrators can install separately from Greenplum
      Database. For more information, see the Greenplum Command Center documentation.</p>
    <image href="../../graphics/cc_arch_gpdb.png" id="image_mt4_ltv_fp"/>
  </body>
</topic>
