<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="about_monitoring">
  <title>About Management and Monitoring Utilities</title>
  <shortdesc>Greenplum Database provides standard command-line utilities for performing common
    monitoring and administration tasks. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum command-line utilities are located in the
        <filepath><varname>$GPHOME</varname>/bin</filepath> directory and are executed on the master
      host. Greenplum provides utilities for the following administration tasks:</p>
    <ul id="ul_mtm_tsv_fp">
      <li>Installing Greenplum Database on an array</li>
      <li>Initializing a Greenplum Database System</li>
      <li>Starting and stopping Greenplum Database</li>
      <li>Adding or removing a host</li>
      <li>Expanding the array and redistributing tables among new segments</li>
      <li>Managing recovery for failed segment instances</li>
      <li>Managing failover and recovery for a failed master instance</li>
      <li>Backing up and restoring a database (in parallel)</li>
      <li>Loading data in parallel</li>
      <li>Transferring data between Greenplum databases</li>
      <li>System state reporting</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Greenplum Database includes an optional performance management database that contains query
      status information and system metrics. The <codeph>gpperfmon_install</codeph> management
      utility creates the database, named <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph>, and enables data collection
      agents that execute on the Greenplum Database master and segment hosts. Data collection agents on the
      segment hosts collect query status from the segments, as well as system metrics such as CPU
      and memory utilization. An agent on the master host periodically (typically every 15 seconds)
      retrieves the data from the segment host agents and updates the <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph>
      database. Users can query the <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph> database to see the query and system
      metrics. </p>
    <p otherprops="pivotal">Pivotal provides an optional system monitoring and management tool,
      Greenplum Command Center, which administrators can install and enable with Greenplum Database.
      Greenplum Command Center provides a web-based user interface for viewing system metrics and
      allows administrators to perform additional system management tasks. For more information
      about Greenplum Command Center, see the <xref href="https://gpcc.docs.pivotal.io"
        format="html" scope="external">Greenplum Command Center documentation</xref>.</p>
    <fig id="kf145043" otherprops="pivotal">
      <title>Greenplum Command Center Architecture</title>
      <image href="../graphics/cc_arch_gpdb.png" placement="break" width="299px" height="304px"
        id="image_uyw_k2k_r1b"/>
    </fig>
  </body>
</topic>
