<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN"
"ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="about_ha" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="iw157531">About Redundancy and Failover in Greenplum Database</title>
  <shortdesc>This topic provides a high-level overview of Greenplum Database high availability
    features.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>You can deploy Greenplum Database without a single point of failure by mirroring components.
      The following sections describe the strategies for mirroring the main components of a
      Greenplum system. For a more detailed overview of Greenplum high availability features, see
        <xref
        href="../highavail/topics/g-overview-of-high-availability-in-greenplum-database.xml#topic2"
      />.</p>
    <note type="important">When data loss is not acceptable for a Greenplum Database cluster,
      Greenplum master and segment mirroring is recommended. If mirroring is not enabled then
      Greenplum stores only one copy of the data, so the underlying storage media provides the only
      guarantee for data availability and correctness in the event of a hardware failure.<p
        otherprops="pivotal">Kubernetes enables quick recovery from both pod and host failures, and
        Kubernetes storage services provide a high level of availability for the underlying data.
        Furthermore, virtualized environments make it difficult to ensure the anti-affinity
        guarantees required for Greenplum mirroring solutions. For these reasons, mirrorless
        deployments are fully supported with Greenplum for Kubernetes. Other deployment environments
        are generally not supported for production use unless both Greenplum master and segment
        mirroring are enabled.</p></note>
    <section id="segment_mirroring" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="iw157552">About Segment Mirroring</title>
      <p>When you deploy your Greenplum Database system, you can configure <i>mirror</i> segment
        instances. Mirror segments allow database queries to fail over to a backup segment if the
        primary segment becomes unavailable. The mirror segment is kept current by a transaction log
        replication process, which synchronizes the data between the primary and mirror instances.
        Mirroring is strongly recommended for production systems<ph otherprops="pivotal"> and
          required for Pivotal support</ph>. </p>
      <p>As a best practice, the secondary (mirror) segment instance must always reside on a
        different host than its primary segment instance to protect against a single host failure.
        In virtualized environments, the secondary (mirror) segment must always reside on a
        different storage system than the primary. Mirror segments can be arranged over the
        remaining hosts in the cluster in configurations designed to maximize availability, or
        minimize the performance degradation when hosts or multiple primary segments fail. </p>
      <p>Two standard mirroring configurations are available when you initialize or expand a
        Greenplum system. The default configuration, called <i>group mirroring</i>, places all the
        mirrors for a host's primary segments on one other host in the cluster. The other standard
        configuration, <i>spread mirroring</i>, can be selected with a command-line option. Spread
        mirroring spreads each host's mirrors over the remaining hosts and requires that there are
        more hosts in the cluster than primary segments per host. </p>
      <p><xref format="dita" href="#about_ha/iw157574" type="fig"/> shows how table data is
        distributed across segments when spread mirroring is configured.</p>
      <fig id="iw157574">
        <title>Spread Mirroring in Greenplum Database</title>
        <image href="../graphics/spread-mirroring.png" placement="break" id="image_rvc_rfx_2fb"/>
      </fig>
    </section>
    <section id="segment_failover" xml:lang="en">
      <title>Segment Failover and Recovery</title>
      <p>When segment mirroring is enabled in a Greenplum Database system, the system will
        automatically fail over to the <i>mirror segment</i> instance if a <i>primary segment</i>
        instance becomes unavailable. A Greenplum Database system can remain operational if a
        segment instance or host goes down as long as all the data is available on the remaining
        active segment instances.</p>
      <p>If the master cannot connect to a segment instance, it marks that segment instance as down
        in the Greenplum Database system catalog and brings up the mirror segment in its place. A
        failed segment instance will remain out of operation until an administrator takes steps to
        bring that segment back online. An administrator can recover a failed segment while the
        system is up and running. The recovery process copies over only the changes that were missed
        while the segment was out of operation.</p>
      <p>If you do not have mirroring enabled, the system will automatically shut down if a segment
        instance becomes invalid. You must recover all failed segments before operations can
        continue.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="master_mirroring" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="iw157589">About Master Mirroring</title>
      <p>You can also optionally deploy a backup or mirror of the master instance on a separate host
        from the master host. The backup master instance (the <i>standby master</i>) serves as a
          <i>warm standby</i> in the event that the primary master host becomes non-operational. The
        standby master is kept current by a transaction log replication process, which synchronizes
        the data between the primary and standby master.</p>
      <p>If the primary master fails, the log replication process stops, and the standby master can
        be activated in its place. The switchover does not happen automatically, but must be
        triggered externally. Upon activation of the standby master, the replicated logs are used to
        reconstruct the state of the master host at the time of the last successfully committed
        transaction. The activated standby master effectively becomes the Greenplum Database master,
        accepting client connections on the master port (which must be set to the same port number
        on the master host and the backup master host).</p>
      <p>Since the master does not contain any user data, only the system catalog tables need to be
        synchronized between the primary and backup copies. When these tables are updated, changes
        are automatically copied over to the standby master to ensure synchronization with the
        primary master.</p>
      <fig id="iw157606">
        <title>Master Mirroring in Greenplum Database</title>
        <image height="165px" href="../graphics/standby_master.jpg" placement="break" width="271px"
        />
      </fig>
    </section>
    <section id="interconnect_redundancy" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="iw157609">About Interconnect Redundancy</title>
      <p>The <i>interconnect</i> refers to the inter-process communication between the segments and
        the network infrastructure on which this communication relies. You can achieve a highly
        available interconnect using by deploying dual Gigabit Ethernet switches on your network and
        redundant Gigabit connections to the Greenplum Database host (master and segment) servers.
        For performance reasons, 10-Gb Ethernet, or faster, is recommended. </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
