<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="ij138244">Text Analytics and Search</title>
  <body>
    <p>Greenplum Database offers two different methods for text search and analytics, <b>Greenplum
        Database full text search</b> and <b>Tanzu Greenplum Text</b>.</p>
    <section id="section_yby_nv1_rqb">
      <title>Greenplum Database Full Text Search</title>
      <p>Greenplum Database text search is PostgreSQL text search ported to the Greenplum Database
        MPP platform. Greenplum Database text search is immediately available to you, with no need
        to install and maintain additional software. For full details on this topic, see <xref
          href="../admin_guide/textsearch/intro.xml" format="dita" scope="peer">Greenplum Database
          text search</xref>.</p>
    </section>
    <section otherprops="Pivotal" id="section_ywf_4v1_rqb">
      <title>Tanzu Greenplum Text</title>
      <p>For advanced text analysis applications, VMWare also offers <xref
          href="http://gptext.docs.pivotal.io/330/topics/intro.html" format="html" scope="external"
            >Tanzu Greenplum Text</xref>, which integrates Greenplum Database with the Apache
        Solr text search platform. Tanzu Greenplum Text installs an Apache Solr cluster alongside
        your Greenplum Database cluster and provides Greenplum Database functions you can use to
        create Solr indexes, query them, and receive results in the database session.</p>
      <p>Both of these systems provide powerful, enterprise-quality document indexing and searching
        services. Tanzu Greeenplum Text, with Solr, has many capabilities that are not available
        with Greenplum Database text search. In particular, Tanzu Greenplum Text is better for
        advanced text analysis applications. For a comparative between these methods, see <xref
          href="../admin_guide/textsearch/intro.xml#gptext">Comparing Greenplum Database Text Search
          with Tanzu Greenplum Text</xref>.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
