<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="ij138244">Text Analytics and Search</title>
  <body>
    <p>Cloudberry Database offers two different methods for text search and analytics, <b>Cloudberry
        Database full text search</b> and <b>Tanzu Cloudberry Text</b>.</p>
    <section id="section_yby_nv1_rqb">
      <title>Cloudberry Database Full Text Search</title>
      <p>Cloudberry Database text search is PostgreSQL text search ported to the Cloudberry Database
        MPP platform. Cloudberry Database text search is immediately available to you, with no need
        to install and maintain additional software. For full details on this topic, see <xref
          href="../admin_guide/textsearch/intro.xml" format="dita" scope="peer">Cloudberry Database
          text search</xref>.</p>
    </section>
    <section otherprops="Pivotal" id="section_ywf_4v1_rqb">
      <title>Tanzu Cloudberry Text</title>
      <p>For advanced text analysis applications, VMWare also offers <xref
          href="http://gptext.docs.pivotal.io/330/topics/intro.html" format="html" scope="external"
            >Tanzu Cloudberry Text</xref>, which integrates Cloudberry Database with the Apache
        Solr text search platform. Tanzu Cloudberry Text installs an Apache Solr cluster alongside
        your Cloudberry Database cluster and provides Cloudberry Database functions you can use to
        create Solr indexes, query them, and receive results in the database session.</p>
      <p>Both of these systems provide powerful, enterprise-quality document indexing and searching
        services. Tanzu Greeenplum Text, with Solr, has many capabilities that are not available
        with Cloudberry Database text search. In particular, Tanzu Cloudberry Text is better for
        advanced text analysis applications. For a comparative between these methods, see <xref
          href="../admin_guide/textsearch/intro.xml#gptext">Comparing Cloudberry Database Text Search
          with Tanzu Cloudberry Text</xref>.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
