<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic9" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="im140259">Creating and Managing Tablespaces</title>
  <body>
    <p>Tablespaces allow database administrators to have multiple file systems per machine and
      decide how to best use physical storage to store database objects. They are named locations
      within a filespace in which you can create objects. Tablespaces allow you to assign different
      storage for frequently and infrequently used database objects or to control the I/O
      performance on certain database objects. For example, place frequently-used tables on file
      systems that use high performance solid-state drives (SSD), and place other tables on standard
      hard drives.</p>
    <p>A tablespace requires a file system location to store its database files. In Greenplum
      Database, the master and each segment (primary and mirror) require a distinct storage
      location. The collection of file system locations for all components in a Greenplum system is
      a <i>filespace</i>. Filespaces can be used by one or more tablespaces.</p>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic10" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="im199401">Creating a Filespace</title>
    <body>
      <p>A filespace sets aside storage for your Greenplum system. A filespace is a symbolic storage
        identifier that maps onto a set of locations in your Greenplum hosts' file systems. To
        create a filespace, prepare the logical file systems on all of your Greenplum hosts, then
        use the <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph> utility to define the filespace. You must be a database
        superuser to create a filespace.</p>
      <note type="note">Greenplum Database is not directly aware of the file system boundaries on
        your underlying systems. It stores files in the directories that you tell it to use. You
        cannot control the location on disk of individual files within a logical file system.</note>
      <section id="im178954">
        <title>To create a filespace using gpfilespace</title>
        <ol id="ol_ojl_hvy_sp">
          <li id="im178990">Log in to the Greenplum Database master as the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>
            user.<codeblock>$ su - <codeph>gpadmin</codeph></codeblock></li>
          <li id="im178959">Create a filespace configuration
            file:<codeblock>$ gpfilespace -o gpfilespace_config</codeblock></li>
          <li id="im179004">At the prompt, enter a name for the filespace, the primary segment file
            system locations, the mirror segment file system locations, and a master file system
            location. Primary and mirror locations refer to directories on segment hosts; the master
            location refers to a directory on the master host and standby master, if configured. For
            example, if your configuration has 2 primary and 2 mirror segments per
            host:<codeblock>Enter a name for this filespace&gt; fastdisk
primary location 1&gt; <i>/gpfs1/seg1
</i>primary location 2&gt; <i>/gpfs1/seg2
</i>mirror location 1&gt; <i>/gpfs2/mir1
</i>mirror location 2&gt; <i>/gpfs2/mir2
</i>master location&gt; <i>/gpfs1/master
</i></codeblock></li>
          <li id="im179011">gpfilespace creates a configuration file. Examine the file to verify
            that the gpfilespace configuration is correct. </li>
          <li id="im179508">Run gpfilespace again to create the filespace based on the configuration file:<p>
              <codeblock>$ gpfilespace -c gpfilespace_config</codeblock>
            </p></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic11" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Moving the Location of Temporary or Transaction Files</title>
    <body>
      <p>You can move temporary or transaction files to a specific filespace to improve database
        performance when running queries, creating backups, and to store data more sequentially. </p>
      <p>The dedicated filespace for temporary and transaction files is tracked in two separate flat
        files called gp_temporary_files_filespace and gp_transaction_files_filespace. These are
        located in the pg_system directory on each primary and mirror segment, and on master and
        standby. You must be a superuser to move temporary or transaction files. Only the
          <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph> utility can write to this file.</p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic12" xml:lang="en">
      <title>About Temporary and Transaction Files</title>
      <body>
        <p>Unless otherwise specified, temporary and transaction files are stored together with all
          user data. The default location of temporary files,
            <i>&lt;filespace_directory&gt;</i>/<i>&lt;tablespace_oid&gt;</i>/<i>&lt;database_oid&gt;</i>/pgsql_tmp
          is changed when you use <codeph>gpfilespace --movetempfiles</codeph> for the first time. </p>
        <p>Also note the following information about temporary or transaction files:</p>
        <ul id="ul_gkl_hvy_sp">
          <li id="im198887">You can dedicate only one filespace for temporary or transaction files,
            although you can use the same filespace to store other types of files.</li>
          <li id="im198888">You cannot drop a filespace if it used by temporary files.</li>
          <li id="im198892">You must create the filespace in advance. See <xref href="#topic10"
              type="topic" format="dita"/>.</li>
        </ul>
        <section id="im198893">
          <title>To move temporary files using gpfilespace</title>
          <ol id="ol_bll_hvy_sp">
            <li id="im198894">Check that the filespace exists and is different from the filespace
              used to store all other user data.</li>
            <li id="im198895">Issue smart shutdown to bring the Greenplum Database offline.<p>If any
                connections are still in progess,the gpfilespace --movetempfiles utility will
                fail.</p></li>
            <li id="im198897">Bring Greenplum Database online with no active session and run the
              following command:<p>
                <codeblock>gpfilespace --movetempfilespace filespace_name</codeblock>
              </p><p>The location of the temporary files is stored in the segment configuration
                shared memory (PMModuleState) and used whenever temporary files are created, opened,
                or dropped.</p></li>
          </ol>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>To move transaction files using gpfilespace</title>
          <ol id="ol_vll_hvy_sp">
            <li id="im198901">Check that the filespace exists and is different from the filespace
              used to store all other user data.</li>
            <li id="im198902">Issue smart shutdown to bring the Greenplum Database offline.<p>If any
                connections are still in progess, the <codeph>gpfilespace --movetransfiles</codeph>
                utility will fail.</p></li>
            <li id="im198904">Bring Greenplum Database online with no active session and run the
              following command:<p>
                <codeblock>gpfilespace --movetransfilespace filespace_name</codeblock>
              </p><p>The location of the transaction files is stored in the segment configuration
                shared memory (PMModuleState) and used whenever transaction files are created,
                opened, or dropped.</p></li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic13" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Creating a Tablespace</title>
    <body>
      <p>After you create a filespace, use the <codeph>CREATE TABLESPACE</codeph> command to define
        a tablespace that uses that filespace. For example:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>=# CREATE TABLESPACE fastspace FILESPACE fastdisk;
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>Database superusers define tablespaces and grant access to database users with the
          <codeph>GRANT</codeph><codeph>CREATE </codeph><ph>command</ph>. For example:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>=# GRANT CREATE ON TABLESPACE fastspace TO admin;
</codeblock>
      </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic14" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Using a Tablespace to Store Database Objects</title>
    <body>
      <p>Users with the <codeph>CREATE</codeph> privilege on a tablespace can create database
        objects in that tablespace, such as tables, indexes, and databases. The command is:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>CREATE TABLE tablename(options) TABLESPACE spacename
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>For example, the following command creates a table in the tablespace <i>space1</i>:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>CREATE TABLE foo(i int) TABLESPACE space1;
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>You can also use the <codeph>default_tablespace</codeph> parameter to specify the default
        tablespace for <codeph>CREATE TABLE</codeph> and <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph> commands that
        do not specify a tablespace:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>SET default_tablespace = space1;
CREATE TABLE foo(i int);
</codeblock>
      </p>
      <p>The tablespace associated with a database stores that database's system catalogs, temporary
        files created by server processes using that database, and is the default tablespace
        selected for tables and indexes created within the database, if no
          <codeph>TABLESPACE</codeph> is specified when the objects are created. If you do not
        specify a tablespace when you create a database, the database uses the same tablespace used
        by its template database.</p>
      <p>You can use a tablespace from any database if you have appropriate privileges.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic15" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Viewing Existing Tablespaces and Filespaces</title>
    <body>
      <p>Every Greenplum Database system has the following default tablespaces.</p>
      <ul id="ul_mml_hvy_sp">
        <li id="im200050"><codeph>pg_global</codeph> for shared system catalogs.</li>
        <li id="im200067"><codeph>pg_default</codeph>, the default tablespace. Used by the
            <i>template1</i> and <i>template0</i> databases. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>These tablespaces use the system default filespace, <codeph>pg_system</codeph>, the data
        directory location created at system initialization.</p>
      <p>To see filespace information, look in the <i>pg_filespace</i> and <i>pg_filespace_entry</i>
        catalog tables. You can join these tables with <i>pg_tablespace</i> to see the full
        definition of a tablespace. For example:</p>
      <p>
        <codeblock>=# SELECT spcname as tblspc, fsname as filespc, 
          fsedbid as seg_dbid, fselocation as datadir 
   FROM   pg_tablespace pgts, pg_filespace pgfs, 
          pg_filespace_entry pgfse 
   WHERE  pgts.spcfsoid=pgfse.fsefsoid 
          AND pgfse.fsefsoid=pgfs.oid 
   ORDER BY tblspc, seg_dbid;
</codeblock>
      </p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic16" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Dropping Tablespaces and Filespaces</title>
    <body>
      <p>To drop a tablespace, you must be the tablespace owner or a superuser. You cannot drop a
        tablespace until all objects in all databases using the tablespace are removed.</p>
      <p>Only a superuser can drop a filespace. A filespace cannot be dropped until all tablespaces
        using that filespace are removed.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>DROP TABLESPACE</codeph> command removes an empty tablespace.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>DROP FILESPACE</codeph> command removes an empty filespace.</p>
      <note type="note">You cannot drop a filespace if it stores temporary or transaction
        files.</note>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
