<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_dn2_52b_3lb">
  <title>Best Practices when Creating Views</title>
  <body>
    <p>When defining and using a view, remember that a view is just an SQL statement and is replaced
      by its definition when the query is run.</p>
    <p>These are some common uses of views.</p>
    <ul id="ul_jrc_15l_flb">
      <li>They allow you to have a recurring SQL query or expression in one place for easy
        reuse.</li>
      <li>They can be used as an interface to abstract from the actual table definitions, so that
        you can reorganize the tables without having to modify the interface.</li>
    </ul>
    <p>If a subquery is associated with a single query, consider using the <codeph>WITH</codeph>
      clause of the <codeph>SELECT</codeph> command instead of creating a seldom-used view.</p>
    <p>In general, these uses do not require nesting views, that is, defining views based on other
      views.</p>
    <p>These are two patterns of creating views that tend to be problematic because the view's SQL
      is used during query execution.</p>
    <ul id="ul_krc_15l_flb">
      <li>
        <p>Defining many layers of views so that your final queries look deceptively simple.</p>
        <p>Problems arise when you try to enhance or troubleshoot queries that use the views, for
          example by examining the execution plan. The query's execution plan tends to be
          complicated and it is difficult to understand and how to improve it.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>Defining a denormalized "world" view. A view that joins a large number of database tables
          that is used for a wide variety of queries.</p>
        <p>Performance issues can occur for some queries that use the view for some
            <codeph>WHERE</codeph> conditions while other <codeph>WHERE</codeph> conditions work
          well.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </body>
</topic>
