<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic11">
  <title>Checking for Failed Segments</title>
  <body>
    <p>With mirroring enabled, you can have failed segment instances in the system without
      interruption of service or any indication that a failure has occurred. You can verify the
      status of your system using the <codeph>gpstate</codeph> utility, by examing the contents of
      the <codeph>gp_segment_configuration</codeph> catalog table, or by checking log files.</p>
    <section id="use_gpstate">
      <title>Check for failed segments using gpstate</title>
      <p>The <codeph>gpstate</codeph> utility provides the status of each individual component of a
        Greenplum Database system, including primary segments, mirror segments, master, and standby
        master.</p>
      
       <p>On the master host, run the <xref
              href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpstate.xml" type="topic" format="dita"/>
          utility with the <codeph>-e</codeph> option to show segment instances with error
            conditions:<codeblock>$ gpstate -e</codeblock>
         If the utility lists <codeph>Segments
              with Primary and Mirror Roles Switched</codeph>, the segment is not in its
              <i>preferred role</i> (the role to which it was assigned at system initialization).
            This means the system is in a potentially unbalanced state, as some segment hosts may
            have more active segments than is optimal for top system performance. </p><p>Segments
            that display the <codeph>Config status</codeph> as <codeph>Down</codeph> indicate the
            corresponding mirror segment is down. </p><p>See <xref
              href="g-recovering-from-segment-failures.xml"/> for instructions to fix this
              situation.</p></section>
  
    <section id="select_from_table">
      <title>Check for failed segments using the gp_segment_configuration table</title> To get
      detailed information about failed segments, you can check the <xref
          href="../../../ref_guide/system_catalogs/gp_segment_configuration.xml"/> catalog
      table. For example:<p>
        <codeblock>$ psql postgres -c "SELECT * FROM gp_segment_configuration WHERE status='d';"</codeblock>
      </p> For failed segment instances, note the host, port, preferred role, and data directory.
      This information will help determine the host and segment instances to troubleshoot. To
      display information about mirror segment instances, run:<codeblock>$ gpstate -m</codeblock>
    </section>
    
    <section id="check_log_files">
      <title>Check for failed segments by examining log files</title>
    
    </section>
    <p>Log files can provide information to help determine an error's cause. The master and segment
      instances each have their own log file in <codeph>log</codeph> of the data directory. The
      master log file contains the most information and you should always check it first. </p>
    <p>Use the <xref href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gplogfilter.xml" type="topic"
          format="dita"/> utility to check the Greenplum Database log files for additional
      information. To check the segment log files, run <codeph>gplogfilter</codeph> on the segment
      hosts using <xref href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpssh.xml" type="topic"
          format="dita"/>.</p>
    <section id="ki170080">
      <title>To check the log files</title>
      <ol id="ol_ort_blb_yqb">
        <li id="ki168755">Use <codeph>gplogfilter</codeph> to check the master log file for
            <codeph>WARNING</codeph>, <codeph>ERROR</codeph>, <codeph>FATAL</codeph> or
            <codeph>PANIC</codeph> log level messages:<codeblock>$ gplogfilter -t</codeblock></li>
        <li id="ki166372">Use <codeph>gpssh</codeph> to check for <codeph>WARNING</codeph>,
            <codeph>ERROR</codeph>, <codeph>FATAL</codeph>, or <codeph>PANIC</codeph> log level
          messages on each segment instance. For
          example:<codeblock>$ gpssh -f seg_hosts_file -e 'source 
/usr/local/greenplum-db/greenplum_path.sh ; gplogfilter -t 
/data1/primary/*/log/gpdb*.log' &gt; seglog.out
</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </section>
        

  </body>
</topic>
