<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic11">
  <title>Checking for Failed Segments</title>
  <body>
    <p>With mirroring enabled, you can have failed segment instances in the system without
      interruption of service or any indication that a failure has occurred. You can verify the
      status of your system using the <codeph>gpstate</codeph> utility. <codeph>gpstate</codeph>
      provides the status of each individual component of a Greenplum Database system, including
      primary segments, mirror segments, master, and standby master.</p>
    <section id="ki155580">
      <title>To check for failed segments</title>
      <ol>
        <li id="ki155584">On the master host, run the <codeph><xref
              href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpstate.xml" type="topic" format="dita"
            /></codeph> utility with the <codeph>-e</codeph> option to show segment instances with
          error conditions:<codeblock>$ gpstate -e</codeblock><p>If the utility lists
              <codeph>Segments with Primary and Mirror Roles Switched</codeph>, the segment is not
            in its <i>preferred role</i> (the role to which it was assigned at system
            initialization). This means the system is in a potentially unbalanced state, as some
            segment hosts may have more active segments than is optimal for top system performance.
            </p><p>Segments that display the <codeph>Config status</codeph> as <codeph>Down</codeph>
            indicate the corresponding mirror segment is down. </p><p>See <xref
              href="g-recovering-from-segment-failures.xml#topic14"/> for instructions to fix this
            situation.</p></li>
        <li id="ki165350">To get detailed information about failed segments, you can check the
              <codeph><xref href="../../../ref_guide/system_catalogs/gp_segment_configuration.xml"
            /></codeph> catalog table. For example:<p>
            <codeblock>$ psql postgres -c "SELECT * FROM gp_segment_configuration WHERE status='d';"</codeblock>
          </p></li>
        <li id="ki162539">For failed segment instances, note the host, port, preferred role, and
          data directory. This information will help determine the host and segment instances to
          troubleshoot.</li>
        <li id="ki155591">To show information about mirror segment instances,
          run:<codeblock>$ gpstate -m</codeblock>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
