<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic8">
  <title>Enabling Master Mirroring</title>
  <body>
    <p>You can configure a new Greenplum Database system with a standby master using
        <codeph>gpinitsystem</codeph> or enable it later using <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph>. This
      topic assumes you are adding a standby master to an existing system that was initialized
      without one.</p>
    <p>For information about the utilities <codeph>gpinitsystem</codeph> and
        <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph>, see the <cite>Greenplum Database Utility
        Guide</cite>.</p>
    <section id="ki160203">
      <title>To add a standby master to an existing system</title>
      <ol>
        <li id="ki160206">Ensure the standby master host is installed and configured:
            <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> system user created, Greenplum Database binaries installed,
          environment variables set, SSH keys exchanged, and data directory created.</li>
        <li id="ki155475">Run the <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph> utility on the currently active
            <i>primary</i> master host to add a standby master host to your Greenplum Database system. For example:<codeblock>$ gpinitstandby -s smdw</codeblock>
          <p>Where <codeph>-s</codeph> specifies the standby master host name.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="ki155485">To switch operations to a standby master, see <xref
            href="g-recovering-a-failed-master.xml#topic16"/>.</li>
      </ol>
      <title>To check the status of the master mirroring process (optional)</title>
      <p>You can display the information in the Greenplum Database system view
        pg_stat_replication. The view lists information about the <codeph>walsender</codeph> process
        that is used for Greenplum Database master mirroring. For example, this
        command displays the process ID and state of the <codeph>walsender</codeph> process:</p>
      <codeblock>$ psql dbname -c 'SELECT procpid, state FROM pg_stat_replication;'</codeblock>
      <p>For information about the <codeph>pg_stat_replication</codeph> system
        view, see the <i>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</i>. </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
