<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic7">
  <title>Enabling Segment Mirroring</title>
  <body>
    <p>Mirror segments allow database queries to fail over to a backup segment if the primary
      segment is unavailable. By default, mirrors are configured on the same array of hosts as the
      primary segments. You may choose a completely different set of hosts for your mirror segments
      so they do not share machines with any of your primary segments.</p>
    <note type="important">During the online data replication process, Greenplum Database should be
      in a quiescent state, workloads and other queries should not be running.</note>
    <section id="ki169450">
      <title>To add segment mirrors to an existing system (same hosts as primaries)</title>
      <ol>
        <li id="ki156981">Allocate the data storage area for mirror data on all segment hosts. The
          data storage area must be different from your primary segments' file system location.</li>
        <li id="ki156983">Use <codeph><xref
              href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpssh-exkeys.xml" type="topic"
              format="dita"/></codeph> to ensure that the segment hosts can SSH and SCP to each
          other without a password prompt.</li>
        <li id="ki156993">Run the <codeph><xref
              href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpaddmirrors.xml" type="topic"
              format="dita"/></codeph> utility to enable mirroring in your Greenplum Database
          system. For example, to add 10000 to your primary segment port numbers to calculate the
          mirror segment port numbers:<codeblock>$ gpaddmirrors -p 10000</codeblock> Where
            <codeph>-p</codeph> specifies the number to add to your primary segment port numbers.
          Mirrors are added with the default group mirroring configuration. </li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>To add segment mirrors to an existing system (different hosts from primaries)</title>
      <ol>
        <li id="ki155416">Ensure the Greenplum Database software is installed on all hosts. <ph>See
            the <i>Greenplum Database Installation Guide</i> for detailed installation
            instructions.</ph></li>
        <li id="ki161799">Allocate the data storage area for mirror data, and tablespaces if needed,
          on all segment hosts.</li>
        <li id="ki160816">Use <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> to ensure the segment hosts can SSH and
          SCP to each other without a password prompt.</li>
        <li id="ki155422">Create a configuration file that lists the host names, ports, and data
          directories on which to create mirrors. To create a sample configuration file to use as a
          starting point,
            run:<codeblock>$ gpaddmirrors -o <i>filename</i>          </codeblock><p>The format of
            the mirror configuration file is:
            </p><codeblock><b><varname>row_id</varname></b>=<b><varname>contentID</varname></b>|<b><varname>address</varname></b>|<b><varname>port</varname></b>|<b><varname>data_dir</varname></b></codeblock><p>Where
              <codeph>row_id</codeph> is the row in the file, <varname>contentID</varname> is the
            segment instance content ID, <varname>address</varname> is the host name or IP address
            of the segment host, <varname>port</varname> is the communication port, and
              <codeph>data_dir</codeph> is the segment instance data directory.</p><p>For example,
            this is contents of a mirror configuration file for two segment hosts and two segment
            instances per
          host:</p><codeblock>0=2|sdw1-1|41000|/data/mirror1/gp2
1=3|sdw1-2|41001|/data/mirror2/gp3
2=0|sdw2-1|41000|/data/mirror1/gp0
3=1|sdw2-2|41001|/data/mirror2/gp1</codeblock></li>
        <li id="ki155430">Run the <codeph>gpaddmirrors</codeph> utility to enable mirroring in your
          Greenplum Database
            system:<codeblock>$ gpaddmirrors -i <i>mirror_config_file</i></codeblock><p>The
              <codeph>-i</codeph> option specifies the mirror configuration file you created.</p>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
