<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic3">
    <title>Overview of Segment Mirroring</title>
    <body>
        <p>When Greenplum Database High Availability is enabled, there are two types of segments:
                <i>primary</i> and <i>mirror</i>. Each primary segment has one corresponding mirror
            segment. A primary segment receives requests from the master to make changes to the
            segment's database and then replicates those changes to the corresponding mirror. If a
            primary segment becomes unavailable, database queries fail over to the mirror
            segment.</p>
        <p>Segment mirroring employs a physical file replication scheme—data file I/O at the primary
            is replicated to the secondary so that the mirror's files are identical to the primary's
            files. Data in Greenplum Database are represented with <i>tuples</i>, which are packed
            into <i>blocks</i>. Database tables are stored in disk files consisting of one or more
            blocks. A change to a tuple changes the block it is saved in, which is then written to
            disk on the primary and copied over the network to the mirror. The mirror updates the
            corresponding block in its copy of the file.</p>
        <p>For heap tables, blocks are saved in an in-memory cache until they are evicted to make
            room for newly changed blocks. This allows the system to read or update a block in
            memory multiple times without performing expensive disk I/O. When the block is evicted
            from the cache, it is written to disk and replicated to the secondary. While the block
            is held in cache, the primary and mirror have different images of the block. However,
            the databases are still consistent because the transaction log has been replicated. If a
            mirror takes over for a failed primary, the transactions in its log are applied to the
            database tables.</p>
        <p>Other database objects — for example filespaces, which are tablespaces internally
            represented with directories—also use file replication to perform various file
            operations in a synchronous way.</p>
        <p>Append-optimized tables do not use the in-memory caching mechanism. Changes made to
            append-optimized table blocks are replicated to the mirror immediately. Typically, file
            write operations are asynchronous, while opening, creating, and synchronizing files are
            "sync-replicated," which means the primary blocks until it receives the acknowledgment
            from the secondary. </p>
        <p>If a primary segment fails, the file replication process stops and the mirror segment
            automatically starts as the active segment instance. The now active mirror's system
            state becomes <i>Change Tracking</i>, which means the mirror maintains a system table
            and change-log of all blocks updated while the primary segment is unavailable. When the
            failed primary segment is repaired and ready to be brought back online, an administrator
            initiates a recovery process and the system goes into <i>Resynchronization</i> state.
            The recovery process applies the logged changes to the repaired primary segment. The
            system state changes to <i>Synchronized</i> when the recovery process completes.</p>
        <p>If the mirror segment fails or becomes inaccessible while the primary is active, the
            primary's system state changes to <i>Change Tracking</i>, and it tracks changes to be
            applied to the mirror when it is recovered.</p>
        <p>Mirror segments can be placed on hosts in the cluster in different configurations, as
            long as the primary and mirror instance for a segment are on different hosts. Each host
            must have the same number of primary and mirror segments. The default mirroring
            configuration is <i>group mirroring</i>, where the mirror segments for each host's
            primary segments are placed on one other host. If a single host fails, the number of
            active primary segments doubles on the host that backs the failed host. <xref
                href="#topic3/fig_rrr_nt2_xt" format="dita"/> illustrates a group mirroring
            configuration.  </p>
        <!--<fig id="ki169754"><image href="../../graphics/mirrorsegs.png" placement="break" width="485px" height="135px"/></fig>-->
        <fig id="fig_rrr_nt2_xt">
            <title>Group Segment Mirroring in Greenplum Database</title>
            <image href="../../graphics/group-mirroring.png" id="image_crm_pt2_xt"/>
        </fig>
        <p><i>Spread mirroring</i> spreads each host's mirrors over multiple hosts so that if any
            single host fails, no other host will have more than one mirror promoted to the active
            primary segment. Spread mirroring is possible only if there are more hosts than segments
            per host. <xref href="#topic3/fig_ew1_qgg_xt" format="dita"/> illustrates the placement
            of mirrors in a spread segment mirroring configuration.</p>
        <fig id="fig_ew1_qgg_xt">
            <title>Spread Segment Mirroring in Greenplum Database</title>
            <image href="../../graphics/spread-mirroring.png" id="image_zjm_wgg_xt"/>
        </fig>
        <p>The Greenplum Database utilities that create mirror segments support group and spread
            segment configurations. Custom mirroring configurations can be described in a
            configuration file and passed on the command line. </p>
    </body>
</topic>
