<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic5">
    <title>Overview of Fault Detection and Recovery</title>
    <body>
        <p>The Greenplum Database server (<codeph>postgres</codeph>) subprocess named
                <codeph>ftsprobe</codeph> handles fault detection. <codeph>ftsprobe</codeph>
            monitors the Greenplum Database array; it connects to and scans all
            segments and database processes at intervals that you can configure. </p>
        <p>If <codeph>ftsprobe</codeph> cannot connect to a segment, it marks the segment as "down"
            in the Greenplum Database system catalog. The segment remains
            nonoperational until an administrator initiates the recovery process.</p>
        <p>With mirroring enabled, Greenplum Database automatically fails over to a
            mirror copy if a primary copy becomes unavailable. The system is operational if a
            segment instance or host fails provided all data is available on the remaining active
            segments. </p>
        <p>To recover failed segments, an administrator runs the <codeph>gprecoverseg</codeph>
            recovery utility. This utility locates the failed segments, verifies they are valid, and
            compares the transactional state with the currently active segment to determine changes
            made while the segment was offline. <codeph>gprecoverseg</codeph> synchronizes the
            changed database files with the active segment and brings the segment back online.
            Administrators perform the recovery while Greenplum Database is up and
            running.</p>
        <p>With mirroring disabled, the system automatically shuts down if a segment instance fails.
            Administrators manually recover all failed segments before operations resume.</p>
        <p>See <xref href="g-detecting-a-failed-segment.xml#topic9"/> for a more
            detailed description of the fault detection and recovery process and configuration
            options. </p>
    </body>
</topic>
