<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic4">
    <title>Overview of Master Mirroring</title>
    <body>
        <p>You can deploy a backup or mirror of the master instance on a separate host machine or on
            the same host machine. A backup master or standby master serves as a warm standby if the
            primary master becomes nonoperational. You create a standby master from the primary
            master while the primary is online. </p>
        <p>The primary master continues to provide service to users while a transactional snapshot
            of the primary master instance is taken. While the transactional snapshot is taken and
            deployed on the standby master, changes to the primary master are also recorded. After
            the snapshot is deployed on the standby master, the updates are deployed to synchronize
            the standby master with the primary master.</p>
        <p>Once the primary master and standby master are synchronized, the standby master is kept
            up to date by the <codeph>walsender</codeph> and <codeph>walreceiver</codeph>
            replication processes. The <codeph>walreceiver</codeph> is a standby master process. The
                <codeph>walsender</codeph> process is a primary master process. The two processes
            use Write-Ahead Logging (WAL)-based streaming replication to keep the primary and
            standby masters synchronized. In WAL logging, all modifications are written to the log
            before being applied, to ensure data integrity for any in-process operations.<note>WAL
                logging is not yet available for segment mirroring.</note></p>
        <p>Since the master does not house user data, only system catalog tables are synchronized
            between the primary and standby masters. When these tables are updated, changes are
            automatically copied to the standby master to keep it current with the primary.</p>
        <fig id="ki155262">
            <title>Master Mirroring in Greenplum Database</title>
            <image href="../../graphics/standby_master.jpg" placement="break" width="271px"
                height="165px"/>
        </fig>
        <p>If the primary master fails, the replication process stops, and an administrator can
            activate the standby master. Upon activation of the standby master, the replicated logs
            reconstruct the state of the primary master at the time of the last successfully
            committed transaction. The activated standby then functions as the Greenplum Database master, accepting connections on the port specified when
            standby master was initialized.</p>
    </body>
</topic>
