<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic3">
    <title>Overview of Segment Mirroring</title>
    <body>
        <p>When Greenplum Database High Availability is enabled, there are two types of segment
            instances: <i>primary</i> and <i>mirror</i>. Each primary segment has one corresponding
            mirror segment. A primary segment instance receives requests from the master to make
            changes to the segment data and then replicates those changes to the corresponding
            mirror. If Greenplum Database detects that a primary segment has failed or become
            unavailable, it changes the role of its mirror segment to primary segment and the role
            of the unavailable primary segment to mirror segment. Transactions in progress when the
            failure occurred roll back and must be restarted. The administrator must then recover
            the mirror segment, allow the mirror to synchronize with the current primary segment, and
            then exchange the primary and mirror segments so they are in their preferred roles.</p>
        <p>If segment mirroring is not enabled, the Greenplum Database system shuts down if a
            segment instance fails. Administrators must manually recover all failed segments before
            Greenplum Database operations can resume.</p>
        <p>When segment mirroring is enabled for an existing system, the primary segment instances
            continue to provide service to users while a snapshot of the primary segments are taken.
            While the snapshots are taken and deployed on the mirror segment instances, changes to
            the primary segment are also recorded. After the snapshot has been deployed on the
            mirror segment, the mirror segment is synchronized and kept current using Write-Ahead
            Logging (WAL)-based streaming replication. Greenplum Database WAL replication uses the
                <codeph>walsender</codeph> and <codeph>walreceiver</codeph> replication processes.
            The <codeph>walsender</codeph> process is a primary segment process. The
                <codeph>walreceiver</codeph> is a mirror segment process. </p>
        <p>When database changes occur, the logs that capture the changes are streamed to the mirror
            segment to keep it current with the corresponding primary segments. During WAL
            replication, database changes are written to the logs before being applied, to ensure
            data integrity for any in-process operations. </p>
        <p>When Greenplum Database detects a primary segment failure, the WAL replication process
            stops and the mirror segment automatically starts as the active primary segment. If a
            mirror segment fails or becomes inaccessible while the primary is active, the primary
            segment tracks database changes in logs that are applied to the mirror when it is
            recovered. For information about segment fault detection and the recovery process, see
                <xref href="g-detecting-a-failed-segment.xml#topic9"/>. </p>
        <p>These Greenplum Database system catalog tables contain mirroring and replication
            information. <ul id="ul_nn3_yjm_rdb">
                <li>The catalog table <codeph><xref
                            href="../../../ref_guide/system_catalogs/gp_segment_configuration.xml#topic1"
                        /></codeph> contains the current configuration and state of primary and
                    mirror segment instances and the master and standby master instance. </li>
                <li>The catalog view <codeph><xref
                            href="../../../ref_guide/system_catalogs/gp_stat_replication.xml#topic1"
                        /></codeph> contains replication statistics of the
                        <codeph>walsender</codeph> processes that are used for Greenplum Database
                    master and segment mirroring.</li>
            </ul></p>
        <section>
            <title>About Segment Mirroring Configurations</title>
            <p>Mirror segment instances can be placed on hosts in the cluster in different
                configurations. As a best practice, a primary segment and the corresponding mirror
                are placed on different hosts. Each host must have the same number of primary and
                mirror segments. When you create segment mirrors with the Greenplum Database
                utilities <codeph><xref
                        href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpinitsystem.xml"/></codeph> or
                        <codeph><xref href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpaddmirrors.xml"
                    /></codeph> you can specify the segment mirror configuration, group mirroring
                (the default) or spread mirroring. With <codeph>gpaddmirrors</codeph>, you can
                create custom mirroring configurations with a <codeph>gpaddmirrors</codeph>
                configuration file and specify the file on the command line.</p>
            <p><i>Group mirroring</i> is the default mirroring configuration. The mirror segments
                for each host's primary segments are placed on one other host. If a single host
                fails, the number of active primary segments doubles on the host that backs the
                failed host. The diagram <xref href="#topic3/fig_rrr_nt2_xt" format="dita"/>
                illustrates a group mirroring configuration. </p>
            <!--<fig id="ki169754"><image href="../../graphics/mirrorsegs.png" placement="break" width="485px" height="135px"/></fig>-->
            <fig id="fig_rrr_nt2_xt">
                <title>Group Segment Mirroring in Greenplum Database</title>
                <image href="../../graphics/group-mirroring.png" id="image_crm_pt2_xt"/>
            </fig>
            <p><i>Spread mirroring</i> spreads each host's mirrors over multiple hosts so that if
                any single host fails, no other host will have more than one mirror promoted to an
                active primary segment. Spread mirroring is possible only if there are more hosts
                than segments per host. The diagram <xref href="#topic3/fig_ew1_qgg_xt"
                    format="dita"/> illustrates the placement of mirrors in a spread segment
                mirroring configuration.</p>
            <fig id="fig_ew1_qgg_xt">
                <title>Spread Segment Mirroring in Greenplum Database</title>
                <image href="../../graphics/spread-mirroring.png" id="image_zjm_wgg_xt"/>
            </fig>
        </section>
        <p> </p>
    </body>
</topic>
