<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic16">
  <title>Recovering a Failed Master</title>
  <body>
    <p>If the primary master fails, log replication stops. Use the <codeph>gpstate -f</codeph>
      command to check the state of standby replication. Use <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> to
      activate the standby master. Upon activation of the standby master, Greenplum Database reconstructs the master host state at the time of the last
      successfully committed transaction. </p>
    <section id="ki181117">
      <title>To activate the standby master</title>
      <ol>
        <li id="ki155784">Ensure a standby master host is configured for the system. See <xref
            href="g-enabling-master-mirroring.xml#topic8"/>.</li>
        <li id="ki155791">Run the <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> utility from the standby master
          host you are activating. For example:<codeblock>$ gpactivatestandby -d /data/master/gpseg-1</codeblock>
          <p>Where <codeph>-d</codeph> specifies the data directory of the master host you are
            activating.</p>
          <p>After you activate the standby, it becomes the <i>active</i> or <i>primary</i> master
            for your Greenplum Database array. </p>
        </li>
        <li id="ki155816">After the utility finishes, run <codeph>gpstate</codeph> to check the status:<codeblock>$ gpstate -f</codeblock>
          <p>The newly activated master's status should be <i>Active</i>. If you configured a new
            standby host, its status is <i>Passive</i>. When a standby master is not configured, the
            command displays <codeph>-No entries found</codeph> and the message indicates that a
            standby master instance is not configured.</p>
        </li>
        <li id="ki169625">After switching to the newly active master host, run
            <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> on it. For
          example:<codeblock>$ psql <codeph>dbname</codeph> -c 'ANALYZE;'</codeblock>
        </li>
        <li id="ki155823">Optional: If you did not specify a new standby host when running the
            <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> utility, use <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph> to
          configure a new standby master at a later time. Run <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph> on your
          active master host. For
          example:<codeblock>$ gpinitstandby -s <i>new_standby_master_hostname</i>
               </codeblock>
        </li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
