<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic16">
  <title>Recovering a Failed Master</title>
  <body>
    <p>If the primary master fails, the Greenplum Database system is not accessible and WAL
      replication stops. Use <codeph><xref
          href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpactivatestandby.xml"
          >gpactivatestandby</xref></codeph> to activate the standby master. Upon activation of the
      standby master, Greenplum Database reconstructs the master host state at the time of the last
      successfully committed transaction. </p>
    <p>These steps assume a standby master host is configured for the system. See <xref
        href="g-enabling-master-mirroring.xml#topic8"/>.</p>
    <section id="ki181117">
      <title>To activate the standby master</title>
      <ol>
        <li id="ki155791">Run the <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> utility from the standby master
          host you are activating. For
            example:<codeblock>$ gpactivatestandby -d /data/master/gpseg-1</codeblock><p>Where
              <codeph>-d</codeph> specifies the data directory of the master host you are
            activating.</p><p>After you activate the standby, it becomes the <i>active</i> or
              <i>primary</i> master for your Greenplum Database array. </p></li>
        <li id="ki155816">After the utility completes, run <codeph>gpstate</codeph> with the
            <codeph>-b</codeph> option to display a summary of the system
            status:<codeblock>$ gpstate -b</codeblock><p>The master instance status should be
              <codeph>Active</codeph>. When a standby master is not configured, the command displays
              <codeph>No master standby configured</codeph> for the standby master status. If you
            configured a new standby master, its status is <codeph>Passive</codeph>. </p></li>
        <li id="ki155823">Optional: If you have not already done so while activating the prior
          standby master, you can run <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph> on the active master host to
          configure a new standby master.
          <note type="important">You must initialize a new standby master to continue providing
            master mirroring.</note><p>For information about restoring the original master and
            standby master configuration, see <xref
              href="g-restoring-master-mirroring-after-a-recovery.xml#topic17"/>.</p></li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
