<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic17">
  <title>Restoring Master Mirroring After a Recovery</title>
  <body>
    <p>After you activate a standby master for recovery, the standby master becomes the primary
      master. You can continue running that instance as the primary master if it has the same
      capabilities and dependability as the original master host. </p>
    <p>You must initialize a new standby master to continue providing master mirroring unless you
      have already done so while activating the prior standby master. Run <codeph><xref
          href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpinitstandby.xml"
        >gpinitstandby</xref></codeph> on the active master host to configure a new standby master.
      See <xref href="g-enabling-master-mirroring.xml#topic8"/>.</p>
    <p>You can restore the primary and standby master instances on the original hosts. This process
      swaps the roles of the primary and standby master hosts, and it should be performed only if
      you strongly prefer to run the master instances on the same hosts they occupied prior to the
      recovery scenario. </p>
    <note type="important">Restoring the primary and standby master instances to their original
      hosts is not an online operation. The master host must be stopped to perform the
      operation.</note>
    <p>For information about the Greenplum Database utilities, see the <cite>Greenplum Database
        Utility Guide</cite>.</p>
    <section id="ki160986">
      <title>To restore the master and standby instances on original hosts (optional)</title>
      <ol>
        <li id="ki160936">Ensure the original master host is in dependable running condition; ensure
          the cause of the original failure is fixed.</li>
        <li>On the original master host, move or remove the data directory,
          <codeph>gpseg-1</codeph>. This example moves the directory to
            <codeph>backup_gpseg-1</codeph>:<codeblock>$ mv /data/master/gpseg-1 /data/master/backup_gpseg-1</codeblock><p>You
            can remove the backup directory once the standby is successfully configured.</p></li>
        <li id="ki160940">Initialize a standby master on the original master host. For example, run
          this command from the current master host,
          smdw:<codeblock>$ gpinitstandby -s mdw</codeblock></li>
        <li>After the initialization completes, check the status of standby master, mdw. Run
              <codeph><xref href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpstate.xml#topic1"
              type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph> with the <codeph>-f</codeph> option to check the
          standby master status:<codeblock>$ gpstate -f</codeblock> The standby master status should
          be <codeph>passive</codeph>, and the WAL sender state should be
          <codeph>streaming</codeph>.</li>
        <li>Stop the Greenplum Database master instance on the standby master. For
          example:<codeblock>$ gpstop -m</codeblock></li>
        <li id="ki160961">Run the <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> utility from the original
          master host, mdw, that is currently a standby master. For
            example:<codeblock>$ gpactivatestandby -d $MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY</codeblock><p>Where the
              <codeph>-d</codeph> option specifies the data directory of the host you are
            activating.</p></li>
        <li id="ki165618">After the utility completes, run <codeph>gpstate</codeph> with the
            <codeph>-b</codeph> option to display a summary of the system
            status:<codeblock>$ gpstate -b</codeblock><p>The master instance status should be
              <codeph>Active</codeph>. When a standby master is not configured, the command displays
              <codeph>No master standby configured</codeph> for the standby master state.</p></li>
        <li>On the standby master host, move or remove the data directory, <codeph>gpseg-1</codeph>.
          This example moves the
            directory:<codeblock>$ mv /data/master/gpseg-1 /data/master/backup_gpseg-1</codeblock><p>You
            can remove the backup directory once the standby is successfully configured.</p></li>
        <li id="ki165609">After the original master host runs the primary Greenplum Database master,
          you can initialize a standby master on the original standby master host. For
            example:<codeblock>$ gpinitstandby -s smdw</codeblock><p>After the command completes,
            you can run the <codeph>gpstate -f</codeph> command on the primary master host, to check
            the standby master status. </p></li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>To check the status of the master mirroring process (optional)</title>
      <p>You can run the <codeph>gpstate</codeph> utility with the <codeph>-f</codeph> option to
        display details of the standby master host. <codeblock>$ gpstate -f</codeblock></p>
      <p>The standby master status should be <codeph>passive</codeph>, and the WAL sender state
        should be <codeph>streaming</codeph>.</p>
      <p>For information about the <codeph><xref
            href="../../../utility_guide/ref/gpstate.xml" type="topic" format="dita"
          /></codeph> utility, see the <cite>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</cite>.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
