<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="oe138244">Running the Greenplum Client Tools</title>
    <body>
        <p>This section contains information for connecting to Greenplum Database using the
                <codeph>psql.exe</codeph> command-line client tool.</p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic2" xml:lang="en">
        <title>Connecting to Greenplum Database</title>
        <body>
            <p>Users and administrators <i>always</i> connect to Greenplum Database through the
                master host. In order to establish a connection to the Greenplum Database master,
                you will need to know the following connection information and configure your client
                program accordingly. See <xref href="win_client_install.xml#topic4" type="topic"
                    format="dita"/> for more information.</p>
            <table id="oe150047">
                <title>Connection Parameters</title>
                <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colnum="1" colname="col1" colwidth="119pt"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="139pt"/>
                    <colspec colnum="3" colname="col3" colwidth="118pt"/>
                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry colname="col1">Connection Parameter</entry>
                            <entry colname="col2">Description</entry>
                            <entry colname="col3">Environment Variable</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry colname="col1">Database name</entry>
                            <entry colname="col2">The name of the database to which you want to
                                connect. For a newly initialized system, use the
                                    <codeph>postgres</codeph> database to connect for the first
                                time.</entry>
                            <entry colname="col3"><codeph>$PGDATABASE</codeph></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry colname="col1">Host name</entry>
                            <entry colname="col2">The host name of the Greenplum Database master.
                                The default host is the local host. </entry>
                            <entry colname="col3"><codeph>$PGHOST</codeph></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry colname="col1">Port</entry>
                            <entry colname="col2">The port number that the Greenplum Database master
                                instance is running on. The default is 5432.</entry>
                            <entry colname="col3"><codeph>$PGPORT</codeph></entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry colname="col1">User name</entry>
                            <entry colname="col2">The database user (role) name to connect as. This
                                is not necessarily the same as your OS user name. Check with your
                                Greenplum administrator if you are not sure what you database user
                                name is. Note that every Greenplum Database system has one superuser
                                account that is created automatically at initialization time. This
                                account has the same name as the OS name of the user who initialized
                                the Greenplum system (typically <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>).</entry>
                            <entry colname="col3"><codeph>$PGUSER</codeph></entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic3" xml:lang="en">
        <title>Running psql.exe</title>
        <body>
            <p>The <codeph>psql.exe</codeph> program is invoked from a Windows command-line session.
                For complete command syntax and options for <codeph>psql.exe</codeph>, see <xref
                    href="./psqlexe.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</p>
            <p>Depending on the default values used or the environment variables you have set, the
                following examples show how to access a database in Greenplum Database via
                    <codeph>psql</codeph>:</p>
            <codeblock>$ psql.exe -d gpdatabase -h master_host -p 5432 -U gpadmin

$ psql.exe gpdatabase

$ psql.exe</codeblock>
            <p>If a user-defined database has not yet been created, you can access the system by
                connecting to the <codeph>postgres</codeph> database. For example:</p>
            <codeblock>$ psql.exe postgres</codeblock>
            <p>After connecting to a database, <codeph>psql</codeph> provides a prompt with the name
                of the database to which <codeph>psql</codeph> is currently connected, followed by
                the string <codeph>=&gt;</codeph> (or <codeph>=#</codeph> if you are the database
                superuser). For example:</p>
            <codeblock>gpdatabase=&gt;</codeblock>
            <p>At the prompt, you may type in SQL commands. A SQL command must end with a
                    <codeph>;</codeph> (semicolon) in order to be sent to the server and executed.
                For example:</p>
            <codeblock>=&gt; SELECT count(*) FROM mytable;</codeblock>
            <p>For more information on using the <codeph>psql.exe</codeph> client application, see
                        <codeph><xref href="./psqlexe.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                    /></codeph>. For more information on SQL commands and syntax, see <xref
                    href="../../common/client_sql_ref.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</p>
        </body>
    </topic>
</topic>
