<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en"><title id="od138244">Installing the Greenplum Client Tools</title><body><p>This section contains information for installing the various client
programs on your Windows machine and for enabling Greenplum Database
to accept remote client connections:</p><ul><li id="od145908"><xref href="#topic2" type="topic" format="dita"/></li><li id="od145926"><xref href="#topic4" type="topic" format="dita"/></li><li id="od149642"><xref href="#topic5" type="topic" format="dita"/></li><li id="od150914"><xref href="#topic6" type="topic" format="dita"/></li></ul><p>See the <i>Greenplum Database Release Notes</i> for the list of currently supported platforms for
      the Client Tools.</p></body><topic id="topic2" xml:lang="en"><title id="od145498">Running the Client Tools Installer</title><body><p>The Greenplum Database client tools installer installs <codeph>psql.exe</codeph>,
the interactive command-line client interface to Greenplum Database.</p><section id="od149882"><title>To install the Greenplum Database client tools</title><ol><li id="od149886">Download the
              <codeph>greenplum-clients-<varname>&lt;version></varname>-WinXP-x86_32.msi</codeph>
            package from <xref href="https://network.pivotal.io" scope="external" format="html"
                ><ph>Pivotal Network</ph></xref>.</li><li id="od150199">Double-click on the
              <codeph>greenplum-clients-<varname>&lt;version></varname>-WinXP-x86_32.msi</codeph>
            package to launch the installer.</li><li id="od145456">Click <b>Next</b> on the Welcome screen.</li><li id="od145457">Click <b>I Agree</b> on the License Agreement screen.</li><li id="od145465">By default, the Greenplum Database client tools will be installed into
                <codeph>greenplum-db-<varname>&lt;version></varname></codeph>. Click <b>Browse</b>
            if you want to choose another location.</li><li id="od145480">Click <b>Next</b> when you have chosen the install path you want.</li><li id="od145466">Click <b>Install</b> to begin the installation.</li><li id="od145491">Click <b>Finish</b> to exit the installer.</li></ol></section></body><topic id="topic3" xml:lang="en"><title>About Your Installation</title><body><p>Your Greenplum Database client tools installation contains the following
files and directories:</p><ul><li id="od148216"><b>bin</b> — client tools programs</li><li id="od148217"><b>greenplum_clients_path.bat</b> — sets environment variables</li><li id="od148220"><b>lib</b> — client tools library files</li></ul></body></topic></topic><topic id="topic4" xml:lang="en"><title id="od146343">Configuring the Client Tools</title><body><p>Greenplum provides a batch program (<codeph>greenplum_clients_path.bat</codeph>) to set the
        required environment settings for Greenplum loader (located in
            <codeph>greenplum-db-<varname>&lt;version></varname></codeph> by default).</p><section id="od149555"><title>To set the required environment settings</title><ol><li id="od149556">Open a Windows command prompt (<b>Start</b> &gt; <b>Run</b> and type
<codeph>cmd</codeph>).</li><li id="od149560">At the command prompt, go to the directory where you installed Greenplum loader.
            For
            example:<codeblock>cd \"Program Files"\Greenplum\greenplum-clients-&lt;version>
dir</codeblock></li><li id="od149563">Execute the <codeph>greenplum_loaders_path.bat</codeph>
            program:<codeblock>greenplum_clients_path.bat</codeblock></li></ol><p>The PostgreSQL command-line tools also require several connection parameters
in order to be able to connect to a Greenplum database. In order to save
some typing on the command-line, you can optionally create the following
environment variables in your Windows Control Panel.</p><ul><li id="od146423"><codeph>PGDATABASE</codeph> — The name of the default Greenplum database to
            connect to.</li><li id="od146428"><codeph>PGHOST</codeph> — The Greenplum Database master host name or IP
            address.</li><li id="od146434"><codeph>PGPORT</codeph> — The port number that the Greenplum master instance
            (postmaster process) is running on.</li><li id="od146433"><codeph>PGUSER</codeph> — The default database role name to use for login.</li></ul></section><section id="od146459"><title>To add a new user environment variable on Windows XP</title><ol><li id="od146460">In Windows Explorer, go to <codeph>C:\\Control Panel</codeph>.</li><li id="od146461">Double-click the <b>System</b> icon.</li><li id="od146462">On the <b>Advanced</b> tab, click <b>Environment Variables</b> (bottom).</li><li id="od146494">Click <b>New</b>.</li><li id="od146464">Define the new environment variable. For example:<image href="images/win_0001.png" placement="break" width="268px" height="114px"/></li><li id="od146457">Click <b>OK</b>.</li></ol></section></body></topic><topic id="topic5" xml:lang="en"><title id="od146223">Enabling Greenplum Database for Remote Client Connections</title><body><p>In order for Greenplum Database to be able to accept remote client connections,
you must configure your Greenplum Database master so that connections
are allowed from the client hosts and database users that will be connecting
to Greenplum Database.</p><section id="od150543"><title>To enable remote client connections</title><ol><li id="od150548">Make sure that the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file of the Greenplum Database
            master is correctly configured to allow connections from the users to the database(s)
            using the authentication method you want. For details, see "Editing the pg_hba.conf
            File" in the <i>Greenplum Database Administration Guide</i>, and also see the
              <i>Greenplum Database Security Configuration Guide</i>.<p>Make sure the authentication
              method you choose is supported by the client tool you are using.</p></li><li id="od150553">If you edited <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file, the change requires a server
            reload (using the <codeph>gpstop -u</codeph> command) to take effect.</li><li id="od150554">Make sure that the databases and roles you are using to connect exist
in the system and that the roles have the correct privileges to the database
objects.</li></ol></section></body></topic><topic id="topic6" xml:lang="en"><title id="od150657">Configuring a Client System for Kerberos Authentication</title><body><p>If you use Kerberos authentication to connect to your Greenplum Database
with the <codeph>psql</codeph> utility, your client system must be configured
to use Kerberos authentication. If you are not using Kerberos authentication
to connect to a Greenplum Database, Kerberos is not needed on your client
system.</p><ul><li id="od150668"><xref href="#topic7" type="topic" format="dita"/></li><li id="od150672"><xref href="#topic10" type="topic" format="dita"/></li><li id="od150676"><xref href="#topic11" type="topic" format="dita"/></li></ul><p>For information about enabling Kerberos authentication with Greenplum Database, see the chapter
        "Kerberos Authentication" in the <i>Greenplum Database Administrator Guide</i>. </p></body><topic id="topic7" xml:lang="en"><title id="od150685">Requirements</title><body><p>The following are requirements to connect to a Greenplum Database that
is enabled with Kerberos authentication from a client system with Greenplum
Database client software.</p><ul><li id="od150696"><xref href="#topic8" type="topic" format="dita"/></li><li id="od150700"><xref href="#topic9" type="topic" format="dita"/></li></ul></body><topic id="topic8" xml:lang="en"><title id="od150702">Prerequisites</title><body><ul><li id="od150706">Kerberos must be installed and configured on the Greenplum Database
master host. See "<xref href="#topic5" type="topic" format="dita"/>."</li><li id="od150710">The client systems require the Kerberos configuration file <codeph>krb5.conf</codeph>
from the Greenplum Database master. </li><li id="od150714">The client systems require a Kerberos keytab file that contains the
authentication credentials for the Greenplum Database user that is used
to log into the database. </li><li id="od150721">The client machines must be able to connect to Greenplum Database master host.
                <p>If necessary, add the Greenplum Database master host name and IP address to the
                system <codeph>hosts</codeph> file. On Windows 7 systems, the <codeph>hosts</codeph>
                file is located in <codeph>C:\Windows\System32\drivers\etc\</codeph>.</p></li></ul></body></topic><topic id="topic9" xml:lang="en"><title id="od150728">Required Software on the Client Machine</title><body><ul><li id="od150822">The Kerberos <codeph>kinit</codeph> utility. The <codeph>kinit.exe</codeph>
              utility is available with Kerberos for Windows. Greenplum Database supports Kerberos
              for Windows version 3.2.2. Kerberos for Windows is available from the Kerberos web
              site <xref href="http://web.mit.edu/kerberos/" scope="external" format="html"
                >http://web.mit.edu/kerberos/</xref>. <note>When you install the Kerberos software,
                you can use other Kerberos utilities such as <codeph>klist</codeph> to display
                Kerberos ticket information. </note></li></ul></body></topic></topic><topic id="topic10" xml:lang="en"><title id="od150732">Setting Up a Client System with Kerberos Authentication</title><body><p>To connect to Greenplum Database with Kerberos authentication requires
a Kerberos ticket. On client systems, tickets are generated from Kerberos
keytab files with the <codeph>kinit</codeph> utility and are stored in
a cache file.</p><ol><li id="od150739">Install a copy of the Kerberos configuration file <codeph>krb5.conf</codeph> from
            the Greenplum Database master. The file is used by the Greenplum Database client
            software and the Kerberos utilities. <p>Rename <codeph>krb5.conf</codeph> to
                <codeph>krb5.ini</codeph> and move it to the Windows directory. On Windows 7, the
              Windows directory is <codeph>C:\Windows</codeph>. </p><p>If needed, add the parameter
                <codeph>default_ccache_name</codeph> to the <codeph>[libdefaults]</codeph> section
              of the <codeph>krb5.ini</codeph> file and specify the location of the Kerberos ticket
              cache file on the client system. </p></li><li id="od150746">Obtain a Kerberos keytab file that contains the authentication credentials
for the Greenplum Database user. </li><li id="od150750">Run <codeph>kinit</codeph> specifying the keytab file to create a ticket on the
            client machine. For the following example, the keytab file
              <codeph>gpdb-kerberos.keytab</codeph> is in the current directory. The ticket cache
            file is in the gpadmin user home directory.
            <codeblock>&gt; kinit -k -t gpdb-kerberos.keytab 
   -c C:\Users\gpadmin\cache.txt 
   gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb@KRB.EXAMPLE.COM</codeblock></li></ol></body></topic><topic id="topic11" xml:lang="en"><title id="od150756">Accessing Greenplum Database with psql </title><body><p>From a remote system, you can access a Greenplum Database that has Kerberos
authentication enabled. </p><ol><li id="od150886">As the gpadmin user, open a command window. </li><li id="od150887">Run the client tool batch file from command window
              <codeph>greenplum_clients_path.bat</codeph><p>Change the current directory to the
                <codeph>bin</codeph> directory of the Kerberos for Windows installation. For
              example:</p><codeblock>&gt; cd C:\test\MIT\Kerberos\bin</codeblock></li><li id="od150890">Start <codeph>psql</codeph> from the command window and specify a connection to
            the Greenplum Database specifying the user that is configured with Kerberos
              authentication.<p>The following example logs into the Greenplum Database on the
              machine <codeph>keberos-gpdb</codeph> as the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user with the
              Kerberos credentials
            <codeph>gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb</codeph>:</p><codeblock>&gt; psql -U "gpadmin/kerberos-gpdb" -h kerberos-gpdb template1
</codeblock></li></ol><p>For information about running <codeph>psql</codeph>, see "<xref href="./win_client_run.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/>." </p></body></topic></topic></topic>