<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic3">
   <title>Defining External Tables</title>
   <shortdesc>External tables enable accessing external data as if it were a regular database
      table. They are often used to move data into and out of a Greenplum database.</shortdesc>
   <body>
      <p>To create an external table definition, you specify the format of your input files and the
         location of your external data sources. For information input file formats, see <xref
            href="../load/topics/g-formatting-data-files.xml#topic95"/>.</p>
      <p>Use one of the following protocols to access external table data sources. You cannot mix
         protocols in <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> statements:<ul id="ul_zj5_prj_kr">
            <li><codeph>file://</codeph> accesses external data files on segment host that the
               Greenplum Database superuser (<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>) can access. See <xref
                  href="g-file-protocol.xml#topic_qbh_pwh_kr"/>.</li>
            <li><codeph>gpfdist://</codeph> points to a directory on the file host and serves
               external data files to all Greenplum Database segments in parallel. See <xref
                  href="g-gpfdist-protocol.xml#topic_sny_yph_kr"/>.</li>
            <li><codeph>gpfdists://</codeph> is the secure version of <codeph>gpfdist</codeph>. See
                  <xref href="g-gpfdists-protocol.xml#topic_sny_yph_kr"/>.</li>
            <li><codeph>gphdfs://</codeph> accesses files on a Hadoop Distributed File System
               (HDFS). See <xref href="g-gphdfs-protocol.xml#topic_z5g_l5h_kr"/>.<p>The files can be
                  stored on an Amazon EMR instance HDFS. See <xref
                     href="g-hdfs-emr-config.xml#amazon-emr"/>.</p></li>
            <li><codeph>s3://</codeph> accesses files in an Amazon S3 bucket. See <xref
                  href="g-s3-protocol.xml#amazon-emr"/>.</li>

            <li>The <codeph>pxf://</codeph> protocol accesses external HDFS files and Hive tables using the PXF Extension Framework. See <xref href="g-pxf-protocol.xml"></xref>.</li>
         </ul></p>
      <p>External tables access external files from within the database as if they are regular
         database tables. External tables defined with the
            <codeph>gpfdist</codeph>/<codeph>gpfdists</codeph>, <codeph>gphdfs</codeph>, and
            <codeph>s3</codeph> protocols utilize Greenplum parallelism by using the resources of
         all Greenplum Database segments to load or unload data. The <codeph>gphdfs</codeph>
         protocol leverages the parallel architecture of the Hadoop Distributed File System to
         access files on that system. The <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol utilizes the Amazon Web
         Services (AWS) capabilities. </p>
      <p>You can query external table data directly and in parallel using SQL commands such as
            <codeph>SELECT</codeph>, <codeph>JOIN</codeph>, or <codeph>SORT EXTERNAL TABLE
            DATA</codeph>, and you can create views for external tables. </p>
      <p>The steps for using external tables are:</p>
      <ol>
         <li id="du215913">Define the external table. <p>To use the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol,
               you must also configure Greenplum Database and enable the protocol. See <xref
                  href="g-s3-protocol.xml#amazon-emr"/>.</p></li>
         <li id="du220314">Do one of the following:<ul id="ul_nd1_gd5_h4">
               <li id="du220318">Start the Greenplum Database file server(s) when using the
                     <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> or <codeph>gpdists</codeph> protocols. </li>
               <li id="du220319">Verify that you have already set up the required one-time
                  configuration for the <codeph>gphdfs</codeph> protocol.</li>
               <li>Verify the Greenplum Database configuration for the <codeph>s3</codeph>
                  protocol.</li>
            </ul></li>
         <li id="du215986">Place the data files in the correct locations.</li>
         <li id="du216021">Query the external table with SQL commands.</li>
      </ol>
      <p>Greenplum Database provides readable and writable external tables:</p>
      <ul>
         <li id="du210036">Readable external tables for data loading. Readable external tables
            support basic extraction, transformation, and loading (ETL) tasks common in data
            warehousing. Greenplum Database segment instances read external table data in parallel
            to optimize large load operations. You cannot modify readable external tables. </li>
         <li id="du220433">Writable external tables for data unloading. Writable external tables support:<ul>
               <li id="du220434">Selecting data from database tables to insert into the writable
                  external table.</li>
               <li id="du220435">Sending data to an application as a stream of data. For example,
                  unload data from Greenplum Database and send it to an application that connects to
                  another database or ETL tool to load the data elsewhere. </li>
               <li id="du210321">Receiving output from Greenplum parallel MapReduce
                  calculations.</li>
            </ul><p>Writable external tables allow only <codeph>INSERT</codeph> operations.</p></li>
      </ul>
      <p>External tables can be file-based or web-based. External tables using the
            <codeph>file://</codeph> protocol are read-only tables.</p>
      <ul>
         <li id="du209906">Regular (file-based) external tables access static flat files. Regular
            external tables are rescannable: the data is static while the query runs.</li>
         <li id="du209907">Web (web-based) external tables access dynamic data sources, either on a
            web server with the <codeph>http://</codeph> protocol or by executing OS commands or
            scripts. External web tables are not rescannable: the data can change while the query
            runs. </li>
      </ul>
      <p>Dump and restore operate only on external and external web table <i>definitions</i>, not on
         the data sources.</p>
   </body>
</topic>
