<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_sny_yph_kr">
  <title>gpfdist:// Protocol</title>
  <shortdesc>The <codeph>gpfdist://</codeph> protocol is used in a URI to reference a running
      <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> instance. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>The <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> utility serves external data files from a directory on a file
      host to all Greenplum Database segments in parallel. </p>
    <p><codeph>gpfdist</codeph> is located in the <codeph>$GPHOME/bin</codeph> directory on your
      Greenplum Database master host and on each segment host. </p>
    <p>Run <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> on the host where the external data files reside.
        <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> uncompresses <codeph>gzip</codeph> (<codeph>.gz</codeph>) and
        <codeph>bzip2</codeph> (.<codeph>bz2</codeph>) files automatically. You can use the wildcard
      character (*) or other C-style pattern matching to denote multiple files to read. The files
      specified are assumed to be relative to the directory that you specified when you started the
        <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> instance. </p>
    <p>All primary segments access the external file(s) in parallel, subject to the number of
      segments set in the <codeph>gp_external_max_segments</codeph> server configuration parameter.
      Use multiple <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> data sources in a <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph>
      statement to scale the external table's scan performance. </p>
    <p><codeph>gpfdist</codeph> supports data transformations. You can write a transformation
      process to convert external data from or to a format that is not directly supported with
      Greenplum Database external tables.</p>
    <p>For more information about configuring <codeph>gpfdist</codeph>, see <xref
        href="g-using-the-greenplum-parallel-file-server--gpfdist-.xml#topic13">Using the Greenplum
        Parallel File Server (gpfdist)</xref>. </p>
    <p>See the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> reference documentation for more information about using
        <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> with external tables.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
