<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_sny_yph_kr">
  <title>gpfdists:// Protocol</title>
  <shortdesc>The <codeph>gpfdists://</codeph> protocol is a secure version of the <codeph>gpfdist://
      protocol</codeph>. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>To use it, you run the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> utility with the <codeph>--ssl</codeph>
      option. When specified in a URI, the <codeph>gpfdists://</codeph> protocol enables encrypted
      communication and secure identification of the file server and the Greenplum Database to
      protect against attacks such as eavesdropping and man-in-the-middle attacks. </p>
    <p><codeph>gpfdists</codeph> implements SSL security in a client/server scheme with the
      following attributes and limitations:<ul id="ul_z3p_mrh_kr">
        <li>Client certificates are required.</li>
        <li>Multilingual certificates are not supported.</li>
        <li>A Certificate Revocation List (CRL) is not supported.</li>
        <li>The <codeph>TLSv1</codeph> protocol is used with the
            <codeph>TLS_RSA_WITH_AES_128_CBC_SHA</codeph> encryption algorithm.</li>
        <li>SSL parameters cannot be changed.</li>
        <li>SSL renegotiation is supported.</li>
        <li>The SSL ignore host mismatch parameter is set to <codeph>false</codeph>.</li>
        <li>Private keys containing a passphrase are not supported for the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph>
          file server (server.key) and for the Greenplum Database (client.key).</li>
        <li>Issuing certificates that are appropriate for the operating system in use is the user's
          responsibility. Generally, converting certificates as shown in <xref
            href="https://www.sslshopper.com/ssl-converter.html" scope="external" type=""
            format="html">https://www.sslshopper.com/ssl-converter.html</xref> is supported. <note>A
            server started with the <codeph>gpfdist --ssl</codeph> option can only communicate with
            the <codeph>gpfdists</codeph> protocol. A server that was started with
              <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> without the <codeph>--ssl</codeph> option can only
            communicate with the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> protocol. </note></li>
        <li>The client certificate file, client.crt</li>
        <li>The client private key file, client.key</li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>Use one of the following methods to invoke the <codeph>gpfdists</codeph> protocol.<ul
        id="ul_nb2_ksh_kr">
        <li>Run <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> with the <codeph>--ssl</codeph> option and then use the
            <codeph>gpfdists</codeph> protocol in the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause of a
            <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> statement.</li>
        <li>Use a <codeph>gpload</codeph> YAML control file with the <codeph>SSL</codeph> option set
          to true. Running <codeph>gpload</codeph> starts the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> server with
          the <codeph>--ssl</codeph> option, then uses the <codeph>gpfdists</codeph> protocol. </li>
      </ul></p>
    <p>Using <codeph>gpfdists</codeph> requires that the following client certificates reside in the
        <codeph>$PGDATA/gpfdists</codeph> directory on each segment.</p>
    <ul id="ul_bjb_2kj_kr">
      <li>The client certificate file, <codeph>client.crt</codeph></li>
      <li>The client private key file, <codeph>client.key</codeph></li>
      <li>The trusted certificate authorities, <codeph>root.crt</codeph></li>
    </ul>
    <p>For an example of loading data into an external table security, see <xref
        href="g-example-3-multiple-gpfdists-instances.xml#topic47"/>.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
