<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_z5g_l5h_kr">
  <title>gphdfs:// Protocol</title>
  <shortdesc>The <codeph>gphdfs://</codeph> protocol specifies an external file path on a Hadoop
    Distributed File System (HDFS). </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>The protocol allows specifying external files in Hadoop clusters configured with or without
      Hadoop HA (high availability) and in MapR clusters. File names may contain wildcard characters
      and the files can be in <codeph>CSV</codeph>, <codeph>TEXT</codeph>, or custom formats. </p>
    <p>When Greenplum links with HDFS files, all the data is read in parallel from the HDFS data
      nodes into the Greenplum segments for rapid processing. Greenplum determines the connections
      between the segments and nodes. </p>
    <p>Each Greenplum segment reads one set of Hadoop data blocks. For writing, each Greenplum
      segment writes only the data it contains. The following figure illustrates an external table
      located on a HDFS file system.</p>
    <fig id="fig_gjc_5vh_kr">
      <title>External Table Located on a Hadoop Distributed File System</title>
      <image href="../graphics/ext_tables_hadoop.jpg" id="image_qks_kvh_kr" width="472px"/>
    </fig>
    <p>The <codeph>FORMAT</codeph> clause describes the format of the external table files. Valid
      file formats are similar to the formatting options available with the PostgreSQL
        <codeph>COPY</codeph> command and user-defined formats for the <codeph>gphdfs</codeph>
      protocol. If the data in the file does not use the default column delimiter, escape character,
      null string and so on, you must specify the additional formatting options so that Greenplum
      Database reads the data in the external file correctly. The <codeph>gphdfs</codeph> protocol
      requires a one-time setup. See <xref href="g-one-time-hdfs-protocol-installation.xml#topic20"
        >One-time HDFS Protocol Installation</xref>.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
