<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="amazon-emr">
   <title>s3:// Protocol</title>
   <shortdesc>The <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol is used in a URL that specifies the location of an
      Amazon S3 bucket and a prefix to use for reading or writing files in the bucket. </shortdesc>
   <body>
      <p>Amazon Simple Storage Service (Amazon S3) provides secure, durable, highly-scalable object
         storage. For information about Amazon S3, see <xref href="https://aws.amazon.com/s3/"
            format="html" scope="external">Amazon S3</xref>. </p>
      <p>You can define read-only external tables that use existing data files in the S3 bucket for
         table data, or writable external tables that store the data from INSERT operations to files
         in the S3 bucket. Greenplum Database uses the S3 URL and prefix specified in the protocol
         URL either to select one or more files for a read-only table, or to define the location and
         filename format to use when uploading S3 files for <codeph>INSERT</codeph> operations to
         writable tables.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol also supports <xref
            href="https://www.emc.com/en-us/storage/ecs/index.htm" format="html" scope="external"
            >Dell EMC Elastic Cloud Storage</xref> (ECS), an Amazon S3 compatible service. </p>
      <p>This topic contains the sections:<ul id="ul_o15_22r_kx">
            <li><xref href="#amazon-emr/s3_prereq" format="dita"/></li>
            <li><xref href="#amazon-emr/section_stk_c2r_kx" format="dita"/></li>
            <li><xref href="#amazon-emr/section_c2f_zvs_3x" format="dita"/></li>
            <li><xref href="#amazon-emr/s3_serversideencrypt" format="dita"/></li>
            <li><xref href="#amazon-emr/s3_proxy" format="dita"/></li>
            <li><xref href="#amazon-emr/s3_config_param" format="dita"/></li>
            <li><xref href="#amazon-emr/s3_config_file" format="dita"/></li>
            <li><xref href="#amazon-emr/section_tsq_n3t_3x" format="dita"/></li>
            <li><xref href="#amazon-emr/s3chkcfg_utility" format="dita"/></li>
         </ul></p>
      <section id="s3_prereq">
         <title>Configuring and Using S3 External Tables</title>
         <p>Follow these basic steps to configure the S3 protocol and use S3 external tables, using
            the available links for more information. See also <xref
               href="#amazon-emr/section_tsq_n3t_3x" format="dita"/> to better understand the
            capabilities and limitations of S3 external tables:<ol id="ol_pbb_rmq_kx">
               <li>Configure each database to support the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol:<ol
                     id="ol_w3z_dpq_kx">
                     <li>In each database that will access an S3 bucket with the <codeph>s3</codeph>
                        protocol, create the read and write functions for the <codeph>s3</codeph>
                        protocol
                        library:<codeblock>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION write_to_s3() RETURNS integer AS
   '$libdir/gps3ext.so', 's3_export' LANGUAGE C STABLE;</codeblock><codeblock>CREATE OR REPLACE FUNCTION read_from_s3() RETURNS integer AS
   '$libdir/gps3ext.so', 's3_import' LANGUAGE C STABLE;</codeblock></li>
                     <li> In each database that will access an S3 bucket, declare the
                           <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol and specify the read and write functions you
                        created in the previous
                           step:<codeblock>CREATE PROTOCOL s3 (writefunc = write_to_s3, readfunc = read_from_s3);</codeblock><note>The
                           protocol name <codeph>s3</codeph> must be the same as the protocol of the
                           URL specified for the external table you create to access an S3 resource.
                              <p>The corresponding function is called by every Greenplum Database
                              segment instance. All segment hosts must have access to the S3
                              bucket.</p></note></li>
                  </ol></li>
               <li>On each Greenplum Database segment, create and install the <codeph>s3</codeph>
                  protocol configuration file:<ol id="ol_mnq_rnq_kx">
                     <li>Create a template <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol configuration file using the
                           <codeph>gpcheckcloud</codeph>
                        utility:<codeblock>gpcheckcloud -t > ./mytest_s3.config</codeblock></li>
                     <li>Edit the template file to specify the <codeph>accessid</codeph> and
                           <codeph>secret</codeph> required to connect to the S3 location. See <xref
                           href="#amazon-emr/s3_config_file" format="dita"/> for information about
                        other <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol configuration parameters.</li>
                     <li>Copy the file to the same location and filename for all Greenplum Database
                        segments on all hosts. The default file location is
                              <codeph><varname>gpseg_data_dir</varname>/<varname>gpseg_prefix</varname><varname>N</varname>/s3/s3.conf</codeph>.
                           <varname>gpseg_data_dir</varname> is the path to the Greenplum Database
                        segment data directory, <varname>gpseg_prefix</varname> is the segment
                        prefix, and <varname>N</varname> is the segment ID. The segment data
                        directory, prefix, and ID are set when you initialize a Greenplum Database
                        system. <p>If you copy the file to a different location or filename, then
                           you must specify the location with the <codeph>config</codeph> parameter
                           in the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol URL. See <xref
                              href="#amazon-emr/s3_config_param" format="dita"/>.</p></li>
                     <li>Use the <codeph>gpcheckcloud</codeph> utility to validate connectivity to
                        the S3
                           bucket:<codeblock>gpcheckcloud -c "s3://&lt;s3-endpoint>/&lt;s3-bucket> config=./mytest_s3.config"</codeblock><p>Specify
                           the correct path to the configuration file for your system, as well as
                           the S3 endpoint name and bucket that you want to check.
                              <codeph>gpcheckcloud</codeph> attempts to connect to the S3 endpoint
                           and lists any files in the S3 bucket, if available. A successful
                           connection ends with the
                           message:<codeblock>Your configuration works well.</codeblock>You can
                           optionally use <codeph>gpcheckcloud</codeph> to validate uploading to and
                           downloading from the S3 bucket, as described in <xref
                              href="#amazon-emr/s3chkcfg_utility" format="dita"/>.</p></li>
                  </ol></li>
               <li>After completing the previous steps to create and configure the
                     <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol, you can specify an <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol
                  URL in the <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> command to define S3 external
                  tables. For read-only S3 tables, the URL defines the location and prefix used to
                  select existing data files that comprise the S3 table. For example:
                     <codeblock>CREATE READABLE EXTERNAL TABLE S3TBL (date text, time text, amt int)
   LOCATION('s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/s3test.example.com/dataset1/normal/
      config=/home/gpadmin/aws_s3/s3.conf')
   FORMAT 'csv';</codeblock><p>For
                     writable S3 tables, the protocol URL defines the S3 location in which Greenplum
                     database stores data files for the table, as well as a prefix to use when
                     creating files for table <codeph>INSERT</codeph> operations. For
                     example:<codeblock>CREATE WRITABLE EXTERNAL TABLE S3WRIT (LIKE S3TBL)
   LOCATION('s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/s3test.example.com/dataset1/normal/
      config=/home/gpadmin/aws_s3/s3.conf')
   FORMAT 'csv';</codeblock></p><p>See
                        <xref href="#amazon-emr/section_stk_c2r_kx" format="dita"/> for more
                     information.</p></li>
            </ol></p>
      </section>
      <section id="section_stk_c2r_kx">
         <title>About the S3 Protocol URL</title>
         <p>For the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol, you specify a location for files and an optional
            configuration file location in the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause of the
               <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> command. This is the syntax:</p>
         <codeblock>'s3://<varname>S3_endpoint</varname>[:<varname>port</varname>]/<varname>bucket_name</varname>/[<varname>S3_prefix</varname>] [region=<varname>S3_region</varname>] [config=<varname>config_file_location</varname>]'</codeblock>
         <p>The <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol requires that you specify the S3 endpoint and S3 bucket
            name. Each Greenplum Database segment instance must have access to the S3 location. The
            optional <varname>S3_prefix</varname> value is used to select files for read-only S3
            tables, or as a filename prefix to use when uploading files for S3 writable tables.</p>
         <note>The Greenplum Database <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol URL must include the S3 endpoint
            hostname.</note>
         <p>To specify an ECS endpoint (an Amazon S3 compatible service) in the
               <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause, you must set the <codeph>s3</codeph> configuration
            file parameter <codeph>version</codeph> to 2. The <codeph>version</codeph> parameter
            controls whether the <codeph>region</codeph> parameter is used in the
               <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause. You can also specify an Amazon S3 location when the
               <codeph>version</codeph> parameter is 2. For information about
               <codeph>version</codeph> parameter, see <xref href="#amazon-emr/s3_config_file"
               format="dita"/>.</p>
         <note id="s3-prefix-note">Although the <varname>S3_prefix</varname> is an optional part of
            the syntax, you should always include an S3 prefix for both writable and read-only S3
            tables to separate datasets as part of the <codeph><xref
                  href="../../ref_guide/sql_commands/CREATE_EXTERNAL_TABLE.xml#topic1">CREATE
                  EXTERNAL TABLE</xref></codeph> syntax.</note>
         <p>For writable S3 tables, the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol URL specifies the endpoint and
            bucket name where Greenplum Database uploads data files for the table. The S3 bucket
            permissions must be <codeph>Upload/Delete</codeph> for the S3 user ID that uploads the
            files. The S3 file prefix is used for each new file uploaded to the S3 location as a
            result of inserting data to the table. See <xref href="#amazon-emr/section_c2f_zvs_3x"
               format="dita"/>.</p>
         <p>For read-only S3 tables, the S3 file prefix is optional. If you specify an
               <varname>S3_prefix</varname>, then the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol selects all files
            that start with the specified prefix as data files for the external table. The
               <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol does not use the slash character (<codeph>/</codeph>) as
            a delimiter, so a slash character following a prefix is treated as part of the prefix
            itself. </p>
         <p>For example, consider the following 5 files that each have the
               <varname>S3_endpoint</varname> named <codeph>s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com</codeph> and
            the <varname>bucket_name</varname>
            <codeph>test1</codeph>:</p>
         <codeblock>s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc
s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc/
s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc/xx
s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abcdef
s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abcdefff</codeblock>
         <ul id="ul_yll_xjm_qv">
            <li>If the S3 URL is provided as
                  <codeph>s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc</codeph>, then the
                  <codeph>abc</codeph> prefix selects all 5 files.</li>
            <li>If the S3 URL is provided as
                  <codeph>s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc/</codeph>, then the
                  <codeph>abc/</codeph> prefix selects the files
                  <codeph>s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc/</codeph> and
                  <codeph>s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc/xx</codeph>.</li>
            <li>If the S3 URL is provided as
                  <codeph>s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abcd</codeph>, then the
                  <codeph>abcd</codeph> prefix selects the files
                  <codeph>s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abcdef</codeph> and
                  <codeph>s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abcdefff</codeph></li>
         </ul>
         <p>Wildcard characters are not supported in an <varname>S3_prefix</varname>; however, the
            S3 prefix functions as if a wildcard character immediately followed the prefix
            itself.</p>
         <p>All of the files selected by the S3 URL
               (<varname>S3_endpoint</varname>/<varname>bucket_name</varname>/<varname>S3_prefix</varname>)
            are used as the source for the external table, so they must have the same format. Each
            file must also contain complete data rows. A data row cannot be split between files. The
            S3 file permissions must be <codeph>Open/Download</codeph> and <codeph>View</codeph> for
            the S3 user ID that is accessing the files. </p>
         <p>For information about the Amazon S3 endpoints see <xref
               href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/rande.html#s3_region"
               format="html" scope="external"
               >http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/rande.html#s3_region</xref>. For
            information about S3 buckets and folders, see the Amazon S3 documentation <xref
               href="https://aws.amazon.com/documentation/s3/" format="html" scope="external"
               >https://aws.amazon.com/documentation/s3/</xref>. For information about the S3 file
            prefix, see the Amazon S3 documentation <xref
               href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/ListingKeysHierarchy.html"
               format="html" scope="external">Listing Keys Hierarchically Using a Prefix and
               Delimiter</xref>.</p>
         <p>The <codeph>config</codeph> parameter specifies the location of the required
               <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol configuration file that contains AWS connection
            credentials and communication parameters. See <xref href="#amazon-emr/s3_config_param"
               format="dita"/>.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="section_c2f_zvs_3x">
         <title>About S3 Data Files</title>
         <p>For each <codeph>INSERT</codeph> operation to a writable S3 table, each Greenplum
            Database segment uploads a single file to the configured S3 bucket using the filename
            format <codeph> &lt;prefix>&lt;segment_id>&lt;random>.&lt;extension>[.gz]</codeph>
               where:<ul id="ul_sw1_qvs_3x">
               <li><codeph>&lt;prefix></codeph> is the prefix specified in the S3 URL.</li>
               <li><codeph>&lt;segment_id></codeph> is the Greenplum Database segment ID.</li>
               <li><codeph>&lt;random></codeph> is a random number that is used to ensure that the
                  filename is unique.</li>
               <li><codeph>&lt;extension></codeph> describes the file type (<codeph>.txt</codeph> or
                     <filepath>.csv</filepath>, depending on the value you provide in the
                     <codeph>FORMAT</codeph> clause of <codeph>CREATE WRITABLE EXTERNAL
                     TABLE</codeph>). Files created by the <codeph>gpcheckcloud</codeph> utility
                  always uses the extension <filepath>.data</filepath>.</li>
               <li><filepath>.gz</filepath> is appended to the filename if compression is enabled
                  for S3 writable tables (the default).</li>
            </ul></p>
         <p>For writable S3 tables, you can configure the buffer size and the number of threads that
            segments use for uploading files. See <xref href="#amazon-emr/s3_config_file"
               format="dita"/>.</p>
         <p>For read-only S3 tables, all of the files specified by the S3 file location
               (<varname>S3_endpoint</varname>/<varname>bucket_name</varname>/<varname>S3_prefix</varname>)
            are used as the source for the external table and must have the same format. Each file
            must also contain complete data rows. If the files contain an optional header row, the
            column names in the header row cannot contain a newline character (<codeph>\n</codeph>)
            or a carriage return (<codeph>\r</codeph>). Also, the column delimiter cannot be a
            newline character (<codeph>\n</codeph>) or a carriage return character
               (<codeph>\r</codeph>). </p>
         <p>The <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol recognizes the gzip format and uncompress the files.
            Only the gzip compression format is supported. </p>
         <p>The S3 file permissions must be <codeph>Open/Download</codeph> and <codeph>View</codeph>
            for the S3 user ID that is accessing the files. Writable S3 tables require the S3 user
            ID to have <codeph>Upload/Delete</codeph> permissions.</p>
         <p>For read-only S3 tables, each segment can download one file at a time from S3 location
            using several threads. To take advantage of the parallel processing performed by the
            Greenplum Database segments, the files in the S3 location should be similar in size and
            the number of files should allow for multiple segments to download the data from the S3
            location. For example, if the Greenplum Database system consists of 16 segments and
            there was sufficient network bandwidth, creating 16 files in the S3 location allows each
            segment to download a file from the S3 location. In contrast, if the location contained
            only 1 or 2 files, only 1 or 2 segments download data.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="s3_serversideencrypt">
         <title>s3 Protocol AWS Server-Side Encryption Support</title>
         <p>Greenplum Database supports server-side encryption using Amazon S3-managed keys (SSE-S3)
            for AWS S3 files you access with readable and writable external tables created using the
               <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol. SSE-S3 encrypts your object data as it writes to disk,
            and transparently decrypts the data for you when you access it.</p>
         <note>The <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol supports SSE-S3 only for Amazon Web Services S3
            files. SS3-SE is not supported when accessing files in S3 compatible services.</note>
         <p> Your S3 <codeph>accessid</codeph> and <codeph>secret</codeph> permissions govern your
            access to all S3 bucket objects, whether the data is encrypted or not. However, you must
            configure your client to use S3-managed keys for accessing encrypted data.</p>
         <p>Refer to <xref
               href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/serv-side-encryption.html"
               format="html" scope="external">Protecting Data Using Server-Side Encryption</xref> in
            the AWS documentation for additional information about AWS Server-Side Encryption. </p>
         <sectiondiv>
            <p><b>Configuring S3 Server-Side Encryption</b></p>
            <p><codeph>s3</codeph> protocol server-side encryption is disabled by default. To take
               advantage of server-side encryption on AWS S3 objects you write using the Greenplum
               Database <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol, you must set the
                  <codeph>server_side_encryption</codeph> configuration parameter in your
                  <codeph>s3</codeph> configuration file to the value <codeph>sse-s3</codeph>:</p>
            <p>
               <codeblock>
server_side_encryption = sse-s3
</codeblock>
            </p>
            <p>When the configuration file you provide to a <codeph>CREATE WRITABLE EXTERNAL
                  TABLE</codeph> call using the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol includes the
                  <codeph>server_side_encryption = sse-s3</codeph> setting, Greenplum Database
               applies encryption headers for you on all <codeph>INSERT</codeph> operations on that
               external table. S3 then encrypts on write the object(s) identified by the URI you
               provided in the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause.</p>
            <p>S3 transparently decrypts data during read operations of encrypted files accessed via
               readable external tables you create using the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol. No
               additional configuration is required. </p>
            <p>For further encryption configuration granularity, you may consider creating Amazon
               Web Services S3 <i>Bucket Policy</i>(s), identifying the objects you want to encrypt
               and the write actions on those objects as described in the <xref
                  href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/UsingServerSideEncryption.html"
                  format="html" scope="external">Protecting Data Using Server-Side Encryption with
                  Amazon S3-Managed Encryption Keys (SSE-S3)</xref> AWS documentation.</p>
         </sectiondiv>
      </section>
      <section id="s3_proxy">
         <title>s3 Protocol Proxy Support </title>
         <p>You can specify a URL that is the proxy that S3 uses to connect to a data source. S3
            supports these protocols: HTTP, HTTPS, and SOCKS (4, 4a, 5, 5h). You can specify a proxy
            with the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol configuration parameter <codeph>proxy</codeph> or
            an environment variable. If the configuration parameter is set, the environment
            variables are ignored. </p>
         <p>To specify proxy with an environment variable, you set the environment variable based on
            the protocol: <codeph>http_proxy</codeph>, <codeph>https_proxy</codeph>, or
               <codeph>socks_proxy</codeph>. You can specify a different URL for each protocol by
            setting the appropriate environment variable. S3 supports these environment
               variables.<ul id="ul_cy3_km2_r1b">
               <li><codeph>all_proxy</codeph> specifies the proxy URL that is used if an environment
                  variable for a specific protocol is not set. </li>
               <li><codeph>no_proxy</codeph> specifies a comma-separated list of hosts names that do
                  not use the proxy specified by an environment variable. </li>
            </ul></p>
         <p>The environment variables must be set must and must be accessible to Greenplum Database
            on all Greenplum Database hosts.</p>
         <p>For information about the configuration parameter <codeph>proxy</codeph>, see <xref
               href="#amazon-emr/s3_config_file" format="dita"/>.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="s3_config_param">
         <title>About the s3 Protocol config Parameter</title>
         <p>The optional <codeph>config</codeph> parameter specifies the location of the required
               <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol configuration file. The file contains Amazon Web
            Services (AWS) connection credentials and communication parameters. For information
            about the file, see <xref href="#amazon-emr/s3_config_file" format="dita"/>.</p>
         <p>The configuration file is required on all Greenplum Database segment hosts. This is
            default location is a location in the data directory of each Greenplum Database segment
            instance.<codeblock><varname>gpseg_data_dir</varname>/<varname>gpseg_prefix</varname><varname>N</varname>/s3/s3.conf</codeblock></p>
         <p>The <varname>gpseg_data_dir</varname> is the path to the Greenplum Database segment data
            directory, the <varname>gpseg_prefix</varname> is the segment prefix, and
               <varname>N</varname> is the segment ID. The segment data directory, prefix, and ID
            are set when you initialize a Greenplum Database system.</p>
         <p>If you have multiple segment instances on segment hosts, you can simplify the
            configuration by creating a single location on each segment host. Then you specify the
            absolute path to the location with the <codeph>config</codeph> parameter in the
               <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause. This example specifies
            a location in the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> home directory. </p>
         <codeblock>LOCATION ('s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test/my_data config=/home/gpadmin/s3.conf')</codeblock>
         <p>All segment instances on the hosts use the file
            <codeph>/home/gpadmin/s3.conf</codeph>.</p>
      </section>
      <section id="s3_config_file">
         <title>s3 Protocol Configuration File</title>
         <p>When using the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol, an <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol
            configuration file is required on all Greenplum Database segments. The default location
            is:<codeblock><varname>gpseg_data_dir</varname>/<varname>gpseg-prefix</varname><varname>N</varname>/s3/s3.conf</codeblock></p>
         <p>The <varname>gpseg_data_dir</varname> is the path to the Greenplum Database segment data
            directory, the <varname>gpseg-prefix</varname> is the segment prefix, and
               <varname>N</varname> is the segment ID. The segment data directory, prefix, and ID
            are set when you initialize a Greenplum Database system.</p>
         <p>If you have multiple segment instances on segment hosts, you can simplify the
            configuration by creating a single location on each segment host. Then you can specify
            the absolute path to the location with the <codeph>config</codeph> parameter in the
               <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause. However, note that
            both read-only and writable S3 external tables use the same parameter values for their
            connections. If you want to configure protocol parameters differently for read-only and
            writable S3 tables, then you must use two different <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol
            configuration files and specify the correct file in the <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL
               TABLE</codeph> statement when you create each table.</p>
         <p>This example specifies a single file location in the <codeph>s3</codeph> directory of
            the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> home directory:</p>
         <codeblock>config=/home/gpadmin/s3/s3.conf</codeblock>
         <p>All segment instances on the hosts use the file
               <codeph>/home/gpadmin/s3/s3.conf</codeph>.</p>
         <p>The <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol configuration file is a text file that consists of a
               <codeph>[default]</codeph> section and parameters This is an example configuration
            file:<codeblock>[default]
secret = "secret"
accessid = "user access id"
threadnum = 3
chunksize = 67108864</codeblock></p>
         <p>You can use the Greenplum Database <codeph>gpcheckcloud</codeph> utility to test the S3
            configuration file. See <xref href="#amazon-emr/s3chkcfg_utility" format="dita"/>.</p>
         <sectiondiv>
            <p><b>s3 Configuration File Parameters</b></p>
            <parml>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>accessid</pt>
                  <pd>Required. AWS S3 ID to access the S3 bucket.</pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>secret</pt>
                  <pd>Required. AWS S3 passcode for the S3 ID to access the S3 bucket.</pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>autocompress</pt>
                  <pd>For writable S3 external tables, this parameter specifies whether to compress
                     files (using gzip) before uploading to S3. Files are compressed by default if
                     you do not specify this parameter.</pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>chunksize</pt>
                  <pd>The buffer size that each segment thread uses for reading from or writing to
                     the S3 server. The default is 64 MB. The minimum is 8MB and the maximum is
                     128MB. <p>When inserting data to a writable S3 table, each Greenplum Database
                        segment writes the data into its buffer (using multiple threads up to the
                           <codeph>threadnum</codeph> value) until it is full, after which it writes
                        the buffer to a file in the S3 bucket. This process is then repeated as
                        necessary on each segment until the insert operation
                        completes.</p><p>Because Amazon S3 allows a maximum of 10,000 parts for
                        multipart uploads, the minimum <codeph>chunksize</codeph> value of 8MB
                        supports a maximum insert size of 80GB per Greenplum database segment. The
                        maximum <codeph>chunksize</codeph> value of 128MB supports a maximum insert
                        size 1.28TB per segment. For writable S3 tables, you must ensure that the
                           <codeph>chunksize</codeph> setting can support the anticipated table size
                        of your table. See <xref
                           href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/mpuoverview.html"
                           format="html" scope="external">Multipart Upload Overview</xref> in the S3
                        documentation for more information about uploads to S3.</p></pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>encryption</pt>
                  <pd>Use connections that are secured with Secure Sockets Layer (SSL). Default
                     value is <codeph>true</codeph>. The values <codeph>true</codeph>,
                        <codeph>t</codeph>, <codeph>on</codeph>, <codeph>yes</codeph>, and
                        <codeph>y</codeph> (case insensitive) are treated as <codeph>true</codeph>.
                     Any other value is treated as <codeph>false</codeph>. <p>If the port is not
                        specified in the URL in the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause of the
                           <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> command, the configuration file
                           <codeph>encryption</codeph> parameter affects the port used by the
                           <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol (port 80 for HTTP or port 443 for HTTPS). If
                        the port is specified, that port is used regardless of the encryption
                        setting.</p></pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>gpcheckcloud_newline</pt>
                  <pd>When downloading files from an S3 location, the <codeph>gpcheckcloud</codeph>
                     utility appends a new line character to last line of a file if the last line of
                     a file does not have an EOL (end of line) character. The default character is
                        <codeph>\n</codeph> (newline). The value can be <codeph>\n</codeph>,
                        <codeph>\r</codeph> (carriage return), or <codeph>\n\r</codeph>
                     (newline/carriage return).<p>Adding an EOL character prevents the last line of
                        one file from being concatenated with the first line of next file.</p></pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>low_speed_limit</pt>
                  <pd>The upload/download speed lower limit, in bytes per second. The default speed
                     is 10240 (10K). If the upload or download speed is slower than the limit for
                     longer than the time specified by <codeph>low_speed_time</codeph>, then the
                     connection is aborted and retried. After 3 retries, the <codeph>s3</codeph>
                     protocol returns an error. A value of 0 specifies no lower limit.</pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>low_speed_time</pt>
                  <pd>When the connection speed is less than <codeph>low_speed_limit</codeph>, this
                     parameter specified the amount of time, in seconds, to wait before aborting an
                     upload to or a download from the S3 bucket. The default is 60 seconds. A value
                     of 0 specifies no time limit.</pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>proxy</pt>
                  <pd>Specify a URL that is the proxy that S3 uses to connect to a data source. S3
                     supports these protocols: HTTP, HTTPS, and SOCKS (4, 4a, 5, 5h). This is the
                     format for the
                     parameter.<codeblock>proxy = <varname>protocol</varname>://[<varname>user</varname>:<varname>password</varname>@]<varname>proxyhost</varname>[:<varname>port</varname>]</codeblock></pd>
                  <pd>If this parameter is not set or is an empty string (<codeph>proxy =
                        ""</codeph>), S3 uses the proxy specified by the environment variable
                        <codeph>http_proxy</codeph>, <codeph>https_proxy</codeph>, or
                        <codeph>socks_proxy</codeph> (and the environment variables
                        <codeph>all_proxy</codeph> and <codeph>no_proxy</codeph>). The environment
                     variable that S3 uses depends on the protocol. For information about the
                     environment variables, see <xref href="g-s3-protocol.xml#amazon-emr/s3_proxy"
                        format="dita" scope="peer">s3 Protocol Proxy Support</xref><ph
                        otherprops="op-print"> in the <cite>Greenplum Database Administrator
                           Guide</cite></ph>.</pd>
                  <pd>There can be at most one <codeph>proxy</codeph> parameter in the configuration
                     file. The URL specified by the parameter is the proxy for all supported
                     protocols. </pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>server_side_encryption</pt>
                  <pd>The S3 server-side encryption method that has been configured for the bucket.
                     Greenplum Database supports only server-side encryption with Amazon S3-managed
                     keys, identified by the configuration parameter value <codeph>sse-s3</codeph>.
                     Server-side encryption is disabled (<codeph>none</codeph>) by default.</pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>threadnum</pt>
                  <pd>The maximum number of concurrent threads a segment can create when uploading
                     data to or downloading data from the S3 bucket. The default is 4. The minimum
                     is 1 and the maximum is 8.</pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>verifycert</pt>
                  <pd>Controls how the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol handles authentication when
                     establishing encrypted communication between a client and an S3 data source
                     over HTTPS. The value is either <codeph>true</codeph> or
                     <codeph>false</codeph>. The default value is <codeph>true</codeph>.<ul
                        id="ul_hxt_gkl_wy">
                        <li><codeph>verifycert=false</codeph> - Ignores authentication errors and
                           allows encrypted communication over HTTPS.</li>
                        <li><codeph>verifycert=true</codeph> - Requires valid authentication (a
                           proper certificate) for encrypted communication over HTTPS.</li>
                     </ul></pd>
                  <pd>Setting the value to <codeph>false</codeph> can be useful in testing and
                     development environments to allow communication without changing
                        certificates.<note type="warning">Setting the value to
                           <codeph>false</codeph> exposes a security risk by ignoring invalid
                        credentials when establishing communication between a client and a S3 data
                        store. </note></pd>
               </plentry>
               <plentry>
                  <pt>version</pt>
                  <pd>Specifies the version of the information specified in the
                        <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause of the <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL
                        TABLE</codeph> command. The value is either <codeph>1</codeph> or
                        <codeph>2</codeph>. The default value is <codeph>1</codeph>.</pd>
                  <pd>If the value is <codeph>1</codeph>, the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause
                     supports an Amazon S3 URL, and does not contain the <codeph>region</codeph>
                     parameter. If the value is <codeph>2</codeph>, the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph>
                     clause supports S3 compatible services and must include the
                        <codeph>region</codeph> parameter. The <codeph>region</codeph> parameter
                     specifies the S3 data source region. For this S3 URL
                        <codeph>s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/s3test.example.com/dataset1/normal/</codeph>,
                     the AWS S3 region is <codeph>us-west-2</codeph>. </pd>
                  <pd>If <codeph>version</codeph> is 1 or is not specified, this is an example of
                     the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause of the <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL
                        TABLE</codeph> command that specifies an Amazon S3
                     endpoint.<codeblock>LOCATION ('s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/s3test.example.com/dataset1/normal/
      config=/home/gpadmin/aws_s3/s3.conf')</codeblock></pd>
                  <pd> If <codeph>version</codeph> is 2, this is an example
                        <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause with the <codeph>region</codeph> parameter
                     for an AWS S3 compatible
                     service.<codeblock>LOCATION ('s3://test.company.com/s3test.company/test1/normal/ region=local-test
      config=/home/gpadmin/aws_s3/s3.conf') </codeblock></pd>
                  <pd>If <codeph>version</codeph> is 2, the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause can
                     also specify an Amazon S3 endpoint. This example specifies an Amazon S3
                     endpoint that uses the <codeph>region</codeph>
                     parameter.<codeblock>LOCATION ('s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/s3test.example.com/dataset1/normal/ region=us-west-2
      config=/home/gpadmin/aws_s3/s3.conf') </codeblock></pd>
               </plentry>
            </parml>
            <note><ph id="memory-phrase">Greenplum Database can require up to <codeph>threadnum *
                     chunksize</codeph> memory on each segment host when uploading or downloading S3
                  files. Consider this <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol memory requirement when you
                  configure overall Greenplum Database memory.</ph>
            </note>
         </sectiondiv>
      </section>
      <section id="section_tsq_n3t_3x">
         <title>s3 Protocol Limitations</title>
         <p>These are <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol limitations: <ul id="ul_qqg_qcz_55">
               <li>Only the S3 path-style URL is
                  supported.<codeblock>s3://<varname>S3_endpoint</varname>/<varname>bucketname</varname>/[<varname>S3_prefix</varname>]</codeblock></li>
               <li>Only the S3 endpoint is supported. The protocol does not support virtual hosting
                  of S3 buckets (binding a domain name to an S3 bucket).</li>
               <li>AWS signature version 4 signing process is supported. <p>For information about
                     the S3 endpoints supported by each signing process, see <xref
                        href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/rande.html#s3_region"
                        format="html" scope="external"
                        >http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/rande.html#s3_region</xref>.</p></li>
               <li>Only a single URL and optional configuration file is supported in the
                     <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause of the <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph>
                  command.</li>
               <li>If the <codeph>NEWLINE</codeph> parameter is not specified in the <codeph>CREATE
                     EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> command, the newline character must be identical in all
                  data files for specific prefix. If the newline character is different in some data
                  files with the same prefix, read operations on the files might fail.</li>
               <li>For writable S3 external tables, only the <codeph>INSERT</codeph> operation is
                  supported. <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, <codeph>DELETE</codeph>, and
                     <codeph>TRUNCATE</codeph> operations are not supported.</li>
               <li>Because Amazon S3 allows a maximum of 10,000 parts for multipart uploads, the
                  maximum <codeph>chunksize</codeph> value of 128MB supports a maximum insert size
                  of 1.28TB per Greenplum database segment for writable s3 tables. You must ensure
                  that the <codeph>chunksize</codeph> setting can support the anticipated table size
                  of your table. See <xref
                     href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/mpuoverview.html"
                     format="html" scope="external">Multipart Upload Overview</xref> in the S3
                  documentation for more information about uploads to S3.</li>
               <li>To take advantage of the parallel processing performed by the Greenplum Database
                  segment instances, the files in the S3 location for read-only S3 tables should be
                  similar in size and the number of files should allow for multiple segments to
                  download the data from the S3 location. For example, if the Greenplum Database
                  system consists of 16 segments and there was sufficient network bandwidth,
                  creating 16 files in the S3 location allows each segment to download a file from
                  the S3 location. In contrast, if the location contained only 1 or 2 files, only 1
                  or 2 segments download data.</li>
            </ul></p>
      </section>
      <section id="s3chkcfg_utility"><title>Using the gpcheckcloud Utility</title><p>The Greenplum
            Database utility <codeph>gpcheckcloud</codeph> helps users create an <codeph>s3</codeph>
            protocol configuration file and test a configuration file. You can specify options to
            test the ability to access an S3 bucket with a configuration file, and optionally upload
            data to or download data from files in the bucket.</p><p>If you run the utility without
            any options, it sends a template configuration file to <codeph>STDOUT</codeph>. You can
            capture the output and create an <codeph>s3</codeph> configuration file to connect to
            Amazon S3. </p><p>The utility is installed in the Greenplum Database
               <codeph>$GPHOME/bin</codeph> directory.</p><b>Syntax</b>
         <codeblock>gpcheckcloud {<b>-c</b> | <b>-d</b>} "<b>s3://</b><varname>S3_endpoint</varname>/<varname>bucketname</varname>/[<varname>S3_prefix</varname>] [config=<varname>path_to_config_file</varname>]"

gpcheckcloud <b>-u</b> &lt;file_to_upload> "<b>s3://</b><varname>S3_endpoint</varname>/<varname>bucketname</varname>/[<varname>S3_prefix</varname>] [config=<varname>path_to_config_file</varname>]"
gpcheckcloud <b>-t</b>

gpcheckcloud <b>-h</b></codeblock>
         <b>Options</b>
         <parml>
            <plentry>
               <pt>-c</pt>
               <pd>Connect to the specified S3 location with the configuration specified in the
                     <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol URL and return information about the files in the
                  S3 location.</pd>
               <pd>If the connection fails, the utility displays information about failures such as
                  invalid credentials, prefix, or server address (DNS error), or server not
                  available.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
               <pt>-d</pt>
               <pd>Download data from the specified S3 location with the configuration specified in
                  the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol URL and send the output to
                     <codeph>STDOUT</codeph>.</pd>
               <pd>If files are gzip compressed, the uncompressed data is sent to
                     <codeph>STDOUT</codeph>.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
               <pt>-u</pt>
               <pd>Upload a file to the S3 bucket specified in the <codeph>s3</codeph> protocol URL
                  using the specified configuration file if available. Use this option to test
                  compression and <codeph>chunksize</codeph> and <codeph>autocompress</codeph>
                  settings for your configuration.</pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
               <pt>-t</pt>
               <pd>Sends a template configuration file to <codeph>STDOUT</codeph>. You can capture
                  the output and create an <codeph>s3</codeph> configuration file to connect to
                  Amazon S3. </pd>
            </plentry>
            <plentry>
               <pt>-h</pt>
               <pd>Display <codeph>gpcheckcloud</codeph> help.</pd>
            </plentry>
         </parml><p><b>Examples</b>
         </p><p>This example runs the utility without options to create a template
               <codeph>s3</codeph> configuration file <codeph>mytest_s3.config</codeph> in the
            current directory.<codeblock>gpcheckcloud -t > ./mytest_s3.config</codeblock></p><p>This
            example attempts to upload a local file, <filepath>test-data.csv</filepath> to an S3
            bucket location using the <codeph>s3</codeph> configuration file
               <codeph>s3.mytestconf</codeph>:<codeblock>gpcheckcloud -u ./test-data.csv "s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc config=s3.mytestconf"</codeblock></p><p>A
            successful upload results in one or more files placed in the S3 bucket using the
            filename format <codeph> abc&lt;segment_id>&lt;random>.data[.gz]</codeph>. See <xref
               href="#amazon-emr/section_c2f_zvs_3x" format="dita"/>.</p><p>This example attempts to
            connect to an S3 bucket location with the <codeph>s3</codeph> configuration file
               <codeph>s3.mytestconf</codeph>.<codeblock>gpcheckcloud -c "s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc config=s3.mytestconf"</codeblock></p><p>Download
            all files from the S3 bucket location and send the output to <codeph>STDOUT</codeph>.
            <codeblock>gpcheckcloud -d "s3://s3-us-west-2.amazonaws.com/test1/abc config=s3.mytestconf"</codeblock></p></section>
   </body>
</topic>
