<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic13">
   <title>Using the Greenplum Parallel File Server (gpfdist)</title>
   <shortdesc>The <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> protocol is used in a <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL
         TABLE</codeph> SQL command to access external data served by the Greenplum Database
         <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> file server utility. When external data is served by
         <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>, all segments in the Greenplum Database system can read or write
      external table data in parallel.</shortdesc>
   <body>
      <p>This topic describes the setup and management tasks for using <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>
         with external tables.</p>
      <ul id="ul_krw_tmg_bbb">
         <li><xref href="#topic_xkt_vjy_4bb" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic14" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic15" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic16" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic17" format="dita"/></li>
         <li><xref href="#topic18" format="dita"/></li>
      </ul>
   </body>
   <topic id="topic_xkt_vjy_4bb">
      <title>About gpfdist and External Tables</title>
      <body>
         <p>The <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> file server utility is located in the
               <codeph>$GPHOME/bin</codeph> directory on your Greenplum Database master host and on
            each segment host. When you start a <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> instance you specify a
            listen port and the path to a directory containing files to read or where files are to
            be written. For example, this command runs <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> in the background,
            listening on port 8801, and serving files in the
               <codeph>/home/gpadmin/external_files</codeph> directory:</p>
         <codeblock>$ gpfdist -p 8801 -d /home/gpadmin/external_files &amp;</codeblock>
         <p>The <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> command <codeph>LOCATION</codeph> clause
            connects an external table definition to one or more <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> instances.
            If the external table is readable, the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> server reads data
            records from files from in specified directory, packs them into a block, and sends the
            block in a response to a Greenplum Database segment's request. The segments unpack rows
            they receive and distribute them according to the external table's distribution policy.
            If the external table is a writable table, segments send blocks of rows in a request to
            gpfdist and gpfdist writes them to the external file.</p>
         <p>External data files can contain rows in CSV format or any delimited text format
            supported by the <codeph>FORMAT</codeph> clause of the <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL
               TABLE</codeph> command. In addition, <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> can be configured with
            a YAML-formatted file to transform external data files between a supported text format
            and another format, for example XML or JSON. See &lt;ref> for an example that shows how
            to use <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> to read external XML files into a Greenplum Database
            readable external table. </p>
         <p>For readable external tables, <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> uncompresses
               <codeph>gzip</codeph> (<codeph>.gz</codeph>) and <codeph>bzip2</codeph>
               (.<codeph>bz2</codeph>) files automatically. You can use the wildcard character (*)
            or other C-style pattern matching to denote multiple files to read. External files are
            assumed to be relative to the directory specified when you started the
               <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> instance. </p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic14">
      <title>About gpfdist Setup and Performance</title>
      <body>
         <p>You can run <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> instances on multiple hosts and you can run
            multiple <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> instances on each host. This allows you to deploy
               <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> servers strategically so that you can attain fast data load
            and unload rates by utilizing all of the available network bandwidth and Greenplum
            Database's parallelism. </p>
         <ul id="ul_rkb_plg_bbb">
            <li id="du165860">Allow network traffic to use all ETL host network interfaces
               simultaneously. Run one instance of <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> for each interface on
               the ETL host, then declare the host name of each NIC in the <codeph>LOCATION</codeph>
               clause of your external table definition (see <xref
                  href="g-creating-external-tables---examples.xml#topic44"/>).</li>
         </ul>
         <fig id="du165872">
            <title>External Table Using Single gpfdist Instance with Multiple NICs</title>
            <image href="../graphics/ext_tables_multinic.jpg" placement="break" width="472px"
               height="271px" id="image_skb_plg_bbb"/>
         </fig>
         <ul id="ul_tkb_plg_bbb">
            <li id="du212280">Divide external table data equally among multiple
                  <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> instances on the ETL host. For example, on an ETL
               system with two NICs, run two <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> instances (one on each NIC)
               to optimize data load performance and divide the external table data files evenly
               between the two <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> servers.</li>
         </ul>
         <fig id="du165882">
            <title>External Tables Using Multiple gpfdist Instances with Multiple NICs</title>
            <image href="../graphics/ext_tables.jpg" placement="break" width="467px" height="282px"
               id="image_ukb_plg_bbb"/>
         </fig>
         <note type="note">Use pipes (|) to separate formatted text when you submit files to
               <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>. Greenplum Database encloses comma-separated text strings
            in single or double quotes. <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> has to remove the quotes to parse
            the strings. Using pipes to separate formatted text avoids the extra step and improves
            performance.</note>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic15">
      <title>Controlling Segment Parallelism</title>
      <body>
         <p>The <codeph>gp_external_max_segs</codeph> server configuration parameter controls the
            number of segment instances that can access a single <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> instance
            simultaneously. 64 is the default. You can set the number of segments such that some
            segments process external data files and some perform other database processing. Set
            this parameter in the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file of your master instance.</p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic16">
      <title>Installing gpfdist</title>
      <body>
         <p>
            <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> is installed in <codeph>$GPHOME/bin</codeph> of your
            Greenplum Database master host installation. Run <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> on a machine
            other than the Greenplum Database master or standby master, such as on a machine devoted
            to ETL processing. Running <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> on the master or standby master
            can have a performance impact on query execution. To install <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>
            on your ETL server, get it from the <i>Greenplum Load Tools</i> package and follow its
            installation instructions.</p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic17">
      <title>Starting and Stopping gpfdist</title>
      <body>
         <p>You can start <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> in your current directory location or in any
            directory that you specify. The default port is <codeph>8080</codeph>.</p>
         <p>From your current directory, type: </p>
         <p>
            <codeblock>gpfdist &amp;</codeblock>
         </p>
         <p>From a different directory, specify the directory from which to serve files, and
            optionally, the HTTP port to run on.</p>
         <p>To start <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> in the background and log output messages and errors
            to a log file:</p>
         <p>
            <codeblock>$ gpfdist -d /var/load_files -p 8081 -l /home/<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>/log &amp;
</codeblock>
         </p>
         <p>For multiple <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> instances on the same ETL host (see <xref
               href="#topic14/du165872" format="dita"/>), use a different base directory and port
            for each instance. For example:</p>
         <p>
            <codeblock>$ gpfdist -d /var/load_files1 -p 8081 -l /home/<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>/log1 &amp;
$ gpfdist -d /var/load_files2 -p 8082 -l /home/<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>/log2 &amp;
</codeblock>
         </p>
         <p>To stop <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> when it is running in the background:</p>
         <p>First find its process id:</p>
         <p>
            <codeblock>$ ps -ef | grep gpfdist</codeblock>
         </p>
         <p>Then kill the process, for example (where 3456 is the process ID in this example):</p>
         <p>
            <codeblock>$ kill 3456
</codeblock>
         </p>
      </body>
   </topic>
   <topic id="topic18">
      <title>Troubleshooting gpfdist</title>
      <body>
         <p>The segments access <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> at runtime. Ensure that the Greenplum
            segment hosts have network access to <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>.
               <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> is a web server: test connectivity by running the
            following command from each host in the Greenplum array (segments and master):</p>
         <p>
            <codeblock>$ wget http://<i>gpfdist_hostname</i>:<i>port</i>/<i>filename</i>
         </codeblock>
         </p>
         <p>The <codeph>CREATE EXTERNAL TABLE</codeph> definition must have the correct host name,
            port, and file names for <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname>. Specify file names and paths
            relative to the directory from which <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> serves files (the
            directory path specified when <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> started). See <xref
               href="g-creating-external-tables---examples.xml#topic44"/>.</p>
         <p>If you start <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> on your system and IPv6 networking is disabled,
               <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> displays this warning message when testing for an IPv6
            port.</p>
         <codeblock>[WRN gpfdist.c:2050] Creating the socket failed
</codeblock>
         <p>If the corresponding IPv4 port is available, <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> uses that port
            and the warning for IPv6 port can be ignored. To see information about the ports that
               <cmdname>gpfdist</cmdname> tests, use the <codeph>-V</codeph> option.</p>
         <p>For information about IPv6 and IPv4 networking, see your operating system
            documentation.</p>
         <p>When reading or writing data with the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> or
               <codeph>gfdists</codeph> protocol, the <codeph>gpfdist</codeph> utility rejects HTTP
            requests that do not include <codeph>X-GP-PROTO</codeph> in the request header. If
               <codeph>X-GP-PROTO</codeph> is not detected in the header request
               <codeph>gpfist</codeph> returns a 400 error in the status line of the HTTP response
            header: <codeph>400 invalid request (no gp-proto)</codeph>.</p>
         <p>Greenplum Database includes <codeph>X-GP-PROTO</codeph> in the HTTP request header to
            indicate that the request is from Greenplum Database. </p>
      </body>
   </topic>
</topic>
