<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_f5l_qnh_kr">
  <title>Working with External Data</title>
  <shortdesc>Both external and foreign tables provide access to data stored in
    data sources outside of Greenplum Database as if the data were stored in
    regular database tables. You can read data from and write data to external
    and foreign tables.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>An external table is a Greenplum Database table backed with data that
      resides outside of the database. You create a readable external table
      to read data from the external data source and create a writable
      external table to write data to the external source. You can use
      external tables in SQL commands just as you would a regular database
      table. For example, you can <codeph>SELECT</codeph> (readable external
      table), <codeph>INSERT</codeph> (writable external table), and join
      external tables with other Greenplum tables. External tables are most
      often used to load and unload database data. Refer to
      <xref href="g-external-tables.xml#topic3"/> for more information about
      using external tables to access external data.</p>
    <p><xref href="pxf-overview.xml" type="topic">Accessing External Data with PXF</xref>
      describes using PXF and external tables to access external data sources.</p>
    <p>A foreign table is a different kind of Greenplum Database table backed with
      data that resides outside of the database. You can both read from and write
      to the same foreign table. You can similarly use foreign tables in SQL
      commands as described above for external tables. Refer to
      <xref href="g-foreign.xml#topic1"/> for more information about accessing
      external data using foreign tables.</p>
    <p>Web-based external tables provide access to data served by an HTTP server or an operating
      system process. See <xref href="g-creating-and-using-web-external-tables.xml#topic31"/> for
      more about web-based tables. </p>
  </body>
</topic>
