<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE dita PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<dita>
  <topic id="topic_vmf_z4c_qfb">
    <title>Pseudo-Types</title>
    <body>
      <p>Greenplum Database supports special-purpose data type entries that are collectively called
          <i>pseudo-types</i>. A pseudo-type cannot be used as a column data type, but it can be
        used to declare a function's argument or result type. Each of the available pseudo-types is
        useful in situations where a function's behavior does not correspond to simply taking or
        returning a value of a specific SQL data type.</p>
      <p>Functions coded in procedural languages can use pseudo-types only as allowed by their
        implementation languages. The procedural languages all forbid use of a pseudo-type as an
        argument type, and allow only <i>void</i> and <i>record</i> as a result type. </p>
      <p>A function with the pseudo-type <i>record</i> as a return data type returns an unspecified
        row type. The <i>record</i> represents an array of possibly-anonymous composite types. Since
        composite datums carry their own type identification, no extra knowledge is needed at the
        array level.</p>
      <p>The pseudo-type <i>void</i> indicates that a function returns no value.</p>
      <note>Greenplum Database does not support triggers and the pseudo-type <i>trigger</i>.</note>
      <p>The types <i>anyelement</i>, <i>anyarray</i>, <i>anynonarray</i>, and <i>anyenum</i> are
        pseudo-types called polymorphic types. Some procedural languages also support polymorphic
        functions using the types <i>anyarray</i>, <i>anyelement</i>, <i>anyenum</i>, and
          <i>anynonarray</i>.</p>
      <p>The pseudo-type <i>anytable</i> is a Greenplum Database type that specifies a table
        expression—an expression that computes a table. Greenplum Database allows this type only as
        an argument to a user-defined function. See <xref href="#topic_ig2_1pc_qfb" format="dita"/>
        for more about the <i>anytable</i> pseudo-type.</p>
      <p>For more information about pseudo-types, see the PostgreSQL documentation about <xref
          href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/datatype-pseudo.html" format="html"
          scope="external">Pseudo-Types</xref>.</p>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic_dbn_bpc_qfb">
      <title>Polymorphic Types</title>
      <body>
        <p>Four pseudo-types of special interest are <i>anyelement</i>, <i>anyarray</i>,
            <i>anynonarray</i>, and <i>anyenum</i>, which are collectively called <i>polymorphic</i>
          types. Any function declared using these types is said to be a polymorphic function. A
          polymorphic function can operate on many different data types, with the specific data
          types being determined by the data types actually passed to it at runtime.</p>
        <p>Polymorphic arguments and results are tied to each other and are resolved to a specific
          data type when a query calling a polymorphic function is parsed. Each position (either
          argument or return value) declared as <i>anyelement</i> is allowed to have any specific
          actual data type, but in any given call they must all be the same actual type. Each
          position declared as <i>anyarray</i> can have any array data type, but similarly they must
          all be the same type. If there are positions declared <i>anyarray</i> and others declared
            <i>anyelement</i>, the actual array type in the <i>anyarray</i> positions must be an
          array whose elements are the same type appearing in the <i>anyelement</i> positions.
            <i>anynonarray</i> is treated exactly the same as <i>anyelement</i>, but adds the
          additional constraint that the actual type must not be an array type. <i>anyenum</i> is
          treated exactly the same as <i>anyelement</i>, but adds the additional constraint that the
          actual type must be an <codeph>enum</codeph> type. </p>
        <p>When more than one argument position is declared with a polymorphic type, the net effect
          is that only certain combinations of actual argument types are allowed. For example, a
          function declared as <codeph>equal(<i>anyelement</i>, <i>anyelement</i>)</codeph> takes
          any two input values, so long as they are of the same data type.</p>
        <p>When the return value of a function is declared as a polymorphic type, there must be at
          least one argument position that is also polymorphic, and the actual data type supplied as
          the argument determines the actual result type for that call. For example, if there were
          not already an array subscripting mechanism, one could define a function that implements
          subscripting as <codeph>subscript(<i>anyarray</i>, integer) returns
            <i>anyelement</i></codeph>. This declaration constrains the actual first argument to be
          an array type, and allows the parser to infer the correct result type from the actual
          first argument's type. Another example is that a function declared as
              <codeph>myfunc(<i>anyarray</i>) returns <i>anyenum</i></codeph> will only accept
          arrays of <codeph>enum</codeph> types.</p>
        <p>Note that <i>anynonarray</i> and <i>anyenum</i> do not represent separate type variables;
          they are the same type as <i>anyelement</i>, just with an additional constraint. For
          example, declaring a function as <codeph>myfunc(<i>anyelement</i>,
            <i>anyenum</i>)</codeph> is equivalent to declaring it as <codeph>myfunc(<i>anyenum</i>,
              <i>anyenum</i>)</codeph>: both actual arguments must be the same <codeph>enum</codeph>
          type.</p>
        <p>A variadic function (one taking a variable number of arguments) is polymorphic when its
          last parameter is declared as <codeph>VARIADIC <i>anyarray</i></codeph>. For purposes of
          argument matching and determining the actual result type, such a function behaves the same
          as if you had declared the appropriate number of <i>anynonarray</i> parameters.</p>
        <p>For more information about polymorphic types, see the PostgreSQL documentation about <xref
            href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/9.4/xfunc-c.html#AEN56822" format="html"
            scope="external">Polymorphic Arguments and Return Types</xref>.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_ig2_1pc_qfb">
      <title>Table Value Expressions</title>
      <body>
        <p>The <i>anytable</i> pseudo-type declares a function argument that is a table value
          expression. The notation for a table value expression is a <codeph>SELECT</codeph>
          statement enclosed in a <codeph>TABLE()</codeph> function. You can specify a distribution
          policy for the table by adding <codeph>SCATTER RANDOMLY</codeph>, or a <codeph>SCATTER
            BY</codeph> clause with a column list to specify the distribution key. </p>
        <p>The <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement is executed when the function is called and the
          result rows are distributed to segments so that each segment executes the function with a
          subset of the result table.</p>
        <p>For example, this table expression selects three columns from a table named
            <codeph>customer</codeph> and sets the distribution key to the first column:</p>
        <codeblock>TABLE(SELECT cust_key, name, address FROM customer SCATTER BY 1)</codeblock>
        <p>The <codeph>SELECT</codeph> statement may include joins on multiple base tables,
            <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clauses, aggregates, and any other valid query syntax.</p>
        <p>The <i>anytable</i> type is only permitted in functions implemented in the C or C++
          languages. The body of the function can access the table using the Greenplum Database
          Server Programming Interface (SPI) or the Greenplum Partner Connector (GPPC) API. </p>
        <p otherprops="pivotal">The <i>anytable</i> type is used in some user-defined functions in
          the Pivotal GPText API. The following GPText example uses the <codeph>TABLE</codeph>
          function with the <codeph>SCATTER BY</codeph> clause in the GPText function
            <codeph>gptext.index()</codeph> to populate the index
            <codeph>mydb.mytest.articles</codeph> with data from the messages
          table:<codeblock>SELECT * FROM gptext.index(TABLE(SELECT * FROM mytest.messages 
          SCATTER BY distrib_id), 'mydb.mytest.messages');
        </codeblock></p>
        <p otherprops="pivotal">For information about the function <codeph>gptext.index()</codeph>,
          see the Pivotal GPText documentation.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</dita>
