<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_dyz_d5j_tbb">
  <title>gpbackup</title>
  <body>
    <p>Create a Greenplum Database backup for use with the <codeph>gprestore</codeph> utility. </p>
    <note><codeph>gpbackup</codeph> and <codeph>gprestore</codeph> are experimental utilities and
      are not intended for use in a production environment. Experimental features are subject to
      change without notice in future releases.</note>
    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock><b>gpbackup -dbname</b> <varname>database_name</varname>
   [<b>-backupdir</b> <varname>directory</varname>]
   [<b>-compression-level</b> <varname>level</varname>
   [<b>-data-only</b>]
   [<b>-debug</b>]
   [<b>-exclude-schema</b> <varname>schema_name</varname>]
   [<b>-exclude-table</b> <varname>schema.table</varname>]
   [<b>-exclude-table-file</b> <varname>file_name</varname>]
   [<b>-include-schema</b> <varname>schema_name</varname>]
   [[<b>-include-table</b> <varname>schema.table</varname>]
   [<b>-include-table-file</b> <varname>file_name</varname>]
   [<b>-leaf-partition-data</b>]
   [<b>-metadata-only</b>]
   [<b>-no-compression</b>]
   [<b>-quiet</b>]
   [<b>-single-data-file]</b>
   [<b>-verbose</b>]
   [<b>-version</b>]
   [<b>-with-stats</b>]</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section><title>Description</title><p>The <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> utility backs up the
        contents of a database into a collection of metadata files and data files that can be used
        to restore the database at a later time using <codeph>gprestore</codeph>. When you back up a
        database, you can specify table level and schema level filter options to back up specific
        tables. For example, you can combine schema level and table level options to back up all the
        tables in a schema except for a single table. </p><p>By default, <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>
        backs up objects in the specified database as well as global Greenplum Database system
        objects. You can optionally supply the <codeph>-globals</codeph> option with
          <codeph>gprestore</codeph> to restore global objects. See <xref
          href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_x3s_lqj_tbb"/> for additional
        information.</p><p><codeph>gpbackup</codeph> stores the object metadata files and DDL files
        for a backup in the Greenplum Database master data directory by default. Greenplum Database
        segments use the <codeph>COPY ... ON SEGMENT</codeph> command to store their data for
        backed-up tables in compressed CSV data files, located in each segment's data directory. See
          <xref href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_xnj_b4c_tbb"/> for
        additional information.</p><p>You can add the <codeph>-backupdir</codeph> option to copy all
        backup files from the Greenplum Database master and segment hosts to an absolute path for
        later use. Additional options are provided to filter the backup set in order to include or
        exclude specific tables.</p><p>Each <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> task uses a single transaction
        on the Greenplum database master host. Utility-mode connections are created for each segment
        host, which perform the associated <codeph>COPY ... ON SEGMENT</codeph> operations in
        parallel. The backup process acquires an <codeph>ACCESS SHARE</codeph> lock on each table
        that is backed up.</p><codeph>gpbackup</codeph> will send out status email notifications
      after a back up operation completes, if you place a file named
        <filepath>mail_contacts</filepath> in the home directory of the Greenplum database superuser
      (gpadmin) or in the same directory as the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> utility
        (<filepath>$GPHOME/bin</filepath>). See <xref
        href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_qwd_d5d_tbb"/>.</section>
    <section>
      <title>Options</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-dbname</b>
            <varname>database_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Required. Specifies the database to back up.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-backupdir</b>
            <varname>directory</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Copies all required backup files (metadata files and data files) to the
            specified directory. You must specify <varname>directory</varname> as an absolute path
            (not relative). If you do not supply this option, metadata files are created on the
            Greenplum Database master host in the
              <filepath>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath>
            directory. Segment hosts create CSV data files in the
              <filepath>&lt;seg_dir>/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath> directory. When you
            specify a custom backup directory, files are copied to these paths in subdirectories of
            the backup directory.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-compression-level</b>
            <varname>level</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies the gzip compression level (from 1 to 9) used to compress data
            files. The default is 1. Note that <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> uses compression by
            default.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-data-only</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Backs up only the table data into CSV files, but does not backup metadata
            files needed to recreate the tables and other database objects.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-debug</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Displays verbose debug messages during operation.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-exclude-schema</b>
            <varname>schema_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a database schema to exclude from the backup. You can specify this
            option multiple times to exclude multiple schemas. You cannot combine this option with
            the option <codeph>-include-schema</codeph>, or a table filtering option such as
              <codeph>-include-table</codeph>. See <xref
              href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_et4_b5d_tbb"/> for more
            information.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-exclude-table</b>
            <varname>schema.table</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a table to exclude from the backup. The table must be in the
            format <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. If a table or schema name uses
            any character other than a lowercase letter, number, or an underscore character, then
            you must include that name in double quotes. You can specify this option multiple times.
            You cannot combine this option with the option <codeph>-exclude-schema</codeph>, or
            another a table filtering option such as <codeph>-include-table</codeph>.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot use this option in combination with <codeph>-leaf-partition-data</codeph>.
            Although you can specify leaf partition names, <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> ignores the
            partition names.</pd>
          <pd>See <xref href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_et4_b5d_tbb"/>
            for more information.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-exclude-table-file</b>
            <varname>file_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a text file containing a list of tables to exclude from the
            backup. Each line in the text file must define a single table using the format
              <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. The file must not include trailing
            lines. If a table or schema name uses any character other than a lowercase letter,
            number, or an underscore character, then you must include that name in double quotes.
            You cannot combine this option with the option <codeph>-exclude-schema</codeph>, or
            another a table filtering option such as <codeph>-include-table</codeph>.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot use this option in combination with <codeph>-leaf-partition-data</codeph>.
            Although you can specify leaf partition names in a file specified with
              <codeph>-exclude-table-file</codeph>, <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> ignores the partition
            names.</pd>
          <pd>See <xref href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_et4_b5d_tbb"/>
            for more information.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-include-schema</b>
            <varname>schema_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a database schema to include in the backup. You can specify this
            option multiple times to include multiple schemas. If you specify this option, any
            schemas that are not included in subsequent <codeph>-include-schema</codeph> options are
            omitted from the backup set. You cannot combine this option with the options
              <codeph>-exclude-schema</codeph>, <codeph>-include-table</codeph>, or
              <codeph>-include-table-file</codeph>. See <xref
              href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_et4_b5d_tbb"/> for more
            information.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-include-table</b>
            <varname>schema.table</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a table to include in the backup. The table must be in the format
              <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. If a table or schema name uses any
            character other than a lowercase letter, number, or an underscore character, then you
            must include that name in double quotes. You can specify this option multiple times. You
            cannot combine this option with a schema filtering option such as
              <codeph>-include-schema</codeph>, or another table filtering option such as
              <codeph>-exclude-table-file</codeph>.</pd>
          <pd>You can optionally specify a table leaf partition name in place of the table name, to
            include only specific leaf partitions in a backup with the
              <codeph>-leaf-partition-data</codeph> option. </pd>
          <pd>See <xref href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_et4_b5d_tbb"/>
            for more information.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-include-table-file</b>
            <varname>file_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a text file containing a list of tables to include in the backup.
            Each line in the text file must define a single table using the format
              <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. The file must not include trailing
            lines. If a table or schema name uses any character other than a lowercase letter,
            number, or an underscore character, then you must include that name in double quotes.
            Any tables not listed in this file are omitted from the backup set. You cannot combine
            this option with a schema filtering option such as <codeph>-include-schema</codeph>, or
            another table filtering option such as <codeph>-exclude-table-file</codeph>.</pd>
          <pd>You can optionally specify a table leaf partition name in place of the table name, to
            include only specific leaf partitions in a backup with the
              <codeph>-leaf-partition-data</codeph> option. </pd>
          <pd>See <xref href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_et4_b5d_tbb"/>
            for more information.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-leaf-partition-data</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. For partitioned tables, creates one data file per leaf partition instead of
            one data file for the entire table (the default). Using this option also enables you to
            specify individual leaf partitions to include in a backup, with the
              <codeph>-include-table-file</codeph> option. You cannot use this option in combination
            with <codeph>-exclude-table-file</codeph> or <codeph>-exclude-table</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-metadata-only</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Creates only the metadata files (DDL) needed to recreate the database
            objects, but does not back up the actual table data.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-no-compression</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Do not compress the table data CSV files.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-quiet</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Suppress all non-warning, non-error log messages.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-single-data-file</pt>
          <pd>Optional. Create a single data file on each segment host for all tables backed up on
            that segment. By default, each <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> creates one compressed CSV file
            for each table that is backed up on the segment.<note>If you use the
                <codeph>-single-data-file</codeph> option to combine table backups into a single
              file per segment, you cannot perform a parallel restore operation with
                <codeph>gprestore</codeph>, and you cannot use the <codeph>-include-schema</codeph>
              option with <codeph>gprestore</codeph>.</note></pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-verbose</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Print verbose log messages.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-version</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Print the version number and exit.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-with-stats</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Include query plan statistics in the backup set.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>Backup all schemas and tables in the "demo" database, including global Greenplum Database
        system objects statistics:<codeblock>$ gpbackup -dbname demo</codeblock></p>
      <p>Backup all schemas and tables in the "demo" database except for the "twitter"
        schema:<codeblock>$ gpbackup -dbname demo -exclude-schema twitter</codeblock></p>
      <p>Backup only the "twitter" schema in the "demo"
        database:<codeblock>$ gpbackup -dbname demo -include-schema twitter</codeblock></p>
      <p>Backup all schemas and tables in the "demo" database, including global Greenplum Database
        system objects and query statistics, and copy all backup files to the
          <filepath>/home/gpadmin/backup</filepath>
        directory:<codeblock>$ gpbackup -dbname demo -with-stats -backupdir /home/gpadmin/backup</codeblock></p>
      <p>This example uses <codeph>-include-schema</codeph> with <codeph>-exclude-table</codeph> to
        back up a schema except for a single table. </p>
      <codeblock>$ gpbackup -dbname demo -include-schema mydata -exclude-table mydata.addresses</codeblock>
      <p>You cannot use the option <codeph>-exclude-schema</codeph> with a table filtering option
        such as <codeph>-include-table</codeph>.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section9">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p>
        <codeph>
          <xref href="./gprestore.xml" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </codeph>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
