<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" otherprops="pivotal">
    <!--install_guide has a link to this topic. -->
    <title id="pk138417">gpcopy</title>
    <body>
        <p>The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility copies objects from databases in a source Greenplum
            Database system to databases in a destination Greenplum Database system. </p>
        <note> The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility is available only in the commercial release of
            Pivotal Greenplum Database.</note>
        <section id="section2">
            <title>Synopsis</title>
            <codeblock><b>gpcopy</b>
   { <b>--full </b>|
     { <b>--dbname</b> <varname>database1</varname>[, <varname>database2</varname> ... ] 
        [<b>--dest-dbname</b> <varname>dest-db1</varname>[, <varname>dest-db2</varname> ... ]] } |
     <b>--include-table</b> <varname>db</varname>.<varname>schema</varname>.<varname>table</varname>[, <varname>db</varname>.<varname>schema1</varname>.<varname>table1</varname> ... ] |
     <b>--include-table-file</b> <varname>table-file1</varname>
        [ <b>--include-table-file</b> <varname>table-file2</varname>] ... ] }
   [<b>--exclude-table</b> <varname>db</varname>.<varname>schema</varname>.<varname>table</varname>[, <varname>db</varname>.<varname>schema1</varname>.<varname>table1</varname> ... ]]
   [<b>--exclude-table-file</b> <varname>table-file1</varname>]
      [ <b>--exclude-table-file</b> <varname>table-file2</varname>] ... ]]
   [<b>--skip-existing</b> | <b>--truncate</b> | <b>--drop</b> | <b>--append</b> ]
   [<b>--parallelize-leaf-partitions</b>] 
   [<b>--dry-run</b>]
   [<b>--analyze</b>]
   [<b>--validate</b> <varname>type</varname>]
   [<b>--no-distribution-check</b>]
   [<b>--truncate-source-after</b> [<b>--yes</b>]]
   [<b>--metadata-only</b>]
   { <b>--dest-host</b> <varname>dest_host</varname> [<b>--dest-port</b> <varname>dest_port</varname>]
      [<b> --dest-user</b> <varname>dest_user</varname>] }
   [<b>--source-host</b> <varname>source_host</varname> [<b>--source-port</b> <varname>source_port</varname>]
   [<b>--source-user</b> <varname>source_user</varname>]]
   [<b>--no-compression</b>]
   [<b>--on-segment-threshold</b> <varname>int</varname>]
   [<b>--jobs</b> <varname>int</varname>]
   [<b>--quiet</b> | <b>--debug</b>]

<b>gpcopy --version</b>
<b>gpcopy</b> <b>--help</b></codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="section3">
            <title>Description</title>
            <p>The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility copies database objects from a source Greenplum
                Database system to a destination system. You can perform one of the following types
                of copy operations: </p>
            <ul>
                <li id="pk138459">Copy a Greenplum Database system with the <codeph>--full</codeph>
                    option. This option copies all database objects including, tables, table data,
                    indexes, views, users, roles, functions, and resource queues for all
                    user-defined databases to a different destination system. </li>
                <li id="pk138461">Copy a set of user-defined database tables to a destination
                    system. <ul id="ul_ly3_v5c_vdb">
                        <li>The <codeph>--dbname</codeph> option copies all user-defined tables,
                            table data, and re-creates the table indexes from specified
                            databases.</li>
                        <li>The <codeph>--include-table</codeph> or
                                <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph> option copies a specified set
                            of user-defined tables, table data, and re-creates the table indexes. </li>
                        <li>The <codeph>--exclude-table</codeph> and
                                <codeph>--exclude-table-file</codeph> options exclude a specified
                            set of user-defined tables and table data to be copied. </li>
                    </ul></li>
                <li>Copy only the database schemas with the <codeph>--metadata-only</codeph>
                    option.</li>
            </ul>
            <p>When running <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>, you must specify the data to copy from the
                source database and how to manage data in the destination database.<ul
                    id="ul_ehn_fvx_vdb">
                    <li>You must use one and only one of these options to specify the data to be
                        copied from the source database: -<codeph>-full</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--dbname</codeph>, <codeph>--include-table</codeph>, or
                            <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph>. </li>
                    <li>You must use one of these options to specify how manage data in the
                        destination database: <codeph>--skip-existing</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--truncate</codeph>, <codeph>--drop</codeph>, or
                            <codeph>--append</codeph>.<p>If you specify both the
                                <codeph>--append</codeph> and <codeph>--validation</codeph> options,
                            validation of source table data fails if a destination table contains
                            data. </p></li>
                </ul></p>
            <p>If you specify the option <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph>, you must also
                specify the <codeph>--validate</codeph> option. When
                    <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> is specified, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>
                truncates the source table after the table data is copied and destination table data
                has been validated. </p>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Prerequisites</title>
            <p>The user IDs connecting to the source and destination Greenplum Database systems, the
                    <codeph>--source-user</codeph> and <codeph>--dest-user</codeph>, must have
                appropriate access to the systems.</p>
            <p>The source and destination Greenplum Database segment hosts need to be able to
                communicate with each other. To ensure that the segment hosts can communicate, you
                can use a tool such as the Linux <codeph>netperf</codeph> utility. </p>
            <p>When the <codeph>--full</codeph> option is specified, resource groups and table
                spaces are copied, however, the utility does not configure the destination system.
                You must configure the system to use resource groups and create filespaces for the
                tablespaces. </p>
        </section>
        <section id="section6">
            <title>Options</title>
            <parml>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--analyze</pt>
                    <pd>Run the <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> command on non-system tables. The default
                        is to not run the <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> command. The operation is
                        performed for each table after the table data is copied.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--append</pt>
                    <pd>Append data to the table in the destination database if it already exists. </pd>
                    <pd>At most, only one of the options can be specified:
                            <codeph>--skip-existing</codeph>, <codeph>--truncate</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--drop</codeph>, or <codeph>--append</codeph>.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--dry-run</pt>
                    <pd>When you specify this option, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> generates a list of
                        the migration operations that would have been performed with the specified
                        options. The data is not migrated. </pd>
                    <pd>The information is displayed at the command line and written to the log
                        file.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--jobs <varname>int</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Specify the number processes that <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> runs in parallel.
                        The default is 4. The range is from 1 to 64.</pd>
                    <pd>The option <codeph>--jobs</codeph> produces
                            <codeph>2*<varname>n</varname>+1</codeph> database connections. The
                        default value 4, creates 9 connections.</pd>
                    <pd>If you increase this option, ensure that Greenplum Database systems are
                        configured with a sufficient maximum concurrent connection value to
                        accommodate the <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> connections and other concurrent
                        connections such as user connections. See the Greenplum Database server
                        configuration parameter <codeph>max_connections</codeph>.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--dbname <varname>database</varname></pt>
                    <pd>A source database to copy. To copy multiple databases to the destination
                        system specify a comma-separated list of databases with no spaces between
                        the names. All the user-defined tables and table data are copied to the
                        destination system. </pd>
                    <pd>If the source database does not exist, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> returns an
                        error and quits. If a destination database does not exist a database is
                        created. </pd>
                    <pd>Not valid with the <codeph>--full</codeph>,
                        <codeph>--include-table</codeph>, or <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph>,
                        options.</pd>
                    <pd>Alternatively, you can copy a set of tables with the
                            <codeph>--include-table</codeph>, or
                            <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph> option.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--debug</pt>
                    <pd>If specified, debug messages are displayed at the command prompt.</pd>
                    <pd>This option cannot be specified with the <codeph>--quiet</codeph>
                        option.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--dest-dbname <varname>database</varname></pt>
                    <pd>To copy a database to a different destination database, specify the name of
                        the destination database. For multiple databases, specify a comma-separated
                        list of databases with no spaces between the names. The number of database
                        names must match the number of names specified in the
                            <codeph>--dbname</codeph> option. The utility copies the source
                        databases to the destination databases in the listed order. In this example,
                            <codeph>db1</codeph> is copied to <codeph>destdb1</codeph>,
                            <codeph>db2</codeph> is copied to <codeph>destdb2</codeph>, and
                            <codeph>db3</codeph> is copied to <codeph>db3</codeph>.
                        <codeblock>gpcopy --dest-host mdw-2 --dbname=db1,db2,db3 --dest-dbname=destdb1,destdb2,db3 --drop</codeblock></pd>
                    <pd>If the source database does not exist, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> returns an
                        error and quits. If a destination database does not exist a database is
                        created. </pd>
                    <pd>Valid only with the <codeph>--dbname</codeph> option.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--dest-host <varname>dest_host</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Required. Destination Greenplum Database hostname or IP address. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--dest-port <varname>dest_port</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Destination Greenplum Database port number, If not specified, the default is
                        5432.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--dest-user <varname>dest_user</varname></pt>
                    <pd>User ID that is used to connect to the destination Greenplum Database
                        system. If not specified, the default is the user gpadmin. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--drop</pt>
                    <pd>Specify this option to drop the table that is in the destination database if
                        it already exists. Before copying table data, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> drops
                        the table and creates it again. </pd>
                    <pd>At most, only one of the options can be specified:
                            <codeph>--skip-existing</codeph>, <codeph>--truncate</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--drop</codeph>, or <codeph>--append</codeph>.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--exclude-table
                            <varname>db</varname>.<varname>schema</varname>.<varname>table</varname></pt>
                    <pd>A table from the source database system to exclude from transfer. The fully
                        qualified table name must be specified
                            (<varname>database</varname>.<varname>schema</varname>.<varname>table</varname>). </pd>
                    <pd>To exclude multiple tables, specify a comma-separated list of table
                        names.</pd>
                    <pd>A set of tables can be specified using the Go language regular expression
                        syntax. See the <codeph><xref href="#topic1/include-file-gpcopy"
                                format="dita">--include-table</xref></codeph> option for information
                        about using regular expressions.</pd>
                    <pd>Only the specified tables are excluded, not dependent objects. You cannot
                        specify views or system catalog tables. </pd>
                    <pd>This option must be specified with one of these options:
                            <codeph>--full</codeph>, <codeph>--dbname</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--include-table</codeph>, or
                            <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph>. If the option
                            <codeph>--exclude-table</codeph> results in no table to copy, the
                        database or schema is not created in the destination system.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--exclude-table-file <varname>table-file</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The location and name of file containing a list of fully qualified table
                        names to exclude from copying to the destination system. In the text file,
                        specify a single fully qualified table per line
                            (<varname>database</varname>.<varname>schema</varname>.<varname>table</varname>).
                        To specify multiple files, specify this option for each
                        file.<codeblock>--exclude-table-file &lt;<varname>path_to_file1</varname>> --exclude-table-file &lt;<varname>path_to_file2</varname>></codeblock></pd>
                    <pd>In the file, a set of tables can be specified using the Go language regular
                        expression syntax. See the <codeph><xref href="#topic1/include-file-gpcopy"
                                format="dita">--include-table</xref></codeph> option for information
                        about using regular expressions.</pd>
                    <pd>If a source table does not exist, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> displays a
                        warning. </pd>
                    <pd>Only the specified tables are excluded. You cannot specify views or system
                        catalog tables.</pd>
                    <pd>This option must be specified with one of these options:
                            <codeph>--full</codeph>, <codeph>--dbname</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--include-table</codeph>, or
                            <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph>. If the option
                            <codeph>--exclude-table</codeph> results in no tables to copy, the
                        database or schema is not created in the destination system.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry id="include-file-gpcopy">
                    <pt>--include-table
                            <varname>db</varname>.<varname>schema</varname>.<varname>table</varname></pt>
                    <pd>A table from the source database system to copy. The fully qualified table
                        name must be specified
                            (<varname>database</varname>.<varname>schema</varname>.<varname>table</varname>).
                        You cannot specify views or system catalog tables. To copy multiple tables,
                        specify a comma-separated list of table names.</pd>
                    <pd>A set of tables can be specified using the Go language regular expression
                        syntax. You can use regular expressions in table names and schema names.
                        Regular expressions are not supported for database names. </pd>
                    <pd>The regular expression pattern must be enclosed in slashes
                                (<codeph>/<varname>RE_pattern</varname>/</codeph>). This example
                            <codeph>--include-table mytest.public.demo/.*/</codeph> specifies all
                        tables that begin with <codeph>demo</codeph> in the database
                            <codeph>mytest</codeph> in the <codeph>public</codeph> schema.</pd>
                    <pd>The following two examples for the <codeph>--include-table</codeph> option
                        are equivalent. They both specify a set of tables that begins with demo and
                        ends with zero or more
                        digits.<codeblock>--include-table testdb.schema1.demo/[0-9]*/
--include-table testdb.schema1./demo[0-9]*/</codeblock></pd>
                    <pd>If the source table does not exist, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> returns an error
                        and quits. </pd>
                    <pd>If the destination table or database does not exist, it is created. Only the
                        table and table data are copied, not dependant objects. Indexes are
                        re-created only if the <codeph>--drop</codeph> option is specified.
                        Dependent objects are not copied. </pd>
                    <pd>This option is not allowed with the options: <codeph>--full</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--dbname</codeph>, or <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph>.
                    </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--include-table-file <varname>table-file</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The location and name of file containing a list of fully qualified table
                        names to copy from the Greenplum Database source system. To specify multiple
                        files, specify this option for each
                        file.<codeblock>--include-table-file &lt;<varname>path_to_file1</varname>> --include-table-file &lt;<varname>path_to_file2</varname>></codeblock></pd>
                    <pd>In the text file, specify a single fully qualified table per line
                            (<varname>database</varname>.<varname>schema</varname>.<varname>table</varname>).
                        You cannot specify views or system catalog tables. In the file, a set of
                        tables can be specified with regular expression syntax. See the
                                <codeph><xref href="#topic1/include-file-gpcopy" format="dita"
                                >--include-table</xref></codeph> option for information about using
                        regular expressions.</pd>
                    <pd>This option cannot be specified with the <codeph>--full</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--dbname</codeph>, or <codeph>--include-table</codeph>
                        options.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--full</pt>
                    <pd>This option performs a migration of a Greenplum Database source system to a
                        destination system. </pd>
                    <pd>A migration copies all database objects including, tables, indexes, views,
                        roles, functions, user-defined types (UDT), resource queues, and resource
                        groups for all user-defined databases. The default databases,
                            <codeph>postgres</codeph>, <codeph>template0</codeph>, and
                            <codeph>template1</codeph>, are not copied.</pd>
                    <pd>This option cannot be specified with the <codeph>--dbname</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--include-table</codeph>, or
                            <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph> options.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--no-compression</pt>
                    <pd>If specified, data is transferred without compression. By default,
                            <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> compresses data during transfer from the source
                        to the destination database when copying data to a different host.</pd>
                    <pd>The utility does not compress data when copying data to the same host.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--no-distribution-check</pt>
                    <pd>Specify this option to disable table data distribution checking. By default,
                            <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> performs data distribution checking to ensure
                        data is distributed to segment instances correctly. If distribution checking
                        fails, the table copy fails. </pd>
                    <pd>The utility does not support table data distribution checking when copying a
                        partitioned table that is defined with a leaf table that is an external
                        table or if a leaf table is defined with a distribution policy that is
                        different from the root partitioned table.
                        <note type="warning">Before you perform a <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> operation
                            with the <codeph>--no-distribution-check</codeph> option, ensure that
                            you have a backup of the destination database and that the distribution
                            policies of the tables that are being copied are the same in the source
                            and destination database. Copying data into segment instances with
                            incorrect data distribution can cause incorrect query results and can
                            cause database corruption.</note></pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--on-segment-threshold <varname>int</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Specifies the number of rows that determines when <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>
                        copies a table using the Greenplum Database source and destination master
                        instead of the source and destination segment instances. The default value
                        is 10000 rows. If a table contains 10000 rows or less, the table is copied
                        using the Greenplum Database master. </pd>
                    <pd>The value <codeph>-1</codeph> disables copying tables using the master. All
                        tables are copied using the segment instances.</pd>
                    <pd>For smaller tables, copying tables using the Greenplum Database master is
                        more efficient than using segment instances.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--parallelize-leaf-partitions</pt>
                    <pd>If specified, the utility copies the leaf partition tables of a partitioned
                        table in parallel. The default is to copy the partitioned table as a single
                        table based on the root partition table. </pd>
                    <pd>If the <codeph>--validate</codeph> option is also specified, the utility
                        validates each leaf partition table during the copy process and then
                        validates the entire partitioned table.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--quiet</pt>
                    <pd>If specified, suppress status messages at the command prompt. The messages
                        are sent only to the log file. Higher level messages such as warning and
                        error messages are still displayed. </pd>
                    <pd>This option cannot be specified with the <codeph>--debug</codeph>
                        option.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--metadata-only</pt>
                    <pd>Create only the schemas specified by the command. Data is not
                        transferred.</pd>
                    <pd>If specified with the <codeph>--full</codeph> option,
                            <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> replicates the complete database schema,
                        including all tables, indexes, views, user-defined types (UDT), and
                        user-defined functions (UDF) for the source databases. No data is
                        transferred. </pd>
                    <pd>If you specify databases with the <codeph>--dbname</codeph> option or tables
                        with the <codeph>--include-table</codeph> or
                            <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph> options, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>
                        creates only the tables and indexes. No data is transferred.</pd>
                    <pd>This option cannot be used with <codeph>--truncate</codeph> option.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--skip-existing</pt>
                    <pd>Specify this option to skip copying a table from the source database if the
                        table already exists in the destination database. </pd>
                    <pd>At most, only one of the options can be specified:
                            <codeph>--skip-existing</codeph>, <codeph>--truncate</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--drop</codeph>, or <codeph>--append</codeph>. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--source-host <varname>source_host</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Source Greenplum Database host name or IP address. If not specified, the
                        default host is the system running <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> (127.0.0.1).</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--source-port <varname>source_port</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Source Greenplum Database port number. If not specified, the default is
                        5432.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--source-user <varname>source_user</varname></pt>
                    <pd>User ID that is used to connect to the source Greenplum Database system. If
                        not specified, the default is the user gpadmin.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--truncate</pt>
                    <pd>Specify this option to truncate the table that is in the destination
                        database if it already exists. </pd>
                    <pd>At most, only one of the options can be specified:
                            <codeph>--skip-existing</codeph>, <codeph>--truncate</codeph>,
                            <codeph>--drop</codeph>, or <codeph>--append</codeph>. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--truncate-source-after</pt>
                    <pd>Specify this option to truncate the table that is in the source database
                        after <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> copies the table and validates the table data
                        in the destination database. </pd>
                    <pd>If you specify this option, you must also specify the
                            <codeph>--validate</codeph> option.<parml>
                            <plentry>
                                <pt>--yes</pt>
                                <pd>Optional. Automatic confirmation to truncate source table data
                                    after copying and validating table data. The prompt to truncate
                                    source tables does not appear. The default is to prompt to
                                    confirm truncating source table data after copying and
                                    validating the data.</pd>
                            </plentry>
                        </parml></pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--validate <varname>type</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Perform data validation on the table data in the destination database after
                        the table data is copied. These are the supported type of validation.<ul
                            id="ul_hf1_k21_xdb">
                            <li><codeph>count</codeph> - compares row counts between source and
                                destination table data.</li>
                            <li><codeph>md5xor</codeph> - calculates the MD5 value of all rows, then
                                performs an XOR over the MD5 values</li>
                        </ul></pd>
                    <pd>If you specify the <codeph>--append</codeph> option, and the destination
                        table contains data, validation fails for the table.</pd>
                    <pd>If validation for a table fails, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> rolls back the
                        destination table. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--help</pt>
                    <pd>Displays the online help. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--version</pt>
                    <pd>Displays the version of this utility.</pd>
                </plentry>
            </parml>
        </section>
        <section id="notes_gpcopy">
            <title>Notes</title>
            <p>If a <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> command specifies an invalid option, or specifies a
                source table or database that does not exist, the utility returns an error and
                quits. No data is copied. </p>
            <p>The source table data can change while the data is being copied. A lock is not
                acquired on the source table when data is copied. </p>
            <p>The utility cannot copy a row with a width greater than 1GB (a PostgreSQL
                limitation). </p>
            <p>If you copy a set of database tables with the <codeph>--dbname</codeph>,
                    <codeph>--include-table</codeph>, or <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph>
                option, and the destination database does not exist, the utility creates the
                database before copying the tables. If the destination database exists, the utility
                creates the tables in the database if required.</p>
            <p>The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility does not copy dependent database objects unless
                you specify the <codeph>--full</codeph> option. For example, if a table has a
                default value on a column that is a user-defined function, that function must exist
                in the destination system database when using the <codeph>--dbname</codeph>,
                    <codeph>--include-table</codeph>, or <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph>
                options. </p>
            <p>When copying tables, sequences defined for tables are considered table data and are
                copied. A sequence is copied if a table is created with a serial column or if a
                sequence is specified as a default value. The sequences are reset if you specify the
                    <codeph>--truncate</codeph> option.</p>
            <p>The utility re-creates table indexes only with <codeph>--full</codeph> or
                    <codeph>--drop</codeph> options. </p>
            <p>The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility does not copy configuration files such as
                    <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> and <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph>. You must set
                up the destination system configuration separately. </p>
            <p>The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility does not copy external objects such as Greenplum
                Database extensions, third party jar files, and shared object files. You must
                install the external objects separately. </p>
            <sectiondiv>
                <p><b>Specifying Table Names with Special Characters</b></p>
                <p dir="ltr">When you list a table with the option <codeph>--include-table</codeph>
                    or <codeph>--exclude-table</codeph>, and the table name or schema name contains
                    single quote (<codeph>'</codeph>), double quote (<codeph>"</codeph>) , or
                    backslash (<codeph>\</codeph>), you must escape the character with a backslash
                        (<systemoutput>\</systemoutput>). These are the escaped characters:
                        <codeph>\'</codeph>, <codeph>\"</codeph>, <codeph>\\</codeph>. If the table
                    or schema name contains a period (<codeph>.</codeph>), comma
                    (<codeph>,</codeph>), or a space character, you must enclose the entire name in
                    single quotes (<codeph>'</codeph>) and enclose the table and schema in double
                    quotes (<codeph>"</codeph>) at the command prompt shell. In this example, the
                    fully qualified name of the table is
                    <codeph>testdb.schema'1.table"test</codeph>.<codeblock>--include-table 'testdb."schema\'1"."table\"test"'</codeblock></p>
                <p dir="ltr">For fully qualified table names listed in a file that is used the
                    option <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph> or
                        <codeph>--exclude-table-file</codeph>, if the table name or schema name
                    contains a period (<codeph>.</codeph>), the name must be enclosed in double
                    quotes (<systemoutput>"</systemoutput>). In this example, the table
                        <codeph>table.test</codeph> is in the <codeph>testdb</codeph>, and belongs
                    to the schema
                    <codeph>schema.1</codeph>.<codeblock>testdb."schema.1"."table.test"</codeblock></p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv>
                <p><b>Copying Partitioned Tables</b></p>
                <p>When copying data for a partitioned table, if a leaf partition has been exchanged
                    with an external table, that leaf partition is created, but data is not copied. </p>
                <p>If you specify copying leaf partitions of a partitioned table with an option such
                    as <codeph>--include-table</codeph> or <codeph>--exclude-table</codeph>,
                        <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> creates the partitioned table if it does not exist.
                    Only the data for the specified leaf partitions are added to the partitioned
                    table. Specifying individual leaf partitions is useful when the entire
                    partitioned tabled does not need to be copied.</p>
                <p><codeph>gpcopy</codeph> does not support table data distribution checking when
                    copying a partitioned table that is defined with a leaf table that is an
                    external table or if a leaf table is defined with a distribution policy that is
                    different from the root partitioned table. You can copy those tables in a
                        <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> operation and specify the option
                        <codeph>--no-distribution-check</codeph> to disable checking of data
                    distribution. </p>
                <note type="warning">Before you perform a <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> operation with the
                        <codeph>--no-distribution-check</codeph> option, ensure that you have a
                    backup of the destination database and that the distribution policies of the
                    tables that are being copied are the same in the source and destination
                    database. Copying data into segment instances with incorrect data distribution
                    can cause incorrect query results and can cause database corruption.</note>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv>
                <p><b>Handling gpcopy Errors</b></p>
                <p>When <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> encounters errors and quits or is cancelled by the
                    user, current copy operations on tables in the destination database are rolled
                    back. Copy operations that have completed are not rolled back. </p>
                <p>If an error occurs during the process of copying a table, or table validation
                    fails, <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> continues copying the other specified tables.
                    After <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> finishes, it displays a list of tables where
                    errors occurred or validation failed and displays a <codeph>gpcopy</codeph>
                    command. You can use the provided command to retry copying the failed tables. </p>
                <p>The <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> utility logs messages in log file
                            <codeph>gpcopy_<varname>date</varname>.log</codeph> in the
                        <codeph>~/gpAdminLogs</codeph> directory on the master host. If you run
                    multiple <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> commands on the same day, the utility appends
                    messages to that day's log file. </p>
                <p>After <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> completes, it displays a summary of the operations
                    performed. If the utility fails to copy tables, they are highlighted in summary,
                    and there is a <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> command provided in summary for user to
                    just copy the failed tables. The information is displayed at the command prompt
                    and in the <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> log file. </p>
                <p>After resolving the issues that caused the copy operations to fail, you can run
                    the provided command to copy the tables that failed in the previous
                        <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> command. </p>
            </sectiondiv>
            <sectiondiv>
                <p><b>Database Connections Created by gpcopy</b></p>
                <p>The option <codeph>--jobs</codeph> produces
                        <codeph>2*<varname>n</varname>+1</codeph> database connections. The default
                    value 4, creates 9 connections.</p>
                <p>If you increase this option, ensure that both source and destination Greenplum
                    Database is configured with a sufficient maximum concurrent connection value to
                    accommodate the <codeph>gpcopy</codeph> connections and other concurrent
                    connections such as user connections. See the Greenplum Database server
                    configuration parameter <codeph><xref
                            href="../../ref_guide/config_params/guc-list.xml#max_connections"
                            type="dita">max_connections</xref></codeph><ph otherprops="op-print"> in
                        the <cite>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</cite></ph>.</p>
            </sectiondiv>
        </section>
        <section id="section7">
            <title>Examples</title>
            <p dir="ltr" id="docs-internal-guid-12cd43d8-6521-a9e1-6f15-4eeab6c1f3df">This command
                copies all user created databases in a source system to a destination system with
                the <codeph>--full</codeph> option. And drops the table and creates it again if it
                already exists in the destination.</p>
            <codeblock dir="ltr">gpcopy --source-host mytest --source-port 1234 --source-user gpuser \
    --dest-host demohost --dest-port 1234 --dest-user gpuser \
    --full --drop</codeblock>
            <p dir="ltr">This command copies the specified databases in a source system to a
                destination system with the <codeph>--dbname</codeph> option. The
                    <codeph>--truncate</codeph> option truncates the table data before copying table
                data from the source table.</p>
            <codeblock dir="ltr">gpcopy --source-host mytest --source-port 1234 --source-user gpuser \
   --dest-host demohost --dest-port 1234 --dest-user gpuser \
   --dbname database1, database2 --truncate</codeblock>
            <p dir="ltr">This command copies the specified tables in a source system to a
                destination system with the <codeph>--include-table</codeph> option. The
                    <codeph>--skip-existing</codeph> option skips the table if it already exists in
                the destination database.</p>
            <codeblock dir="ltr">gpcopy --source-host mytest --source-port 1234 --source-user gpuser \
   --dest-host demohost --dest-port 1234 --dest-user gpuser \
   --include-table database.schema.table1, database.schema.table2 --skip-existing</codeblock>
            <p dir="ltr">This command copies the tables from the source database to the destination
                system, excluding the tables specified in the specified tables in
                    <codeph>/home/gpuser/mytables</codeph> with
                    <codeph>--exclude-table-file</codeph> option. The <codeph>--truncate</codeph>
                option truncates tables that already exist in the destination system. With the
                options <codeph>--analyze</codeph> and <codeph>--validate count</codeph>, the
                utility performs an ANALYZE operation on the copied tables, and validates the copied
                table data by comparing row counts between source and destination tables.</p>
            <codeblock dir="ltr">gpcopy --source-host mytest --source-port 1234 --source-user gpuser \
   --dest-host demohost --dest-port 1234 --dest-user gpuser \
   --dbname database1 --exclude-table-file /home/gpuser/mytables \
   --truncate --analyze --validate count</codeblock>
            <p dir="ltr">This command specifies the <codeph>--full</codeph> and
                    <codeph>--metadata-only</codeph> options to copy the complete database schema,
                including all tables, indexes, views, user-defined types (UDT), and user-defined
                functions (UDF) from all the source databases. No data is copied, The
                    <codeph>--drop</codeph> option specifies that the table is dropped in the
                destination database before it is created again if the table exists in both the
                source and destination database.</p>
            <codeblock dir="ltr">gpcopy --source-host mytest --source-port 1234 --source-user gpuser \
   --dest-host demohost --dest-port 1234 --dest-user gpuser \
   --full --metadata-only --drop</codeblock>
            <p dir="ltr">This command copies the specified databases in a source system to a
                destination system with the <codeph>--dbname</codeph> option and specifies 8
                parallel processes with the <codeph>--jobs</codeph> option. The command specifies
                the <codeph>--truncate</codeph> option to truncate the table and create it again if
                it already exists in the destination database.</p>
            <codeblock dir="ltr">gpcopy --source-host mytest --source-port 1234 --source-user gpuser \
   --dest-host demohost --dest-port 1234 --dest-user gpuser \
   --dbname database1, database2 --truncate --jobs 8</codeblock>
            <p dir="ltr" id="docs-internal-guid-cbf0fcbb-893d-f28a-6bc9-3caae975b2e3">This command
                copies the specified database in a source system to a destination system with the
                    <codeph>--dbname</codeph> option and specifies 16 parallel processes with the
                    <codeph>--jobs</codeph> option. The <codeph>--truncate</codeph> option truncates
                the table and creates it again if it already exists in the destination database. The
                    <codeph>--truncate-source-after</codeph> option truncates the tables in source
                database after that table data has been validated in the destination database.</p>
            <codeblock dir="ltr">gpcopy --source-host mytest --source-port 1234 --source-user gpuser \
   --dest-host demohost --dest-port 1234 --dest-user gpuser \
   --dbname database1 --truncate --jobs 16 --truncate-source-after --validate count</codeblock>
            <p>In the previous example, if <codeph>--truncate</codeph> was not specified and the
                destination table contained data, validation would fail.</p>
            <p>This is an example table file that uses regular expressions.</p>
            <p>
                <codeblock>"test1.arc/.*/./.*/"
"test1.c/(..)/y./.*/"</codeblock>
            </p>
            <p>In the first line, the regular expressions for the schemas, <codeph>arc/.*/</codeph>,
                and for the tables, <codeph>/.*/</codeph>, limit the transfer to all tables with the
                schema names that start with <codeph>arc</codeph>.</p>
            <p>In the second line, the regular expressions for the schemas,
                    <codeph>c/(..)/y</codeph>, and for the tables, <codeph>/.*/</codeph>, limit the
                transfer to all tables with the schema names that are four characters long and that
                start with <codeph>c</codeph> and end with <codeph>y</codeph>, for example,
                    <codeph>crty</codeph>. </p>
            <p>When the command is run, tables in the database <codeph>test1</codeph> that satisfy
                either condition are copied to the destination database.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="section8">
            <title>See Also</title>
            <p>For information about migrating data, see the <i>Greenplum Database Administrator
                    Guide</i>.</p>
        </section>
    </body>
</topic>
