<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title id="kt20941">gpexpand</title>
  <body>
    <p>Expands an existing Greenplum Database across new hosts in the array.</p>
    <section id="section2">
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock><b>gpexpand</b> [{<b>-f</b>|<b>--hosts-file</b>} <varname>hosts_file</varname>]
        | {<b>-i</b>|<b>--input</b>} <varname>input_file</varname> [<b>-B</b> <varname>batch_size</varname>] [<b>-V</b>|<b>--novacuum</b>] 
        | {{<b>-d</b> | <b>--duration</b>} <varname>hh:mm:ss</varname> | {<b>-e</b>|<b>--end</b>} '<varname>YYYY-MM-DD hh:mm:ss</varname>'} 
          [<b>-a</b>|<b>-analyze</b>] 
          [<b>-n </b> <varname>parallel_processes</varname>]
        | {<b>-r</b>|<b>--rollback</b>}
        | {<b>-c</b>|<b>--clean</b>}
        [<b>-D</b> <varname>database_name</varname>] [<b>-v</b>|<b>--verbose</b>] [<b>-s</b>|<b>--silent</b>]
        [{<b>-t</b>|<b>--tardir</b>} <varname>directory </varname>]
        [<b>-S</b>|<b>--simple-progress </b>]

<b>gpexpand -?</b> | <b>-h</b> | <b>--help</b> 

<b>gpexpand --version</b></codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section3">
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <ul>
        <li id="kt137989">You are logged in as the Greenplum Database superuser
            (<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>).</li>
        <li id="kt136978">The new segment hosts have been installed and configured as per the
          existing segment hosts. This involves:<ul id="ul_att_m1q_n4"><li id="kt138636">Configuring
              the hardware and OS</li><li id="kt138640">Installing the Greenplum software</li><li id="kt138641">Creating the
                <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user account</li><li id="kt138642">Exchanging SSH keys.
            </li></ul></li>
        <li id="kt137052">Enough disk space on your segment hosts to temporarily hold a copy of your
          largest table. </li>
        <li>When redistributing data, Greenplum Database must be running in production
          mode. Greenplum Database cannot be restricted mode or in master mode. The
            <codeph>gpstart</codeph> options <codeph>-R</codeph> or <codeph>-m</codeph> cannot be
          specified to start Greenplum Database. </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="section4">
      <title>Description</title>
      <p>The <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> utility performs system expansion in two phases: segment
        initialization and then table redistribution. </p>
      <p>In the initialization phase, <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> runs with an input file that
        specifies data directories, <varname>dbid</varname> values, and other characteristics of the
        new segments. You can create the input file manually, or by following the prompts in an
        interactive interview.</p>
      <p>If you choose to create the input file using the interactive interview, you can optionally
        specify a file containing a list of expansion hosts. If your platform or command shell
        limits the length of the list of hostnames that you can type when prompted in the interview,
        specifying the hosts with <codeph>-f</codeph> may be mandatory. </p>
      <p>In addition to initializing the segments, the initialization phase performs these
        actions:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="kt138259">Creates an expansion schema to store the status of the expansion
          operation, including detailed status for tables.</li>
        <li id="kt138260">Changes the distribution policy for all tables to <codeph>DISTRIBUTED
            RANDOMLY</codeph>. The original distribution policies are later restored in the
          redistribution phase.</li>
      </ul>
      <note>Data redistribution should
          be performed during low-use hours. Redistribution can divided into batches over an
          extended period.</note>
      <p>To begin the redistribution phase, you must run <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> with either the
          <codeph>-d</codeph> (duration) or <codeph>-e</codeph> (end time) options. Until the
        specified end time or duration is reached, the utility will redistribute tables in the
        expansion schema. Each table is reorganized using <codeph>ALTER TABLE</codeph> commands to
        rebalance the tables across new segments, and to set tables to their original distribution
        policy. If <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> completes the reorganization of all tables before the
        specified duration, it displays a success message and ends.</p>
      <note>This utility uses secure shell (SSH) connections between systems to
         perform its tasks. In large Greenplum Database deployments, cloud deployments,
         or deployments with a large number of segments per host, this utility may
         exceed the host's maximum threshold for unauthenticated connections.
         Consider updating the SSH <codeph>MaxStartups</codeph> configuration parameter
         to increase this threshold. For more information about SSH configuration
         options, refer to the SSH documentation for your Linux distribution.</note>
    </section>
    <section id="section5">
      <title>Options</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-a | --analyze</pt>
          <pd>Run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> to update the table statistics after expansion. The
            default is to not run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-B <varname>batch_size</varname></pt>
          <pd>Batch size of remote commands to send to a given host before making a one-second
            pause. Default is <codeph>16</codeph>. Valid values are 1-128.</pd>
          <pd>The <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> utility issues a number of setup commands that may
            exceed the host's maximum threshold for unauthenticated connections as defined by
              <codeph>MaxStartups</codeph> in the SSH daemon configuration. The one-second pause
            allows authentications to be completed before <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> issues any more
            commands. </pd>
          <pd>The default value does not normally need to be changed. However, it may be necessary
            to reduce the maximum number of commands if <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> fails with
            connection errors such as <codeph>'ssh_exchange_identification: Connection closed by
              remote host.'</codeph></pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-c | --clean</pt>
          <pd>Remove the expansion schema.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-d | --duration <varname>hh:mm:ss</varname></pt>
          <pd>Duration of the expansion session from beginning to end.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-D <varname>database_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Specifies the database in which to create the expansion schema and tables. If this
            option is not given, the setting for the environment variable
              <codeph>PGDATABASE</codeph> is used. The database templates
              <varname>template1</varname> and <varname>template0</varname> cannot be used.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-e | --end '<varname>YYYY-MM-DD hh:mm:ss</varname>'</pt>
          <pd>Ending date and time for the expansion session.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-f | --hosts-file <varname>filename</varname></pt>
          <pd>Specifies the name of a file that contains a list of new hosts for system expansion.
            Each line of the file must contain a single host name. </pd>
          <pd>This file can contain hostnames with or without network interfaces specified. The
              <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> utility handles either case, adding interface numbers to end
            of the hostname if the original nodes are configured with multiple network
              interfaces.<note>The Greenplum Database segment host naming convention is
                <codeph>sdwN</codeph> where <codeph>sdw</codeph> is a prefix and <codeph>N</codeph>
              is an integer. For example, <codeph>sdw1</codeph>, <codeph>sdw2</codeph> and so on.
              For hosts with multiple interfaces, the convention is to append a dash
                (<codeph>-</codeph>) and number to the host name. For example,
                <codeph>sdw1-1</codeph> and <codeph>sdw1-2</codeph> are the two interface names for
              host <codeph>sdw1</codeph>. </note></pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-i | --input <varname>input_file</varname></pt>
          <pd>Specifies the name of the expansion configuration file, which contains one line for
            each segment to be added in the format of:</pd>
          <pd>
            <varname>hostname:address:port:fselocation:dbid:content:preferred_role:replication_port</varname>
          </pd>
          <pd>If your system has filespaces, <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> will expect a filespace
            configuration file (<varname>input_file_name</varname><codeph>.fs</codeph>) to exist in
            the same directory as your expansion configuration file. The filespace configuration
            file is in the format of:</pd>
          <pd>
            <codeblock>filespaceOrder=<varname>filespace1_name</varname>:<varname>filespace2_name</varname>: ...
dbid:<varname>/path/for/filespace1</varname>:<varname>/path/for/filespace2</varname>: ...
dbid:<varname>/path/for/filespace1</varname>:<varname>/path/for/filespace2</varname>: ...
...</codeblock>
          </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-n <varname>parallel_processes</varname></pt>
          <pd>The number of tables to redistribute simultaneously. Valid values are 1 - 96.</pd>
          <pd>Each table redistribution process requires two database connections: one to alter the
            table, and another to update the table's status in the expansion schema. Before
            increasing <codeph>-n</codeph>, check the current value of the server configuration
            parameter <codeph>max_connections</codeph> and make sure the maximum connection limit is
            not exceeded.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-r | --rollback</pt>
          <pd>Roll back a failed expansion setup operation. If the rollback command fails, attempt
            again using the <codeph>-D</codeph> option to specify the database that contains the
            expansion schema for the operation that you want to roll back.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-s | --silent</pt>
          <pd>Runs in silent mode. Does not prompt for confirmation to proceed on warnings.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-S | --simple-progress</pt>
          <pd>If specified, the <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> utility records only the minimum progress
            information in the Greenplum Database table <i>gpexpand.expansion_progress</i>. The
            utility does not record the relation size information and status information in the
            table <i>gpexpand.status_detail</i>. </pd>
          <pd>Specifying this option can improve performance by reducing the amount of progress
            information written to the <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> tables.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>[-t | --tardir] <varname>directory</varname></pt>
          <pd>The fully qualified path to a <varname>directory</varname> on segment hosts were the
              <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> utility copies a temporary tar file. The file contains
            Greenplum Database files that are used to create segment instances. The default
            directory is the user home directory.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-v | --verbose</pt>
          <pd>Verbose debugging output. With this option, the utility will output all DDL and DML
            used to expand the database.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--version</pt>
          <pd>Display the utility's version number and exit.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-V | --novacuum</pt>
          <pd>Do not vacuum catalog tables before creating schema copy.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-? | -h | --help</pt>
          <pd>Displays the online help.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section id="section6">
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>Run <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> with an input file to initialize new segments and create the
        expansion schema in the default database:</p>
      <codeblock>$ gpexpand -i input_file</codeblock>
      <p>Run <codeph>gpexpand</codeph> for sixty hours maximum duration to redistribute tables to
        new segments:</p>
      <codeblock>$ gpexpand -d 60:00:00</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section7">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p>
        <codeph>
          <xref href="gpssh-exkeys.xml#topic1"/>
        </codeph>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
