<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1"><title id="kv137980">gpfilespace</title><body><p>Creates a filespace using a configuration file that defines per-segment
file system locations. Filespaces describe the physical file system resources
to be used by a tablespace.</p><section id="section2"><title>Synopsis</title><codeblock><b>gpfilespace</b> [<varname>connection_option</varname> ...] [<b>-l</b> <varname>logfile_directory</varname>] 
              [<b>-o</b> <varname>output_file_name</varname>]

<b>gpfilespace</b> [<varname>connection_option</varname> ...] [<b>-l</b> <varname>logfile_directory</varname>] 
              [<b>-c</b> <varname>fs_config_file</varname>]

<ph><b>gpfilespace</b> <b>--movetempfilespace</b> {<varname>filespace_name</varname> | default}

<b>gpfilespace</b> <b>--movetransfilespace</b> {<varname>filespace_name</varname> | default}

<b>gpfilespace</b> <b>--showtempfilespace</b> 

<b>gpfilespace</b> <b>--showtransfilespace</b></ph> 

<b>gpfilespace -v</b> 

<b>gpfilespace -?</b></codeblock></section><section id="section3"><title>Description</title><p>A tablespace requires a file system location to store its database files. In Greenplum Database, the master and each segment (primary and mirror) needs its own
        distinct storage location. This collection of file system locations for all components in a
          Greenplum system is referred to as a
          <varname>filespace</varname>. Once a filespace is defined, it can be used by one or more
        tablespaces.</p><p>When used with the <codeph>-o</codeph> option, the <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph> utility looks up
        your system configuration information in the Greenplum Database catalog tables
        and prompts you for the appropriate file system locations needed to create the filespace. It
        then outputs a configuration file that can be used to create a filespace. If a file name is
        not specified, a <codeph>gpfilespace_config_</codeph><varname>#</varname> file will be
        created in the current directory by default. </p><p>Once you have a configuration file, you can run <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph> with the
          <codeph>-c</codeph> option to create the filespace in Greenplum Database.</p><p outputclass="">You will need to create a filespace before you can use the
          <codeph>gpfilespace --movetempfilespace</codeph> or <codeph>--movetransfilespace</codeph>
        option to move your temporary or transaction files to the new location.</p><p>Use either <codeph>gpfilespace --showtempfilespace</codeph> or
          <codeph>--showtransfilespace</codeph> options to show the name of the filespace currently
        associated with temporary or transaction files. </p><note type="note">If segments are down due to a power or nic failure, you may see inconsistencies
        during filespace creation. You may not be able to bring up the Greenplum Database.</note></section><section id="section4"><title>Options</title><parml><plentry><pt>-c | --config <varname>fs_config_file</varname></pt><pd>A configuration file containing:<ul id="ul_xrn_qr2_44"><li id="kv139272">An initial line denoting the new filespace name. For
                    example:<p>filespace:<varname>myfs</varname></p></li><li id="kv139279">One line each for the master, the primary segments, and the mirror
                segments. A line describes a file system location that a particular segment database
                instance should use as its data directory location to store database files
                associated with a tablespace. Each line is in the format
                of:<codeblock><varname>hostname</varname>:<varname>dbid</varname>:/<varname>filesystem_dir</varname>/<varname>seg_datadir_name</varname></codeblock></li></ul></pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-l | --logdir <varname>logfile_directory</varname></pt><pd>The directory to write the log file. Defaults to <codeph>~/gpAdminLogs</codeph>.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-o | --output <varname>output_file_name</varname></pt><pd>The directory location and file name to output the generated filespace configuration file. You
            will be prompted to enter a name for the filespace, a master file system location, the
            primary segment file system locations, and the mirror segment file system locations. For
            example, if your configuration has 2 primary and 2 mirror segments per host, you will be
            prompted for a total of 5 locations (including the master). The file system locations
            must exist on all hosts in your system prior to running the <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph>
            utility. The utility will designate segment-specific data directories within the
            location(s) you specify, so it is possible to use the same location for multiple
            segments. However, primaries and mirrors cannot use the same location. After the utility
            creates the configuration file, you can manually edit the file to make any required
            changes to the filespace layout before creating the filespace in Greenplum Database.</pd></plentry><plentry>
          <pt>--movetempfilespace {<varname>filespace_name</varname> | default}</pt>
          <pd>Moves temporary files to a new filespace or to the default location.</pd>
        </plentry><plentry>
          <pt>--movetransfilespace {<varname>filespace_name</varname> | default}</pt>
          <pd>Moves transaction files to a new filespace or to the default location.</pd>
        </plentry><plentry>
          <pt>--showtempfilespace</pt>
          <pd>Show the name of the filespace currently associated with temporary files. This option
            checks that all primary and mirror segments, master and master standby are using the
            same filespace or temporary files. You will receive a warning message and an email if any
            inconsistencies exist.</pd>
        </plentry><plentry>
          <pt>--showtransfilespace</pt>
          <pd>Show the name of the filespace currently associated with transaction files. This
            option checks that all primary and mirror segments, master and master standby are using
            the same filespace or transaction files. You will receive a warning message and an email
            if any inconsistencies exist.</pd>
        </plentry><plentry><pt>-v | --version (show utility version)</pt><pd>Displays the version of this utility.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-? | --help (help)</pt><pd>Displays the utility usage and syntax.</pd></plentry></parml><sectiondiv id="section5"><b>Connection Options</b><parml><plentry><pt>-h host | --host <varname>host</varname></pt><pd>The host name of the machine on which the Greenplum master database
              server is running. If not specified, reads from the environment variable
                <codeph>PGHOST</codeph> or defaults to localhost.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-p port | --port <varname>port</varname></pt><pd>The TCP port on which the Greenplum master database server is
              listening for connections. If not specified, reads from the environment variable
                <codeph>PGPORT</codeph> or defaults to 5432.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-U username | --username <varname>superuser_name</varname></pt><pd>The database superuser role name to connect as. If not specified,
reads from the environment variable <codeph>PGUSER</codeph> or defaults
to the current system user name. Only database superusers are allowed
to create filespaces.</pd></plentry><plentry><pt>-W | --password</pt><pd>Force a password prompt.</pd></plentry></parml></sectiondiv></section><section id="section6"><title>Examples</title><p>Create a filespace configuration file. You will be prompted to enter
a name for the filespace, a master file system location, the primary
segment file system locations, and the mirror segment file system locations.
For example, if your configuration has 2 primary and 2 mirror segments
per host, you will be prompted for a total of 5 locations (including
the master). The file system locations must exist on all hosts in your
system prior to running the <codeph>gpfilespace</codeph> utility:</p><codeblock>$ <b>gpfilespace -o .
</b>Enter a name for this filespace
&gt; <b>fastdisk</b>

Checking your configuration:

Your system has 2 hosts with 2 primary and 2 mirror segments 
per host.

Configuring hosts: [sdw1, sdw2]

Please specify 2 locations for the primary segments, one per line:
primary location 1&gt; <b>/gp_pri_filespc</b>
primary location 2&gt; <b>/gp_pri_filespc</b>

Please specify 2 locations for the mirror segments, one per line:
mirror location 1&gt; <b>/gp_mir_filespc</b>
mirror location 2&gt; <b>/gp_mir_filespc</b>

Enter a file system location for the master:
master location&gt; <b>/gp_master_filespc</b></codeblock><p>Example filespace configuration file:</p><codeblock>filespace:fastdisk
mdw:1:/gp_master_filespc/gp-1
sdw1:2:/gp_pri_filespc/gp0
sdw1:3:/gp_mir_filespc/gp1
sdw2:4:/gp_mir_filespc/gp0
sdw2:5:/gp_pri_filespc/gp1</codeblock><p>Execute the configuration file to create the filespace in Greenplum Database:</p><codeblock>$ gpfilespace -c gpfilespace_config_1</codeblock></section><section id="section7"><title>See Also</title><p><codeph>CREATE TABLESPACE</codeph><ph> in the <i>Greenplum Database Reference
            Guide</i></ph></p></section></body></topic>
