<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
    <!--install_guide/refs/gpinitstandby.xml has a conref to this topic. -->
    <title id="js140845">gpinitstandby</title>
    <body>
        <p>Adds and/or initializes a standby master host for a Greenplum Database
            system.</p>
        <section id="section2">
            <title>Synopsis</title>
            <codeblock><b>gpinitstandby</b> { <b>-s</b> <varname>standby_hostname</varname> [<b>-P</b> port] 
      [<b>-F</b> <varname>list_of_filespaces</varname>] | <b>-r</b> | <b>-n</b> } 
      [<b>-a</b>] [<b>-q</b>] [<b>-D</b>] [<b>-l</b> <varname>logfile_directory</varname>]

<b>gpinitstandby</b> <b>-v</b> 

<b>gpinitstandby</b> <b>-?</b></codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="section3">
            <title>Description</title>
            <p>The <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph> utility adds a backup, standby master host to your
                    Greenplum Database system. If your system has an existing standby
                master host configured, use the <codeph>-r</codeph> option to remove it before
                adding the new standby master host. </p>
            <p>Before running this utility, make sure that the Greenplum Database
                software is installed on the standby master host and that you have exchanged SSH
                keys between the hosts. It is recommended that the master port is set to the same
                port number on the master host and the backup master host. </p>
            <p>This utility should be run on the currently active <i>primary</i> master host.<ph
                   > See the <i>Greenplum Database Installation Guide</i> for
                    instructions.</ph></p>
            <p>The utility performs the following steps:</p>
            <ul>
                <li id="js138559">Updates the Greenplum Database system catalog to
                    remove the existing standby master host information (if the <codeph>-r</codeph>
                    option is supplied) </li>
                <li id="js138555">Updates the Greenplum Database system catalog to add
                    the new standby master host information </li>
                <li id="js138431">Edits the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file of the Greenplum Database master to allow access from the newly added standby
                    master.</li>
                <li id="js137684">Sets up the standby master instance on the alternate master
                    host</li>
                <li id="js137686">Starts the synchronization process</li>
            </ul>
            <p>A backup, standby master host serves as a 'warm standby' in the event of the primary
                master host becoming non-operational. The standby master is kept up to date by
                transaction log replication processes (the <codeph>walsender</codeph> and
                    <codeph>walreceiver</codeph>), which run on the primary master and standby
                master hosts and keep the data between the primary and standby master hosts
                synchronized. If the primary master fails, the log replication process is shut down,
                and the standby master can be activated in its place by using the
                    <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> utility. Upon activation of the standby
                master, the replicated logs are used to reconstruct the state of the master host at
                the time of the last successfully committed transaction. </p>
            <p>The activated standby master effectively becomes the Greenplum Database
                master, accepting client connections on the master port and performing normal master
                operations such as SQL command processing and resource management. </p>
            <note type="important">If the <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph> utility previously failed
                to initialize the standby master, you must delete the files in the standby master
                data directory before running <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph> again. The standby
                master data directory is not cleaned up after an initialization failure because it
                contains log files that can help in determining the reason for the failure.<p>If an
                    initialization failure occurs, a summary report file is generated in the standby
                    host directory <codeph>/tmp</codeph>. The report file lists the directories on
                    standby host that require clean up.</p></note>
        </section>
        <section id="section4">
            <title>Options</title>
            <parml>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-a (do not prompt)</pt>
                    <pd>Do not prompt the user for confirmation.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-D (debug)</pt>
                    <pd>Sets logging level to debug.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-F <varname>list_of_filespaces</varname></pt>
                    <pd>A list of filespace names and the associated locations. Each filespace name
                        and its location is separated by a colon. If there is more than one file
                        space name, each pair (name and location) is separated by a comma. For
                        example: </pd>
                    <pd>
                        <codeblock>filespace1_name:fs1_location,filespace2_name:fs2_location</codeblock>
                    </pd>
                    <pd>If this option is not specified, <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph> prompts the
                        user for the filespace names and locations.</pd>
                    <pd>If the list is not formatted correctly or number of filespaces do not match
                        the number of filespaces already created in the system,
                            <codeph>gpinitstandby</codeph> returns an error.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-l <varname>logfile_directory</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The directory to write the log file. Defaults to
                            <codeph>~/gpAdminLogs</codeph>.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-n (restart standby master)</pt>
                    <pd>Specify this option to start a Greenplum Database standby
                        master that has been configured but has stopped for some reason.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-P <varname>port</varname></pt>
                    <pd>This option specifies the port that is used by the Greenplum Database standby master. The default is the same port
                        used by the active Greenplum Database master. </pd>
                    <pd>If the Greenplum Database standby master is on the same host
                        as the active master, the ports must be different. If the ports are the same
                        for the active and standby master and the host is the same, the utility
                        returns an error. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-q (no screen output)</pt>
                    <pd>Run in quiet mode. Command output is not displayed on the screen, but is
                        still written to the log file.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-r (remove standby master)</pt>
                    <pd>Removes the currently configured standby master host from your Greenplum Database system.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-s standby_hostname</pt>
                    <pd>The host name of the standby master host.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-v (show utility version)</pt>
                    <pd>Displays the version, status, last updated date, and check sum of this
                        utility.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-? (help)</pt>
                    <pd>Displays the online help.</pd>
                </plentry>
            </parml>
        </section>
        <section id="section5">
            <title>Examples</title>
            <p>Add a standby master host to your Greenplum Database system and start
                the synchronization process:</p>
            <codeblock>gpinitstandby -s host09</codeblock>
            <p>Start an existing standby master host and synchronize the data with the current
                primary master host:</p>
            <codeblock>gpinitstandby -n</codeblock>
            <note type="note">Do not specify the -n and -s options in the same command.</note>
            <p>Add a standby master host to your Greenplum Database system specifying
                a different port:</p>
            <codeblock>gpinitstandby -s myhost -P 2222</codeblock>
            <p>If you specify the same host name as the active Greenplum Database
                master, the installed Greenplum Database software that is used as a
                standby master must be in a separate location from the active Greenplum Database master. Also, filespace locations that are used by the
                standby master must be different than the filespace locations used by the active
                    Greenplum Database master. </p>
            <p>Remove the existing standby master from your Greenplum
                system configuration:</p>
            <codeblock>gpinitstandby -r</codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="section6">
            <title>See Also</title>
            <p><codeph><xref href="./gpinitsystem.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
                        <codeph><xref href="gpaddmirrors.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                    /></codeph>, <codeph><xref href="gpactivatestandby.xml#topic1" type="topic"
                        format="dita"/></codeph></p>
        </section>
    </body>
</topic>
