<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title id="kz141610">gpmigrator</title>
  <body>
    <p>Upgrades an existing Greenplum Database 4.2.x system without mirrors to 4.3.x.</p>
    <p>Use <codeph><xref href="./gpmigrator_mirror.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>
      to upgrade a 4.2.x system that has mirrors. </p>
    <note type="note">Using <codeph>gpmigrator</codeph> on a system with mirrors causes an
      error.</note>
    <section id="section2">
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock><b>gpmigrator</b> <varname>old_GPHOME_path</varname> <varname>new_GPHOME_path</varname>
           [<b>-d</b> <varname>master_data_directory</varname>] 
           [<b>-l</b> <varname>logfile_directory</varname>] [<b>-q</b>] [<b>--debug</b>] 
           [<b>--check-only</b>] [<b>--skip-check</b>] [<b>-R</b>]

<b>gpmigrator</b> <b>--version</b> | <b>-v</b> 

<b>gpmigrator</b> <b>--help</b> | <b>-h</b></codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section3">
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <p>The following tasks should be performed prior to executing an upgrade:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="kz140057">Make sure you are logged in to the master host as the Greenplum Database
          superuser (<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>).</li>
        <li id="kz140828">Install the Greenplum Database 4.3 binaries on all Greenplum hosts.</li>
        <li id="kz142587">Copy or preserve any additional folders or files (such as backup folders)
          that you have added in the Greenplum data directories or <codeph>$GPHOME</codeph>
          directory. Only files or folders strictly related to Greenplum Database operations are
          preserved by the migration utility.</li>
        <li id="kz142588">(<b>Optional</b>) Run <codeph>VACUUM</codeph> on all databases, and remove
          old server log files from <codeph>pg_log</codeph> in your master and segment data
          directories. This is not required, but will reduce the size of Greenplum Database files to
          be backed up and migrated.</li>
        <li id="kz140747">Check for and recover any failed segments in your current Greenplum
          Database system (<codeph>gpstate</codeph>, <codeph>gprecoverseg</codeph>).</li>
        <li id="kz142626">(<b>Optional, but highly recommended</b>) Backup your current databases
            (<codeph>gpcrondump</codeph>). If you find any issues when testing your upgraded system,
          you can restore this backup.</li>
        <li id="kz141594">Remove the standby master from your system configuration
            (<codeph>gpinitstandby -r</codeph>).</li>
        <li id="kz140080">Do a clean shutdown of your current system (<codeph>gpstop</codeph>).</li>
        <li id="kz140669">Update your environment to source the 4.3 installation.</li>
        <li id="kz140852">Inform all database users of the upgrade and lockout time frame. Once the
          upgrade is in process, users will not be allowed on the system until the upgrade is
          complete.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section id="section4">
      <title>Description</title>
      <p>The <codeph>gpmigrator</codeph> utility upgrades an existing Greenplum Database 4.2.x.x
        system without mirrors to 4.3. This utility updates the system catalog and internal version
        number, but not the actual software binaries. During the migration process, all client
        connections to Greenplum Database will be locked out.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section5">
      <title>Options</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>old_GPHOME_path</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>Required. The absolute path to the current version of Greenplum Database software you
            want to migrate away from.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>
            <varname>new_GPHOME_path</varname>
          </pt>
          <pd>Required. The absolute path to the new version of Greenplum Database software you want
            to migrate to.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-d <varname>master_data_directory</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. The current master host data directory. If not specified, the value set for
              <codeph>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY</codeph> will be used.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-l <varname>logfile_directory</varname></pt>
          <pd>The directory to write the log file. Defaults to <codeph>~/gpAdminLogs</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-q (quiet mode)</pt>
          <pd>Run in quiet mode. Command output is not displayed on the screen, but is still written
            to the log file.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>-R (revert)</pt>
          <pd>In the event of an error during upgrade, reverts all changes made by
              <codeph>gpmigrator</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--check-only</pt>
          <pd>Runs pre-migrate checks to verify that your database is healthy.</pd>
          <pd>Checks include: <ul id="ul_ldz_4rm_z4"><li>Check catalog health</li><li>Check that the
                Greenplum Database binaries on each segment match those on the master</li><li>Check
                for a minimum amount of free disk space</li></ul><p>Performing a pre-migration check
              of your database should done during a database maintenance period. If the utility
              detects catalog errors, the utility stops the database.</p></pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--skip-check</pt>
          <pd>Skip the catalog check during the normal upgrade process. This can save some time, if
            a catalog check was performed separately during the upgrade process. <note
              type="important">Use this option only after you have
              checked for catalog issues with the <cmdname>--check-only</cmdname> option and have
              resolved any catalog issues.</note></pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--help | -h</pt>
          <pd>Displays the online help.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--debug</pt>
          <pd>Sets logging level to debug.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--version | -v</pt>
          <pd>Displays the version of this utility. </pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section id="section6">
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>Upgrade to version 4.3.x from version 4.2.x (make sure you are using the 4.3 version of
          <codeph>gpmigrator</codeph>). This example upgrades to version 4.3.0.0 from version
        4.2.6.3:</p>
      <codeblock>/usr/local/greenplum-db-4.3.0.0/bin/gpmigrator \
  /usr/local/greenplum-db-4.2.6.3 \
  /usr/local/greenplum-db-4.3.0.0</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section7">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p><codeph><xref href="./gpmigrator_mirror.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./gpstop.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./gpstate.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="./gprecoverseg.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="gpcrondump.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
