<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title>gpperfmon_install</title>
  <body>
    <p>Installs the Command Center database (<codeph>gpperfmon</codeph>) and optionally enables the
      data collection agents.</p>
    <section id="section2">
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock><b>gpperfmon_install</b>
      [<b>--enable</b> <b>--password</b> <varname>gpmon_password</varname> <b>--port</b> <varname>gpdb_port</varname>]
      [<b>--pgpass</b> <varname>path_to_file</varname>]
      [<b>--verbose</b>]

<b>gpperfmon_install</b> <b>--help</b> | <b>-h</b> | <b>-?</b></codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section3">
      <title>Description</title>
      <p>The <codeph>gpperfmon_install</codeph> utility automates the steps required to enable the
        data collection agents. You must be the Greenplum Database system user
          (<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>) in order to run this utility. If using the
          <codeph>--enable</codeph> option, Greenplum Database must be restarted after the utility
        completes.</p>
      <note type="important">Greenplum Command Center does not support the <i>gpperfmon</i> database
        when GPORCA is enabled for the database. To ensure that the Pivotal
        Query Optimizer is disabled for the <i>gpperfmon</i> database, run this command on the
        system where the database is
          installed:<codeblock>ALTER DATABASE gpperfmon SET OPTIMIZER = OFF</codeblock><p>In
          Greenplum Database 4.3.5.0, GPORCA co-exists with the legacy query
          optimizer. For information about GPORCA, see "Querying Data" in the
            <cite>Greenplum Database Administrator Guide</cite>.</p></note>
      <p>When run without any options, the utility will just create the <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph>
        database (the database used to store system metrics collected by the data collection
        agents). When run with the <codeph>--enable</codeph> option, the utility will also run the
        following additional tasks necessary to enable the data collection agents:</p>
      <ol>
        <li id="ou143278">Creates the <codeph>gpmon</codeph> superuser role in Greenplum Database.
          The data collection agents require this role to connect to the database and write their
          data. The <codeph>gpmon</codeph> superuser role uses MD5-encrypted password authentication
          by default. Use the <codeph>--password</codeph> option to set the <codeph>gpmon</codeph>
          superuser's password. Use the <codeph>--port</codeph> option to supply the port of the
          Greenplum Database master instance.</li>
        <li id="ou143437">Updates the <codeph>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY/pg_hba.conf</codeph> file. The
          utility adds the following lines to the host-based authentication file
            (<codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph>):<codeblock>local      gpperfmon     gpmon                 md5 
host       all           gpmon  127.0.0.1/28   md5</codeblock><note>
            <p>It may be necessary to edit the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file after running the
                <codeph>gpperfmon_install</codeph> utility to limit the <codeph>gpmon</codeph>
              role's access to databases or to change the authentication method. After you edit the
              file, run <codeph>gpstop -u</codeph> to reload the file in Greenplum Database.</p>
            <ul id="ul_ffm_ysw_k5">
              <li>To limit access to just the <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph> database edit the
                  <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file and in the host entry for the
                  <codeph>gpmon</codeph> user change the second field from <codeph>all</codeph> to
                  <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph>:<codeblock>host       gpperfmon     gpmon    127.0.0.1/28  md5</codeblock></li>
              <li>
                <p>The <codeph>gpperfmon_install</codeph> utility assumes the default MD5
                  authentication method. Greenplum Database may optionally be configured to use the
                  SHA-256 or SHA-256-FIPS hash algorithm to compute the password hashes saved in the
                  system catalog. This is incompatible with the MD5 authentication method, which
                  expects an MD5 hash or clear text password in the system catalog. Because of this,
                  if you have enabled the SHA-256 or SHA-256-FIPS hash algorithm in the database,
                  you must edit the <codeph>pg_hba.conf</codeph> file after running the
                    <codeph>gpperfmon_install</codeph> utility to change the authentication method
                  for the <codeph>gpmon</codeph> role from <codeph>md5</codeph> to
                    <codeph>password</codeph>:<codeblock>local      gpperfmon     gpmon                 md5 
host       all           gpmon  127.0.0.1/28   password</codeblock></p>
                <p>The <codeph>password</codeph> authentication method submits the user's clear text
                  password for authentication and should not be used on an untrusted network. See
                  "Protecting Passwords in Greenplum Database" in the <i>Greenplum Database
                    Administrator Guide</i> for more information about configuring password
                  hashing.</p>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </note></li>
        <li id="ou143384">Updates the password file (<codeph>.pgpass</codeph>). In order to allow
          the data collection agents to connect as the <codeph>gpmon</codeph> role without a
          password prompt, you must have a password file that has an entry for the
            <codeph>gpmon</codeph> user. The utility adds the following entry to your password file
          (if the file does not exist, the utility will create
          it):<codeblock>*:5432:gpperfmon:gpmon:<varname>gpmon_password</varname></codeblock> If
          your password file is not located in the default location (<codeph>~/.pgpass</codeph>),
          use the <codeph>--pgpass</codeph> option to specify the file location.</li>
        <li id="ou140687">Sets the server configuration parameters for Greenplum Command Center. The
          following parameters must be enabled for the data collection agents to begin collecting
          data. The utility will set the following parameters in the Greenplum Database
            <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> configuration files:<ul id="ul_wrp_dtx_wr">
            <li><codeph>gp_enable_gpperfmon=on</codeph> (in all <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph>
              files)</li>
            <li><codeph>gpperfmon_port=8888</codeph> (in all <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> files) </li>
            <li><codeph>gp_external_enable_exec=on</codeph> (in the master
                <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> file)</li>
          </ul><p>For information about the Greenplum Command Center, see the <cite>Greenplum
              Command Center Administrator Guide</cite>.</p></li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section id="section4">
      <title>Options</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--enable</pt>
          <pd>In addition to creating the <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph> database, performs the
            additional steps required to enable the data collection agents. When
              <codeph>--enable</codeph> is specified the utility will also create and configure the
              <codeph>gpmon</codeph> superuser account and set the Command Center server
            configuration parameters in the <codeph>postgresql.conf</codeph> files.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--password <varname>gpmon_password</varname></pt>
          <pd>Required if <codeph>--enable</codeph> is specified. Sets the password of the
              <codeph>gpmon</codeph> superuser.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--port <varname>gpdb_port</varname></pt>
          <pd>Required if <codeph>--enable</codeph> is specified. Specifies the connection port of
            the Greenplum Database master.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--pgpass <varname>path_to_file</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional if <codeph>--enable</codeph> is specified. If the password file is not in the
            default location of <codeph>~/.pgpass</codeph>, specifies the location of the password
            file.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--verbose</pt>
          <pd>Sets the logging level to verbose.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--help | -h | -?</pt>
          <pd>Displays the online help.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Notes</title>
      <p>Greenplum Command Center requires the <i>gpperfmon</i> the database role
          <codeph>gpmon</codeph>. After the <i>gpperfmon</i> database and <codeph>gpmon</codeph>
        role have been created, you can change the password for the <codeph>gpmon</codeph> role and
        update the information that Greenplum Command Center uses to connect to the <i>gpperfmon</i>
        database: </p>
      <ol id="ol_wss_knp_wr">
        <li>Log into Greenplum Database as a superuser and change the <codeph>gpmon</codeph>
          password with the <codeph>ALTER ROLE</codeph>
          command.<codeblock># ALTER ROLE gpmon WITH PASSWORD '<varname>new_password</varname>' ;</codeblock></li>
        <li>Update the password in <codeph>.pgpass</codeph> file that is used by Greenplum Command
          Center. The default file location is the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> home directory
            (<codeph>~/.pgpass</codeph>). The <codeph>.pgpass</codeph> file contains a line with the
            <codeph>gpmon</codeph>
          password.<codeblock>*:5432:gpperfmon:gpmon:<varname>new_password</varname></codeblock></li>
        <li>Restart the Greenplum Command Center with the Command Center <codeph>gpcmdr</codeph>
          utility. <codeblock> $ gpcmdr --restart</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
	  <p>This gpperfmon monitoring system requires some initialization after startup,
		  so expect monitoring information to appear after a few minutes have passed, and not 
		  immediately after installation and startup of the gpperfmon system.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="section5">
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>Create the <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph> database only:</p>
      <codeblock>$ su - gpadmin
$ gpperfmon_install</codeblock>
      <p>Create the <codeph>gpperfmon</codeph> database, create the<codeph> gpmon</codeph>
        superuser, and enable the data collection agents:</p>
      <codeblock>$ su - gpadmin
$ gpperfmon_install --enable --password p@$$word --port 5432
$ gpstop -r</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section6">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p>
        <codeph>
          <xref href="./gpstop.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </codeph>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
