<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_phj_g5j_tbb">
  <title>gprestore</title>
  <body>
    <p>Restore a Greenplum Database backup that was created using the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>
      utility. By default <codeph>gprestore</codeph> uses backed up metadata files and DDL files
      located in the Greenplum Database master host data directory, with table data stored locally
      on segment hosts in CSV data files.</p>
    <note><codeph>gpbackup</codeph> and <codeph>gprestore</codeph> are not provided with the SuSE
      Linux Enterprise Server build of Pivotal Greenplum Database.</note>
    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock><b>gprestore -timestamp</b> <varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname>
   [<b>-backup-dir</b> <varname>directory</varname>]
   [<b>-create-db</b>]
   [<b>-debug</b>]
   [<b>-exclude-schema</b> <varname>schema_name</varname>]
   [<b>-exclude-table</b> <varname>schema.table</varname>]
   [<b>-exclude-table-file</b> <varname>file_name</varname>]
   [<b>-include-schema</b> <varname>schema_name</varname>]
   [<b>-include-table</b> <varname>schema.table</varname>]
   [<b>-include-table-file</b> <varname>file_name</varname>]
   [<b>-jobs</b> <varname>int</varname>]
   [<b>-quiet</b>]
   [<b>-redirect-db</b> <varname>database_name</varname>]
   [<b>-verbose</b>]
   [<b>-version</b>]
   [<b>-with-globals</b>]
   [<b>-with-stats</b>]</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Description</title>
      <p>To use <codeph>gprestore</codeph> to restore from a backup set, you must include the
          <codeph>-timestamp</codeph> option to specify the exact timestamp value
          (<codeph>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</codeph>) of the backup set to restore. If you specified a custom
          <codeph>-backup-dir</codeph> to consolidate the backup files, include the same
          <codeph>-backup-dir</codeph> option with <codeph>gprestore</codeph> to locate the backup
        files.</p>
      <p>When restoring from a backup set, <codeph>gprestore</codeph> restores to a database with
        same name as the name specified when creating the backup set. If the target database exists
        and a table being restored exists in the database, the restore operation fails. Include the
          <codeph>-create-db</codeph> option if the target database does not exist in the cluster.
        You can optionally restore a backup set to a different database by using the
          <codeph>-redirect-db</codeph> option.</p>
      <p>When restoring a backup set that contains data from some leaf partitions of a partitioned
        tables, the partitioned table is restored along with the data for the leaf partitions. For
        example, you create a backup with the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> option
          <codeph>-include-table-file</codeph> and the text file lists some leaf partitions of a
        partitioned table. Restoring the backup creates the partitioned table and restores the data
        only for the leaf partitions listed in the file. </p>
      <p>Greenplum Database system objects are automatically included in a <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>
        backup set, but these objects are only restored if you include the
          <codeph>-with-globals</codeph> option to <codeph>gprestore</codeph>. Similarly, if you
        backed up query plan statistics using the <codeph>-with-stats</codeph> option, you can
        restore those statistics by providing <codeph>-with-stats</codeph> to
          <codeph>gprestore</codeph>. By default, only database objects in the backup set are
        restored.</p>
      <p>Performance of restore operations can be improved by creating multiple parallel connections
        to restore table data. By default <codeph>gprestore</codeph> uses 1 connection, but you can
        increase this number with the <codeph>-jobs</codeph> option for large restore
        operations.</p>
      <p>When a restore operation completes, <codeph>gprestore</codeph> returns a status code. See
          <xref href="#topic_phj_g5j_tbb/return_codes" format="dita"/>.</p>
      <p><codeph>gprestore</codeph> can send status email notifications after a back up operation
        completes. You specify when the utility sends the mail and the email recipients in a
        configuration file. See <xref
          href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_qwd_d5d_tbb" format="dita"
        />.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Options</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-timestamp</b>
            <varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname></pt>
          <pd>Required. Specifies the timestamp of the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> backup set to
            restore. By default <codeph>gprestore</codeph> tries to locate metadata files for the
            timestamp on the Greenplum Database master host in the
              <filepath>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath>
            directory, and CSV data files in the
              <filepath>&lt;seg_dir>/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath> directory of each
            segment host.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-backup-dir</b>
            <varname>directory</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Sources all backup files (metadata files and data files) from the specified
            directory. You must specify <varname>directory</varname> as an absolute path (not
            relative). If you do not supply this option, <codeph>gprestore</codeph> tries to locate
            metadata files for the timestamp on the Greenplum Database master host in the
              <filepath>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath>
            directory. CSV data files must be available on each segment in the
              <filepath>&lt;seg_dir>/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath> directory. Include
            this option when you specify a custom backup directory with
            <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-create-db</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Creates the database before restoring the database object metadata.</pd>
          <pd>The database is created by cloning the empty standard system database
              <codeph>template0</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-debug</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Displays verbose debug messages during operation.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-exclude-schema</b>
            <varname>schema_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a database schema to exclude from the restore operation. You can
            specify this option multiple times to exclude multiple schemas. You cannot combine this
            option with the option <codeph>-include-schema</codeph>, or a table filtering option
            such as <codeph>-include-table</codeph>. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-exclude-table</b>
            <varname>schema.table</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a table to exclude from the restore operation. The table must be
            in the format <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. If a table or schema
            name uses any character other than a lowercase letter, number, or an underscore
            character, then you must include that name in double quotes. You can specify this option
            multiple times. If the table is not in the backup set, the restore operation fails. You
            cannot specify a leaf partition of a partitioned table.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot combine this option with the option <codeph>-exclude-schema</codeph>, or
            another a table filtering option such as <codeph>-include-table</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-exclude-table-file</b>
            <varname>file_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a text file containing a list of tables to exclude from the
            restore operation. Each line in the text file must define a single table using the
            format <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. The file must not include
            trailing lines. If a table or schema name uses any character other than a lowercase
            letter, number, or an underscore character, then you must include that name in double
            quotes. If a table is not in the backup set, the restore operation fails. You cannot
            specify a leaf partition of a partitioned table.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot combine this option with the option <codeph>-exclude-schema</codeph>, or
            another a table filtering option such as <codeph>-include-table</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-include-schema</b>
            <varname>schema_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a database schema to restore. You can specify this option multiple
            times to include multiple schemas. If you specify this option, any schemas that you
            specify must be available in the backup set. Any schemas that are not included in
            subsequent <codeph>-include-schema</codeph> options are omitted from the restore
            operation. </pd>
          <pd>If a schema that you specify for inclusion exists in the database, the utility issues
            an error and continues the operation. The utility fails if a table being restored exists
            in the database. </pd>
          <pd>You cannot use this option if the backup set uses a single data file for all tables on
            each segment (<codeph>gpbackup -single-data-file</codeph> option), or if objects in the
            backup set have dependencies on multiple schemas.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-include-table</b>
            <varname>schema.table</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a table to restore. The table must be in the format
              <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. If a table or schema name uses any
            character other than a lowercase letter, number, or an underscore character, then you
            must include that name in double quotes. You can specify this option multiple times. You
            cannot specify a leaf partition of a partitioned table.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot combine this option with a schema filtering option such as
              <codeph>-include-schema</codeph>, or another table filtering option such as
              <codeph>-exclude-table-file</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-include-table-file</b>
            <varname>file_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a text file containing a list of tables to restore. Each line in
            the text file must define a single table using the format
              <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. The file must not include trailing
            lines. If a table or schema name uses any character other than a lowercase letter,
            number, or an underscore character, then you must include that name in double quotes.
            Any tables not listed in this file are omitted from the restore operation. You cannot
            specify a leaf partition of a partitioned table.</pd>
          <pd>If you use the <codeph>-include-table-file</codeph> option, <codeph>gprestore</codeph>
            does not create roles or set the owner of the tables. The utility restores table indexes
            and rules. Triggers are also restored but are not supported in Greenplum Database.</pd>
          <pd>See <xref href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_et4_b5d_tbb"/>
            for more information.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-jobs</b>
            <varname>int</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies the number of parallel connections to use when restoring table
            data. By default, <codeph>gprestore</codeph> uses 1 connection. Increasing this number
            can improve the speed of restoring data.<note>If you used the <codeph>gpbackup
                -single-data-file</codeph> option to combine table backups into a single file per
              segment, you cannot perform a parallel restore operation with
                <codeph>gprestore</codeph>.</note></pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-quiet</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Suppress all non-warning, non-error log messages.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-redirect-db</b>
            <varname>database_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Restore to the specified <varname>database_name</varname> instead of to the
            database that was backed up.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-verbose</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Print verbose log messages.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-version</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Print the version number and exit.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-with-globals</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Restores Greenplum Database system objects in the backup set, in addition to
            database objects. See <xref
              href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_x3s_lqj_tbb"/>.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>-with-stats</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Restore query plan statistics from the backup set.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section id="return_codes">
      <title>Return Codes</title>
      <p>One of these codes is returned after <codeph>gprestore</codeph> completes.<ul
          id="ul_hhb_sqp_n4">
          <li><b>0</b> – Restore completed with no problems.</li>
          <li><b>1</b> – Restore completed with non-fatal errors. See log file for more
            information.</li>
          <li><b>2</b> – Restore failed with a fatal error. See log file for more information.</li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>Create the demo database and restore all schemas and tables in the backup set for the
        indicated
        timestamp:<codeblock>$ dropdb demo
$ gprestore -timestamp 20171103152558 -create-db</codeblock></p>
      <p>Restore the backup set to the "demo2" database instead of the "demo" database that was
        backed
        up:<codeblock>$ createdb demo2
$ gprestore -timestamp 20171103152558 -redirect-db demo2</codeblock></p>
      <p>Restore global Greenplum Database metadata and query plan statistics in addition to the
        database
        objects:<codeblock>$ gprestore -timestamp 20171103152558 -create-db -with-globals -with-stats</codeblock></p>
      <p>Restore, using backup files that were created in the
          <filepath>/home/gpadmin/backup</filepath> directory, creating 8 parallel
        connections:<codeblock>$ gprestore -backup-dir /home/gpadmin/backups/ -timestamp 20171103153156 -create-db -jobs 8</codeblock></p>
      <p>Restore only the "wikipedia" schema included in the backup
        set:<codeblock>$ dropdb demo
$ gprestore -include-schema wikipedia -backup-dir /home/gpadmin/backups/ -timestamp 20171103153156 -create-db</codeblock></p>
    </section>
    <section id="section9">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p>
        <codeph><xref href="./gpbackup.xml" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>, <xref
          href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml" format="dita"/></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
