<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
    <!--install_guide/refs/gpseginstall.xml has a conref to this topic. -->
    <title id="jv133181">gpseginstall</title>
    <body>
        <p>Installs Greenplum Database on segment hosts.</p>
        <section id="section2">
            <title>Synopsis</title>
            <codeblock><b>gpseginstall</b> <b>-f</b> <varname>hostfile</varname> [<b>-u</b> <varname>gpdb_admin_user</varname>] [<b>-p</b> <varname>password</varname>] 
             [<b>-c</b> u|p|c|s|E|e|l|v]

<b>gpseginstall</b> --help</codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="section3">
            <title>Description</title>
            <p>The <codeph>gpseginstall</codeph> utility provides a simple way to quickly install
                Greenplum Database on segment hosts that you specify in a host list file. The
                utility does not install or update Greenplum Database on the master host. You can
                run <codeph>gpseginstall</codeph> as <codeph>root</codeph> or as a non-root user.
                    <codeph>gpseginstall</codeph> does not perform database initialization. See
                    <codeph>gpinitsystem</codeph> for more information about initializing Greenplum
                Database.</p>
            <p>When run as root, <codeph>gpseginstall</codeph> default actions are to add a system
                user (default is <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>), create a password (default is
                    <codeph>changeme</codeph>), and deploy and install Greenplum Database on segment
                hosts. To do this, <codeph>gpseginstall</codeph> locates the current Greenplum
                Database binaries on the master from the installation path in the current user's
                environment variables (<codeph>$GPHOME</codeph>). It compresses Greenplum Database
                software into a <codeph>tar.gz</codeph> file and performs an MD5 checksum to verify
                file integrity. </p>
            <p>Then, it copies Greenplum Database to the segment hosts, installs (decompresses)
                Greenplum Database, and changes the ownership of the Greenplum Database installation
                to the system user you specify with the <codeph>-u</codeph> option. Lastly, it
                exchanges keys between all Greenplum Database hosts as both root and as the system
                user you specify with the -u option. gpseginstall also perform a user limit check
                and verifies the version number of Greenplum Database on all the segments.</p>
            <p>If you run gpseginstall as a non-root user, gpseginstall only compresses, copies, and
                installs Greenplum Database on segment hosts. It can also exchanges keys between
                Greenplum Database hosts for the current system user, and verifies the version
                number of Greenplum Database on all the segments.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="section4">
            <title>Options</title>
            <parml>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-c | --commands <varname>option_list</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Optional. This allows you to customize <codeph>gpseginstall</codeph>
                        actions. Note that these command options are executed by default if you do
                        not specify the <codeph>-c</codeph> option in the
                            <codeph>gpseginstall</codeph> syntax.<ul id="ul_vby_bnk_44">
                            <li id="jv144166"><codeph>u</codeph>: Adds a system user.
                                    (<codeph>root</codeph> only)</li>
                            <li id="jv144168"><codeph>p</codeph>: Changes the password for a system
                                user. (<codeph>root</codeph> only)</li>
                            <li id="jv144170"><codeph>s</codeph>: Compresses, copies, decompresses
                                (installs) Greenplum Database on all segments.</li>
                            <li id="jv144173"><codeph>c</codeph>: Changes the ownership of the
                                Greenplum Database installation directory on the segment hosts.
                                    (<codeph>root</codeph> only)</li>
                            <li id="jv144176"><codeph>E</codeph>: Exchange keys between Greenplum
                                Database master and segment hosts for the root user.
                                    (<codeph>root</codeph> only)</li>
                            <li id="jv144179"><codeph>e</codeph>: Exchange keys between Greenplum
                                Database master and segment hosts for the non-root system user. </li>
                            <li id="jv144182"><codeph>l</codeph>: (Linux only) Checks and modifies
                                the user limits configuration file
                                    (<codeph>/etc/security/limits.conf</codeph> file) when adding a
                                new user to segment hosts. (<codeph>root</codeph> only)</li>
                            <li id="jv144186"><codeph>v</codeph>: Verifies the version of Greenplum
                                Database running on all segments. <codeph>gpseginstall</codeph>
                                checks the version number of the Greenplum Database installation
                                referenced by the <codeph>$GPHOME</codeph> environment variable and
                                symbolic link to the installation directory. An error occurs if
                                there is a version number mismatch or the Greenplum Database
                                installation directory cannot be found.</li>
                        </ul></pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-f | --file <varname>hostfile</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Required. This specifies the file that lists the segment hosts onto which
                        you want to install Greenplum Database.</pd>
                    <pd>The host list file must have one host name per line and includes a host name
                        for each segment host in your Greenplum system. Make sure there are no blank
                        lines or extra spaces. If a host has multiple configured host names, use
                        only one host name per host. For example:</pd>
                    <pd>
                        <codeblock>sdw1-1
sdw2-1
sdw3-1
sdw4-1</codeblock>
                    </pd>
                    <pd>If available, you can use the same <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> host list
                        file you used to exchange keys between Greenplum Database hosts.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-p | --password <varname>password</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Optional. Sets the password for the user you specify with the
                            <codeph>-u</codeph> option. The default password is
                            <codeph>changeme</codeph>. This option is only available when you run
                            <codeph>gpsetinstall</codeph> as root.</pd>
                    <pd>Recommended security best practices:<ul id="ul_zwv_fnk_44">
                            <li id="jv143869">Always use passwords.</li>
                            <li id="jv144536">Do not use default passwords.</li>
                            <li id="jv143870">Change default passwords immediately after
                                installation.</li>
                        </ul></pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-u | --user <varname>user</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Optional. This specifies the system user. This user is also the Greenplum
                        Database administrative user. This user owns Greenplum Database installation
                        and administers the database. This is also the user under which Greenplum
                        Database is started/initialized. This option is only available when you run
                            <codeph>gpseginstall</codeph> as <codeph>root</codeph>. The default is
                            <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--help (help)</pt>
                    <pd>Displays the online help.</pd>
                </plentry>
            </parml>
        </section>
        <section id="section5">
            <title>Examples</title>
            <p>As <codeph>root</codeph>, install a Greenplum Database on all segments, leave the
                system user as the default (<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>) and set the
                    <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> password to <codeph>secret123</codeph>:</p>
            <codeblock># gpseginstall -f my_host_list_file -p secret123</codeblock>
            <p>As a non-root user, compress and copy Greenplum Database binaries to all segments (as
                    <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>):</p>
            <codeblock>$ gpseginstall -f host_file</codeblock>
            <p>As root, add a user (<codeph>gpadmin2</codeph>), set the password for the user
                    (<codeph>secret1234</codeph>), exchange keys between hosts as the new user,
                check user limits, and verify version numbers, but do not change ownership of
                Greenplum binaries, compress/copy/ install Greenplum Database on segments, or
                exchange keys as <codeph>root</codeph>.</p>
            <codeblock>$ gpseginstall -f host_file -u gpadmin2 -p secret1234 -c upelv</codeblock>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>See Also</title>
            <p><codeph><xref href="gpinitsystem.xml#topic1"/></codeph>, <codeph><xref
                        href="gpssh-exkeys.xml#topic1"/></codeph></p>
        </section>
    </body>
</topic>
