<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
    <!--install_guide/refs/gpssh-exkeys.xml has a conref to this topic. -->
    <title id="jw137116">gpssh-exkeys</title>
    <body>
        <p>Exchanges SSH public keys between hosts.</p>
        <section id="section2">
            <title>Synopsis</title>
            <codeblock><b>gpssh-exkeys</b> <b>-f</b> <varname>hostfile_exkeys</varname> | <b>-h</b> <varname>hostname</varname> [<b>-h</b> <varname>hostname</varname> ...]

<b>gpssh-exkeys</b> <b>-e</b> <varname>hostfile_exkeys</varname> <b>-x</b> <varname>hostfile_gpexpand</varname>

<b>gpssh-exkeys</b> <b>-?</b> 

<b>gpssh-exkeys</b> <b>--version</b></codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="section3">
            <title>Description</title>
            <p>The <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> utility exchanges SSH keys between the specified
                host names (or host addresses). This allows SSH connections between Greenplum hosts
                and network interfaces without a password prompt. The utility is used to initially
                prepare a Greenplum Database system for passwordless SSH access, and also to prepare
                additional hosts for passwordless SSH access when expanding a Greenplum Database 
                system.</p>
            <p>Keys are exchanged as the currently logged in user. You run the utility on the master
                host as the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user (the user designated to own your Greenplum
                Database installation). Greenplum Database management utilities require that the
                    <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user be created on all hosts in the Greenplum Database
                system, and the utilities must be able to connect as that user to all hosts without
                a password prompt.</p>
            <p>You can also use <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> to enable passwordless SSH for
                additional users, <codeph>root</codeph>, for example.</p>
            <p>The <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> utility has the following prerequisites:<ul
                    id="ul_fgv_hjd_vhb">
                    <li>The user must have an account on the master, standby, and every segment host
                        in the Greenplum Database cluster.</li>
                    <li>The user must have an <codeph>id_rsa</codeph> SSH key pair installed on the
                        master host.</li>
                    <li>The user must be able to connect with SSH from the master host to every
                        other host machine without entering a password. (This is called "1-<i>n</i>
                        passwordless SSH.") </li>
                </ul></p>
            <p>You can enable 1-<i>n</i> passwordless SSH using the <codeph>ssh-copy-id</codeph>
                command to add the user's public key to each host's <codeph>authorized_keys</codeph>
                file.  The <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> utility enables "<i>n</i>-<i>n</i>
                passwordless SSH," which allows the user to connect with SSH from any host to any
                other host in the cluster without a password.</p>
            <p>To specify the hosts involved in an SSH key exchange, use the <codeph>-f</codeph>
                option to specify a file containing a list of host names (recommended), or use the
                    <codeph>-h</codeph> option to name single host names on the command-line. At
                least one host name (<codeph>-h</codeph>) or a host file (<codeph>-f</codeph>) is
                required. Note that the local host is included in the key exchange by default.</p>
            <p>To specify new expansion hosts to be added to an existing Greenplum Database system,
                use the <codeph>-e</codeph> and <codeph>-x</codeph> options. The <codeph>-e</codeph>
                option specifies a file containing a list of existing hosts in the system that have
                aready exchanged SSH keys. The <codeph>-x</codeph> option specifies a file
                containing a list of new hosts that need to participate in the SSH key exchange. </p>
            <p>The <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> utility performs key exchange using the following
                steps:</p>
            <ul>
                <li id="jw140375">Adds the user's public key to the user's own
                        <codeph>authorized_keys</codeph> file on the current host.</li>
                <li>Updates the <codeph>known_hosts</codeph> file of the current user with the host
                    key of each host specified using the <codeph>-h</codeph>, <codeph>-f</codeph>,
                        <codeph>-e</codeph>, and <codeph>-x</codeph> options.</li>
                <li id="jw140377">Connects to each host using <codeph>ssh</codeph> and obtains the
                    user's <codeph>authorized_keys</codeph>, <codeph>known_hosts</codeph>, and
                        <codeph>id_rsa.pub</codeph> files. </li>
                <li id="jw140378">Adds keys from the <codeph>id_rsa.pub</codeph> files obtained from
                    each host to the <codeph>authorized_keys</codeph> file of the current user.</li>
                <li id="jw140379">Updates the <codeph>authorized_keys</codeph>,
                        <codeph>known_hosts</codeph>, and <codeph>id_rsa.pub</codeph> files on all
                    hosts with new host information (if any).</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section id="section4">
            <title>Options</title>
            <parml>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-e <varname>hostfile_exkeys</varname></pt>
                    <pd>When doing a system expansion, this is the name and location of a file
                        containing all configured host names and host addresses (interface names)
                        for each host in your <varname>current</varname> Greenplum system (master,
                        standby master, and segments), one name per line without blank lines or
                        extra spaces. Hosts specified in this file cannot be specified in the host
                        file used with <codeph>-x</codeph>. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-f <varname>hostfile_exkeys</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Specifies the name and location of a file containing all configured host
                        names and host addresses (interface names) for each host in your Greenplum
                        system (master, standby master and segments), one name per line without
                        blank lines or extra spaces.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-h <varname>hostname</varname></pt>
                    <pd>Specifies a single host name (or host address) that will participate in the
                        SSH key exchange. You can use the <codeph>-h</codeph> option multiple times
                        to specify multiple host names and host addresses.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>--version</pt>
                    <pd>Displays the version of this utility.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-x <varname>hostfile_gpexpand</varname></pt>
                    <pd>When doing a system expansion, this is the name and location of a file
                        containing all configured host names and host addresses (interface names)
                        for each <varname>new segment host</varname> you are adding to your
                        Greenplum system, one name per line without blank lines or extra spaces.
                        Hosts specified in this file cannot be specified in the host file used with
                            <codeph>-e</codeph>.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-? (help)</pt>
                    <pd>Displays the online help.</pd>
                </plentry>
            </parml>
        </section>
        <section id="section5">
            <title>Examples</title>
            <p>Exchange SSH keys between all host names and addresses listed in the file
                    <codeph>hostfile_exkeys</codeph>:</p>
            <codeblock>$ gpssh-exkeys -f hostfile_exkeys</codeblock>
            <p>Exchange SSH keys between the hosts <codeph>sdw1</codeph>, <codeph>sdw2</codeph>, and
                    <codeph>sdw3</codeph>:</p>
            <codeblock>$ gpssh-exkeys -h sdw1 -h sdw2 -h sdw3</codeblock>
            <p>Exchange SSH keys between existing hosts <codeph>sdw1</codeph>,
                <codeph>sdw2</codeph>, and <codeph>sdw3</codeph>, and new hosts
                    <codeph>sdw4</codeph> and <codeph>sdw5</codeph> as part of a system expansion
                operation:</p>
            <codeblock>$ cat hostfile_exkeys
mdw
mdw-1
mdw-2
smdw
smdw-1
smdw-2
sdw1
sdw1-1
sdw1-2
sdw2
sdw2-1
sdw2-2
sdw3
sdw3-1
sdw3-2
$ cat hostfile_gpexpand
sdw4
sdw4-1
sdw4-2
sdw5
sdw5-1
sdw5-2
$ gpssh-exkeys -e hostfile_exkeys -x hostfile_gpexpand</codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="section6">
            <title>See Also</title>
            <p><codeph><xref href="gpssh.xml#topic1">gpssh</xref></codeph>, <codeph><xref
                        href="gpscp.xml#topic1">gpscp</xref></codeph></p>
        </section>
    </body>
</topic>
