<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
  <topic id="topic1">
    <title>pgbouncer</title>
    <body>
      <p>Manages database connection pools.</p>
      <section>
        <title>Synopsis</title>
        <codeblock>pgbouncer [OPTION ...] pgbouncer.ini

  OPTION
   [ -d | --daemon ]
   [ -R | --restart ]
   [ -q | --quiet ]
   [ -v | --verbose ]
   [ {-u | --user}=<varname>username</varname> ]

pgbouncer [ -V | --version ] | [ -h | --help ]</codeblock>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Description</title>
        <p>PgBouncer is a light-weight connection pool manager for Greenplum and
          PostgreSQL databases. PgBouncer maintains a pool of connections for each
          database user and database combination. PgBouncer either creates a new
          database connection for the client or reuses an existing pooled connection
          for the same user and database. When the client disconnects, PgBouncer
          returns the connection to the pool for re-use. </p>
        <p>PgBouncer supports the standard connection interface shared by PostgreSQL
          and Greenplum Database. The Greenplum Database client application (for example,
          <codeph>psql</codeph>) should connect to the host and port on which PgBouncer
          is running rather than directly to the Greenplum Database master host and port.</p>
         <p>You configure PgBouncer and its access to Greenplum Database via a
           configuration file. You provide the configuration file name, usually <codeph>pgbouncer.ini</codeph>,
           when you run the <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> command. This file provides location information
           for Greenplum databases. The <codeph>pgbouncer.ini</codeph> file also specifies
           process, connection pool, authorized users, and authentication configuration
           for PgBouncer, among other configuration options.</p>
        <p>By default, the <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> process runs as a foreground
          process. You can optionally start <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> as a
          background (daemon) process with the <codeph>-d</codeph> option.</p>
 
        <p>The <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph> process is owned by the operating system
          user that starts the process. You can optionally specify a different
          user name under which to start <codeph>pgbouncer</codeph>.</p>
        <p>PgBouncer includes a <codeph>psql</codeph>-like administration console.
          Authorized users can connect to a virtual database to monitor and
          manage PgBouncer. You can manage a PgBouncer daemon process via the admin
          console. You can also use the console to update and reload the PgBouncer 
          configuration at runtime without stopping and restarting the process.</p>
        <p>For additional information about PgBouncer, refer to the
          <xref href="https://pgbouncer.github.io/faq.html" format="html" scope="external"
            >PgBouncer FAQ</xref>.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Options</title>
        <parml>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-d | --daemon</pt>
            <pd>Run PgBouncer as a daemon (a background process). The default start-up
              mode is to run as a foreground process.</pd>
            <pd>When run as a daemon, PgBouncer displays start-up messages to
              <codeph>stdout</codeph>. To suppress the display of these messages,
              include the <codeph>-q</codeph> option when you start PgBouncer.</pd>
            <pd>To stop a PgBouncer process that was started as a daemon, issue the
                <codeph>SHUTDOWN</codeph> command from the PgBouncer administration
                console.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-R | --restart </pt>
            <pd>Restart PgBouncer using the specified command line arguments. Non-TLS connections to
              databases are maintained during restart; TLS connections are dropped.</pd>
            <pd>To restart PgBouncer as a daemon, specify the options
              <codeph>-Rd</codeph>.<note>Restart is available only if the operating
               system supports Unix sockets and the PgBouncer <codeph>unix_socket_dir</codeph>
               configuration is not disabled.</note></pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-q | --quiet </pt>
            <pd>Run quietly. Do not display messages to <codeph>stdout</codeph>.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-v | --verbose</pt>
            <pd>Increase message verbosity. Can be specified multiple times.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>{-u | --user}=<varname>username</varname></pt>
            <pd>Assume the identity of <varname>username</varname> on PgBouncer process start-up.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-V | --version</pt>
            <pd>Show the version and exit.</pd>
          </plentry>
          <plentry>
            <pt>-h | --help</pt>
            <pd>Show the command help message and exit.</pd>
          </plentry>
        </parml>
      </section>
      <section id="section7">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p><codeph><xref href="pgbouncer-ini.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
            <codeph><xref href="pgbouncer-admin.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph></p>
    </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
