<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="analyze">
  <title>Updating Statistics with ANALYZE</title>
  <body>
    <p>The most important prerequisite for good query performance is to begin with accurate
      statistics for the tables. Updating stastistics with the <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> statement
      enables the query planner to generate optimal query plans. When a table is analyzed,
      information about the data is stored in the system catalog tables. If the stored information
      is out of date, the planner can generate inefficient plans.</p>
    <section>
      <title>Generating Statistics Selectively</title>
      <p>Running <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> with no arguments updates statistics for all tables in the
        database. This can be a very long-running process and it is not recommended. You should
          <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> tables selectively when data has changed or use the
          <codeph>analyzedb</codeph> utility. </p>
      <p>Running <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> on a large table can take a long time. If it is not
        feasible to run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> on all columns of a very large table, you can
        generate statistics for selected columns only using <codeph>ANALYZE table(column,
          ...)</codeph>. Be sure to include columns used in joins, <codeph>WHERE</codeph> clauses,
          <codeph>SORT</codeph> clauses, <codeph>GROUP BY</codeph> clauses, or
          <codeph>HAVING</codeph> clauses. </p>
      <p>For a partitioned table, you can run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> on just partitions that have
        changed, for example, if you add a new partition. Note that for partitioned tables, you can
        run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> on the parent (main) table, or on the leaf nodes&#8212;the
        partition files where data and statistics are actually stored. The intermediate files for
        sub-partitioned tables store no data or statistics, so running <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> on
        them does not work. You can find the names of the partition tables in the
          <codeph>pg_partitions</codeph> system
        catalog:<codeblock>SELECT partitiontablename from pg_partitions WHERE tablename='<i>parent_table</i>;</codeblock></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Improving Statistics Quality</title>
      <p>There is a trade-off between the amount of time it takes to generate statistics and the
        quality, or accuracy, of the statistics. </p>
      <p>To allow large tables to be analyzed in a reasonable amount of time,
          <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> takes a random sample of the table contents, rather than
        examining every row. To increase the number of sample values for all table columns adjust
        the <codeph>default_statistics_target</codeph> configuration parameter. The target value
        ranges from 1 to 1000; the default target value is 100. The
          <codeph>default_statistics_target</codeph> variable applies to all columns by default, and
        specifies the number of values that are stored in the list of common values. A larger target
        may improve the quality of the query planner’s estimates, especially for columns with
        irregular data patterns. <codeph>default_statistics_target</codeph> can be set at the
        master/session level and requires a reload. </p>
      <p>The <codeph>gp_analyze_relative_error</codeph> configuration parameter affects the sampling
        rate during statistics collection to determine cardinality in a column. For example, a value
        of .5 is equivalent to an acceptable error of 50%. The default is .25. Use the
          <codeph>gp_analyze_relative_error</codeph> parameter to set the acceptable estimated
        relative error in the cardinality of a table. If statistics do not produce good estimates of
        cardinality for a particular table attribute, decreasing the relative error fraction
        (accepting less errors) tells the system to sample more rows. However, it is not recommended
        to reduce this below 0.1 as it will increase <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> time
        substantially.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>When to Run ANALYZE</title>
    </section>
    <p>Run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph>:<ul id="ul_f5c_gnj_bp">
        <li>after loading data,</li>
        <li>after <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph> operations,</li>
        <li>and after <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, and <codeph>DELETE</codeph>
          operations that significantly change the underlying data.</li>
      </ul><codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> requires only a read lock on the table, so it may be run in
      parallel with other database activity, but do not run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> while
      performing loads, <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, <codeph>DELETE</codeph>,
      and <codeph>CREATE INDEX</codeph> operations.</p>
    <section>
      <title>Configuring Automatic Statistics Collection</title>
      <p>The <codeph>gp_autostats_mode</codeph> configuration parameter, together with the
          <codeph>gp_autostats_on_change_threshold</codeph> parameter, determines when an automatic
        analyze operation is triggered. When automatic statistics collection is triggered, the
        planner adds an <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> step to the query. </p>
      <p>By default, <codeph>gp_autostats_mode</codeph> is <codeph>on_no_stats</codeph>, which
        triggers statistics collection for <codeph>CREATE TABLE AS SELECT</codeph>,
          <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, or <codeph>COPY</codeph> operations on any table that has no
        existing statistics. </p>
      <p>Setting <codeph>gp_autostats_mode</codeph> to <codeph>on_change</codeph> triggers
        statistics collection only when the number of rows affected exceeds the threshold defined by
          <codeph>gp_autostats_on_change_threshold</codeph>, which has a default value of
        2147483647. Operations that can trigger automatic statistics collection with
          <codeph>on_change</codeph> are: <codeph>CREATE TABLE AS SELECT</codeph>,
          <codeph>UPDATE</codeph>, <codeph>DELETE</codeph>, <codeph>INSERT</codeph>, and
          <codeph>COPY</codeph>.</p>
      <p>Setting <codeph>gp_autostats_mode</codeph> to <codeph>none</codeph> disables automatics
        statistics collection. </p>
      <p> For partitioned tables, automatic statistics collection is not triggered if data is
        inserted from the top-level parent table of a partitioned table. But automatic statistics
        collection <i>is</i> triggered if data is inserted directly in a leaf table (where the data
        is stored) of the partitioned table.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
