<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic_yrk_bcx_r4">
  <title>System Monitoring and Maintenance</title>
  <shortdesc>Best practices for regular maintenance that will ensure Greenplum Database high
    availability and optimal performance.</shortdesc>
  <topic id="topic_izw_bwb_s4">
    <title id="monitoring">Monitoring</title>
    <body>
      <p>Greenplum Database includes utilities that are useful for monitoring the system.</p>
      <p>The <codeph>gp_toolkit</codeph> schema conatains several views that can be accessed using
        SQL commands to query system catalogs, log files, and operating environment for system
        status information. </p>
      <p>The <codeph>gp_stats_missing</codeph> view shows tables that do not have statistics and
        require <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> to be run.</p>
      <p>For additional information on <codeph>gpstate</codeph> and <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph>
        refer to the <i>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</i>. For information about the
          gp_<codeph>toolkit</codeph> schema, see the <i>Greenplum Database Reference Guide</i>. </p>
      <section>
        <title>gpstate</title>
        <p>The <codeph>gpstate</codeph> utility program displays the status of the Greenplum system,
          including which segments are down, master and segment configuration information (hosts,
          data directories, etc.), the ports used by the system, and mapping of primary segments to
          their corresponding mirror segments.</p>
        <p>Run <codeph>gpstate -Q</codeph> to get a list of segments that are marked "down" in the
          master system catalog.</p>
        <p>To get detailed status information for the Greenplum system, run <codeph>gpstate
            -s</codeph>.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>gpcheckperf</title>
        <p>The <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> utility tests baseline hardware performance for a list
          of hosts. The results can help identify hardware issues. It performs the following checks:
            <ul id="ul_ic1_5xb_s4">
            <li>disk I/O test &#8211; measures I/O performance by writing and reading a large file
              using the <codeph>dd</codeph> operating system command. It reports read and write
              rates in megabytes per second.</li>
            <li>memory bandwidth test &#8211; measures sustainable memory bandwidth in megabytes per
              second using the STREAM benchmark.</li>
            <li>network performance test &#8211; runs the <codeph>gpnetbench</codeph> network
              benchmark program (optionally <codeph>netperf)</codeph> to test network performance.
              The test is run in one of three modes: parallel pair test (<codeph>-r N</codeph>),
              serial pair test (<codeph>-r n</codeph>), or full-matrix test (<codeph>-r
              M)</codeph>.The minimum, maximum, average, and median transfer rates are reported in
              megabytes per second. </li>
          </ul>To obtain valid numbers from <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph>, the database system must
          be stopped. The numbers from <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> can be inaccurate even if the
          system is up and running with no query activity.</p>
        <p><codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> requires a trusted host setup between the hosts involved in
          the performance test. It calls <codeph>gpssh</codeph> and <codeph>gpscp</codeph>, so these
          utilities must also be in your <codeph>PATH</codeph>. Specify the hosts to check
          individually (<codeph>-h <i>host1</i> -h <i>host2</i> ...</codeph>) or with <codeph>-f
              <i>hosts_file</i></codeph>, where <codeph><i>hosts_file</i></codeph> is a text file
          containing a list of the hosts to check. If you have more than one subnet, create a
          separate host file for each subnet so that you can test the subnets separately. </p>
        <p>By default, <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> runs the disk I/O test, the memory test, and a
          serial pair network performance test. With the disk I/O test, you must use the
            <codeph>-d</codeph> option to specify the file systems you want to test. The following
          command tests disk I/O and memory bandwidth on hosts listed in the
            <codeph>subnet_1_hosts</codeph>
          file:<codeblock>$ gpcheckperf -f subnet_1_hosts -d /data1 -d /data2 -r ds</codeblock></p>
        <p>The <codeph>-r</codeph> option selects the tests to run: disk I/O (<codeph>d</codeph>),
          memory bandwidth (<codeph>s</codeph>), network parallel pair (<codeph>N</codeph>), network
          serial pair test (<codeph>n</codeph>), network full-matrix test (<codeph>M</codeph>). Only
          one network mode can be selected per execution. See the <i>Greenplum Database Reference
            Guide</i> for the detailed <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> reference.</p>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Monitoring with Operating System Utilities</title>
      </section>
      <p>The following Linux/UNIX utilities can be used to assess host performance:<ul
          id="ul_hvv_sh4_y4">
          <li><codeph>iostat</codeph> allows you to monitor disk activity on segment hosts.</li>
          <li><codeph>top</codeph> displays a dynamic view of operating system processes.</li>
          <li><codeph>vmstat</codeph> displays memory usage statistics.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>You can use <codeph>gpssh</codeph> to run utilities on multiple hosts.</p>
      <section>
        <title>Best Practices</title>
        <ul id="ul_wd5_bj4_y4">
          <li>Implement the "Recommended Monitoring and Maintenance Tasks" in the <i>Greenplum
              Database Administrator Guide</i>.</li>
          <li>Run <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> at install time and periodically thereafter, saving
            the output to compare system performance over time. </li>
          <li>Use all the tools at your disposal to understand how your system behaves under
            different loads. </li>
          <li>Examine any unusual event to determine the cause.</li>
          <li>Monitor query activity on the system by running explain plans periodically to ensure
            the queries are running optimally.</li>
          <li>Review plans to determine whether index are being used and partition elimination is
            occurring as expected.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Additional Information</title>
        <ul id="ul_ynx_fmn_y4">
          <li><codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> reference in the <i>Greenplum Database Utility
            Guide</i>.</li>
          <li>"Recommended Monitoring and Maintenance Tasks" in the <i>Greenplum Database
              Administrator Guide</i>.</li>
          <li><xref href="http://www.cs.virginia.edu/%7Emccalpin/papers/bandwidth/bandwidth.html"
              format="html" scope="external">Sustainable Memory Bandwidth in Current High
              Performance Computers</xref>. John D. McCalpin. Oct 12, 1995.</li>
          <li><xref href="http://www.netperf.org/netperf" format="html" scope="external"
              >www.netperf.org</xref> to use <codeph>netperf</codeph>, netperf must be installed on
            each host you test. See <codeph>gpcheckperf</codeph> reference for more
            information.</li>
        </ul>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>


</topic>
