<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="Untitled1">
  <title>Example Ansible Playbook</title>
  <shortdesc>A sample Ansible playbook to install a Greenplum Database software release onto the
    hosts that will comprise a Greenplum Database system.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>This Ansible playbook shows how tasks described in <xref href="install_gpdb.xml#topic1"/>
      might be automated using <xref href="https://docs.ansible.com" format="html" scope="external"
        >Ansible</xref>.</p>
    <note type="important">This playbook is provided as an <i>example only</i> to illustrate how
      Greenplum Database cluster configuration and software installation tasks can be automated
      using provisioning tools such as Ansible, Chef, or Puppet. Pivotal does not provide support
      for Ansible or for the playbook presented in this example.</note>
    <p>The example playbook is designed for use with CentOS 7. It creates the
        <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user, installs the Greenplum Database software release, sets the
      owner and group of the installed software to <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>, and sets the Pam
      security limits for the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user. </p>
    <p>You can revise the script to work with your operating system platform and to perform
      additional host configuration tasks.</p>
    <p>Following are steps to use this Ansible playbook.</p>
    <ol id="ol_umm_h25_yhb">
      <li>Install Ansible on the control node using your package manager. See the <xref
          href="https://docs.ansible.com" format="html" scope="external">Ansible documention</xref>
        for help with installation.</li>
      <li>Set up passwordless SSH from the control node to all hosts that will be a part of the
        Greenplum Database cluster. You can use the <codeph>ssh-copy-id</codeph> command to install
        your public SSH key on each host in the cluster. Alternatively, your provisioning software
        may provide more convenient ways to securely install public keys on multiple hosts.</li>
      <li>Create an Ansible inventory by creating a file called <codeph>hosts</codeph> with a list
        of the hosts that will comprise your Greenplum Database cluster. For
        example:<codeblock>mdw
sdw1
sdw2
...</codeblock>This file can be edited and used with the
        Greenplum Database <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> and <codeph>gpinitsystem</codeph> utilities
        later on.</li>
      <li>Copy the playbook code below to a file <codeph>ansible-playbook.yml</codeph> on your
        Ansible control node.</li>
      <li>Edit the playbook variables at the top of the playbook, such as the
          <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> administrative user and password to create, and the version of
        Greenplum Database you are installing. </li>
      <li>Run the playbook, passing the package to be installed to the <codeph>package_path</codeph>
        parameter.<codeblock>ansible-playbook ansible-playbook.yml -i hosts -e package_path=./greenplum-db-6.0.0-rhel7-x86_64.rpm</codeblock></li>
    </ol>
    <section>
      <title>Ansible Playbook - Greenplum Database Installation for CentOS 7</title>
      <codeblock>
---

- hosts: all
  vars:
    - version: "6.0.0"
    - greenplum_admin_user: "gpadmin"
    - greenplum_admin_password: "changeme"
    # - package_path: passed via the command line with: -e package_path=./greenplum-db-6.0.0-rhel7-x86_64.rpm
  remote_user: root
  become: yes
  become_method: sudo
  connection: ssh
  gather_facts: yes
  tasks:
    - name: create greenplum admin user
      user:
        name: "{{ greenplum_admin_user }}"
        password: "{{ greenplum_admin_password | password_hash('sha512', 'DvkPtCtNH+UdbePZfm9muQ9pU') }}"
    - name: copy package to host
      copy:
        src: "{{ package_path }}"
        dest: /tmp
    - name: install package
      yum:
        name: "/tmp/{{ package_path | basename }}"
        state: present
    - name: cleanup package file from host
      file:
        path: "/tmp/{{ package_path | basename }}"
        state: absent
    - name: find install directory
      find:
        paths: /usr/local
        patterns: 'greenplum*'
        file_type: directory
      register: installed_dir
    - name: change install directory ownership
      file:
        path: '{{ item.path }}'
        owner: "{{ greenplum_admin_user }}"
        group: "{{ greenplum_admin_user }}"
        recurse: yes
      with_items: "{{ installed_dir.files }}"
    - name: update pam_limits
      pam_limits:
        domain: "{{ greenplum_admin_user }}"
        limit_type: '-'
        limit_item: "{{ item.key }}"
        value: "{{ item.value }}"
      with_dict:
        nofile: 524288
        nproc: 131072
    - name: find installed greenplum version
      shell: . /usr/local/greenplum-db/greenplum_path.sh &amp;&amp; /usr/local/greenplum-db/bin/postgres --gp-version
      register: postgres_gp_version
    - name: fail if the correct greenplum version is not installed
      fail:
        msg: "Expected greenplum version {{ version }}, but found '{{ postgres_gp_version.stdout }}'"
      when: "version is not defined or version not in postgres_gp_version.stdout"
</codeblock>
    </section>
    <p>When the playbook has executed successfully, you can proceed with <xref
        href="create_data_dirs.xml#topic13"/> and <xref href="init_gpdb.xml#topic1"/>.</p>
  </body>
</topic>
