<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic13">
    <title id="ji162534">Creating the Data Storage Areas</title>
  <shortdesc>Describes how to create the directory locations where Greenplum Database data is stored
    for each coordinator, standby, and segment instance.</shortdesc>
    <topic id="topic_wqb_1lc_wp">
      <title>Creating Data Storage Areas on the Coordinator and Standby Coordinator Hosts</title>
      <body>
        <p>A data storage area is required on the Greenplum Database coordinator and standby coordinator hosts
          to store Greenplum Database system data such as catalog data and other system metadata. </p>
        <section id="topic_ix1_x1n_tp">
          <title>To create the data directory location on the coordinator</title>
          <p>The data directory location on the coordinator is different than those on the segments. The
            coordinator does not store any user data, only the system catalog tables and system metadata
            are stored on the coordinator instance, therefore you do not need to designate as much
            storage space as on the segments.</p>
          <ol id="ol_x3b_clc_wp">
            <li id="ji162541">Create or choose a directory that will serve as your coordinator data
              storage area. This directory should have sufficient disk space for your data and be
              owned by the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user and group. For example, run the following
              commands as <codeph>root</codeph>:<codeblock># mkdir -p /data/coordinator</codeblock></li>
            <li id="ji162549">Change ownership of this directory to the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>
              user. For example:<codeblock># chown gpadmin:gpadmin /data/coordinator</codeblock></li>
            <li id="ji162557">Using <xref href="../utility_guide/ref/gpssh.xml" format="dita"
              scope="peer" type="topic">gpssh</xref>, create the coordinator data directory location
            on your standby coordinator as well. For
            example:<codeblock># source /usr/local/greenplum-db/greenplum_path.sh 
# gpssh -h smdw -e 'mkdir -p /data/coordinator'
# gpssh -h smdw -e 'chown gpadmin:gpadmin /data/coordinator'</codeblock></li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </body>
    </topic>

  <topic id="topic_plx_zps_vhb">
    <title>Creating Data Storage Areas on Segment Hosts</title>
    <body>
      <p>Data storage areas are required on the Greenplum Database segment hosts for primary
        segments. Separate storage areas are required for mirror segments.</p>
      <section id="topic_tnb_v1n_tp">
        <title>To create the data directory locations on all segment hosts</title>
        <ol id="ol_otk_xkc_wp">
          <li id="ji162571">On the coordinator host, log in as
            <codeph>root</codeph>:<codeblock># su</codeblock></li>
          <li id="ji162573">Create a file called <codeph>hostfile_gpssh_segonly</codeph>. This file
            should have only one machine configured host name for each segment host. For example, if
            you have three segment hosts:<codeblock>sdw1
sdw2
sdw3</codeblock></li>
          <li id="ji162580">Using <xref href="../utility_guide/ref/gpssh.xml" format="dita"
              scope="peer">gpssh</xref>, create the primary and mirror data directory locations on
            all segment hosts at once using the <codeph>hostfile_gpssh_segonly</codeph> file you
            just created. For
            example:<codeblock># source /usr/local/greenplum-db/greenplum_path.sh 
# gpssh -f hostfile_gpssh_segonly -e 'mkdir -p /data/primary'
# gpssh -f hostfile_gpssh_segonly -e 'mkdir -p /data/mirror'
# gpssh -f hostfile_gpssh_segonly -e 'chown -R gpadmin /data/*'</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_cwj_hzb_vhb">
    <title>Next Steps</title>
    <body>
      <ul id="ul_xsq_jzb_vhb">
        <li><xref href="validate.xml#topic1">Validating Your Systems</xref></li>
        <li><xref href="init_gpdb.xml#topic1">Initializing a Greenplum Database System</xref></li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </topic>
  
</topic>
