<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic_lvl_dsy_4bb">
  <title>DCA System Installation and Upgrade</title>
  <body>
    <p>On supported Dell EMC DCA systems, you can install Pivotal Greenplum 6, or you can upgrade
      from Pivotal Greenplum 6.x to 6.new.</p>
    <p>Only Pivotal Greenplum Database is supported on DCA systems. Open source versions of
      Greenplum Database are not supported. </p>
    <ul id="ul_ryv_wn2_pbb">
      <li><xref href="#topic_x2w_ltv_yq" format="dita"/></li>
      <li><xref href="#topic_usj_2xl_xq" format="dita"/></li>
    </ul>
    <note type="important">Upgrading Pivotal Greenplum Database 4 or 5 to Pivotal Greenplum 6 is not
      supported.</note>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_x2w_ltv_yq">
    <title class="- topic/title ">Installing the Pivotal Greenplum 6 Software Binaries on DCA
      Systems</title>
    <body class="- topic/body ">
      <note type="important">This section is for installing Pivotal Greenplum 6 only on DCA systems.
        Also, see the information on the <xref href="https://support.emc.com/" format="html"
          scope="external">DELL EMC support site</xref> (requires login). </note>
      <section>
        <title>Prerequisites</title>
        <ul id="ul_fjm_nx2_pbb">
          <li>Ensure your DCA system supports Pivotal Greenplum 6. See <xref
              href="supported-platforms.xml" format="dita"/>.</li>
          <li>Ensure that no previous versions of Greenplum Database are installed on your
              system.<p>Installing Pivotal Greenplum 6 on a DCA system with an existing Greenplum
              Database installation is not supported. For information about uninstalling Greenplum
              Database software, see your Dell EMC DCA documentation.</p></li>
        </ul>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Installing Pivotal Greenplum 6</title>
        <ol class="- topic/ol " id="ol_ctw_ltv_yq">
          <li class="- topic/li ">Download or copy the Greenplum Database DCA installer file to the
            Greenplum Database master host.</li>
          <li class="- topic/li ">As root, run the DCA installer for Greenplum 6 on the Greenplum
            Database master host and specify the file <codeph>hostfile</codeph> that lists all hosts
            in the cluster, one host name per line. If necessary, copy <codeph>hostfile</codeph> to
            the directory containing the installer before running the installer.<p>This example
              command runs the installer for Greenplum Database
            6.</p><codeblock># ./greenplum-db-appliance-&lt;version>-RHEL6-x86_64.bin hostfile</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_usj_2xl_xq">
    <title class="- topic/title ">Upgrading Greenplum 6.x on DCA Systems</title>
    <body class="- topic/body ">
      <p>Upgrading Pivotal Greenplum from 6.x to 6.new on a Dell EMC DCA system involves stopping
        Greenplum Database, updating the Greenplum Database software binaries, and restarting
        Greenplum Database. </p>
      <note type="important">This section is only for upgrading Pivotal Greenplum 6 on DCA systems.
        For information about upgrading on non-DCA systems, see <xref
          href="upgrading.xml#topic_tbx_szy_kbb"/>.</note>
      <ol class="- topic/ol " id="ol_fql_2xl_xq">
        <li class="- topic/li ">Log in to your Greenplum Database master host as the Greenplum
          administrative user (<codeph>gpadmin</codeph>):<codeblock># su - gpadmin</codeblock></li>
        <li class="- topic/li ">Download or copy the installer file
            <codeph>greenplum-db-appliance-&lt;6.new>-RHEL6-x86_64.bin</codeph> to the Greenplum
          Database master host.</li>
        <li class="- topic/li ">Perform a smart shutdown of your existing Greenplum Database 6.x
          system (there can be no active connections to the database). This example uses the
            <codeph>-a</codeph> option to disable confirmation
          prompts:<codeblock>$ gpstop -a</codeblock></li>
        <li class="- topic/li ">As root, run the Greenplum Database DCA installer for 6.new on the
          Greenplum Database master host and specify the file <codeph>hostfile</codeph> that lists
          all hosts in the cluster. If necessary, copy <codeph>hostfile</codeph> to the directory
          containing the installer before running the installer.<p>This example command runs the
            installer for Greenplum Database 6.new for Red Hat Enterprise Linux
            6.x.</p><codeblock># ./greenplum-db-appliance-&lt;6.new>-RHEL6-x86_64.bin hostfile</codeblock><p>The
            file <codeph>hostfile</codeph> is a text file that lists all hosts in the cluster, one
            host name per line.</p></li>
        <li>If needed, update the <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> file for use with your specific
          installation. These are some examples.<ul id="ul_vs1_3lq_cgb">
            <li>If Greenplum Database uses LDAP authentication, edit the
                <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> file to add the
              line:<codeblock>export LDAPCONF=/etc/openldap/ldap.conf</codeblock></li>
            <li>If Greenplum Database uses PL/Java, you might need to set or update the environment
              variables <codeph>JAVA_HOME</codeph> and <codeph>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</codeph> in
                <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph>. </li>
          </ul>
          <note>When comparing the previous and new <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> files, be
            aware that installing some Greenplum Database extensions also updates the
              <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> file. The <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> from
            the previous release might contain updates that were the result of those
            extensions.</note></li>
        <li class="- topic/li ">Install Greenplum Database extension packages. For information about
          installing a Greenplum Database extension package, see <codeph>gppkg</codeph> in the
            <cite>Greenplum Database Utility Guide</cite>.<p>Also migrate any additional files that
            are used by the extensions (such as JAR files, shared object files, and libraries) from
            the previous version installation directory to the new version installation directory.
          </p></li>
        <li class="- topic/li ">After all segment hosts have been upgraded, you can log in as the
            <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user and restart your Greenplum Database
          system:<codeblock># su - gpadmin
$ gpstart</codeblock></li>
        <li class="- topic/li ">If you are utilizing Data Domain Boost, you have to re-enter your DD
          Boost credentials after upgrading to Greenplum Database 6 as follows:<codeblock>gpcrondump --ddboost-host <varname>ddboost_hostname</varname> --ddboost-user <varname>ddboost_user</varname>
  --ddboost-backupdir <varname>backup_directory</varname></codeblock>
          <note>If you do not reenter your login credentials after an upgrade, your backup will
            never start because the Greenplum Database cannot connect to the Data Domain system. You
            will receive an error advising you to check your login credentials. </note></li>
      </ol>
      <p>After upgrading Greenplum Database, ensure features work as expected. For example, you
        should test that backup and restore perform as expected, and Greenplum Database features
        such as user-defined functions, and extensions such as MADlib and PostGIS perform as
        expected.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
