<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="ji163114">Enabling iptables (Optional)</title>
  <shortdesc>On Linux systems, you can configure and enable the <codeph>iptables</codeph> firewall
    to work with Greenplum Database.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <note type="note">Greenplum Database performance might be impacted when
        <codeph>iptables</codeph> is enabled. You should test the performance of your application
      with <codeph>iptables</codeph> enabled to ensure that performance is acceptable.</note>
    <p>For more information about <codeph>iptables</codeph> see the <codeph>iptables</codeph> and
      firewall documentation for your operating system. See also <xref
        href="prep_os.xml#topic_sqj_lt1_nfb" type="topic" format="dita">Disabling SELinux and
        Firewall Software</xref>.</p>
    <section id="ji163124">
      <title>How to Enable iptables</title>
      <ol id="ol_akk_knz_thb">
        <li id="ji163128">As <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>, run this command on the Greenplum Database
          master host to stop Greenplum Database:<codeblock>$ gpstop -a</codeblock></li>
        <li id="ji163139">On the Greenplum Database hosts:<ol id="ol_bkk_knz_thb">
            <li id="ji163142">Update the file <codeph>/etc/sysconfig/iptables</codeph> based on the
                <xref href="#topic16" type="topic" format="dita"/>. </li>
            <li id="ji163144">As root user, run these commands to enable
              <codeph>iptables</codeph>:<codeblock># chkconfig iptables on
# service iptables start</codeblock></li>
          </ol></li>
        <li id="ji163149">As gpadmin, run this command on the Greenplum Database master host to
          start Greenplum Database:<codeblock>$ gpstart -a</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
      <note type="warning">After enabling <codeph>iptables</codeph>, this error in the
          <codeph>/var/log/messages</codeph> file indicates that the setting for the
          <codeph>iptables</codeph> table is too low and needs to be
          increased.<codeblock>ip_conntrack: table full, dropping packet.</codeblock><p>As root, run
          this command to view the <codeph>iptables</codeph> table
          value:</p><codeblock># sysctl net.ipv4.netfilter.ip_conntrack_max</codeblock><p>To ensure
          that the Greenplum Database workload does not overflow the <codeph>iptables</codeph>
          table, as root, set it to the following value:
          </p><codeblock># sysctl net.ipv4.netfilter.ip_conntrack_max=6553600</codeblock><p>The
          value might need to be adjusted for your hosts. To maintain the value after reboot, you
          can update the <codeph>/etc/sysctl.conf</codeph> file as discussed in <xref
            href="prep_os.xml#topic3" format="dita" type="topic">Setting the Greenplum Recommended
            OS Parameters</xref>. </p></note>
    </section>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic16" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="ji163171">Example iptables Rules</title>
    <body>
      <p>When <codeph>iptables</codeph> is enabled, <codeph>iptables</codeph> manages the IP
        communication on the host system based on configuration settings (rules). The example rules
        are used to configure <codeph>iptables</codeph> for Greenplum Database master host, standby
        master host, and segment hosts. </p>
      <ul id="ul_ckk_knz_thb">
        <li id="ji163179">
          <xref href="#topic17" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="ji163183">
          <xref href="#topic18" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>The two sets of rules account for the different types of communication Greenplum Database
        expects on the master (primary and standby) and segment hosts. The rules should be added to
        the <codeph>/etc/sysconfig/iptables</codeph> file of the Greenplum Database hosts. For
        Greenplum Database, <codeph>iptables</codeph> rules should allow the following
        communication: </p>
      <ul id="ul_dkk_knz_thb">
        <li id="ji163197">For customer facing communication with the Greenplum Database master,
          allow at least <codeph>postgres</codeph> and <codeph>28080</codeph> (<codeph>eth1</codeph>
          interface in the example). </li>
        <li id="ji163201">For Greenplum Database system interconnect, allow communication using
            <codeph>tcp</codeph>, <codeph>udp</codeph>, and <codeph>icmp</codeph> protocols
            (<codeph>eth4</codeph> and <codeph>eth5</codeph> interfaces in the example).<p>The
            network interfaces that you specify in the <codeph>iptables</codeph> settings are the
            interfaces for the Greenplum Database hosts that you list in the
              <varname>hostfile_gpinitsystem</varname> file. You specify the file when you run the
              <codeph>gpinitsystem</codeph> command to initialize a Greenplum Database system. See
              <xref href="./init_gpdb.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/> for information about
            the <varname>hostfile_gpinitsystem</varname> file and the <codeph>gpinitsystem</codeph>
            command. </p></li>
        <li id="ji163212" otherprops="dca">For the administration network on a Greenplum DCA, allow
          communication using <codeph>ssh</codeph>, <codeph>ntp</codeph>, and <codeph>icmp</codeph>
          protocols. (<codeph>eth0</codeph> interface in the example).</li>
      </ul>
      <p>In the <codeph>iptables</codeph> file, each append rule command (lines starting with
          <codeph>-A</codeph>) is a single line.</p>
      <p>The example rules should be adjusted for your configuration. For example:</p>
      <ul id="ul_ekk_knz_thb">
        <li id="ji163215">The append command, the <codeph>-A</codeph> lines and connection parameter
            <codeph>-i</codeph> should match the connectors for your hosts.</li>
        <li id="ji163216">the CIDR network mask information for the source parameter
            <codeph>-s</codeph> should match the IP addresses for your network.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic17" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ji163218">Example Master and Standby Master iptables Rules</title>
      <body>
        <p>Example <codeph>iptables</codeph> rules with comments for the
            <codeph>/etc/sysconfig/iptables</codeph> file on the Greenplum Database master host and
          standby master host.</p>
        <codeblock>*filter
# Following 3 are default rules. If the packet passes through
# the rule set it gets these rule.
# Drop all inbound packets by default.
# Drop all forwarded (routed) packets.
# Let anything outbound go through.
:INPUT DROP [0:0]
:FORWARD DROP [0:0]
:OUTPUT ACCEPT [0:0]
# Accept anything on the loopback interface.
-A INPUT -i lo -j ACCEPT
# If a connection has already been established allow the
# remote host packets for the connection to pass through.
-A INPUT -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT
# These rules let all tcp and udp through on the standard
# interconnect IP addresses and on the interconnect interfaces.
# NOTE: gpsyncmaster uses random tcp ports in the range 1025 to 65535
# and Greenplum Database uses random udp ports in the range 1025 to 65535.
-A INPUT -i eth4 -p udp -s 192.0.2.0/22 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth5 -p udp -s 198.51.100.0/22 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth4 -p tcp -s 192.0.2.0/22 -j ACCEPT --syn -m state --state NEW
-A INPUT -i eth5 -p tcp -s 198.51.100.0/22 -j ACCEPT --syn -m state --state NEW<ph otherprops="dca">
# Allow udp/tcp ntp connections on the admin network on Greenplum DCA.
-A INPUT -i eth0 -p udp --dport ntp -s 203.0.113.0/21 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth0 -p tcp --dport ntp -s 203.0.113.0/21 -j ACCEPT --syn -m state --state NEW</ph>
# Allow ssh on all networks (This rule can be more strict).
-A INPUT -p tcp --dport ssh -j ACCEPT --syn -m state --state NEW
# Allow Greenplum Database on all networks.
-A INPUT -p tcp --dport postgres -j ACCEPT --syn -m state --state NEW
# Allow Greenplum Command Center on the customer facing network.
-A INPUT -i eth1 -p tcp --dport 28080 -j ACCEPT --syn -m state --state NEW
# Allow ping and any other icmp traffic on the interconnect networks.
-A INPUT -i eth4 -p icmp -s 192.0.2.0/22 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth5 -p icmp -s 198.51.100.0/22 -j ACCEPT<ph otherprops="dca">
# Allow ping only on the admin network on Greenplum DCA.
-A INPUT -i eth0 -p icmp --icmp-type echo-request -s 203.0.113.0/21 -j ACCEPT</ph>
# Log an error if a packet passes through the rules to the default
# INPUT rule (a DROP).
-A INPUT -m limit --limit 5/min -j LOG --log-prefix "iptables denied: " --log-level 7
COMMIT</codeblock>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic18" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="ji163239">Example Segment Host iptables Rules</title>
      <body>
        <p>Example <codeph>iptables</codeph> rules for the <codeph>/etc/sysconfig/iptables</codeph>
          file on the Greenplum Database segment hosts. The rules for segment hosts are similar to
          the master rules with fewer interfaces and fewer <codeph>udp</codeph> and
            <codeph>tcp</codeph> services. </p>
        <codeblock>*filter
:INPUT DROP
:FORWARD DROP
:OUTPUT ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i lo -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth2 -p udp -s 192.0.2.0/22 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth3 -p udp -s 198.51.100.0/22 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth2 -p tcp -s 192.0.2.0/22 -j ACCEPT --syn -m state --state NEW
-A INPUT -i eth3 -p tcp -s 198.51.100.0/22 -j ACCEPT --syn -m state --state NEW
-A INPUT -p tcp --dport ssh -j ACCEPT --syn -m state --state NEW
-A INPUT -i eth2 -p icmp -s 192.0.2.0/22 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth3 -p icmp -s 198.51.100.0/22 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i eth0 -p icmp --icmp-type echo-request -s 203.0.113.0/21 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -m limit --limit 5/min -j LOG --log-prefix "iptables denied: " --log-level 7
COMMIT</codeblock>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</topic>
