<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="jm138244">Initializing a Greenplum Database System</title>
  <shortdesc>Describes how to initialize a Greenplum Database database system. </shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>The instructions in this chapter assume you have already prepared your hosts as described in
        <xref href="prep_os.xml#topic1"/> and installed the Greenplum Database software on all of
      the hosts in the system according to the instructions in <xref href="install_gpdb.xml#topic1"
        type="topic" format="dita"/>. </p>
    <p>This chapter contains the following topics:</p>
    <ul>
      <li id="jm137819">
        <xref href="#topic2" type="topic" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li id="jm138219">
        <xref href="#topic3" type="topic" format="dita"/>
      </li>
      <li id="jm138984">
        <xref href="#topic9" type="topic" format="dita"/>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic2" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="jm137384">Overview</title>
    <body>
      <p>Because Greenplum Database is distributed, the process for initializing a Greenplum
        Database management system (DBMS) involves initializing several individual PostgreSQL
        database instances (called <i>segment instances</i> in Greenplum).</p>
      <p>Each database instance (the master and all segments) must be initialized across all of the
        hosts in the system in such a way that they can all work together as a unified DBMS.
        Greenplum provides its own version of <codeph>initdb</codeph> called <codeph><xref
            href="../utility_guide/ref/gpinitsystem.html" type="topic" format="dita"
            scope="peer">gpinitsystem</xref></codeph>, which takes care of initializing the database
        on the master and on each segment instance, and starting each instance in the correct order. </p>
      <p>After the Greenplum Database database system has been initialized and started, you can then
        create and manage databases as you would in a regular PostgreSQL DBMS by connecting to the
        Greenplum master.</p>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic3" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="jm137833">Initializing Greenplum Database</title>
    <body>
      <p>These are the high-level tasks for initializing Greenplum Database:</p>
      <ol>
        <li id="jm138478">Make sure you have completed all of the installation tasks described in
            <xref href="prep_os.xml#topic1"/> and <xref href="install_gpdb.xml#topic1" type="topic"
            format="dita"/>.</li>
        <li id="jm138489">Create a host file that contains the host addresses of your
            <varname>segments</varname>. See <xref href="#topic4" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</li>
        <li id="jm138493">Create your Greenplum Database system configuration file. See <xref
            href="#topic5" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</li>
        <li id="jm138497">By default, Greenplum Database will be initialized using the locale of the
          master host system. Make sure this is the correct locale you want to use, as some locale
          options cannot be changed after initialization. See <xref href="localization.xml#topic1"
            type="topic" format="dita"/> for more information.</li>
        <li id="jm143805">Run the Greenplum Database initialization utility on the master host. See
            <xref href="#topic6" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</li>
        <li>Set the Greenplum Database timezone. See <xref href="#topic_xkd_d1q_l2b" format="dita"
          />.</li>
      </ol>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic4" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="jm138555">Creating the Initialization Host File</title>
      <body>
        <p>The <codeph><xref href="../utility_guide/ref/gpinitsystem.xml" type="topic"
              format="dita" scope="peer">gpinitsystem</xref></codeph> utility requires a host file
          that contains the list of addresses for each segment host. The initialization utility
          determines the number of segment instances per host by the number host addresses listed
          per host times the number of data directory locations specified in the
            <codeph>gpinitsystem_config</codeph> file.</p>
        <p>This file should only contain <varname>segment</varname> host addresses (not the master
          or standby master). For segment machines with multiple, unbonded network interfaces, this
          file should list the host address names for each interface — one per line.</p>
        <note type="note">The Greenplum Database segment host naming convention is
            <varname>sdwN</varname> where <varname>sdw</varname> is a prefix and
            <varname>N</varname> is an integer. For example, <codeph>sdw2</codeph> and so on. If
          hosts have multiple unbonded NICs, the convention is to append a dash (<codeph>-</codeph>)
          and number to the host name. For example, <codeph>sdw1-1</codeph> and
            <codeph>sdw1-2</codeph> are the two interface names for host <codeph>sdw1</codeph>.
          However, NIC bonding is recommended to create a load-balanced, fault-tolerant
          network.</note>
        <section id="jm138608">
          <title>To create the initialization host file</title>
          <ol>
            <li id="jm144077">Log in as
              <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>.<codeblock>$ su - gpadmin</codeblock></li>
            <li id="jm144112">Create a file named <codeph>hostfile_gpinitsystem</codeph>. In this
              file add the host address name(s) of your <i>segment</i> host interfaces, one name per
              line, no extra lines or spaces. For example, if you have four segment hosts with two
              unbonded network interfaces
              each:<codeblock>sdw1-1
sdw1-2
sdw2-1
sdw2-2
sdw3-1
sdw3-2
sdw4-1
sdw4-2</codeblock></li>
            <li id="jm138635">Save and close the file.</li>
          </ol>
          <note type="note">If you are not sure of the host names and/or interface address names
            used by your machines, look in the <codeph>/etc/hosts</codeph> file.</note>
        </section>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic5" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="jm138566">Creating the Greenplum Database Configuration File</title>
      <body>
        <p>Your Greenplum Database configuration file tells the <codeph><xref
              href="../utility_guide/ref/gpinitsystem.html" type="topic" format="dita"
              scope="peer">gpinitsystem</xref></codeph> utility how you want to configure your
          Greenplum Database system. An example configuration file can be found in
            <codeph>$GPHOME/docs/cli_help/gpconfigs/gpinitsystem_config</codeph>.</p>
        <section id="jm138725">
          <title>To create a gpinitsystem_config file</title>
          <ol>
            <li id="jm144228">Log in as
              <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>.<codeblock>$ su - gpadmin</codeblock></li>
            <li id="jm144214">Make a copy of the <codeph>gpinitsystem_config</codeph> file to use as
              a starting point. For
              example:<codeblock>$ cp $GPHOME/docs/cli_help/gpconfigs/gpinitsystem_config \
     /home/gpadmin/gpconfigs/gpinitsystem_config</codeblock></li>
            <li id="jm138730">Open the file you just copied in a text editor. <p>Set all of the
                required parameters according to your environment. See <xref
                  href="../utility_guide/ref/gpinitsystem.xml" type="topic"
                  format="dita" scope="peer">gpinitsystem</xref> for more information. A Greenplum
                Database system must contain a master instance and at <i>least two</i> segment
                instances (even if setting up a single node system). </p><p>The
                  <codeph>DATA_DIRECTORY</codeph> parameter is what determines how many segments per
                host will be created. If your segment hosts have multiple network interfaces, and
                you used their interface address names in your host file, the number of segments
                will be evenly spread over the number of available interfaces.</p><p>To specify
                  <codeph>PORT_BASE</codeph>, review the port range specified in the
                  <codeph>net.ipv4.ip_local_port_range</codeph> parameter in the <xref
                  href="../install_guide/prep_os.html#topic3" format="dita" scope="peer"
                    ><codeph>/etc/sysctl.conf</codeph></xref> file. </p><p>Here is an example of the
                  <i>required</i> parameters in the <codeph>gpinitsystem_config</codeph> file:
              </p><codeblock>ARRAY_NAME="Greenplum Data Platform"
SEG_PREFIX=gpseg
PORT_BASE=6000 
declare -a DATA_DIRECTORY=(/data1/primary /data1/primary /data1/primary /data2/primary /data2/primary /data2/primary)
MASTER_HOSTNAME=mdw 
MASTER_DIRECTORY=/data/master 
MASTER_PORT=5432 
TRUSTED SHELL=ssh
CHECK_POINT_SEGMENTS=8
ENCODING=UNICODE</codeblock></li>
            <li id="jm143448">(Optional) If you want to deploy mirror segments, uncomment and set
              the mirroring parameters according to your environment. To specify
                <codeph>MIRROR_PORT_BASE</codeph>, review the port range specified under the
                <codeph>net.ipv4.ip_local_port_range</codeph> parameter in the <xref
                href="../install_guide/prep_os.html#topic3" format="dita" scope="peer"
                  ><codeph>/etc/sysctl.conf</codeph></xref> file. Here is an example of the
                <i>optional</i> mirror parameters in the <codeph>gpinitsystem_config</codeph> file:<codeblock>MIRROR_PORT_BASE=7000
declare -a MIRROR_DATA_DIRECTORY=(/data1/mirror /data1/mirror /data1/mirror /data2/mirror /data2/mirror /data2/mirror)</codeblock>
              <note>You can initialize your Greenplum system with primary segments only and deploy
                mirrors later using the <codeph><xref
                    href="../utility_guide/ref/gpaddmirrors.xml" type="topic"
                    format="dita" scope="peer">gpaddmirrors</xref></codeph> utility.</note></li>
            <li id="jm138783">Save and close the file.</li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic6" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="jm142333">Running the Initialization Utility</title>
      <body>
        <p>The <codeph><xref href="../utility_guide/ref/gpinitsystem.xml" type="topic"
              format="dita" scope="peer">gpinitsystem</xref></codeph> utility will create a
          Greenplum Database system using the values defined in the configuration file.</p>
        <section id="jm138821">
          <title>To run the initialization utility</title>
          <ol>
            <li id="jm143533">Run the following command referencing the path and file name of your
              initialization configuration file (<codeph>gpinitsystem_config</codeph>) and host file
                (<codeph>hostfile_gpinitsystem</codeph>). For
                example:<codeblock>$ cd ~
$ gpinitsystem -c gpconfigs/gpinitsystem_config -h gpconfigs/hostfile_gpinitsystem</codeblock><p>For
                a fully redundant system (with a standby master and a <i>spread</i> mirror
                configuration) include the <codeph>-s</codeph> and <codeph>-S</codeph> options. For
                example:</p><codeblock>$ gpinitsystem -c gpconfigs/gpinitsystem_config -h gpconfigs/hostfile_gpinitsystem \
  -s <varname>standby_master_hostname</varname> -S</codeblock></li>
            <li id="jm138853">The utility will verify your setup information and make sure it can
              connect to each host and access the data directories specified in your configuration.
              If all of the pre-checks are successful, the utility will prompt you to confirm your
              configuration. For
              example:<codeblock>=&gt; Continue with Greenplum creation? <b>Yy/Nn</b></codeblock></li>
            <li id="jm143919">Press <codeph>y</codeph> to start the initialization.</li>
            <li id="jm141337">The utility will then begin setup and initialization of the master
              instance and each segment instance in the system. Each segment instance is set up in
              parallel. Depending on the number of segments, this process can take a while.</li>
            <li id="jm141341">At the end of a successful setup, the utility will start your
              Greenplum Database system. You should
              see:<codeblock><varname>=&gt; Greenplum Database instance successfully created.</varname></codeblock></li>
          </ol>
        </section>
      </body>
      <topic id="topic7" xml:lang="en">
        <title id="jm138878">Troubleshooting Initialization Problems</title>
        <body>
          <p>If the utility encounters any errors while setting up an instance, the entire process
            will fail, and could possibly leave you with a partially created system. Refer to the
            error messages and logs to determine the cause of the failure and where in the process
            the failure occurred. Log files are created in <codeph>~/gpAdminLogs</codeph>.</p>
          <p>Depending on when the error occurred in the process, you may need to clean up and then
            try the gpinitsystem utility again. For example, if some segment instances were created
            and some failed, you may need to stop <codeph>postgres</codeph> processes and remove any
            utility-created data directories from your data storage area(s). A backout script is
            created to help with this cleanup if necessary.</p>
          <section id="jm139087">
            <title>Using the Backout Script</title>
            <p>If the gpinitsystem utility fails, it will create the following backout script if it
              has left your system in a partially installed state:</p>
            <p>
              <codeph>~/gpAdminLogs/backout_gpinitsystem_<varname>&lt;user></varname>_<varname>&lt;timestamp&gt;</varname></codeph>
            </p>
            <p>You can use this script to clean up a partially created Greenplum Database system.
              This backout script will remove any utility-created data directories,
                <codeph>postgres</codeph> processes, and log files. After correcting the error that
              caused gpinitsystem to fail and running the backout script, you should be ready to
              retry initializing your Greenplum Database array.</p>
            <p>The following example shows how to run the backout script:</p>
            <codeblock>$ sh backout_gpinitsystem_gpadmin_20071031_121053</codeblock>
          </section>
        </body>
      </topic>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic_xkd_d1q_l2b">
      <title>Setting the Greenplum Database Timezone</title>
      <body>
        <!--GPDB 6.0 TimeZone is set in config. file-->
        <p>As a best practice, configure Greenplum Database and the host systems to use a known,
          supported timezone. Greenplum Database uses a timezone from a set of internally stored
          PostgreSQL timezones. Setting the Greenplum Database timezone prevents Greenplum Database
          from selecting a timezone each time the cluster is restarted and sets the timezone for the
          Greenplum Database master and segment instances. </p>
        <p>Use the <codeph><xref href="../utility_guide/ref/gpconfig.xml" type="topic"
              format="dita" scope="peer">gpconfig</xref></codeph> utility to show and set the
          Greenplum Database timezone. For example, these commands show the Greenplum Database
          timezone and set the timezone to
          <codeph>US/Pacific</codeph>.<codeblock># gpconfig -s TimeZone
# gpconfig -c TimeZone -v 'US/Pacific'</codeblock>You
          must restart Greenplum Database after changing the timezone. The command <codeph>gpstop
            -ra</codeph> restarts Greenplum Database. The catalog view
            <codeph>pg_timezone_names</codeph> provides Greenplum Database timezone information. </p>
        <p>For more information about the Greenplum Database timezone, see <xref
            href="localization.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/>.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic8" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="jm144793">Setting Greenplum Environment Variables</title>
    <body>
      <p>You must configure your environment on the Greenplum Database master (and standby master).
        A <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> file is provided in your <codeph>$GPHOME</codeph>
        directory with environment variable settings for Greenplum Database. You can source this
        file in the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user's startup shell profile (such as
          <codeph>.bashrc</codeph>). </p>
      <p>The Greenplum Database management utilities also require that the
          <codeph>MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY</codeph> environment variable be set. This should point to
        the directory created by the gpinitsystem utility in the master data directory location. </p>
      <note>The <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> script changes the operating environment in order
        to support running the Greenplum Database-specific utilities. These same changes to the
        environment can negatively affect the operation of other system-level utilities, such as
          <codeph>ps</codeph> or <codeph>yum</codeph>. Use separate accounts for performing system
        administration and database administration, instead of attempting to perform both functions
        as <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>.</note>
      <section id="jm144961">
        <title>To set up your user environment for Greenplum</title>
        <ol>
          <li id="jm144981">Make sure you are logged in as
            <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>:<codeblock>$ su - gpadmin</codeblock></li>
          <li id="jm145055">Open your profile file (such as <codeph>.bashrc</codeph>) in a text
            editor. For example:<codeblock>$ vi ~/.bashrc</codeblock></li>
          <li id="jm145072">Add lines to this file to source the <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph>
            file and set the <codeph>MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY</codeph> environment variable. For
            example:<codeblock>source /usr/local/greenplum-db/greenplum_path.sh
export MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY=/data/master/gpseg-1</codeblock></li>
          <li id="jm145148">(Optional) You may also want to set some client session environment
            variables such as <codeph>PGPORT</codeph>, <codeph>PGUSER</codeph> and
              <codeph>PGDATABASE</codeph> for convenience. For
            example:<codeblock>export PGPORT=5432
export PGUSER=gpadmin export PGDATABASE=<varname>default_login_database_name</varname></codeblock></li>
          <li>(Optional) If you use RHEL 7 or CentOS 7, add the following line to the end of the
              <codeph>.bashrc</codeph> file to enable using the <codeph>ps</codeph> command in the
              <codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph>
            environment:<codeblock>export LD_PRELOAD=/lib64/libz.so.1 ps</codeblock></li>
          <li id="jm145208">Save and close the file.</li>
          <li id="jm145155">After editing the profile file, source it to make the changes active.
            For example:<codeblock>$ source ~/.bashrc
</codeblock></li>
          <li id="jm145342">If you have a standby master host, copy your environment file to the
            standby master as well. For
            example:<codeblock>$ cd ~
$ scp .bashrc <varname>standby_hostname</varname>:`pwd`</codeblock></li>
        </ol>
        <note type="note">The <codeph>.bashrc</codeph> file should not produce any output. If you
          wish to have a message display to users upon logging in, use the <codeph>.profile</codeph>
          file instead. </note>
      </section>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic9" xml:lang="en">
    <title id="jm138979">Next Steps</title>
    <body>
      <p>After your system is up and running, the next steps are:</p>
      <ul>
        <li id="jm139449">
          <xref href="#topic10" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
        <li id="jm142387">
          <xref href="#topic11" type="topic" format="dita"/>
        </li>
      </ul>
    </body>
    <topic id="topic10" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="jm138989">Allowing Client Connections</title>
      <body>
        <p>After a Greenplum Database is first initialized it will only allow local connections to
          the database from the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> role (or whatever system user ran
            <codeph>gpinitsystem</codeph>). If you would like other users or client machines to be
          able to connect to Greenplum Database, you must give them access. See the <i>Greenplum
            Database Administrator Guide</i> for more information.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
    <topic id="topic11" xml:lang="en">
      <title id="jm139424">Creating Databases and Loading Data</title>
      <body>
        <p>After verifying your installation, you may want to begin creating databases and loading
          data. See <xref href="../admin_guide/ddl/ddl.xml" format="dita" type="topic" scope="peer"
            >Defining Database Objects</xref> and <xref
            href="../admin_guide/load/topics/g-loading-and-unloading-data.xml" type="topic"
            format="dita" scope="peer">Loading and Unloading Data</xref> in the <i>Greenplum
            Database Administrator Guide</i> for more information about creating databases, schemas,
          tables, and other database objects in Greenplum Database and loading your data.</p>
      </body>
    </topic>
  </topic>
</topic>
