<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="ji162018">Installing the Greenplum Database Software</title>
  <shortdesc>Describes how to install the Greenplum Database software binaries on all of the hosts
    that will comprise your Greenplum Database system, how to enable passwordless SSH for the
      <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user, and how to verify the installation.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>Perform the following tasks in order:</p>
    <ol>
      <li><xref href="#topic_oy5_21n_1jb" format="dita"/></li>
      <li><xref href="#topic_xmb_gb5_vhb" format="dita"/></li>
      <li><xref href="#topic10" format="dita">Confirm the software installation.</xref></li>
      <li><xref href="#topic_cwj_hzb_vhb" format="dita"/></li>
    </ol>
  </body>
  <topic id="topic_oy5_21n_1jb">
    <title>Installing Greenplum Database</title>
    <body>
      <p>You must install Greenplum Database on each host machine of the Greenplum Database
          system.<ph otherprops="oss-only"> You can configure a minimal Greenplum Database system to
          run on a single host system with the master instance and segment instances running on the
          same host system.</ph><ph otherprops="pivotal"> Pivotal distributes the Greenplum Database
          software as a downloadable package that you install on each host system with the operating
          system's package management system. You can download the package from <xref
            href="https://network.pivotal.io/products/pivotal-gpdb" format="html" scope="external"
            >Pivotal Network</xref>.</ph></p>
      <!--OSS only-->
      <p otherprops="oss-only">Greenplum Database releases are available as: source code tarballs,
        RPM installers for CentOS, and DEB packages for Debian and Ubuntu. See <xref
          href="https://greenplum.org/download/" format="html" scope="external"
          >https://greenplum.org/download/</xref> for links to source code and instructions to
        compile Greenplum Database from source, and for links to download pre-built binaries in RPM
        and DEB format. For the Ubuntu operating system, Greenplum also offers a binary that can be
        installed via the <codeph>apt-get</codeph> command with the Ubuntu Personal Package Archive
        system.</p>
      <p>Before you begin installing Greenplum Database, be sure you have completed the steps in
          <xref href="prep_os.xml#topic1"/> to configure each of the master, standby master, and
        segment host machines for Greenplum Database.</p>
      <note type="important">After installing Greenplum Database, you must set Greenplum Database
        environment variables. See <xref href="init_gpdb.xml#topic8"/>.</note>
      <p>See <xref href="ansible-example.xml#Untitled1"/> for an example script that shows how you
        can automate creating the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user and installing the Greenplum
        Database.</p>
      <p>Follow these instructions to install Greenplum Database<ph otherprops="oss-only"> from a
          pre-built binary</ph>.</p>
      <note type="important">You will need sudo or root user access to install from a pre-built
        binary. </note>
      <ol id="ol_mm5_v1n_1jb">
        <li>Download and copy the Greenplum Database package to the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user's
          home directory on the master, standby master, and every segment host machine. The
          distribution file name has the format
            <codeph>greenplum-db-&lt;version>-&lt;platform>.rpm</codeph> for RHEL and CentOS
          systems, or <codeph>greenplum-db-&lt;version>-&lt;platform>.deb</codeph> for Ubuntu
          systems, where <codeph>&lt;platform></codeph> is similar to <codeph>rhel7-x86_64</codeph>
          (Red Hat 7 64-bit).</li>
        <li>With sudo (or as root), install the Greenplum Database package on each host machine
          using your system's package manager software. <ul id="ol_wgt_mxz_1jb">
            <li>For RHEL/CentOS systems, execute the <codeph>yum</codeph> command:
              <codeblock>$ sudo yum install ./greenplum-db-&lt;version>-&lt;platform>.rpm</codeblock></li>
            <li>For Ubuntu systems, execute the <codeph>apt</codeph>
              command:<codeblock>$ sudo apt install ./greenplum-db-&lt;version>-&lt;platform>.deb</codeblock></li>
          </ul><p>The <codeph>yum</codeph> or <codeph>apt</codeph> command installs software
            dependencies, copies the Greenplum Database software files into a version-specific
            directory, <codeph>/usr/local/greenplum-db-&lt;version></codeph>, and creates the
            symbolic link <codeph>/usr/local/greenplum-db</codeph> to the installation
            directory.</p></li>
        <li>Change the owner and group of the installed files to
          <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>:<codeblock>$ sudo chown -R gpadmin:gpadmin /usr/local/greenplum*</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_xmb_gb5_vhb">
    <title>Enabling Passwordless SSH</title>
    <body>
      <p>The <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user on each Greenplum host must be able to SSH from any host
        in the cluster to any other host in the cluster without entering a password or passphrase
        (called "passwordless SSH"). If you enable passwordless SSH from the master host to every
        other host in the cluster ("1-<i>n</i> passwordless SSH"), you can use the Greenplum
        Database <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> command-line utility to enable passwordless SSH from
        every host to every other host ("<i>n</i>-<i>n</i> passwordless SSH"). </p>
      <ol id="ol_iyx_3b5_vhb">
        <li>Log in to the master host as the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user.</li>
        <li>Source the <codeph>path</codeph> file in the Greenplum Database installation directory.<codeblock>$ source /usr/local/greenplum-db-&lt;version>/greenplum_path.sh</codeblock>
          <note>Add the above <codeph>source</codeph> command to the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user's
              <codeph>.bashrc</codeph> or other shell startup file so that the Greenplum Database
            path and environment variables are set whenever you log in as
            <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>.</note></li>
        <li>Use the <codeph>ssh-copy-id</codeph> command to add the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user's
          public key to the <codeph>authorized_hosts</codeph> SSH file on every other host in the
          cluster.
          <codeblock>$ ssh-copy-id smdw
$ ssh-copy-id sdw1
$ ssh-copy-id sdw2
$ ssh-copy-id sdw3
. . .</codeblock>
          This enables 1-<i>n</i> passwordless SSH. You will be prompted to enter the
            <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user's password for each host. If you have the
            <codeph>sshpass</codeph> command on your system, you can use a command like the
          following to avoid the
          prompt.<codeblock>$ SSHPASS=&lt;password> sshpass -e ssh-copy-id smdw</codeblock></li>
        <li>In the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> home directory, create a file named
            <codeph>hostfile_exkeys</codeph> that has the machine configured host names and host
          addresses (interface names) for each host in your Greenplum system (master, standby
          master, and segment hosts). Make sure there are no blank lines or extra spaces. Check the
            <codeph>/etc/hosts</codeph> file on your systems for the correct host names to use for
          your environment. For example, if you have a master, standby master, and three segment
          hosts with two unbonded network interfaces per host, your file would look something like
          this:<codeblock>mdw
mdw-1
mdw-2
smdw
smdw-1
smdw-2
sdw1
sdw1-1
sdw1-2
sdw2
sdw2-1
sdw2-2
sdw3
sdw3-1
sdw3-2</codeblock></li>
        <li>Run the <codeph>gpssh-exkeys</codeph> utility with your <codeph>hostfile_exkeys</codeph>
          file to enable <i>n</i>-<i>n</i> passwordless SSH for the <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>
          user.<codeblock>$ gpssh-exkeys -f hostfile_exkeys</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic10" xml:lang="en">
    <title>Confirming Your Installation</title>
    <body>
      <p>To make sure the Greenplum software was installed and configured correctly, run the
        following confirmation steps from your Greenplum master host. If necessary, correct any
        problems before continuing on to the next task.</p>
      <ol id="ol_yjk_knz_thb">
        <li id="ji162490">Log in to the master host as
          <codeph>gpadmin</codeph>:<codeblock>$ su - <varname>gpadmin</varname></codeblock></li>
        <li id="ji162506">Use the <codeph>gpssh</codeph> utility to see if you can log in to all
          hosts without a password prompt, and to confirm that the Greenplum software was installed
          on all hosts. Use the <codeph>hostfile_exkeys</codeph> file you used to set up
          passwordless SSH. For
            example:<codeblock>$ gpssh -f hostfile_exkeys -e 'ls -l /usr/local/greenplum-db-&lt;version>'</codeblock><p>If
            the installation was successful, you should be able to log in to all hosts without a
            password prompt. All hosts should show that they have the same contents in their
            installation directories, and that the directories are owned by the
              <codeph>gpadmin</codeph> user.</p><p>If you are prompted for a password, run the
            following command to redo the ssh key
          exchange:</p><codeblock>$ gpssh-exkeys -f hostfile_exkeys</codeblock></li>
      </ol>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_zdf_1f5_vhb">
    <title>About Your Greenplum Database Installation</title>
    <body>
      <ul id="ul_a2f_1f5_vhb">
        <li><codeph>greenplum_path.sh</codeph> — This file contains the environment variables for
          Greenplum Database. See <xref href="./init_gpdb.xml#topic8" type="topic" format="dita"
          />.</li>
        <li><b>bin</b> — This directory contains the Greenplum Database management utilities. This
          directory also contains the PostgreSQL client and server programs, most of which are also
          used in Greenplum Database.</li>
        <li><b>docs/cli_help</b> — This directory contains help files for Greenplum Database
          command-line utilities. </li>
        <li><b>docs/cli_help/gpconfigs</b> — This directory contains sample
            <codeph>gpinitsystem</codeph> configuration files and host files that can be modified
          and used when installing and initializing a Greenplum Database system.</li>
        <li><b>ext</b> — Bundled programs (such as Python) used by some Greenplum Database
          utilities.</li>
        <li><b>include</b> — The C header files for Greenplum Database.</li>
        <li><b>lib</b> — Greenplum Database and PostgreSQL library files.</li>
        <li><b>sbin</b> — Supporting/Internal scripts and programs.</li>
        <li><b>share</b> — Shared files for Greenplum Database.</li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </topic>
  <topic id="topic_cwj_hzb_vhb">
    <title>Next Steps</title>
    <body>
      <ul id="ul_xsq_jzb_vhb">
        <li><xref href="create_data_dirs.xml#topic13"/></li>
        <li><xref href="validate.xml#topic1">Validating Your Systems</xref></li>
        <li><xref href="init_gpdb.xml#topic1">Initializing a Greenplum Database System</xref></li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </topic>
</topic>
