<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1" xml:lang="en">
  <title id="ji162018">Verifying the VMware Tanzu Greenplum Software Download</title>
  <shortdesc>Describes how to verify Greenplum Database software that you download
    from VMware Tanzu Network.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>VMware generates a SHA256 fingerprint for each Greenplum Database software
      download available from <xref href="https://network.pivotal.io/products/pivotal-gpdb"
        format="html" scope="external">VMware Tanzu Network</xref>. This fingerprint enables
      you to verify that your downloaded file is unaltered from the original.</p>
    <p>After you download a Greenplum Database server or component software package,
      you can verify the integrity of the software as follows:</p>
    <ol>
      <li>On VMware Tanzu Network, navigate to the Greenplum Database version and package
        that you downloaded.</li>
      <li>On the VMware Tanzu Greenplum <i>Release Download Files</i> page, click the
        <b>i</b> icon to the right of the Greenplum Database software package that
        you downloaded.<p>This action displays a dialog that contains information about
        the package file, including the <b>File</b> name and the <b>SHA256</b>
        fingerprint.</p></li>
      <li>Copy/paste the <b>SHA256</b> to a local file, or keep the Tanzu Network browser
        tab open.</li>
      <li>On your local host, open a terminal window, navigate to the download directory,
        and locate the Greenplum package file that you downloaded from Tanzu Network.</li>
      <li>Compare the downloaded file name with the <b>File</b> name specified in the
        Tanzu Network package information, and verify that they are the same.</li>
      <li>Identify an OS utility that you can use to locally calculate a file checksum.
        On CentOS, this utility command is named <codeph>sha256sum</codeph>.</li>
      <li>Run the utility to display the checksum of the package file that you downloaded
        from Tanzu Network. For example, if you downloaded the <b>Greenplum Database
        Server</b> package on CentOS:
        <codeblock>$ sha256sum greenplum-db-6.18.0-rhel7-x86_64.rpm</codeblock></li>
      <li>If the command checksum output matches the <b>SHA256</b> fingerprint specified
        in the Tanzu Network package information, the file was downloaded intact. You
        can safely proceed to install the software.</li>
    </ol>
  </body>
</topic>

