<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Composite//EN" "ditabase.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
    <title id="jo20941">gpactivatestandby</title>
    <body>
        <p>Activates a standby coordinator host and makes it the active coordinator for the Greenplum Database
            system.</p>
        <section id="section2">
            <title>Synopsis</title>
            <codeblock><b>gpactivatestandby</b> [<b>-d</b> <varname>standby_coordinator_datadir</varname>] [<b>-f</b>] [<b>-a</b>] [<b>-q</b>] 
    [<b>-l</b> <varname>logfile_directory</varname>]

<b>gpactivatestandby</b> <b>-v</b> 

<b>gpactivatestandby</b> <b>-?</b> | <b>-h</b> | <b>--help</b></codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="section3">
            <title>Description</title>
            <p>The <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> utility activates a backup, standby coordinator
                host and brings it into operation as the active coordinator instance for a Greenplum
                Database system. The activated standby coordinator effectively becomes the Greenplum
                Database coordinator, accepting client connections on the coordinator port. </p>
            <p>When you initialize a standby coordinator, the default is to use the same port as the
                active coordinator. For information about the coordinator port for the standby coordinator, see
                        <codeph><xref href="./gpinitstandby.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                    /></codeph>. </p>
            <p>You must run this utility from the coordinator host you are activating, not the failed
                coordinator host you are disabling. Running this utility assumes you have a standby
                coordinator host configured for the system (see <codeph><xref
                        href="./gpinitstandby.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                /></codeph>).</p>
            <p>The utility will perform the following steps:</p>
            <ul>
                <li id="jo140686">Stops the synchronization process (<codeph>walreceiver</codeph>)
                    on the standby coordinator</li>
                <li id="jo140687">Updates the system catalog tables of the standby coordinator using the
                    logs</li>
                <li id="jo140409">Activates the standby coordinator to be the new active coordinator for the
                    system</li>
                <li id="jo141105">Restarts the Greenplum Database system with the new coordinator
                    host</li>
            </ul>
            <p>A backup, standby Greenplum coordinator host serves as a 'warm standby' in the event of
                the primary Greenplum coordinator host becoming non-operational. The standby coordinator is
                kept up to date by transaction log replication processes (the
                    <codeph>walsender</codeph> and <codeph>walreceiver</codeph>), which run on the
                primary coordinator and standby coordinator hosts and keep the data between the primary and
                standby coordinator hosts synchronized. </p>
            <p>If the primary coordinator fails, the log replication process is shutdown, and the standby
                coordinator can be activated in its place by using the <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph>
                utility. Upon activation of the standby coordinator, the replicated logs are used to
                reconstruct the state of the Greenplum coordinator host at the time of the last
                successfully committed transaction. </p>
            <p>In order to use <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> to activate a new primary coordinator
                host, the coordinator host that was previously serving as the primary coordinator cannot be
                running. The utility checks for a <codeph>postmaster.pid</codeph> file in the data
                directory of the disabled coordinator host, and if it finds it there, it will assume the
                old coordinator host is still active. In some cases, you may need to remove the
                    <codeph>postmaster.pid</codeph> file from the disabled coordinator host data
                directory before running <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> (for example, if the
                disabled coordinator host process was terminated unexpectedly).</p>
            <p>After activating a standby coordinator, run <codeph>ANALYZE</codeph> to update the
                database query statistics. For example:</p>
            <codeblock>psql <varname>dbname</varname> -c 'ANALYZE;'</codeblock>
            <p>After you activate the standby coordinator as the primary coordinator, the Greenplum Database
                system no longer has a standby coordinator configured. You might want to specify another
                host to be the new standby with the <codeph><xref href="./gpinitstandby.xml#topic1"
                        type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph> utility. </p>
        </section>
        <section id="section4">
            <title>Options</title>
            <parml>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-a (do not prompt)</pt>
                    <pd>Do not prompt the user for confirmation.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-d <varname>standby_coordinator_datadir</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The absolute path of the data directory for the coordinator host you are
                        activating.</pd>
                    <pd>If this option is not specified, <codeph>gpactivatestandby</codeph> uses the
                        value of the 
                            <codeph>COORDINATOR_DATA_DIRECTORY</codeph> environment variable setting on the coordinator host you are
                        activating. If this option is specified, it overrides any setting of <codeph>COORDINATOR_DATA_DIRECTORY</codeph>. </pd>
                    <pd>If a directory cannot be determined, the utility returns an error. </pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-f (force activation)</pt>
                    <pd>Use this option to force activation of the backup coordinator host. Use this
                        option only if you are sure that the standby and primary coordinator hosts are
                        consistent.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-l <varname>logfile_directory</varname></pt>
                    <pd>The directory to write the log file. Defaults to
                            <codeph>~/gpAdminLogs</codeph>.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-q (no screen output)</pt>
                    <pd>Run in quiet mode. Command output is not displayed on the screen, but is
                        still written to the log file.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-v (show utility version)</pt>
                    <pd>Displays the version, status, last updated date, and check sum of this
                        utility.</pd>
                </plentry>
                <plentry>
                    <pt>-? | -h | --help (help)</pt>
                    <pd>Displays the online help.</pd>
                </plentry>
            </parml>
        </section>
        <section id="section5">
            <title>Example</title>
            <p>Activate the standby coordinator host and make it the active coordinator instance for a
                Greenplum Database system (run from backup coordinator host you are activating):</p>
            <codeblock>gpactivatestandby -d /gpdata</codeblock>
        </section>
        <section id="section6">
            <title>See Also</title>
            <p><codeph><xref href="./gpinitsystem.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>,
                        <codeph><xref href="./gpinitstandby.xml#topic1" type="topic" format="dita"
                    /></codeph></p>
        </section>
    </body>
</topic>
