<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="topic1">
  <title>gprestore</title>
  <body>
    <p>Restore a Greenplum Database backup that was created using the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>
      utility. By default <codeph>gprestore</codeph> uses backed up metadata files and DDL files
      located in the Greenplum Database master host data directory, with table data stored locally
      on segment hosts in CSV data files.</p>
    <section>
      <title>Synopsis</title>
      <codeblock><b>gprestore --timestamp</b> <varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname>
   [<b>--backup-dir</b> <varname>directory</varname>]
   [<b>--create-db</b>]
   [<b>--debug</b>]
   [<b>--exclude-schema</b> <varname>schema_name</varname>]
   [<b>--exclude-table</b> <varname>schema.table</varname>]
   [<b>--exclude-table-file</b> <varname>file_name</varname>]
   [<b>--include-schema</b> <varname>schema_name</varname>]
   [<b>--include-table</b> <varname>schema.table</varname>]
   [<b>--include-table-file</b> <varname>file_name</varname>]
   [<b>--data-only</b> | <b>--metadata-only</b>]
   [<b>--jobs</b> <varname>int</varname>]
   [<b>--on-error-continue</b>]
   [<b>--plugin-config</b> <varname>config_file_location</varname>]
   [<b>--quiet</b>]
   [<b>--redirect-db</b> <varname>database_name</varname>]
   [<b>--verbose</b>]
   [<b>--version</b>]
   [<b>--with-globals</b>]
   [<b>--with-stats</b>]

<b>gprestore --help</b></codeblock>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Description</title>
      <p>To use <codeph>gprestore</codeph> to restore from a backup set, you must include the
          <codeph>--timestamp</codeph> option to specify the exact timestamp value
          (<codeph>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</codeph>) of the backup set to restore. If you specified a custom
          <codeph>--backup-dir</codeph> to consolidate the backup files, include the same
          <codeph>--backup-dir</codeph> option with <codeph>gprestore</codeph> to locate the backup
        files.</p>
      <p>If the backup you specify is an incremental backup, you need a complete set of backup files
        (a full backup and any required incremental backups). <codeph>gprestore</codeph> ensures
        that the complete backup set is available before attempting to restore a backup.
        <note type="important">For incremental backup sets, the backups must be on a single device.
          For example, a backup set must all be on a Data Domain system. </note></p>
      <p>For information about incremental backups, see <xref
          href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup-incremental.xml"/>.</p>
      <p>When restoring from a backup set, <codeph>gprestore</codeph> restores to a database with
        the same name as the name specified when creating the backup set. If the target database
        exists and a table being restored exists in the database, the restore operation fails.
        Include the <codeph>--create-db</codeph> option if the target database does not exist in the
        cluster. You can optionally restore a backup set to a different database by using the
          <codeph>--redirect-db</codeph> option.</p>
      <p>When restoring a backup set that contains data from some leaf partitions of a partitioned
        tables, the partitioned table is restored along with the data for the leaf partitions. For
        example, you create a backup with the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> option
          <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph> and the text file lists some leaf partitions of a
        partitioned table. Restoring the backup creates the partitioned table and restores the data
        only for the leaf partitions listed in the file. </p>
      <p>Greenplum Database system objects are automatically included in a <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>
        backup set, but these objects are only restored if you include the
          <codeph>--with-globals</codeph> option to <codeph>gprestore</codeph>. Similarly, if you
        backed up query plan statistics using the <codeph>--with-stats</codeph> option, you can
        restore those statistics by providing <codeph>--with-stats</codeph> to
          <codeph>gprestore</codeph>. By default, only database objects in the backup set are
        restored.</p>
      <p>Performance of restore operations can be improved by creating multiple parallel connections
        to restore table data and metadata. By default <codeph>gprestore</codeph> uses 1 connection,
        but you can increase this number with the <codeph>--jobs</codeph> option for large restore
        operations.</p>
      <p>When a restore operation completes, <codeph>gprestore</codeph> returns a status code. See
          <xref href="#topic1/return_codes" format="dita"/>.</p>
      <p><codeph>gprestore</codeph> can send status email notifications after a back up operation
        completes. You specify when the utility sends the mail and the email recipients in a
        configuration file. See <xref
          href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_qwd_d5d_tbb" format="dita"
        />.</p>
    </section>
    <note>This utility uses secure shell (SSH) connections between systems to perform its tasks. In
      large Greenplum Database deployments, cloud deployments, or deployments with a large number of
      segments per host, this utility may exceed the host's maximum threshold for unauthenticated
      connections. Consider updating the SSH <codeph>MaxStartups</codeph> and
        <codeph>MaxSessions</codeph> configuration parameters to increase this threshold. For more
      information about SSH configuration options, refer to the SSH documentation for your Linux
      distribution.</note>
    <section>
      <title>Options</title>
      <parml>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--timestamp</b>
            <varname>YYYYMMDDHHMMSS</varname></pt>
          <pd>Required. Specifies the timestamp of the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> backup set to
            restore. By default <codeph>gprestore</codeph> tries to locate metadata files for the
            timestamp on the Greenplum Database master host in the
              <filepath>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath>
            directory, and CSV data files in the
              <filepath>&lt;seg_dir>/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath> directory of each
            segment host.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--backup-dir</b>
            <varname>directory</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Sources all backup files (metadata files and data files) from the specified
            directory. You must specify <varname>directory</varname> as an absolute path (not
            relative). If you do not supply this option, <codeph>gprestore</codeph> tries to locate
            metadata files for the timestamp on the Greenplum Database master host in the
              <filepath>$MASTER_DATA_DIRECTORY/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath>
            directory. CSV data files must be available on each segment in the
              <filepath>&lt;seg_dir>/backups/YYYYMMDD/YYYYMMDDhhmmss/</filepath> directory. Include
            this option when you specify a custom backup directory with
            <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot combine this option with the option <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--create-db</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Creates the database before restoring the database object metadata.</pd>
          <pd>The database is created by cloning the empty standard system database
              <codeph>template0</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="data_only">
          <pt><b>--data-only</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Restores table data from a backup created with the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph>
            utility, without creating the database tables. This option assumes the tables exist in
            the target database. To restore data for a specific set of tables from a backup set, you
            can specify an option to include tables or schemas or exclude tables or schemas. Specify
            the <codeph>--with-stats</codeph> option to restore table statistics from the
            backup.</pd>
          <pd>The backup set must contain the table data to be restored. For example, a backup
            created with the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> option <codeph>--metadata-only</codeph> does
            not contain table data.</pd>
          <pd>To restore only database tables, without restoring the table data, see the option
                <codeph><xref href="#topic1/metadata_only" format="dita"
              >--metadata-only</xref></codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--debug</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Displays verbose and debug log messages during a restore operation.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--exclude-schema</b>
            <varname>schema_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a database schema to exclude from the restore operation. You can
            specify this option multiple times to exclude multiple schemas. You cannot combine this
            option with the option <codeph>--include-schema</codeph>, or a table filtering option
            such as <codeph>--include-table</codeph>. </pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--exclude-table</b>
            <varname>schema.table</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a table to exclude from the restore operation. The table must be
            in the format <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. If a table or schema
            name uses any character other than a lowercase letter, number, or an underscore
            character, then you must include that name in double quotes. You can specify this option
            multiple times. If the table is not in the backup set, the restore operation fails. You
            cannot specify a leaf partition of a partitioned table.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot combine this option with the option <codeph>--exclude-schema</codeph>, or
            another a table filtering option such as <codeph>--include-table</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--exclude-table-file</b>
            <varname>file_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a text file containing a list of tables to exclude from the
            restore operation. Each line in the text file must define a single table using the
            format <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. The file must not include
            trailing lines. If a table or schema name uses any character other than a lowercase
            letter, number, or an underscore character, then you must include that name in double
            quotes. If a table is not in the backup set, the restore operation fails. You cannot
            specify a leaf partition of a partitioned table.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot combine this option with the option <codeph>--exclude-schema</codeph>, or
            another a table filtering option such as <codeph>--include-table</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--include-schema</b>
            <varname>schema_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a database schema to restore. You can specify this option multiple
            times to include multiple schemas. If you specify this option, any schemas that you
            specify must be available in the backup set. Any schemas that are not included in
            subsequent <codeph>--include-schema</codeph> options are omitted from the restore
            operation. </pd>
          <pd>If a schema that you specify for inclusion exists in the database, the utility issues
            an error and continues the operation. The utility fails if a table being restored exists
            in the database. </pd>
          <pd>You cannot use this option if objects in the backup set have dependencies on multiple
            schemas.</pd>
          <pd>See <xref href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_et4_b5d_tbb"
              >Filtering the Contents of a Backup or Restore</xref> for more information.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--include-table</b>
            <varname>schema.table</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a table to restore. The table must be in the format
              <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. If a table or schema name uses any
            character other than a lowercase letter, number, or an underscore character, then you
            must include that name in double quotes. You can specify this option multiple times. You
            cannot specify a leaf partition of a partitioned table.</pd>
          <pd>You can also specify the qualified name of a sequence or a view. </pd>
          <pd>If you specify this option, the utility does not automatically restore dependent
            objects. You must also explicitly specify the dependent objects that are required. For
            example if you restore a view, you must also restore the tables that the view uses. If
            you restore a table that uses a sequence, you must also restore the sequence. The
            dependent objects must exist in the backup set.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot combine this option with a schema filtering option such as
              <codeph>--include-schema</codeph>, or another table filtering option such as
              <codeph>--exclude-table-file</codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--include-table-file</b>
            <varname>file_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies a text file containing a list of tables to restore. Each line in
            the text file must define a single table using the format
              <codeph>&lt;schema-name>.&lt;table-name></codeph>. The file must not include trailing
            lines. If a table or schema name uses any character other than a lowercase letter,
            number, or an underscore character, then you must include that name in double quotes.
            Any tables not listed in this file are omitted from the restore operation. You cannot
            specify a leaf partition of a partitioned table.</pd>
          <pd>You can also specify the qualified name of a sequence or a view. </pd>
          <pd>If you specify this option, the utility does not automatically restore dependent
            objects. You must also explicitly specify dependent objects that are required. For
            example if you restore a view, you must also specify the tables that the view uses. If
            you specify a table that uses a sequence, you must also specify the sequence. The
            dependent objects must exist in the backup set.</pd>
          <pd>If you use the <codeph>--include-table-file</codeph> option,
              <codeph>gprestore</codeph> does not create roles or set the owner of the tables. The
            utility restores table indexes and rules. Triggers are also restored but are not
            supported in Greenplum Database.</pd>
          <pd>See <xref href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_et4_b5d_tbb"/>
            for more information.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--jobs</b>
            <varname>int</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specifies the number of parallel connections to use when restoring table
            data and metadata. By default, <codeph>gprestore</codeph> uses 1 connection. Increasing
            this number can improve the speed of restoring data.
            <note>If you used the <codeph>gpbackup --single-data-file</codeph> option to combine
              table backups into a single file per segment, you cannot set <codeph>--jobs</codeph>
              to a value higher than 1 to perform a parallel restore operation.</note></pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry id="metadata_only">
          <pt><b>--metadata-only</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Creates database tables from a backup created with the
              <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> utility, but does not restore the table data. This option
            assumes the tables do not exist in the target database. To create a specific set of
            tables from a backup set, you can specify an option to include tables or schemas or
            exclude tables or schemas. Specify the option <codeph>--with-globals</codeph> to restore
            the Greenplum Database system objects.</pd>
          <pd>The backup set must contain the DDL for tables to be restored. For example, a backup
            created with the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> option <codeph>--data-only</codeph> does not
            contain the DDL for tables. </pd>
          <pd>To restore table data after you create the database tables, see the option
                <codeph><xref href="#topic1/data_only" format="dita"
            >--data-only</xref></codeph>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--on-error-continue</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Specify this option to continue the restore operation if an SQL error occurs
            when creating database metadata (such as tables, roles, or functions) or restoring data.
            If another type of error occurs, the utility exits. The utility displays an error
            summary and writes error information to the <codeph>gprestore</codeph> log file and
            continues the restore operation. </pd>
          <pd>The default is to exit on the first error.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--plugin-config</b>
            <varname>config-file_location</varname></pt>
          <pd>Specify the location of the <codeph>gpbackup</codeph> plugin configuration file, a
            YAML-formatted text file. The file contains configuration information for the plugin
            application that <codeph>gprestore</codeph> uses during the restore operation.</pd>
          <pd>If you specify the <codeph>--plugin-config</codeph> option when you back up a
            database, you must specify this option with configuration information for a
            corresponding plugin application when you restore the database from the backup.</pd>
          <pd>You cannot combine this option with the option <codeph>--backup-dir</codeph>.</pd>
          <pd>For information about using storage plugin applications, see <xref
              href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-plugins.xml">Using gpbackup Storage
              Plugins</xref>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--quiet</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Suppress all non-warning, non-error log messages.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--redirect-db</b>
            <varname>database_name</varname></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Restore to the specified <varname>database_name</varname> instead of to the
            database that was backed up.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--verbose</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Displays verbose log messages during a restore operation.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--version</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Print the version number and exit.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--with-globals</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Restores Greenplum Database system objects in the backup set, in addition to
            database objects. See <xref
              href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml#topic_x3s_lqj_tbb"/>.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt><b>--with-stats</b></pt>
          <pd>Optional. Restore query plan statistics from the backup set.</pd>
        </plentry>
        <plentry>
          <pt>--help</pt>
          <pd>Displays the online help.</pd>
        </plentry>
      </parml>
    </section>
    <section id="return_codes">
      <title>Return Codes</title>
      <p>One of these codes is returned after <codeph>gprestore</codeph> completes.<ul
          id="ul_hhb_sqp_n4">
          <li><b>0</b> – Restore completed with no problems.</li>
          <li><b>1</b> – Restore completed with non-fatal errors. See log file for more
            information.</li>
          <li><b>2</b> – Restore failed with a fatal error. See log file for more information.</li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Examples</title>
      <p>Create the demo database and restore all schemas and tables in the backup set for the
        indicated
        timestamp:<codeblock>$ dropdb demo
$ gprestore --timestamp 20171103152558 --create-db</codeblock></p>
      <p>Restore the backup set to the "demo2" database instead of the "demo" database that was
        backed
        up:<codeblock>$ createdb demo2
$ gprestore --timestamp 20171103152558 --redirect-db demo2</codeblock></p>
      <p>Restore global Greenplum Database metadata and query plan statistics in addition to the
        database
        objects:<codeblock>$ gprestore --timestamp 20171103152558 --create-db --with-globals --with-stats</codeblock></p>
      <p>Restore, using backup files that were created in the
          <filepath>/home/gpadmin/backup</filepath> directory, creating 8 parallel
        connections:<codeblock>$ gprestore --backup-dir /home/gpadmin/backups/ --timestamp 20171103153156 --create-db --jobs 8</codeblock></p>
      <p>Restore only the "wikipedia" schema included in the backup
        set:<codeblock>$ dropdb demo
$ gprestore --include-schema wikipedia --backup-dir /home/gpadmin/backups/ --timestamp 20171103153156 --create-db</codeblock></p>
      <p>If you restore from an incremental backup set, all the required files in the backup set
        must be available to <codeph>gprestore</codeph>. For example, the following timestamp keys
        specify an incremental backup set. 20170514054532 is the full backup and the others are
        incremental backups.</p>
      <pre>20170514054532 (full backup)
20170714095512 
20170914081205 
20171114064330 
20180114051246</pre>
      <p>The following <codeph>gprestore</codeph> command specifies the timestamp 20121114064330.
        The incremental backup with the timestamps 20120714095512 and 20120914081205 and the full
        backup must be available to perform a restore.</p>
      <codeblock>gprestore --timestamp 20121114064330 --redirect-db mystest --create-db</codeblock>
    </section>
    <section id="section9">
      <title>See Also</title>
      <p>
        <codeph><xref href="./gpbackup.xml" type="topic" format="dita"/></codeph>, <xref
          href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-gpbackup.xml" format="dita"/> and <xref
          href="../../admin_guide/managing/backup-s3-plugin.xml"/></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
